PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video, I want us to
compute the following limit,
if the limit is n goes to
infinity of the sum for i
equals 0 to n minus 1 of the
following, 2 over n times the
quantity 2i over n quantity
squared minus 1.
Now this might look a little
intimidating to try and take a
limit of this, but what I'd like
you to do as a hint to
you is that you should think
about this as being
potentially a Riemann sum
of a certain function.
So if you can figure out the
function, and you can figure
out the appropriate interval
that you're taking a Riemann
sum over, as n goes to infinity,
you should be able
to write this as an integral.
We know how to use the
fundamental theorem of
calculus to determine
that a definite
integral in many cases.
Hopefully this is a function
for which we
know a way to do that.
So that's my hint to you.
Think about it, it's a Riemann
sum approximating an integral,
and I'll give you a while
to work on it, and
then I'll be back.
OK, welcome back.
Well hopefully it's been fun
for you to look at this
problem so far.
Let me just remind you
what we were doing.
We were trying to compute a
limit as n goes to infinity of
the sum from i equals 0 to n
minus 1 of 2 over n times 2i
over n squared minus 1.
So I gave you the big hint that
this is probably going to
be written as an integral.
So let me show you some pieces
of this sum that should help
us see what the integral is,
and then I'll make a guess
about what this is, and then
I'll try to give an educated
way to check my guess.
So the first thing we noticed
is that there is one thing,
this is a product of two
functions, and one of them,
well of n I guess.
But this is a product of two
things, one thing appears in
every single term that
you have for i.
So the sum has n terms, and
they're all going to be 2 over
n times this, and the i
is going to change.
But this does not change,
this 2 over n
does not change, right?
In fact, I could even pull
that out if I wanted.
But, I don't want to pull it
out of the sum right now.
I want us to look at
what's actually
going on in this product.
So if this thing is appearing
over and over again, and we
know this is probably a Riemann
sum, then chances are
this is our delta x.
So delta x being equal to 2 over
n, we know delta x equals
b minus a over n, where b and
a are our left endpoint, oh
sorry, our right endpoint,
and our left endpoint.
Right?
We integrate from a to b.
So b minus a is the length
of the interval.
So this is really dividing up
whatever interval we're
integrating over, into n
equals subintervals.
So that's my first thought, is
that b minus a over n is equal
to 2 over n.
And now we want to try
and figure out
what the heck is this.
Well, when we take a Riemann
sum, remember when we take a
Riemann sum what we get.
We get the sum of delta x times
f of x sub i, and i is
what's varying from
0 to n minus 1.
Let me put a little curve in
here so we see those are two
different things.
So this is i equals
0 to n minus 1.
I have this delta x here.
I'm anticipating this is
some f of x sub i.
And so the question
is, what f is it?
Right?
If I know what f it is, than I
know that this sum will be
equal to something, the integral
from a to b of f of x
dx, and a and b will
differ by 2.
So that's where I'm heading.
So now the question is what
is this a function of?
What function is this,
I should say.
Now first guess would be
something like, well, I'm
taking some quantity,
I'm squaring it,
and subtracting 1.
So my first guess for this
function is x squared minus 1.
I mean, that seems easy to me.
Let's see if this would actually
even make sense just
by looking at the subscripts,
or sorry, the index, the
indices I have here.
So what do I have?
Well, when I put
in i equals 0--
let's put down some of these
values-- when I put in i
equals 0, I get 2 times 0
over n squared minus 1.
When I put in i equals 1,
I get 2 times 1 over n
squared minus 1.
And I go all the way up, to
2 times n minus 1 over n
squared minus 1.
So it's kind of a long sum
there, but these are, this is
what our sum of these things
looks like if I pull
out the 2 over n.
So here I get 0 squared
minus 1.
That looks pretty good.
Here I get 2 times 1 over
n squared minus 1.
So it does look like I'm doing
something, taking something,
squaring it, subtracting 1.
Does it make sense that these
are the kind of x values I
would expect to get if this
were the Riemann sum of x
squared minus 1?
It does, and let's
think about why.
I'm starting at x equals 0
here it sure looks like.
Let's look at what happens
when I go all
the way over here.
What happens when n gets really,
really big, is it that
this ratio approaches 2.
So it's 2 times n minus 1 over
n. n minus 1 over n, as n gets
arbitrarily large, as n gets
really big, then this
approaches 2.
So this is approaching
2 squared minus 1.
So it's giving me more evidence
that this is probably
the function x squared
minus 1.
And now I'm starting
to believe the
interval is 0 to 2.
I know it's length 2 interval,
and it's looking like the
interval is 0 to 2.
Let's come back and talk
about one more thing.
The one other thing that you
should notice is that how does
this value differ from this
value, and the next, and the
next, and the next?
They differ by 2 over n.
So each time whatever input I
had previously, I'm now adding
2 over n to the next input.
And that should make sense of
what we know about Riemann
sums, because what I do, is I
divide my interval into these
subintervals of length
2 over n.
I'm evaluating it at one x value
that I'm starting, in
this case, at 0.
Then the next interval
is 2 over n more.
Then I evaluate at
that x value.
The next one it 2 over
n more, and I
evaluate at that x value.
So this is looking like--
I'm going to write it here,
this is my guess--
integral from 0 to 2 of
x squared minus 1 dx.
And now to make myself feel
good about this--
I'm pretty sure it's that.
To make you feel good about
this, I'm going to divide this
into four subintervals, and I'm
going to show you what the
Riemann sum with four intervals
looks like, and then
we can talk about how it relates
to this one over here.
OK, so let me draw a graph.
Actually, I'll use just
white chalk again.
Let me draw a graph of x squared
minus 1 from 0 to 2.
So 0, 1, 2, minus 1.
OK, so at 0, x squared minus
1 is negative 1.
At x equals 1, x squared
minus 1 is 0.
And at 2, x squared
minus 1 is 3.
So hopefully is all going to go
into the video and in the
video screen I mean.
And there we go, something
like that.
So this is, you know, it
continues over here, but I'm
really only interested
in this part.
So now let's look at what
the subintervals are.
And now I'm going to get
some colored chalk.
So what are the subintervals?
I'm taking 1 over 4, OK?
And so delta x, in this
case, is 2 over 4,
which is equal to 1/2.
Right?
And so what are my, what
are, what is my sum
going to look like?
Well, I am going to tell you
that I'm also going to use
left-handed endpoints.
And I mentioned earlier why
that is, I believe.
Maybe I didn't.
But, I started off at i
equals 0, and my first
input value was 0.
My last input value had an n
minus 1 in it instead of an n.
So I was doing, somehow, the
second to last place that I
was interested in here.
So it's definitely more of a
left-hand endpoint thing.
So I'm going to do this with
left-hand endpoints.
And I'm not going to
simplify as I go.
I'm going to write it out in
sort of an expanded form.
OK, so let's write it out
in expanded form.
So the Riemann sum, this is y
equals x squared minus 1.
The Riemann sum is, the first
term is 1/2 times what?
It's the value, this x value,
which is 0, evaluated on this
curve, so 0 squared minus 1.
The next term--
I'll just write them right
below each other--
is 1/2.
'Cause again, let's draw
a picture of what the
first one is, sorry.
It's this rectangle.
Right?
It's the value, length 1/2,
and it's the function
evaluated at 0.
The next one is length 1/2,
and it's going to be the
function evaluated
at whatever this
left-hand endpoint is here.
So it's going to be this area.
So it's going to be length 1/2,
and then the height is
going to be at x equals
1/2, so 1/2 quantity
squared minus 1.
The next one is going
to be this interval.
Well, there's no rectangle to
draw because it's just, the
output is zero at the
left endpoint there.
So it's just going to be, it's
going to have an output equal
to zero at length 1/2
and height 0.
But, we'll write
it out anyway.
It's going to be 1/2
times the quantity.
Now, I went up 1/2 more, so it's
going to be two 1/2's ,
two times 1/2 squared minus 1.
Let me just show you
why I did this.
OK, if we look at the picture,
here I'd gone up 1/2's for my
initial value.
Here I'd gone up another 1/2
for my initial value.
So that's two 1/2 from my
initial value of 0.
The next one is going to be
three 1/2's, so this is three
1/2's away, or commonly
known as 3/2.
OK?
So that one is going to be 1/2
is the base length again,
times the quantity 3 times
1/2 squared minus 1.
And that is in the picture,
this rectangle.
Great.
So what are we see here?
If we look at this, these four
pieces, what do we have?
We have a 1/2 in front
each time.
Which, what was the 1/2?
It was b minus a over n.
So b minus a was 2, n was 4.
So maybe I should have kept
that as 2 over 4.
But, it's a little easier to
write it as 1/2 because of
what I'm doing next.
I square something,
I subtract 1.
I go up by the value that this
is from the initial one here.
And so now I'm taking the output
of what was in here.
I now take the output at 1/2
more than what was here.
Now I take it at two 1/2's more
than what was here, or
1/2 more than what was there,
and then three 1/2's more than
what was here, or one more
than what was there.
That's kind of confusing, but
let's go back to the picture
and see what it is.
My delta x was 1/2, right?
So I evaluate at the first
place, and I evaluate one more
up, and then I evaluate one more
up, and I evaluate one
more up, which gives
me outputs here,
there, there, and there.
Right?
So really if you go back and you
look at the formulation of
the, of the sum, this was 2 over
n times quantity 2i over
n squared minus 1, you can see
the 2 over n is my 1/2, and
then this is maybe the hardest
part to see, but that's the 2
over n is my 1/2 again, and
the i is this thing that's
coming in as 1, 2, 3.
And so that i was going
from 0 to n minus 1--
so I should have said
0, 1, 2, 3.
Right?
So that i is the 0 to n minus
1, and then I'm evaluating
that, and then I add
them all up.
So when I take the sum, I get,
for n equals 4, I get this.
So in fact, this is just a
guess, still maybe you should,
maybe you should convince
yourself more.
I'm actually convinced at this
point, based on not just this
evidence, but the evidence I
understood before about how
the function works.
Maybe you want to compare
it when n equals 6, or
something like that.
You may need a little more
evidence to make you
understand this particular
piece.
But, hopefully that makes sense
to you that this is
really just i times delta x, and
then evaluated somewhere.
That's the main idea
of this component.
OK, well hopefully this
is informative to you.
If you want to know the exact
answer of how to compute the
sum, obviously you just
take the integral.
So I know you can do that.
So that's where I'll stop.