CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
I want us to work a little
more on finding
anti-derivatives.
In particular, in this video
we want to find an
anti-derivative of a
trigonometric function, a
power of the tangent function.
So I would like you to find an
anti-derivative of tangent
theta quantity to the fourth.
And the hint I will give you is
that you're going to need
some fairly familiar,
hopefully, by now,
trigonometric identities
to get this to work.
And then you will need some
other strategies that you've
also been developing.
So I'll give you a while to work
on it and then I'll be
back and I'll show
you how I did it.
OK.
Welcome back.
We want to, again, we want to
find an anti-derivative for
tangent theta quantity
to the fourth.
And I mentioned that what
we're going to need is a
particular trigonometric--
well, I didn't say particular,
sorry-- but we will need some
trigonometric identities
to make this work.
And the one in particular I'll
be exploiting is a certain
one, which I'll write down here,
which is, 1 plus tangent
squared theta is equal to
secant squared theta.
We've seen that, I think, a fair
amount now, but just to
remind ourselves, it is
important, and this is the one
we're going to use.
So let me show you how this
works, how this identity will
be very useful in here.
And the idea is that we can
break up this tangent to the
fourth theta into two,
the product of two
tangent squared thetas.
So I can rewrite this integral
above as the integral of
tangent squared theta times
another tangent squared theta.
But instead of that, I'm going
to use this identity.
So I'm going to write
it as secant squared
theta minus 1 d theta.
So just let me make sure
everybody follows what I did.
I had tangent to the fourth
theta as my initial integral,
so then I wrote it as tangent
squared times tangent squared.
And this is actually equal
to tangent squared.
You notice I just subtracted
1 from both sides
of the starred identity.
So that's my other
tangent squared.
So these two integrals
are actually equal.
So I haven't changed anything
fundamentally
at all in the problem.
All right.
Now let's look at what
we get here.
We get, if I distribute this,
I get integral tan squared
theta secant squared theta d
theta minus the integral of
tan squared theta d theta.
Now, you should start to see
that maybe even powers of
tangent theta are nice
to deal with.
Because this kind of stuff is
going to happen, this is going
to happen every time with, you
know, n minus 2, the power n
minus 2, here, for any
n I have up here.
And the reason the even is--
actually, I guess the even
doesn't even really matter.
I could just have any n
and this would be n
minus 2 down here.
This is an easy integral
to deal with.
Why is that?
Because what's the derivative
of the tangent function?
It's secant squared.
Right?
So this is actually a straight
up u-substitution, or
substitution type problem.
So this, I can finish and I will
later, but this will be
substitution.
So I'll finish that
in a little bit.
But what about this?
Now I have tan squared
theta d theta.
That's, you know, we don't
have any, we don't have a
secant here.
We don't have secant squared
here, which would make it
obviously nice-- that's
what we had here.
So we need to do something
else with this.
Well, what I'm going to do is,
I'm again going to use the
trigonometric identity.
I'm going to replace this
tangent squares theta by
secant squared theta minus 1.
Let's think about,
why is that good?
Well, that's good because what
I end up with is, if I have
secant squared theta minus 1--
is what this will equal--
secant squared theta is
easy to integrate.
Because it's the derivative of a
trig function we know-- it's
the derivative of tangent.
And 1, I think, is pretty
easy to integrate, too.
So we have two functions we
can integrate very easily.
So I'm going to bring this back
up on the next line, I'm
going to do the replacement
here, and then we'll finish
the problem.
So let me write this down.
OK.
Now I'm going to do my
replacement and minus the
quantity the integral secant
squared theta minus 1 d theta.
Let's make sure I didn't
make any mistakes.
So I had tan squared theta
secant squared theta d theta.
That looks good.
And then I'm subtracting tan
squared theta, the integral of
tan squared theta d theta.
And that's that.
So I'm OK.
So this one, again, I mentioned
that this is going
to be a substitution.
If you need to write it out
explicitly, this is u equals
tan theta, so du is equal to
secant squared theta d theta.
So this is the integral
of u squared.
Right?
If I substitute in I
get u squared du.
So it's the integral of
u squared, which is
u cubed over 3.
So that first part is going to
be tan cubed theta over 3.
That's my first term.
That's a straight up
substitution pretty similar to
what you've seen.
Now I have two things
to integrate.
I have to integrate secant
squared theta, and I have to
integrate the 1.
Well, derivative of tangent
is secant squared.
So the integral of secant
squared theta is
just tangent theta.
So I have to subtract, so
there's a minus sine of
tangent theta.
And then I have a minus, minus,
so when I integrate 1 d
theta, I'm going to
get a plus theta.
And then, obviously, because
it's a family of possible
solutions, I can add a constant
there, plus c.
So again, where did
these come from?
This first one was
a u-substitution
on the first integral.
And then over here I have
another integral with two
terms inside.
The first one is just
the, I just need to
integrate secant squared.
I get tangent theta.
The second one, I just need to
integrate the 1, and so I have
a negative, negative.
That makes it a positive
theta.
And then I have to
add my constant.
So let's come back
and just remind
ourselves where we started.
We started with this
trig function that
was a power of tangent.
And what we ultimately did is
we took two of the powers of
tangent, we made a substitution
with the
appropriate trigonometric
identity to make this an
easier problem to solve.
And actually-- yeah--
if you take two of the powers
of tangent away and replace
them by this, then you're always
going to end up with
something of this form, tangent
to the power 2 less
times secant squared theta d
theta, which you can always
handle by a u-substitution.
And you're going to end
up with an integral--
now here's where it gets a
little tough-- here, you
wouldn't have tangent squared.
I think I might have said that
incorrectly earlier.
If this was any power,
here, you wouldn't
have tangent squared.
You would have had whatever--
if this was power n, this would
be power n minus 2, so
this would be power n minus 2.
Right?
So if this was power 8, when
we do the substitution,
this'll be power 6, so this
would be power 6, so this
would be power 6.
So you'd have to do
the process again.
This should remind you
of the reduction
formulas you've seen.
So it's good of it's even,
because if this is power 6,
you do the problem again and
you end up with, the second
term has a power 4.
You do the problem again, the
second term has a power 2,
and, oh, we know how
to deal with those.
So we like it when it's
an even power.
So that's kind of how these even
powers of tangent, you
can take, you can find
anti-derivatives of the even
powers of tangent by this
strategy that winds up, you
could actually get a reduction
formula out of this.
But I think that's where I
should stop with this problem,
and I hope you enjoyed it.