JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
I've got a nice exercise here
on Stokes' Theorem for you.
Now this problem is a little bit
more sophisticated than a
lot of problems we've been
doing in recitation.
So it requires a little bit
more thought, and it also
involves more mathematical
sophistication.
So we're doing a clever kind
of proof here that I like.
So hopefully you'll
like this one.
It's a little bit in a different
style than some of
the ones we've done.
So I think I need to talk about
it a little bit before
we get started.
So let's let F be the
field x, y, z.
So this is our radial field
that we've seen a lot in
recitation.
So what I'd like you to do is
prove that this field is not
the curl of any field
G. All right.
So I'd like you to show that
there's no field G such that F
is equal to the curl of G.
Now, rather than just saying
that to you and letting you
run off, I have a suggestion
for an interesting way you
could go about this.
And this interesting way is
going to use Stokes' Theorem.
So what I'd like you to do is
a proof by contradiction.
OK, so what you're going to do
is you're going to assume that
F is a curl.
OK?
So you're going to assume that
there is some G such that F is
curl G. And then you're going
to use that to get a
ridiculous conclusion.
So you're going to start with
that premise, and you're going
to end up with a
contradiction.
So these two arrows colliding
into each other is a symbol
that mathematicians use
for a contradiction.
So you're going to start from
this premise, and you're going
to reach a contradiction.
And what that's going
to show is that your
premise couldn't be right.
Yeah?
Because if you start from a true
premise, well then all
your conclusions should
be true as well.
So if you reach a false
conclusion, then you must have
had a false premise.
So what you're going to do is
you're going to take a sphere
of radius b centered
at the origin.
And a curve C on the sphere.
You know, a simple,
closed curve.
So assuming that F is this curl
of G, what I'd like you
to do is use Stokes' Theorem to
interpret the line integral
of G dot dr over C in
two different ways.
OK?
And interpreting this line
integral in two different
ways, you're going to reach a
contradiction, and that will
show that F really
isn't a curl.
So that's what I'd
like you to do.
So why don't you pause the
video, go ahead and see if you
can work that out, come
back, and we'll
talk about it together.
I hope you enjoyed working
on this problem.
Let's get started on it.
So as I was saying before we
started, what we're going to
do is we're looking for a
proof by contradiction.
So as the problem says, we're
going to start with a sphere.
And I'm going to take
this curve C--
some simply connected closed
curve that's going to go
around the back of the sphere,
and it's going to be oriented
one way or the other-- and
it's going to divide this
sphere into two pieces.
So there's the one cap on
one side of it, S1.
And then there's--
whatever the other piece on
the other side of it--
S2.
OK.
And so what we're going to do is
we're going to think about,
what is this line integral?
OK.
So this is our curve C
here on the sphere.
So the integral over C of G dot
dr. So this is what the
problem suggests
we think about.
So this is a line integral of
a field dot dr over the
boundary of two surfaces.
Right?
C is the boundary of S1,
and C-- if we orient
it the other way--
is the boundary of S2, when we
orient them both outwards.
OK, so what is this?
So Stokes' Theorem tells
us something
about this line integral.
So let's first think about
this as the top cap--
that cap S1--
with boundary C oriented
so that they
agree with each other.
So the normal is outwards
on the sphere, and C is
proceeding in the direction
that I've
drawn the arrow here.
Well, in that circumstance, we
have that the integral around
C of G dot dr by Stokes'
Theorem is equal to the
surface integral over S1 of curl
of G dot n with respect
to surface area.
Right?
So this is just Stokes'
Theorem.
Stokes' Theorem says the line
integral of G around the
boundary curve is equal to the
surface integral of the curl
of G over the region,
provided all of our
orientations are correct.
OK.
Well, we know though what
curl of G is, because by
assumption, F is equal to curl
of G. OK, so this is equal to
the surface integral over
S1 of F dot n dS.
So in the first step, we
use Stokes' Theorem.
In the second step, we use our
assumption that curl G is
equal to F. Well, now what.
But we know what F is.
Right?
F is this radial
field x, y, z.
So F and n are pointing
in the same direction.
They're parallel to each other.
n is a unit vector, so
this is just the length of F.
This F dot n is just the
length of F. And since we're
on a sphere of radius b,
this is just b.
OK, so the integrand
is just b.
So this is the integral over S1
of b dS, which is b times
the area of S1.
OK.
One thing I'd like you to notice
is that in particular,
this is a positive number.
b is positive and the
area is positive.
OK.
So that's our first
interpretation.
So we take our field G that
we suppose exists, and we
integrate it around this curve
C, and we apply Stokes'
Theorem, and then the fact that
we know what F is means
that we know what F dot n is,
and so that makes our surface
integral very easy to compute.
And it turns out to be b times
the area of S, which I just
happened to notice is
a positive number.
OK.
Well, now we can do the
same trick on the
other half of the sphere.
Right?
So we just did the
top cap here.
We did S1.
So now we have the bottom
cap, or whatever.
All the rest of the
sphere, S2.
OK.
So we can also get the integral
over C of G dot dr.
We can interpret it in terms
of Stokes' Theorem.
But notice then that in
C we still want to
use the same normal.
We like outwards pointing
normals.
So we're going to have to orient
C the other way in
order to make Stokes'
Theorem make sense.
So let's walk over here
where we have
some empty board space.
So we want to orient
C the other way.
So in other words, we're going
to take the negative of this
line integral.
So it's minus G dot dr. And if
we apply Stokes' Theorem to
this line integral-- so this is
the same line integral, but
with the opposite orientation
on C and so with
the opposite sign--
by Stokes' Theorem, this is
equal to the integral over S2
of the curl of G dot n dS.
And so the way I've set this up,
this is still my outward
pointing normal.
OK.
But again, we can use our
assumption and we can get curl
of G is equal to F, because
we're assuming
that G has this property.
So this is equal to the integral
over S2 of F dot n
with respect to surface area.
And again, n is the outward
pointing normal, and F is
parallel to it.
So this dot product is just the
length of F. The outward
pointing unit normal.
So this is just the length
of F, which is b.
So this is equal to b times
the area of S2,
which is also positive.
So what have we just shown?
Well, we started from the
assumption that there exists a
G such that F is the curl of
G. And starting from that
assumption--
let's look--
we showed that the line integral
around C of G dot dr
is equal to some positive
number.
And we also showed, over here,
that the negative of the line
integral of G around C is equal
to some positive number.
Well, this is clearly absurd.
That can't be true.
So starting from our assumption
that F was the curl
of G-- that there is a G such
the F is the curl of G--
we reached an absurd
conclusion.
We reached a conclusion that
the same number is both
positive and negative.
But that can't happen.
So that means our premise
had to be false.
OK.
So this is a contradiction.
So our assumption is false.
And our assumption that we used
to get this whole thing
started was that F was the curl
of some G. All right.
So what have we shown?
So we used a nice argument here
with Stokes' Theorem in
order to show that certain
fields aren't the curl of
other fields.
So Stokes' Theorem limits the
kind of fields that can be
curls of other fields.
Now perhaps, you may have
thought of other theorems that
you can use that also
limit what sorts of
fields can be curls.
And so there are other ways to
reach this true conclusion
that our field F--
whose components are x,
y, and z-- is not
the curl of any field.
This isn't the only way to
reach that conclusion.
But this is a nice way that
shows that Stokes' Theorem
puts some limitations on what
fields can behave like if
they're going to be curls.
I'll stop there.