CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to do
the following two problems,
both related to the same
position vector.
So we're starting off with a
position vector defined as r
of t is equal to 1 minus 2t
squared i plus t squared j
plus negative 2 plus
2t squared k.
So that's our position vector,
and I'd like us to do the
following two things.
And you'll notice this problem
is pretty much just a
computational problem.
We're going to make sure that we
know what these things I'm
about to talk about are, how you
define them, and how you
get from the position vector
to each of these things.
So we want to compute the
velocity, the speed, the
acceleration, and find
the unit tangent
vector for r of t.
And then, the second part, we
want to compute the arc length
of the trajectory from t
equals 0 to t equals 2.
So I'll give you a moment
to do that problem.
Why don't you pause the video,
work on the problem.
When you're ready to check your
work, bring the video
back up and I'll show
you how I do it.
OK, welcome back.
Well, hopefully, you felt
comfortable with answering
these questions.
So now I will answer them
and you can compare your
answers with mine.
So let me start off
with part a.
Part a, the first thing
we're going to
do is find the velocity.
So velocity is really-- all
we need to do is take the
derivative of the position
vector with respect to t.
So I'm just going to
take r prime of t.
And now I'm going to write it in
the shorthand notation that
you've seen with the brackets
to denote that it's not a
point, but it's a vector.
So this is what you've seen
to denote a vector
rather than a point.
So the derivative with respect
to t of the first component is
just negative 4t.
The derivative with respect to
t of the second component is
just 2t, because we had t
squared, so when we take its
derivative, we just get 2t.
And the third component was
negative two plus 2t squared,
so when I take its derivative,
I get a 4t, so that is
actually v of t, OK?
And then the next thing I asked
you to do is determine
the speed, and the speed, of
course, is just the length of
the velocity vector, right?
So we just need to find the
length of v. Now, to do that,
to remind ourselves what we do
for that, we actually take the
inner product of v with itself,
the dot product of v
with itself, and then we take
the square root of that.
So let's look at what the
dot product will be.
Let me find the squared thing
first, and then I will take
the square root.
So v dotted with v, the first
component I'm going to have
negative 4t quantity
squared, so that's
going to be 16t squared.
And then the second component
is going to be 2t quantity
squared, so I'm going to
have plus 4t squared.
And the third component is going
to be another-- it's
going to be 4t quantity
squared, so I
get another 16t squared.
So when I add those up, I
believe I get 36t squared?
Yes, good.
And so then, I just have to take
the square root of both
sides to get what the speed
actually is instead of the
square of the speed.
So I get 6t, OK?
So that's the velocity;
that's the speed.
Now I need to find the
acceleration and I need to
find the unit tangent vector.
OK, so let me see.
I will come over here.
Let me step off here and I will
find the acceleration and
the unit tangent vector.
So the acceleration, if you
remember, the acceleration is
actually just the derivative
of the velocity
with respect to t.
So the acceleration is going
to be the derivative of
negative 4t is just
negative 4.
The derivative of 2t is just 2,
and the derivative of 4t is
just 4, all with respect to t.
OK.
So the acceleration vector is
equal to negative 4 comma 2
comma 4, so you see this
actually has constant
acceleration.
So at any point, your
acceleration is always this
value, so it's not surprising
that our velocity is
increasing, and actually, it's
increasing-- you'll notice,
each of these components
is constant.
The velocity, each of the
components is linear, and if
we went back, we look at the
position vector, each of those
components is quadratic.
And this is exactly what you
expect from just your
understanding of derivatives in
single-variable calculus.
If you start off with a constant
and you find an
antiderivative, it's going to
be linear, and you find
another antiderivative, you're
going to have a quadratic, so
we shouldn't be surprised
by any of that.
Now we have one more thing to do
with Part a, and that is to
find the unit tangent vector.
And that's fairly easy, because
all we have to do is,
if you notice, we have the
velocity vector and we have
its length.
And so to find the unit tangent
vector, all we have to
do is take the velocity and
divide it by its length, and
that will normalize it.
That means that its length will
be one at that point,
because you're taking a vector,
dividing by its
length, so the length of the
new vector will have to be
length one.
So let me write that down.
And actually, I guess the point
to remember here is that
the velocity vector is tangent
to the path you're carving
out, to the trajectory.
OK, so this is a vector.
This is a scalar.
So I'm going to take 1 over 6t,
and I'm going to multiply
it by negative 4t, 2t, 4t, and
this gives me, when I do my
division, looks like it gives
me a negative 2/3,-- right--
1/3, 2/3.
So that is the unit tangent
vector, OK?
OK, and now, we have one more
point we want to make, and
that is having to do with the
arc length of the trajectory.
That was the second part of this
problem, was to find the
arc length of the trajectory
from t equals 0 to t equals 2.
So let me just draw
another line here.
And what we want to do there
then is-- really what we want
to do is we want to integrate
the speed, right?
We want to integrate the
speed from 0 to 2.
So this--
let me come over here--
this absolute v, you might have
also seen it written as
ds dt, right?
And so we want to integrate
this in dt--
in t-- sorry-- from 0 to 2.
And so we come over here.
We want to integrate
from 0 to 2, 6t dt.
That's fairly easy.
That's going to be 6t squared
over 2, evaluated from 0 to 2.
And so when I write that down,
I'm going to get 6 times 4
divided by 2, 24, divided by
2, I just get 12, and the
other term is 0.
So the arc length is--
of the trajectory from 0
to 2 is just 12 units.
So this really was a purely
computational type of problem.
All we were doing, if you come
back over here and you recall
what we were trying to
do, is we started off
with a position vector.
We just did a lot
of computation.
We found the velocity, the
speed, the acceleration, the
unit tangent vector, and then we
just wanted to find the arc
length of the trajectory.
So this is all very
computational, but just to
make sure we understood what
all the terms meant and how
they were related
to one another.
So I'll stop there.