JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome to recitation.
In lecture you've learned how
to compute derivatives of
polynomials, and you've learned
the relationship
between derivatives and
tangents lines.
So let's do a quick
example that puts
those two ideas together.
So here I have a question
on the board--
compute the tangent line to
the curve y equals x cubed
minus x at the point 2, 6.
So why don't you take a minute,
work on that yourself,
pause the video, we'll come back
and we'll do it together.
All right.
Welcome back.
So we have this function, y
equals x cubed minus x.
Let's just draw a quick
sketch of it.
So looks to me like it has
0's at 0, 1, minus 1.
And it sort of does something
like this in between.
Very rough sketch there.
And way over-- well, OK.
We'll call that the
point, 2, 6.
Feel a little sketchy,
but all right.
OK.
So we want to know what the
tangent line to the curve at
that point is.
So in order to do that, we
need to know what its
derivative is, and then that'll
give us the slope.
And then with the slope, we have
the slope and we have a
point, so we can slap that into,
say, your point-slope
formula for a line.
So, all right, so the
derivative of this
function is y prime.
So, OK, so here we have a sum
of two things, and they're
both powers of x.
And so we learned our rules
for a power of x that the
derivative of x to the n is n
times x to the n minus 1.
And so we also learned that the
derivative of a sum of two
things is the sum of
the derivatives.
So in this case, so the
derivative of x cubed minus x
is 3x squared minus 1.
OK.
So this is the slope of the
function in terms of x.
But in order to compute the
tangent line, we need the
slope at the particular
point in question.
Right?
This is really important.
So we aren't going to use 3x
squared plus 1 as our slope.
Right?
We want the slope at the
point, x equals 2.
Right?
OK.
So what we want for the slope
of the tangent line
is y prime of 2.
Right?
We want it at this point
when x is equal to 2.
So that's equal to, well,
3 times 2 squared is
12 minus 1 is 11.
So this is the slope, this is
the slope of the tangent line.
I just want to say this one
more time for emphasis.
This is a really common mistake
that we see on lots of
homework and exams when
teaching calculus.
You have to remember that when
you compute the slope of the
tangent line, you compute the
derivative and then you need
to plug in the value of x at
the point in question.
Or the value of x and y.
You know, you need to plug in
the values of the point that
you have. So here, the
derivative is 3x squared minus
1, so the slope at the
point, 2, 6 is 11.
It's just a number.
The slope at that point is
that particular number.
OK, so now, to compute the
tangent line, we have a point,
2, 6 and we have a slope, 11.
So we can plug into
point-slope form.
So the equation of
the-- one the--
tangent line is y minus 6 is
equal to 11 times x minus 2.
Right?
So it's y minus y0 is equal to
the slope times x minus x0.
If you like, some people
prefer to write their
equations of their lines in
slope-intercept form.
So if you wanted to do that,
you could just multiply
through by 11 and then bring
the constants together.
So we could say, or,
y equals 11x--
well, we get minus 22 plus 6--
is minus 16.
So either of those is
a perfectly good
answer to the question.
So that's that.