PROFESSOR: OK then, so now I'm
doing turning to problem
number eight, which is the last
one for which I need a
lot of time.
It's a difficult one.
It is the one that
is a mathematical
headache, let's face it.
And personally, I don't care
for that problem too much.
An electric dipole.
Let's try to make
a nice diagram.
x, y, z.
We have at location
a on the x-axis--
as location, I call that point
B. We have a charge + q.
On the other side, a from the
origin on the a-axis, and I
call that point capital A. We
have - q and you're being
asked now to calculate the
e-field everywhere in space.
Let us choose this point in
space, which has as a location
x, y, and z.
And let's try to make a
three-dimensional plot.
So this is the x position of
that point P, this is the z
position of that point
P. I hope that I can
draw straight lines.
It's not so bad.
And this is the y position of
that point P. I hope you can
see this as a box.
And at the corner of the box
here is that point P. And the
vector from the origin to point
P is this vector, and I
call that vector r.
And it is immediately obvious
that r, the magnitude of r,
equals the square root
of x squared plus y
squared plus z squared.
Now I'm going to first calculate
the electric field
at P only due to point B. And
then later we're going to add
the electric field
due to point A.
I'm going to shift the entire
coordinate system to point B.
So I'm going to make a new
coordinate system.
I call this y prime, I called
this x prime, and
I call this z prime.
This point is now not o, but
this point is now point B
where the + q charge is and here
is now that point P. The
distance between B and
P is now this vector.
I call this angle theta.
And I will try to make a
projection again, so that you
can see things.
This is the x prime position,
this is the z prime position.
Let's call these angle phi.
And so this is the y prime
position of P.
If this angle is theta, then of
course, this angle here is
also theta.
I want you to appreciate that
x prime is x minus a because
we have moved up the origin
only in the x-direction.
But that y prime is the same
as y and that z prime
is the same as z.
That has not changed.
So for point P, the x prime
position is x minus a, the y
position is the same as y prime,
and the z position is
the same as z prime.
What is the distance BP?
Well BP is the square root
now of x prime squared.
For which I can write down
x minus a squared.
Plus I can write down y prime
squared, but I might as well
write down y squared plus
z prime squared.
For which I might as well
write z squared.
What is the electric field, E,
at location P only due to this
+ q charge at position B?
We know that it is along the
line BP pointing outwards in
the direction BP.
So I will try to
put it in here.
I will call it E of P. It's in
the same direction as BP.
The magnitude of it equals q
divided by 4 pi epsilon 0
times BP squared.
Namely, the radius squared.
And it is pointing outwards
because this q is positive.
Now I want to know what the
x-component, the y-component,
and the z-component
is of this vector.
And now I need the help of these
angles theta, and these
angles phi.
It's now becoming a mathematical
problem.
No more physics.
E of x, as you can confirm for
yourself, is the magnitude of
EP times the sine of theta
times the cosine of phi.
E of y equals E of P times
the cosine of theta.
That's very easy to see.
Once you know what the magnitude
EP is, if you want
to know the projection in this
direction, then all you have
to do is multiply by the
cosine of theta.
And E of z equals EP times
the sine of theta
times the sine of phi.
Maybe I should have said
here, x prime.
The component in the
x prime direction.
Now, what is cosine theta?
By the way, the x prime
direction of course, is also
the direction of x.
So it's really absurd
to call it x prime.
It is the component of
E in the x direction.
So forget the prime.
Cosine theta equals y
prime divided by BP.
Convince yourself of that.
The sine of theta equals--
now I need this length for
the sine of theta.
And this length here equals
the square root of x prime
squared plus z prime squared.
And so the sine of theta equals
the square of x prime
squared plus z prime squared
divided by BP.
The cosine of phi equals x prime
divided by that same
square root, and the sine
of phi equals z prime.
Again, divided by that
same square root.
And I really think you should
check that very carefully.
And when I substitute these
cosines and sines in here, I
find a very simple answer.
I find that E of x equals this q
divided by 4 pi epsilon 0 BP
squared times x prime
divided by BP.
But remember, x prime
equals x minus a.
x prime equals x minus a.
I find for E of y, the
same thing times y
prime divided by BP.
But remember, y prime = y.
And I find for E of z, the
same things times z prime
divided by BP.
But remember, z prime = z.
And so, for this one charge at
location B, for that one
alone, I find q divided
by 4 pi epsilon 0.
And now I'm going to get here
all the rest. I get here x
minus a unit vector in the x
direction plus y unit vector
in the y direction plus
z times the unit
vector in the k direction.
And downstairs I get x minus a
squared plus y squared plus z
squared to the power 3/2.
That now is the complete
contribution only from the
charge at point B.
You now have to add the part
from point A. So you get a - q
divided by 4 pi epsilon 0.
And you get exactly the same
thing here, except that
wherever you had a -
a, you now get a +
a for obvious reasons.
You have to add the two up and
you'll see immediately the
answer that you were
given in your book.
Now they want you to simplify
this in the case that r is
much larger than a.
And this begins again, to be
mathematical manipulation.
And we're using Taylor's
expansion.
Keep in mind that this
vector is almost r.
It's almost the vector r because
the vector r equals x
times this plus y times this
plus z times the unit vector
in the z direction.
Except for this one here.
So I'm going to rewrite this
and I forget now this term.
Just forget that.
I'm only interested
in the geometry.
So I get r minus ai to
account for this.
And downstairs you can convince
yourself that this is
very close to r squared
to the power 3/2.
But not quite because you
have this term here.
And so if I work that out, I get
r squared minus 2ax to the
power of 3/2.
Have I cheated?
Yes, I have cheated
a little bit.
I have ignored a squared.
Because notice, when
you square this,
you get an a squared.
But since r is much, much
larger than a, I feel
completely justified
doing that.
But I'm going one step
further now.
By the way, I only take
this first term.
Second term you work
out yourself.
I'm going one step further.
And I'm going to use something
that, perhaps you remember
from last year.
That if x equals much, much
less than 1, that this
quantity is approximately
1 plus n times x.
And so I'm going to take
the r squared out of
the brackets here.
So I get r minus a
times the unit
vector in the x direction.
Then I get an r cubed here
because don't forget
there's this 3/2.
And I get 1 minus 2ax divided by
r squared to the power 3/2.
I know that this is much, much
smaller then 1 when r is much,
much larger than a.
And so, I can apply
the same Taylor
expansion that I have here.
And so this now becomes
r minus a i roof
divided by r cubed.
And then I have here
upstairs 1 plus 3ax
divided by r squared.
And this is now where my Taylor
expansion has come in.
You will now have to add the
term due to a, which is due to
the charge f point capital
A. Which is going to
be extremely similar.
Don't forget that the charge
was negative, so you put a
negative sign their first. And
then the signs of a will flip.
So this will become a plus and
this will become a minus.
What you do then is you're
going to add
those two terms up.
So this is the geometry term
only due to capital B. You add
to it the geometry term
only due to capital
A, to the - q charge.
And a lot of terms when you
work this out will vanish.
But they will not all vanish,
and so you'll find then that
the final E vector for the case
that r equals much, much
larger than a, you will find
that that is approximately q
times 2a divided by 4 pi
epsilon 0 r cubed.
And then here, you will get 3 r
vector times x divided by r
squared minus the unit vector
in the x direction.
That is the final result.
The result can be slightly
simplified if you want to.
And you are being asked
to simplify it.
You are being asked to somehow
manipulate this number to
convert it into a dot product.
If we leave this alone and you
are willing to spend the time,
you can prove that the term here
can also be written as 3
times r roof.
That means the unit vector
in the r direction.
Dotted with the unit vector
in the x direction.
This is a dot product.
Times the unit vector in the
r direction minus i.
And it took me a few minutes to
convince me that this and
this is the same.
And this whole term then,
of course, appears here.
And so what you see is that both
this term and this term
fall off as 1 over r cubed.
That may not be so obvious from
this, but it is obvious
once you have massaged
it in this form.
It's proportional to
1 over r cubed.
And that now is very
characteristic for a dipole.
If it were a monopole, if I had
only one charge, we know
we have already done it today,
then the electric field falls
off as 1 over r squared.
But when you have the dipole,
the positive charge and the
negative charge, in a way,
try to cancel each other.
The positive charge at point B
is having an electric field
vector pointing away from point
P. From B to P. But the
negative charge at point A is
introducing an E vector, which
is going towards point A. And
so in a way, they are almost
trying to cancel each other.
But not quite.
And that's why the dependence
becomes 1 over r cubed.
So it's much more sensitive
to how far you are away.
It falls off much faster.
When you're very, very far away,
you can sort of see that
the vector due to B, E due to
that point B. And that the
vector due to point A are
beginning to almost cancel
each other.
Because it's very,
very far away.
The fact that A and B are not
exactly at the same location
almost doesn't matter anymore.
All right, I will also want to
show you why this is minus
unit vector in the
x direction.
If we put a charge either on the
y-axis or on the z-axis,
then this term equals 0.
Convince yourself that both on
the y- and the z-axis, the dot
product between the unit vector
in the r and the unit
vector in the x direction
must be 0.
Because y direction and
z direction are
perpendicular to x.
So it's going to be 0.
Another way of putting it is
when x equals 0, you can also
see here that this term is 0.
So you only end up
with this term.
So let's take that situation
that we have now here the
x-axis, here the y-axis, and
that we have here a charge + q
at location B, and here a - q
at location A. Then we know
that the electric field
lines run like so.
And no matter where you are on
the y-axis, that means as x
equals 0, there will always be
an e vector pointing in the
minus x direction.
Always.
And that is exactly what you see
here if I have the right--
oh, sorry.
Sorry, my sheet fell all
the way on the floor.
But it was in the minus
i direction in the
unit vector x direction.
That's exactly what you see.
It's very easy to imagine.
OK, we've come to the end.
I have a minute and half left.
I will watch the tape to correct
possible slips of the
tongue and slips of the pen.
There are always some.
But I have enough time to
correct them, I hope.
So don't go away yet.
Over, but not yet out.
Well I watched my tape.
It must have been one
of my good days.
I only found two minor
slips of the tongue.
And I bet you, you
both caught them.
I mentioned here with
oxygen 8 protons I
said with two electrons.
But I wrote down the 8 and that
of course, is correct.
Protons--
8 protons and 8 electrons.
And then at the dipole problem,
I said if you put a
charge on the y-
or the z-axis.
Of course, I didn't mean
putting a charge there.
The charge is always on the
x-axis, + a and - a.
What I meant is, if you measure
the electric field on
the y- and the z-axis.
And so, that's what I did
here in this drawing.
You are looking here at the
electric field are you will
see that then the electric
field is always
in the minus x direction.