PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, I'd like
to talk about
positive definite matrices.
And specifically, we're going to
analyze several properties
of positive definite matrices.
And specifically, we're going
to look at why each one of
these following statements
is true.
So first off, why every positive
definite matrix is
invertible.
Why the only positive definite
projection matrix is the
identity matrix.
If d is a diagonal matrix with
positive entries, show that it
must also be positive
definite.
And then lastly, if S is a
symmetric matrix where the
determinant S is bigger than
0, show why this might not
necessarily imply that it's
positive definite.
So I'll let you think about
these for a moment.
And I'll come back
in a second.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
OK.
So let's take a look at part
A. So part A is asking why
every positive definite
matrix is invertible.
Well, let's just recall that if
A is a matrix and if A is
invertible, then this
necessarily implies that the
determinant of A is non-zero.
And I'm going to just write out
detA as the product of the
eigenvalues of A. So lambda
1 to lambda n are the
eigenvalues
of A. OK.
In addition, if A is positive
definite, what does this say
about the eigenvalues of A?
Well, it says that each
eigenvalue of A, lambda 1,
lambda 2, dot, dot, dot, to
lambda n, each one of them
must be bigger than 0.
So this statement that each
eigenvalue of A is bigger than
0 is completely equivalent to A
being positive definite for
symmetric matrices A.
So if I have a whole bunch of
eigenvalues and each of them
are bigger than 0, what does
this say about detA?
Well, I can take the product
of all these eigenvalues.
And of course, the product of
a whole bunch of positive
numbers must also be positive.
So if the quantity is positive,
then it certainly
cannot equal 0.
So this proves that detA
is not equal to 0.
Hence, A must be invertible.
OK.
So for part B, we're asked to
show that the only positive
definite projection matrix
is the identity matrix.
So again, how do we tackle
this problem?
We're going to look at
the eigenvalues.
So remember if P is a
projection, what does it say
about the eigenvalues of P?
Well, it says that the
eigenvalues of P
are either 0 or 1.
So this is point one.
Point two, if P is a positive
definite, what does that say
about the eigenvalues of P?
Well, as I've noted before, it
means that the eigenvalues are
bigger than 0.
So if P is a projection and it's
positive definite, the
only possible eigenvalues that
are both 0 and 1 and bigger
than 0 are 1.
So the conclusion is that
the eigenvalues of P
must all equal 1.
So which matrix has eigenvalues
1 and is also symmetric?
Well, the only matrix that
satisfies this property is the
identity matrix.
Now you might ask, how do
you actually show that?
Well, you could argue
as follows.
If P is diagonalizable and
every symmetric matrix is
diagonalizable--
so I'm not making this up.
So if P is diagonalizable, then
you can always write P as
some matrix, U, times
a diagonal matrix.
And we know in this case,
the diagonal matrix has
eigenvalues 1.
So it's actually the identity
matrix times the inverse of
the eigenvector matrix.
But of course, this is just U
times U inverse, which then
gives me the identity
at the end.
So U times the identity
times U inverse.
This is just U times
U inverse.
And of course, U and
U inverse collapse
back down to the identity.
So this shows you that the
only matrix that has
eigenvalues of 1 is the
identity matrix.
So that's just to cross all the
T's and dot all the I's.
OK.
For part C, we're given D as a
diagonal matrix with positive
entries on the diagonal.
Now we have to show that
it's positive definite.
OK.
So let me write D as follows.
I'll just write it like this.
I'm going to use a compact
notation, which is sometimes
seen diag d1, d2, dn.
So d is a diagonal matrix
whose elements along the
diagonal are d1, d2, dot,
dot, dot, to dn.
Now what does it mean
for a matrix
to be positive definite?
Well, it means that for any x,
for any vector x, I have to
look at the product
x transpose Dx.
And I have to show that
it's bigger than 0.
And I should qualify this and
say that the vector we're
looking at is x not
equal to 0.
So we're now looking
at the 0 vector.
But for D to be positive
definite, we have to show that
x transpose Dx is
bigger than 0.
This is just one way to show
that it's positive definite.
It's not the only way.
So if I write x out using
components, x1, x2, dot, dot,
dot, to xn--
I'll write it like this--
then you can work out the
quantity x transpose Dx.
And we see that we get
a sum of squares.
We get d1 times x1 squared plus
d2 x2 squared plus dot,
dot, dot plus dn xn squared.
Now by definition, each
coefficient is positive.
A sum of a square is positive.
so A product of a
positive number
with a square is positive.
And then of course, a sum of
positive numbers is going to
be positive.
So this means the whole
thing is positive.
Now there's other more efficient
ways of getting at
this using other
tricks we know.
For example, if we're given a
diagonal matrix, we know its
eigenvalues are already d1,
d2, dot, dot, dot, to dn.
And we know that a matrix with
positive eigenvalues is
already positive definite.
But this is kind of starting
from the base to show that
it's positive definite.
And now lastly, let's
look at part D.
So S is a symmetric matrix
with detS bigger than 0.
Show that S might not
necessarily be positive definite.
So there's lots of
counter examples.
I only need to construct one.
So I'm looking at S, which
is a symmetric matrix.
So I'm just going
to throw in some
numbers on some off diagonals.
So I'll just pick one.
And now I need to pick some
numbers along the diagonal.
And the easiest way to do it is
just to pick two negative
numbers on the diagonal.
Because if there's a negative
number on a diagonal, then we
know S can't be positive
definite.
And I'll say more about
that in a second.
So I can just pick negative
2 and negative 3.
So let's quickly check
what detS is.
Well, it's negative 2 times
negative 3 minus 1.
So this gives me 6 minus
1, which is 5.
So by construction, detS is
positive, which is good.
And then as I mentioned before,
if there's negative
elements along the diagonal of
the matrix, that matrix can't
be positive definite.
Well, why is that?
Well, suppose I wanted to take
a look at this upper left
component, negative 3, and it's
negative, how do I show
that that implies S is not
positive definite.
Well, what I can do is I can
look at the product x
transpose Sx.
And what I do is I look at it.
I just take one value of x.
So we know that this has to be
positive for every value of x.
So I can pick any
value I want.
So I can take x, say,
1, 0 transpose.
And when I do this, we end up
getting that x transpose Sx is
equal to negative 3.
So notice how by taking 1 in the
first entry and 0 on the
second entry, that picks
out the upper left
corner negative 3.
If I were to take 0 here and 1
here, it would pick out the
negative 2 entry and S. So by
picking 1 in entry i of a
vector x, and then computing
this product x transpose Sx, I
pick out the i-th element
along the diagonal.
And since that element is
negative, this shows me that
along the direction 1,
0, the product x
transpose Sx is also negative.
And hence, S can't possibly
be positive definite.
OK.
So just to summarize, we've
taken a look at a couple
matrices and a couple different
properties of
positive definite matrices.
And notably, we've used the
eigenvalues to get a handle of
the positive definite
matrices.
And I hope these provide
some useful tricks.
And I'll see you next time.