The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: This is our first lab
session for CMS.608 and,
for folks, who wasn't here
this past Wednesday?
One, two--
AUDIENCE: Who wasn't?
PROFESSOR: Who was not
here on Wednesday?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: And so,
you weren't here.
Let's see, we have some blank
index cards underneath the--
AUDIENCE: The plastic
Tupperware, I think.
[INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: So you can just fill
in your name, your email
address plus favorite board
game or card game.
The email address, basically,
just gets added
to the email list.
Did anyone not get an email
from Jason yesterday?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, last night.
PROFESSOR: You didn't
get an email?
AUDIENCE: I don't think so.
PROFESSOR: OK.
So the email basically said
that there was a swap
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: --of Friday the
17th, and the 20th.
So, basically, we're swapping
your readings around--
and that's really the
only thing, right?
AUDIENCE: Oh, and I fixed the
link for Zimmerman's article.
PROFESSOR: And, unfortunately,
Eric Zimmerman didn't migrate
his website terribly well,
so all of his pictures--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: I actually have one
of his games, SISSYFIGHT 3000.
In fact, this is before
SISSYFIGHT 3000, so this is
probably 2999, which is going to
be the non-digital version,
which is the whole point.
It is actually a
computer game.
It is a pretty decent flash
multiplayer game, back in the
day when flash multiplayer games
were not that common.
And if you haven't played it
before online, after today,
especially if you had a chance
to play with the card deck,
try out the online version.
Do a Google search
for SISSYFIGHT
3000, and try it online.
Hopefully, there are still
people playing it, because you
need kind of like a minimum
of five people to
get a good game going.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] the
one that was taken down.
AUDIENCE: Aw, suck.
It was such a great game.
PROFESSOR: Never mind.
Basically, what you had was, you
got avatar customization
in your game.
You could create your character,
and you could--
you had this really cool retro
pixelated look back in the day
when retro pixelated stuff
was not that popular yet.
But the game-play was pretty
much exactly the same as what
a card game has.
The readings today basically
covered a lot of jargon that
we're going to be using
a lot of that for
the rest of the class.
For the most part, I'm not
going to go through every
single one of them because
you folks can read.
And if I mention something and
you don't get it, you can
always check back there.
So just remember that the first
chapter in Braithwaite
is a pretty good glossary of
terminology that we're going
to keep using.
But one of the big things that
they ask is, what is a game?
And it's one of those--
Does anybody actually want
to offer their definition
of what a game is?
AUDIENCE: A game is something
that involves players and they
set up, define rules beforehand,
rules that you
have to abide by, whether they
be, you can't go outside this
limit, you have to abide by
certain questions and orders.
Something that has structure
that is meant for one person
to go from Point A to Point B.
PROFESSOR: OK.
Structure, rules,
limits, players.
Anything--
AUDIENCE: It's fun.
AUDIENCE: Fun.
AUDIENCE: It accomplishes
some goal.
PROFESSOR: Goal.
AUDIENCE: So you always
have some goal.
AUDIENCE: You're working
towards something.
PROFESSOR: Anything else?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Or it's an
abstract system.
Often an abstraction of
some real system.
PROFESSOR: An abstract system.
So these are actually pretty
good benchmarks.
Now there are, again, as Brandon
describes, there isn't
one that's just the canonical
answer for everything.
It really depends on which
theorist you are reading at
any given time.
But usually it will involve a
significant subset of all of
these in the definition.
And I like to keep things broad
and vague because, for
the most part, if you define
yourselves too strictly, it
might be useful.
You're an academic and you need
to write papers about it,
but if you're a designer and
you're just trying to create
something fun--
the word I would use is
"engaging," because fun means
a lot of different things to
a lot of different people.
Engaging basically means that
this is going to be something
that you're going to want to
do for a while, that is
motivating.
It might be terrifying
you out of your wits.
Some people enjoy that, or would
find that experience
compelling.
I mean they may not
call it fun.
So I call that engagement.
The problem with using fun and
engaging as a metric for
defining what a game is, is
that that means that a bad
game is not a game.
A game that fails to achieve
fun, that fails to be
engaging, is not a game.
But I wouldn't go that far,
largely because that means a
lot of stuff that I created
is not a game.
But it should give you the--
there is no magic point where
a game becomes --the thing
that you're building becomes
fun and then
suddenly becomes a game.
I can't even imagine someone
making that argument, that
it's not a game until
it's fun.
But I much rather sort of say,
fun and engagement is kind of
more of a metric of how well
designed your game is, not
necessarily whether your
game is a game.
But that is a goal of a game
designer, to try to create an
engaging experience, something
that people are
going to want to do.
I know some game designers
who think that is not,
in fact, their job.
Their job is to maximize
revenue, for instance.
Especially if you work in social
games, there's a lot of
discussion now in how business
and game design is basically
just one thing now.
The whole point of game design
is, how do we get people to
pay a little bit more?
Zynga's going to be in town
on September 20th,
they're giving a talk.
That has those two
points in it.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So I always thought
of design as something that
you're working towards.
But all these other things--
a game should have players.
Again, I don't want to be too
strict on that because I've
certainly seen games that
play themselves.
Anyone here involved
in Battle Code?
That game pretty much
plays itself, right?
I mean, you set it going and
then one side wins, but
there's no human person at least
during the time when the
games actually being played.
Or you could argue that the
whole course of Battle Code--
for those people who don't know
it, it's an IP course, I
believe, where Course 6 students
basically write bits
of AI to play a real-time
strategy game against some of
other team's AI.
And the basic idea is that, you
win a real-time strategy
game, your AI wins, but there's
no human actually
playing it at a given time.
But, of course, there are humans
writing the AI, so if
you think of the entire class
as a game, then there are
players, there are people.
I suddenly see people make a
case that there are games that
are zero player, and I've heard,
for example, there's a
game out there called Novick,
which is largely a game about
coming up with rules.
And there is a system, which
are actually in the rules
themselves, about how
you change rules.
And, of course, those rules
themselves can be changed.
And that changes the way how you
change rules and, by the
time you actually play the game,
someone's already won.
Because somebody in the game
has no legal moves.
That's the whole game, is
basically making it impossible
for someone else, or someone
else except for you, to win.
So does that game actually
have players?
Well, yes, it does because you
guys are arguing over all the
rule changes through the
rules of the game.
But, in a sense, it had no
players because the game never
actually got played.
The rules are basically stating,
this is an unplayable
game for everybody except
for one person
who's playing the game.
Goals are one of those things
that I used to be very, very
adamant about.
Like a game had to
have a goal.
You have to know what they're
going towards, and if you
don't have that, then it's a
toy or something, it's a
dollhouse, it's an experiment.
The Sims was the one that I was
like railing about when I
was an undergraduate.
You know-- that's not a game.
And, of course, I was working
with many colleagues and
eventually came across, came
over to decide that it doesn't
matter whether I think
it is a game or not.
If it's in the game shelf of
Best Buy, it's a game.
Because people think it's a
game, and if enough people
think it's a game, then it
might as well be a game.
Otherwise--
because that's what people
think it's going to be.
So when you come up with your
game, I would say that goals
are one of those things that
helps steer player behavior.
So it's one of those tools that
you have as a designer to
basically say, this is
important, this is not.
Reaching the end of 100 meters
is important for a sprinter.
That end is really not
interesting for somebody who
is running 400 meters
or a 50 meter dash.
But that gives someone
a direction
for them to go towards.
But there are plenty of games
where you have to
invent your own goals.
Other than Sims, can anyone
think of any?
Where inventing your own goals
is kind of the fun.
AUDIENCE: A lot of NLRPGs.
PROFESSOR: A lot of NLRPGs.
They have goals.
They have quests.
But that's not where a lot
of fun is, necessarily.
AUDIENCE: Second Life.
PROFESSOR: Second Life.
A lot of virtual worlds.
AUDIENCE: A game like EVE?
PROFESSOR: EVE?
Yeah.
EVE, you kind of, want to, like
you have to set your own
goals, because whatever is in
the game is only good enough
for a single player--
to tell whether a single player
whether they're doing
well or not.
But EVE is not about
a single player.
EVE is about thousands and
thousands of people playing
simultaneously.
Actually, have people
heard of EVE?
All right.
Yeah.
So, cool.
Cool.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Oh, cool.
In Iceland?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: Was it like
really cheap when
you went over there?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR: Could you have bought
the entire studio?
AUDIENCE: No.
Unfortunately.
But it was really cheap.
PROFESSOR: So they must
have been making tons
of money over there.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, they're
making money in US
Dollars and the Euro.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: They probably hire
most, yeah, support most of
the economy.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: The capitol is
20,000 people so...
PROFESSOR: So I'll say goals are
very important tools and
as a result of that you see them
in a lot of the games.
And for most of the games that
you guys are going to be
building, you're going to give a
very clear goal of this what
you want to do--
earn a certain amount of money,
prevent your opponent
from doing anything else,
take over all the land.
That sort of thing.
Let's see.
Oh, I'll get to the
rules last.
But, system.
Systems are--
I might already have mentioned
this in the last class, but
games are systems in a way that
most MIT engineers would
think of systems.
They're a bunch of
interconnected little modules,
all of them with sort of
predictable behavior, and then
you put them into a big
interconnected system, and it
is no longer really all that
predictable anymore.
At least that's the kind of
games that we're interested in
in this class.
There's also the game-theory
games, where the whole point
of it is trying to predict what
could possibly happen.
And those are great thought
experiments and there's some
really, really interesting math
behind all them and some
interesting rules of thumb
that can come out.
But for the most part, we aren't
going to go into too
much detail about that, largely
because I'm not a
mathematician or economist, so
I don't really have a good
sense of game theory.
Just be aware that there is
this whole field of game
theory in economics.
If you're doing a game like an
auction system, if you're
doing a game where people are
doing either a lot of
simultaneous moves or the whole
point of the game is
trying to predict what strategy
your opponent's going
to do, you might actually want
to read up a little bit on
game theory, if nothing else,
just to give you some
vocabulary to talk about it with
your teammates, and some
tools to be able to think
through some of the design
problems that you've got.
And we do have one session
where I'll
introduce some of that.
Finally, we are getting
to rules.
The things that give your game
structure and the constraints
of the things you can't do.
You can't move from here to
there without having your foot
tied to another player, that
sort of constraint.
Or a rule being you can't see
anything during a certain part
of the game.
There are two bits of
terminology introduced by
Brenda and Ian Schreiber in
their book, which is in Core
Mechanic and Core Dynamic.
So before I'm going to go into
the core mechanic and core
dynamic, I'm going to talk about
mechanic and dynamic.
Anyone want to throw out the
definition of mechanic?
AUDIENCE: I reckon it's sort of
the actions like a player
takes during a game like the
physical actions he takes.
PROFESSOR: OK.
The actions that a player
decides to take?
AUDIENCE: Decides
to take, yeah.
PROFESSOR: Sorry if this
is a little low,
I saw Patrick and--
or did those hands
just go down?
I thought I saw a
few more hands.
AUDIENCE: Actions
that are sort of
designed by the game designer.
So it's intended actions.
PROFESSOR: Design is definitely
a good point.
A game mechanic is definitely
something that you as a game
designer control.
There are--
if a player decides to do
something in the game that you
did not explicitly think
about, and you did not
explicitly say, all right this
is what players are going to
be doing in a game,
then it might not
actually be a mechanic.
It might be something that
you're discovering in your
play testing that you will
turn into a mechanic.
But because it's not designed,
it's kind of--
it becomes more like a strategy,
actually, like an
emergent strategy.
Sorry.
You were saying, Jeremy?
AUDIENCE: Is it more
like a dynamic ?
PROFESSOR: Possibly.
There are times where it is.
Yeah.
Actually let's throw out
definitions of dynamic, what
do people--
well, Jeremy?
AUDIENCE: It's behavior that
emerges from mechanics?
PROFESSOR: It's emergent
behavior?
What else?
AUDIENCE: Use of mechanics that
isn't directly stated in
the rules of the game.
PROFESSOR: OK.
So unstated.
I'm running out of space here.
I thought I saw a hand
on this side.
No?
OK.
All right.
So, yeah, dynamics
are basically
interactions of mechanics.
It's like you don't have
anything that may necessarily
explicitly say, because of this
one rule and because of
this other rule, and because of
the things that the players
can do in that, a good
strategy is to
do something else.
So let me see whether I can
think of an example.
Right now, everything
that's coming
to my head is StarCraft.
AUDIENCE: Has that been the case
for the last few weeks?
PROFESSOR: Unfortunately, yes.
By the way, if anybody
is playing
StarCraft, I need testers.
AUDIENCE: StarCraft
II or StarCraft I?
PROFESSOR: Two.
AUDIENCE: Ah, yes.
PROFESSOR: I need testers for
a math game I'm designing.
AUDIENCE: I play Zerg.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: OK.
AUDIENCE: So there's this role
selection mechanic where
everybody picks the thing which
they want to happen
during their turn.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: and mostly everybody
chooses to build
a particular cross.
And the dynamic that emerges
from the sequence of play,
which goes clockwise is that
it's best to optimize your
strategy so that you were doing,
so you were benefiting
from the role of the person
to your right,
is likely to choose.
But you're making the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] of the person
you elect is most likely
win a ship.
So mechanically it's role
selection and turn order and
then the dynamic
is the strategy
written by the program.
PROFESSOR: Which gives
you some idea what
to select as opposed--
the mechanic is you
can select.
The dynamic is, here are a
couple of strategies that you
can use in sort of assessing
what would best to select.
And if all the players start
to understand that, then it
almost becomes like a second
layer of rules almost.
If anyone has played a game
like Bridge, for instance,
there's actually a ton of things
that are assumed in the
play which are not actually in
the rules of Bridge when it
comes to bidding.
Like when you call out a bid,
it's highly dependent on what
you actually have in
your card hand.
And that's not actually written
in the rules anywhere.
But the assumption is that there
is optimal way to do it.
And since there's optimal way to
do it, everyone's expected
to know those optimal ways.
The example in the book was
chess moves, like every single
piece of chess has a set
of moves that it
can perform, right?
Pawns go one or two
squares, depending
where they're starting.
The bishops move diagonally.
But there are also
opening gambits.
Opening gambits that are also
well known, at least among
professional chess players, and
the idea being, oh, this
person is using this opening,
therefore, if I counter it
with this response, I actually
have a reasonable chance of
actually winning this game,
and professional chess
players know this.
The other thing that comes up in
chess, which is not in the
book, is there is the concept
of threatened squares.
If you move, if there is a
square where there is no piece
on a chess board--
everyone here knows the rules
of chess, more or less?
So say you've got a bishop--
and this is quite a simple chess
board-- and you've got
the bishop, and it can move
like that, right?
So every single square on these
lines is threatened.
It's something which the
bishop could move to.
Unless, of course, it's lost by
a pawn or something, then
these are not going to be
threatened by the pawns.
If your knight obviously is no
longer straight lines, it
becomes a specific or sort of
like stochastic pattern of
squares that become
threatened.
But the idea of here's this
square now that nobody dares
move into until something's
done about that bishop.
Either something gets moved in
its way, or something takes
out the bishop or forces the
bishop to move by threatening
it instead in a way that
it cannot respond.
So threatened squares is not a
rule in chess, but it greatly
shapes your decision making
and that's the difference
between dynamic and mechanic.
There's a lot of strong
correspondence between
mechanics and rules.
But--
and I had a long, long little
rant about exactly what the
difference is between
mechanics and rules.
And what I basically--
I know I'm going to get the rant
right now, but it's like
overlapping venn diagram.
There's a very, very large area
where it's exactly the
same thing.
My general rubric for trying
to figure out whether
something is a mechanic or not
is whether this is the thing
that changes the state
of the game.
It is an action.
It is something that someone is
going to be doing to change
the state of what the game is.
In chess, that's largely the
movement of the piece.
If it's ultimate.
It could be just physical
movement.
You are limited on when you
can physically move.
If you have that frisbee,
you're not moving.
Well, your feet are
not moving.
I believe that's a
rule of Ultimate.
So the reason why I use that
definition is because there
are occasionally times when I
need to talk about mechanics
that players aren't
actually doing.
The game requires certain pieces
to move in a certain
way, certain things to
happen in the game in
such and such a time.
For instance, you have
these die rolls and--
actually, that's not
a good example.
Let me think.
Right at the beginning of
Settlers of Catan there is the
way how you set up the board,
and that establishes what a
game state is going to be.
It changes game state by giving
you a game state in the
first place.
I consider that a mechanic.
That is something
that's going--
that's not one rule.
That's actually a whole
collection of rules.
And if you're interested in
finding out what those rules
are, the box is actually in
that closet over there.
There are something like five or
six different rules on how
you set up your board.
It's going to be, set up your
game state, and I consider
that a mechanic.
How people do bidding
and buying things
in Settlers of Catan?
That's dynamic.
There are no real rules on
how much something costs.
That's up to the players to
work out on your own.
So that's how I sort of consider
the difference
between dynamic and mechanic.
They're really, really useful
concepts because really, for
the most part, as a designer you
have an idea of what kind
of dynamics are interesting.
And the more games that you
play, the more inspiration you
get from various sources, your
range of different ideas of
what kind of dynamics might be
interesting is going to expand.
But all you have control on are
mechanics, the specific
rules that you're giving, note
that game mechanics don't
necessarily need to be written
or described out.
This is one thing that I think
you and your teammates should
figure out when you're
talking about
mechanics for a given project.
Are we just talking about the
things we are writing down?
Because there are
some assumptions
that are just given.
We are playing a game, and we're
not playing some sort of
schoolyard game or something,
hitting people with solid
objects that's disallowed.
Not necessarily something
you need to write down.
Unless you're playing
with certain people.
You can assume that
the game again --
things like how fast people
normally do things.
There's a game over here called
Falling, which is
actually a real-time
card game.
It goes as fast you can possibly
play it, and there is
no there is no limit on how fast
you can play these cards.
But there is a real physical
limit on how fast you could
physically grab the card out of
your hand and put it down.
So, actually, it's not even on
your hand, your just moving
cards on table.
So make sure you give
that a try today.
Finally, we'll be getting
to aesthetics, I think--
next class?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So, which
is another thing
which a game designer--
in fact, what I would like game
designers to actually
spend more time thinking about,
which is, what is the
feeling you want your
player to have?
As opposed to, this
might be fun, or
this might be engaging.
And specifically,
how is it fun?
And how is it engaging?
Is it fun as in like,
yes, victory!
I have crushed all
my opponents.
Or is it fun as if, well, we
had a really good time
together and we got to know
each other really well.
There are games that are
designed for both of those.
And what is the aesthetic
you're going for?
Are you going for something
poetic?
fiercely competitive?
Tournament competitive?
Are you going for just a nice
little social experiment?
Core mechanics and core dynamics
are a tool, again,
for designers.
The idea of--
there really isn't a huge
difference between what's a
core mechanic and what's just
a mechanic, except inside a
designer or design team's
discussion.
The idea of having a core
mechanic is you identify this
is what our game's about.
Or a core dynamic means this
And a lot of core mechanics in
first person shooters is
pointing and shooting.
I'm going to point at something
and I'm going to
launch a projectile that way,
and that projectile is going
to move in some physical
properties.
Maybe it arcs, maybe
it goes straight.
I would say that the core
mechanic of Halo isn't
actually that.
Who has not played Halo or
seen someone play Halo?
OK.
So the idea, core mechanic--
or I think my Bungie calls it
the core game play loop--
of Halo is, you shoot at
something, you take cover, you
throw a grenade at it, you wait
for the grenade to go
off, and then you shoot at
it again until it dies.
That's pretty much all
you are doing for the
entirety of Halo 1.
I'm sure Halo 2, Halo 3 gets
complicated, but de-identify
that as you actually read the
post-mortems and if you read
the talks that are given,
they say those--
I can't remember if it was 20
seconds or five seconds of
game play which is used
to describe that.
I think that five seconds
of game play is what
they focused on.
And if they could get every
little thing in that sequence
correct, they can repeat that
same thing at infinitum, and
you'll still will
be having fun.
Halo 1, everyone.
They're kinda right.
But the idea being, if you've
got a core mechanic, and
you've got one thing in your
game that someone's going to
be doing over and over and over
again, all your players
are going to be doing over and
over again-- maybe it's
bidding because it may be some
kind of auction game.
In Falling and Pit,
it's transferring
cards to other people.
I'm trying to think of the other
games that we got here.
In SISSYFIGHT, I would imagine
the main core mechanic would
be putting down the card and
everyone revealing the cards
simultaneously, because of you
all take simultaneous turns.
Make sure that's really,
really fun.
And Yahtzee is rolling dice.
That action, that thing that
you're going to be doing over
and over again, has to be at
least fairly engaging.
Because if you can't get that
right, then what happens is
that that same movement, that
happens 30 to 50 times in your
game, just--
the badness just gets multiplied
by 30 or 50.
And you don't want that.
So for core mechanics, I would
say the thing that happens in
your game the most--
and you want to make sure that
that part is as engaging as
possible because it gives you a
rubric to say, what's not a
core mechanic might be,
in fact, expendable.
You might not actually
need it in your game.
So if you've got a problem--
this game takes too long to
play, this game's too hard to
learn, this game's over too
fast, it's too random
or something--
take a look at all the
things that are--
but first make sure that your
core mechanics not the cause
of the problem.
But if the core mechanics
doesn't seem to be causing the
problem, that seems to be
working, something else in the
game is not working.
Everything else expendable.
And so you can look at
everything else in the game,
all these other rules that
you've got, and say, how does
that work with a
core mechanic?
How does that help?
How does that hurt the
core mechanic?
It just helps your discussion
as a team.
Or as an individual game
designer, it helps you to
think about what could
we throw out?
What could we keep?
Similarly for core dynamic.
It's like here's this particular
interaction that we
really, really want.
And SISSYFIGHT is guessing
what other people
are going to do.
I'm trying to think
of other examples.
And like territorial
space acquisition.
I guess Go is about taking
over territory in space.
If that's your core dynamic,
you say that's kind of fun,
just making sure that I'm in
control of space and nobody
else can do anything they
want to do in a
certain part of the board.
That's fun.
That's what I'm going for;
that's my core dynamic.
That's what this game
is all about.
Then you can look at every
single mechanic, even your
core mechanics, and say, is
it all serving that goal?
Now there's a whole bunch of
tips right at the end of
chapter one of Challenges for
Game Designers about how to
break designer's block.
But I would say, actually, those
things are just things
you should be doing all
the time, not just
when you have a problem.
But you should be
experimenting.
Things like, OK, you've
got a variable.
Draw two cards every
turn or something.
Multiply it by two.
See what it does to your game.
Halve it.
Draw one card.
See what it does to your game.
Through a rule-out, and that
sort of gets you to the whole
iterative design thing, is
that you don't actually,
because games are systems,
these complex little
collections of seemingly simple
things, you don't
actually know how these changes
are really going to
affect the game.
You may have a hunch, but until
you actually play it
out, you don't actually know.
So the whole point of
iterative design in
engineering as well as in
game design is that
you make the change.
It has to be a substantial
change.
And then you actually
put it to the test
and see what happens.
This means, of course, testing,
and testing takes a
long time and if you're going to
be making a game that takes
a long time, then your testing
gets even longer.
So for the first project that's
going to be coming up,
assignment one, you want to be
aiming for games that take
really not very long to play.
These games that we got today,
I'm not sure about
[INAUDIBLE], but I know
everything else that we got on
that table, is pretty
darn fast.
Which means if you play an hour
with four people who've
never played your game before,
you get through two or three
rounds, four rounds, of them.
Each time, you'll be teaching
a rule once, sharing and
seeing how that changed
the game.
If you've got a game that takes
an hour to play, and
believe me, a lot of the
projects that we've gotten
from previous semesters take
at least an hour to play.
You've got four people for an
hour and another definition of
a single-player game.
Because by the time they finish
learning your game ,
half your time's up.
So that's a process that we will
like you all to be using
in your teams and your
assignments, is iterative
design process.
Right from the beginning--
I wish I had more space--
but we're going to start
with brainstorming.
That's actually going to be
Friday, the 17th, where we'll
actually sort of--
for folks who haven't
necessarily formally learned
brainstorming we're just going
to do a quick refresher so
that everyone sort of
is on the same page.
You learn how to do
brainstorming.
You come up with a basic idea
of a game, and you start to
identify things that could
be your core dynamics.
You think of what sort of core
mechanics could address that.
Knock something up really,
really quickly with the
crappiest materials you
can get your hands
on and start playing.
Since nobody on your team
knows, really, what game
you're making at that point of
time, you can probably test it
with your team.
As soon as you do it a few
times, your team becomes
useless as testers because you
already know too much about
the game and what the game
could have been.
And you start playing it in
ways that a fresh person,
who's never seen your
game before,
wouldn't even consider.
So you actually want to keep
looking for people who've
never played your game before.
So the next step would be to
broaden it to other teams in
this class.
Because everyone's going to be
broken up in more or less
teams of three or four.
That's pretty much, I'm going
to take this game that we
designed for a team of three or
four, and give it to that
team of three or four.
And then you play their game,
and give each other feedback.
And that lasts for about one
more session, and after that,
everyone in the class
is useless now.
So you have to look for
dormmates, friends, people on
the street, just go right ahead
and try to get as much
feedback as you can.
There is some value in
replaying, especially later on
once your rules are pretty
set in that people start
developing strategies, still
some of them emergent
behaviors, things to
understanding sort of higher
level play of the game, and
you do want to test that.
But don't let that prevent
you from also
testing with fresh players.
Because in the end, you
have to get past
that initial hurdle.
Anytime someone sees your game,
they are going to have
to learn your game from
scratch at least once.
And if they don't even get
that far, they're never
playing your game a second
or third time.
So don't optimize for the people
who play your game for
four weeks, because you really
want the people who've only
played it once to have
a good time as well.
That's not necessarily the case
if you're making a huge,
well-funded game based
on a franchise
that's been around forever.
If you're doing Halo 3 or Modern
Warfare 3 or something
like that, then sure you can
sort of cater to the fans
who've already developed these
strategies and skills.
But in our case, we're going
after a new audience.
We're going after someone who's
never played anything
like what you've played
with before.
Cool.
Any questions?
Feel like we've been soapboxing
here for a while.
Is there anything?
AUDIENCE: I guess the thing I
would add from my experience,
especially with iterative design
is, a big trick of it
is learning to kind of distance
yourself emotionally
from what you're working on,
because half the time you end
up chucking things that
you really liked.
You think, oh, this would be
so great, but it's best to
just remove it.
And it helps to think of it as
kind of putting it on the
shelf for later, and saying, OK,
I'll deal with this later,
or I can try this
in another game.
And on a related note, I don't
know about you, but I found
that, when games I'm designing
have a problem, it's almost
always fixed by removing
something as opposed to adding
more stuff on it.
Unless you're going for
something, I think, really
complex off to start, I always
prefer to try to take
something out and simplify it.
Especially on short projects
like these it almost always
works better.
And then, in terms of testing,
too, one thing just kind of a
tip that I find works, is if
you're designing a game that
has a lot of different, like,
passive victory and this is a
little bit higher level, which
you'll see when we get there,
where if you want a game that
has different viable
strategies, a really good
testing method is to have
different people kind of
play like a perfect
version of that strategy.
And you say, I'm going to do
this strategy, or I'm always
going to do X, and it doesn't
matter if I think it's dumb,
I'm just going to do it.
Because that will really help
you find rules that are
appropriate, or find something
that's overpowered.
AUDIENCE: A good example would
be Settlers right.
Like if you say, obviously this
wouldn't work because,
the game's a good game, but
like, I'm always going to
build roads.
You know what I mean?
In practice, that would be
stupid,but when you're
designing a game, you do that
kind of strategy, and you just
limit yourself to one action,
you can really find things
that are broken really
quickly.
PROFESSOR: Thank you.
Much appreciated.
Cookies.
Good, we have cookies.
Let's see.
So I think after this, we're
just going to play games.
We do have pre-testing as a
topic coming up later in the
semester, where I will actually
sort of talk about
the discipline on how
do you do testing.
Honestly, you shouldn't wait for
that class to necessarily
start practicing.
It could be as simple as just
grabbing a unit that you have
never seen before and just
trying to get a whole bunch of
people to play it.
And critiquing it at
the same time.
It's like, why did I do that?
Why did you do that?
Why did you do that move?
And there are sort of practices
to make sure that
when it's your game, you are
not sort of telling the
players what they should be
doing while they are trying to
play the game, because that
affects their play of the game
in a way that biases it.
Well, we'll get to that
later in the semester.
For now just be aware, the more
that you're testing, the
more you're sort of tweaking
your rules in between tests
and then getting another chance
to test and test and
test, the closer you are to
getting a game that is
actually fun and engaging
to play.
And that's what we're
looking for.
That's the process that we
expect you folks to suceed in.
When do we ever get to
fun and engaging?
Who knows?
We don't know whether you're
going to get there, so we're
not grading you based on that.
Just remember that.
We're not grading you on how
engaging your games are.
But how well do you stick
to the process?
Yes.
Absolutely.
There was a question in the
forums about when do you stop?
I didn't get a chance to
look too closely at it.
What--can you repeat it?
AUDIENCE: It's essentially,
it's the question of, say,
there is this iterative
design process.
When do you know when
to just sort of
get out of that process?
But--
AUDIENCE: Due date.
OK.
That's always a good reason.
I guess, if you didn't have a
due date, like how would you
know when to shift?
Well, let's say you have control
over the due date.
I guess part of that is, you
should always be updating,
blah blah, so I guess the
question is when do you know
when you have something you can
put out into the world?
PROFESSOR: So the cynical answer
is that, yeah, is that
you wait for --
you have to ship, right, or
you're not getting any cash.
I personally think it would
be sooner than you think.
As, like, my game's almost
ready but I know there's
something wrong with
it, especially
when you're a student.
Right now, I'm in this mode with
my StarCraft games, which
is, this path is cracked.
I know there's something
wrong with it.
I have no idea what it is.
Therefore, I'm going
to release it.
Because until I do that,
I have no idea
what's wrong with it.
I need to get that
information.
The nice thing about stuff like
computer games is that
you can ship updates.
It's annoying but you can.
But even board games and card
games now have rule revisions,
rule clarifications that you
can release over the net.
For the most part, if you're
going to go professional, your
publisher will tell you.
And then the answer really
is due date.
It's going to the presses
on this date.
And that's one maxim,
which is, game
projects are never finished.
They're just abandoned.
It's just horrible.
I can't do anything else about
this because I'm out of time.
Ship it.
But one thing that you can
do to prepare for that--
Let me see.
Is there a laser around here?
There is a guy who runs a
blog called Lost Garden.
His name is Dan Cook.
He works over in Microsoft.
And he talks a lot about
game design.
Specifically about video game
design, but actually his stuff
is actually really,
really impeccable.
And he has this concept that
game design-- or iterative
game design kind of goes in this
kind of cycle, where this
list down here is the
number of features
you've got in the game.
The trick, though, is that what
you're really doing is,
you are taking-- let me
see if this is right.
So this is all the good stuff.
This is all the stuff
that's not so good.
And the whole idea of sort of
like using iterative design is
to allow yourself to the space
to come up with a whole bunch
of ideas, not knowing whether
they're good or bad.
But it also gives you a gate to
cut out all the bad stuff.
So at frequent periodic
intervals, you have a
collection of rules, of cards,
of designs, of whatever
consists your game, that, is
pretty much as good as it
possibly could have been
given the amount of
time that you got.
And that could ship.
So if ship date was here, you
had as good a game as you
possibly could do it.
If ship date turned out to be
there, all of a sudden you've
still had the opportunity to put
out all of the stuff that
you knew was bad.
So iterative design is not
about, let's just keep
accreting more and more and
more and more features.
It's more about, we're going to
add some features and then
we're going to remove the
ones that don't work.
And that's really,
really important.
So at any given time,
you are prepared to
sort of release it.
As for when you actually decide
that this is now ready
to go out, again I will repeat,
sooner day than you
think because you need
that feedback.
Sometimes you don't know how a
market is going to respond
until you actually do it, but
you can do a soft launch.
If you are doing a commercial
product, you can do things
where, we're going to release it
to a few select stores and
get that feedback before we
go into major print run.
Or for 10,000 different copies
of the same board game.
We're going to 200 copies and
see how that does for us.
Gives you the opportunity to
make a revision, but it's
still an official release,
because those 200 people think
that this is the final
packaged product.
That's pretty much how a lot
of manufacturing industries
actually work, anyway, so you
think about any kind of
product design, a lot of them
have a sort of a trial period.
AUDIENCE: Soft drinks
you get a lot.
PROFESSOR: Soft drinks
Japanese electronics,
and other things.
You release it in Tokyo, and
then you release it in the
rest of Japan.
And sometimes it never makes it
out of Japan because that
initial test--
yeah, it was a good product but
not enough people bought
it because of these problems.
So instead of releasing it into
the world, we're going to
make version two, and maybe
that will be one we
release to the world.
That's one example.
All right, so we have games.
Who has not played Uno?
OK, we have more games that--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So Jason, you're going
to do a Euchre table?
So--
AUDIENCE: It sounds like 4
player trick taking game, kind
of like bane or current
speeds or which?
PROFESSOR: Looks like we have
exactly four people-- one,
two, three, four, one,
two, three--
it's an average of three
people per table.
I think most of these games
are three to five player,
although I'm going to
be absolutely sure.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: --so it might
PROFESSOR: You guys might
actually want to try the round
table in the corner?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, it's
a [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: I really want
to play bowling.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So basically, take
a game from the table.
I'll bring some out and
I'll see --play them.
Once you've had a chance
to play a few times,
feel free to switch.
And try to get as many games
played as possible during the
next couple of hours.