The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Ok, cool.
So we've been reading
the assignments.
And we realize that there were
a couple of things about how
to write rules that we hadn't
neccesarily gone through.
One thing that we would like to
see in the next assignment
are a couple things that I'm
going to read out now.
But we'll probably send
out an email, as well.
So you can have it
for reference.
So having a paragraph or an
overview that broadly explains
what the game is about
is actually
really, really useful.
Just jumping straight
into the--
this is how you set up a border
and this is how you
take a turn.
That's the meat of
the assignment.
But just to help people get
a grasp, especially if you
thought about your theme
really, really hard.
And this next coming assignment,
your theme is
right there, explaining who
are you in this game?
What are you trying to do?
What's your overall goal
in broad terms?
Not necessarily very specific
game terms.
Just having one paragraph is
a really, really good idea.
And really, that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
paragraph.
Two, list the components.
In a card game, it would be
like we have this many red
cards, this many blue cards.
Just so we know that we've
got everything.
It also helps, sometimes, to
be able to establish the
vocabulary of the game
really, really early.
So if all your red cards are
attack cards, and all your
blue cards are defense cards,
you want to say your deck
should have 25 red attack
cards and 25
blue defense cards.
And now we know if you use the
words attack card and defense
card later, we now know
what it means.
So this is obvious from just
looking at currents.
But frankly, when we are
opening up these cards,
usually, there is one person
looking at the cards and
somebody else looking
at the rules.
And just having the information
redundant is kind of nice.
Let me see.
The number of players--
in this particular assignment,
I'm trying to remember what
the requirements are for.
It was like two to four?
AUDIENCE: Two to four.
PROFESSOR: Two to four.
A number of your previous
projects
actually allow less players.
We want an explicit line that
says this is how many players
your game supports.
Just one line.
Make it like a bullet point.
By the way, bullet points--
be concise.
Making things really easy to
read is highly valued.
One thing that you absolutely
should do is make sure you're
testing your written rules
as well as your game.
Don't just test the rules
of your game.
And then, you write it down.
And you're never actually
testing the written version of
your rules on someone.
You need to be able to test
your rules, as well.
There are some games that
clearly need that.
And some games that
clearly don't.
And it showed.
By the way, no one really did
badly on the last assignment.
I'm nitpicking because this
is, obviously, from
B to A. Let's see.
Expected playing time.
Especially in this next
assignment, if a game tends to
take 30 minutes, or if your
game tends to take 10.
Just state it.
In some games, it takes a really
long time to set up and
a really fast time to play.
Then, you just state expected
set up time, expected playing
time [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
There was a lot of assumption in
the rules and in the design
of the game that your
players are male.
This is a very
male-proportioned class right now.
But don't assume that
your players are
all going to be male.
It's actually really kind of
off-putting to read a set of
rules that just assumes that if
you're playing this game,
you are a guy.
There are a couple of things
that people have done in
academia to address
that issue.
I've seen papers where they've
used nonspecific
third person pronouns.
They just [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
he/she all the time unless
they're talking about a
specific person.
But in your case, when you're
thinking about your themes,
don't assume that your
players are male.
You can cast them in
the role of a male.
But don't assume that a player,
itself is male.
AUDIENCE: So I'm just
going to say--
put this out there.
In the English language,
it's actually
very masculine oriented.
So the proper way to say in a
third person, if you're not
saying one says this,
it's actually
appropriate to say he.
That's actually proper in
the English language.
PROFESSOR: And I'm saying it's
off-putting from a marketing
standpoint to assume that
your players is male.
It goes more than just gender
specific pronouns.
It goes way more than that.
There were a lot of
assumptions--
there were specific rules that
assumed that you were a
straight male in a
couple of games.
So let's be clear about that.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I was just going to
mention that from what I've
seen in a lot of rule books, it
seems like a lot of people
solve this problem by just
replacing the assumption that
the player's male with
the assumption that
the player's female.
Yeah, I've noticed this.
Every single pronoun in every
like post second edition
Dungeons and Dragons
book is female.
It's kind of interesting.
PROFESSOR: That's actually kind
of an interesting way to
deal with it.
It's just like you
have a lampshade.
You've got to use a pronoun,
but we don't want to use
language that's going to turn
people off the game.
So we just want to swap all
the pronouns around.
And all of a sudden, you
actually have a more
marketable game.
You have a game where someone
is going to read the rules.
And if they're a straight
male reading the
rules, it's like OK.
Clearly it just was a
gender pronoun swap.
But I can read these,
and it makes sense.
Whereas, someone who
is not a straight
male reading the rules.
They're going, oh, this
game is not for me.
So I'm not going to
play the game.
That kind of reaction
does happen.
Board games are supposed
to be inclusive.
Board games and card cames are
supposed to kind of like be
these huge socially enabling
games and [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So keep that in mind.
You want people to
feel welcome when
they read the rules.
AUDIENCE: If I could
just interject.
So something that I've seen
that happens a lot in like
[? bridge ?] literature, is they
make your partner-- so
one person, specifically,
is female and
the others are male.
And that way, you kind of
have this inclusivity.
But that helps clarify who
you're talking about.
So if you are writing up
examples, or sample turns, or
that kind of thing, you
can think about doing
it that way as well.
Because it does the whole
inclusivity, but then again
kind of clarifies who you're
talking about in the set.
PROFESSOR: And we're
in university.
We're trying to be professors
about this.
AUDIENCE: I find it, generally,
people's aversion
to writing using pronouns, which
are identity neutral
specifically, people worry
that there's an ambiguity
between singular and plural.
And that's why you shouldn't
use that kind of pronoun.
But, for the most part, it's
almost always obvious when
you're talking about one
person [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I don't even
see really why
this is still an issue.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
It's one of those things where
it's not technically correct
to say if I'm referring
to a single person
to say they or their.
But then, if you're reading,
other people will say do that.
A lot of people are just still
using he or she now.
It's certainly awkward.
It's kind of [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: You can also use
second person language-- you.
When it's your turn,
you blah blah blah.
And also, the one player is a
great substitue for all that.
Say player one, player two.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And it's tough.
It's tough to write
stuff like this.
But sometimes I find writing
constraints, writing gets
better because you're more
focused on how your writing is
going to be received.
And we're, frankly, trying to
encourage everything in your
games to be better.
I guess this is something
that I hit on earlier.
Try to go for short sentences.
Not paragraphs or prose.
Those are actually difficult to
read when you're trying to
also process what the moves
are going to be.
Go for active voice, rather
than passive voice.
I personally, automatically,
write passive voice when I'm
writing in a report.
And I have to physically
change myself and tell
Microsoft Word to highlight
every single instance of
passive voice so that I can
accurately correct that.
Microsoft Word doesn't do a
great job in highlighting
every single instance.
But if you do this often enough,
you start picking it
out yourself.
It's actually easier to read.
It's uncomfortable if you're
moving from the field of
writing chemical papers into
writing for general public.
But active voice is easier
for someone to read.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
This one I might need more
help and detail.
These substeps of actions.
GUEST SPEAKER: When you're
going through the
instructions, it's really
helpful to have numbered
sequences instead of having a
chunk of prose that's saying
first do this.
Then you do this.
Just bullet point it.
Or make it a numbered list.
And it's a lot easier for
people to follow.
Generally speaking, bullets
versus numbers.
You should use a numbered list
if a sequence really matters
versus bulleted lists are more
like these are the things that
are important.
But there's not necessarily
a temporal relationship
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So just some tips.
In the end, every single game
that we played, we could play.
It didn't take us long to figure
out what was necessary.
The games were good.
The games were entertaining.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
extra people to come
in and play.
And we don't [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
to play again just
the two of us.
Yeah.
I'm actually really, really
impressed because it's a
marketing group.
I know with previous classes
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[APPLAUSE]
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Yay.
All right.
So that was the stuff
on your assignment.
And now onto intellectual
property.
Actually how many people figured
out that we had given
you the wrong chapter to read.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: OK.
All right.
For those of you who
ended up rereading
chapter three, I'm sorry.
It's not a huge chapter.
But I kind of want to talk about
two different things,
both of which are related to
intellectual property.
What is the version of
intellectual property that
presented to you in the book.
In that sense, that's kind of
the game designer concept of
what intellectual property is.
Often it means a franchise.
Often it means somebody else's
story wall or characters.
Maybe it's real people
and images, like the
faces and the bodies.
In sports games, you have
to deal with that a lot.
There was a conference
this last weekend.
And one of the old guards of
the Boston game development
team, who now runs iRacing, was
talking about the amount
of effort it takes to actually
license a NASCAR car.
Because it's not just a car.
But every single logo that's on
their car, and the person
who's inside it, and the uniform
that they're wearing,
every single logo on their
uniform, and their face.
There's a lot that goes into
licensing for that.
It helps that the person who now
owns iRacing is also the
same person who owns
the Red Sox.
So they've got the bank roll to
be able to do all of this.
But that's the idea
of what IP is from
industry point of view.
And there's a couple of
things that you can
do to consider that.
Not just all right, how do we
design this game so that we
can minimize how much IP
we need to license?
Licensing IP generally means
licensing money that needs to
be exchanged.
That means that your splitting
up their royalties or you're
just putting up money
up front.
Of course, this goes for things
like licensed music,
for instance.
EA has an entire music
department.
Sega has an entire
music department.
Its job is either to create
their own music, or more
likely, license popular music.
And, of course, with Harmonix,
that's half the
business right there.
Probably be bought,
at this point.
The other thing they can do is
that, assuming that you are
working with a license.
And the reason why you're
working with licensing--
think of Star Wars, which came
up in the last class.
How do we do justice to it?
How do we sort of make sure
that the fans of those
particular intellectual property
franchises are going
to look at this game that we're
creating, and say, yeah,
that's faithful?
That makes sense.
We'll be actually playing a
lot more of those games, I
think, later on.
For things like Battlestar
Gallactica.
But let's take LEGO Star
Wars as one example.
If you're a fan of LEGO then,
you're probably a fan of
building things up with
little tiny blocks.
You like making stuff combine.
And you kind of like the whole
blockiness, that look of it.
So the folks who made
LEGO Star Wars--
I think they are called
Traveller's Tales.
And LEGO Indiana Jones
and those there
was a bunch of games--
kind of had to play that up.
They made a lot of obstacles
in the game.
Things that you had to put
together with parts.
Sure, it is holding one button
into assemble it from a bunch
of disconnected parts.
But creating all that animation
and sort of making--
this is one of the main game
mechanics of the entire game
was a decision they had to
make. and they're very
consciously making that because
with LEGO, we're going
to assume people are going
to make things.
And then you find parts in the
entire game that you can later
go back to a trophy room and
can see your trophies,
statues, and objects from the
game builds that you're trying
to do sort of built up.
So the more parts you find--
they're like the hidden
collectibles that you find
in Grand Theft Auto.
They're kind of hidden away
in secret locations.
And you find more of them--
you go back to your trophy room
and oh, wow, your X-wing.
Or you have part of an X-wing.
You haven't found half of it.
So all you've got
are the wings.
And none of the guns or
something like that.
They've actually figured out a
way how that weaves back into
basic game mechanics but is
still appealing to LEGO fans.
If you get chopped in half
by a lightsaber,
you fall into pieces.
You don't actually bleed.
When the characters walk, they
actually walk like that.
They're a little bit
more flexible
than actual LEGO pieces.
They don't just move down
like the right angles.
But they try.
They try really, really
hard to make
everything look plasticy.
And it's [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
The same thing goes
with Star Wars.
Right?
What are the things that people
expect from Star Wars?
AUDIENCE: Lightsabers.
PROFESSOR: Lightsabers.
OK.
Anything else?
AUDIENCE: The Force.
PROFESSOR: The Force.
OK.
AUDIENCE: Darth Vader.
PROFESSOR: Darth Vader.
You've got to have Darth--
Well, they're doing it on the
Episodes Four, Five, and Six.
Actually, I believe Darth Vader
is still unlockable on
Episode One, Two, and Three
because people expect there to
be a Darth Vader.
AUDIENCE: Generally,
they use the main
characters from the films.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, the main
characters from films.
AUDIENCE: Dog fights.
PROFESSOR: Dog fights?
You mean like--
that's actually interesting
because I believe they
actually didn't do that.
They didn't manage
to put that in.
But in a lot of other Lucas
games they did.
They focused mostly
on space fights.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Catch phrases.
PROFESSOR: Catch phrases.
I think they've weaved the catch
phrases into the names
of the levels because
they can't--
not that [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Nobody ever
says, I've got a bad
feeling about this?
PROFESSOR: I think there's a
title of a level that says,
I've got a bad feeling
about this.
Because there's no dialog.
No one says anything.
The only thing that says
anything is R2-D2.
And that's just a voice over.
AUDIENCE: Actually, I have a
really good example of catch
phrases in, I think Rogue
Squadron on Nintendo 64.
There's this line in the Star
Wars movies, where Luke is
like, that stabilizer's
broken loose.
If you can, lock it down.
Every like second time
you get shot,
they play that recording.
[LAUGHTER]
And it just even like cut scene
you where this other
pilot is like, Luke, my
stabilizer's broken loose.
And he's like, see if you
can't have your R2
unit lock it down.
[LAUGHTER]
So yeah, I mean a good example
of the worst end is that game.
PROFESSOR: You can over do it.
I'm trying to remember
how the force works.
I think you can assemble LEGO
blocks from a distance in Star
Wars if you're playing
Obi-Wan.
It's kind of, "oooo." And
then, [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: Call Yoda.
Obviously, Darth Vader
is in there.
Darth Vader is in the first
cut scene, obviously.
AUDIENCE: Yoda is?
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
All the big characters have
got to be there, right?
You've got to have your Luke.
You've got to have your C-3PO.
And the interesting thing
about every LEGO game--
this is a nice mix between LEGO
and Star Wars is that you
can play any level with
any character.
So after you've beaten it once,
I think you unlock the
ability to swap characters in,
which is more of a LEGO kind
of thing, right?
I'm just going to take the
characters from the Harry
Potter set and put them in the
LEGO Star Wars game and see
what happens.
But that's one thing
that you get.
You get to unlock all
these characters.
So you can play the whole game
with [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: You want
to add the locales?
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Oh yeah.
The locations.
At least some acknowledgment
that there is some sequence of
when people go to each locale.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, the LEGO
games, in particular,
basically, follow the events of
the movies, specifically.
So it's like each separate event
in the movie is kind of
it's own level.
PROFESSOR: Mos Eisley
Cantina is one
chunk of this one level.
And you beat that, and you're
going to-- what happens after
the cantina?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Tatooine.
AUDIENCE: Probably in
some Death Star.
AUDIENCE: Death Star yeah.
PROFESSOR: Oh right, right.
I was going to say, someone
should invent a game where it
has all the LEGO games.
And you can any of the
characters, interchangably
between them.
PROFESSOR: Well, there's one
company that already has
technology for that.
And I would to see LEGO Star
Wars slash Indiana Jones.
Even better you can change
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Indiana Jones, which
is about it.
AUDIENCE: Like take
off the hat.
PROFESSOR: Blaster?
Whip!
One thing which these particular
games have done a
really good job with
is they'll always
bring the music over.
Actually, every single Star Wars
game has been very, very
careful about making sure that
it sounds like Star Wars.
The sound effects
and the music.
[INAUDIBLE]
A lot of it is actually
developed with the Lucas Arts
license, which is, obviously,
under the Lucas umbrella.
So it makes it a little
bit easier.
The company of the whole Lucas
family, Lucas Arts, Lucas Film
is actually really, really
tightly centrally controlled
by Lucas, himself.
Partly for quality control,
partly for
control freak issues.
In the end, what it does make it
really, really easy as for
say-- how many folks paid
for The Force Unleashed?
AUDIENCE: The live action
trailer was awesome.
The second one?
AUDIENCE: Oh, I haven't seen
live action trailer.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE] they
blend the in-game footage
and live action to get
back and forth.
And it's really hard to tell
where [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: I actually wonder
whether the character is
actually based on the case
of the real world.
AUDIENCE: It must be because
it's the exact same face.
PROFESSOR: OK.
A lot of the assets that are
used in the movies were
brought over into the game.
Obviously with with some tweaks
to make it run better
in the game.
A lot of stuff in the force
unleashed, like when you use
your force power and smash
things, which is actually most
of the game, if I recall.
A lot of that same technology
is actually technology that
they use in the films to
simulate things being smashed.
That being said, that particular
example is probably
not even a good instance of
something that any player is
going to notice.
It's like, why do I care that
things that are breaking in
the game, break exactly the
same way in the movie?
But they do.
More usefully you
see art assets.
You see the same concept art
moving between the games,
moving smoothly.
Traveller's Tales is actually
an illegal Star Wars game.
They're a little bit
further out.
Obviously, those are
third party.
Those are separate from
the Lucas family.
They had to actually license
both LEGO and Star Wars.
But they already had a
relationship with Star Wars.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
So it was a little bit easier
for them to negotiate that.
And as a game developer issue
issue, I believe, with the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] and how they
actually managed that.
Again, they're going to
be very, very capital.
Even though it's not Lucas's own
company, they're going to
be very, very capital and at
least matching up with Lucas's
control of the product.
And if you're a developer
working with a license, often,
it's just a long process of just
earning trust back from
the original license holders.
[? Jason Beam ?]
is actually a partner
entering this lab.
And he used to work with THQ,
which made a lot of DS and Wii
titles, specifically on Disney
and Pixar products.
One problem with the DS is that
it doesn't have a huge
amount of 3D processing
quality.
Whereas, obviously Pixar movies
have all the power in
the world to do awesome
looking 3D.
So some of the tricks that they
have to do to be able to
get the characters--
to be faithful to the characters
in the movie are
kind of interesting.
So the folks who work
for Pixar films--
a lot of them have these opening
and closing sequences
that are actually animated in
completely different style.
Maybe it's hand drawn, maybe
it's paper cutouts.
And those are still emblematic
of Pixar style, even though
they're not super 3D,
realistically rendered.
And a lot of DS games that
[? Jason Beam ?] worked out
will use those tricks.
They'll make a game.
Instead of making it look like
it's all 3D, you can make it
look like it's all cut out of
cardboard because that's part
of the movies.
And the DS has a much easier
time with that.
One thing that's kind of useful
when you're thinking
about what to take from a
franchise or license is to
look at the verbs that come
out from that franchise.
I think we have enough time.
I'd like to do an exercise where
we pick out a franchise.
And you just try to come up
with a bunch of verbs that
make that franchise unique or at
least you expect to see in
a franchise.
But I'd like some examples.
I'm going to just start with
movies and see if you can get
at least one that everyone's
fairly familiar with.
And if not, then I'll try books
or other kinds of media
properties.
Anyone want to throw out a movie
that maybe everyone in
here should be familiar with?
AUDIENCE: Independence Day.
PROFESSOR: Independence Day?
Has anyone not seen
Independence Day?
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Actually, let's
just throw out a few
brainstorming ideas.
There's Independence Day.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: I'm going
to go this way.
AUDIENCE: Ferris Bueller's
Day Off.
AUDIENCE: Twilight.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Lord of the Rings.
AUDIENCE: Inception.
AUDIENCE: Iron Man.
AUDIENCE: The Matrix.
PROFESSOR: OK.
We hit some in there.
And I think that's all
I can remember.
So Inception, Iron Man, The
Matrix, Ferris Bueller's Day
Off, Independence Day, Twilight,
Lord of the Rings.
AUDIENCE: I've never
seen Twilight.
I'm going to pick Inception.
Who has not seen Inception?
AUDIENCE: You should.
PROFESSOR: You haven't
seen Inception?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Which
have you seen?
AUDIENCE: I've seen all
the other ones.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: My problem with The
Matrix [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Has everyone seen
Ferris Bueller's Day Off?
AUDIENCE: Nope.
AUDIENCE: Have you seen it?
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Monty Python, yeah.
PROFESSOR: Monty Python?
Does anyone not know
Monty Python?
AUDIENCE: Wait--
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: --Holy Grail.
AUDIENCE: Home Alone.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: There might have been
a Home Alone game, but I
bet no one here has played it.
AUDIENCE: I have.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: That is impressive.
AUDIENCE: They're for the
original Game Boy.
PROFESSOR: Oh, okay.
AUDIENCE: It's actually one of
the first Game Boy games my
brother ever got.
AUDIENCE: That's old.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: OK.
Let me try Lord of the Rings but
maybe a specific Lord of
the Rings movie.
AUDIENCE: [TRANSPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: --The Matrix.
How about The Matrix.
PROFESSOR: No, the problem with
The Matrix is that there
are too many games on it.
AUDIENCE: The Two Towers?
PROFESSOR: I'm really curious
about Ferris Bueller's
Day Off as a game.
If somebody would like to
volunteer a quick summary of
what Ferris Bueller's
Day Off is about?
AUDIENCE: Which is Matthew --
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Well, OK.
So the basic idea is the main
character is Ferris Bueller
played by Matthew Broderick.
The idea is that he's the
infamously super popular like
class clown kid in school.
And he decides to just play
hooky with, essentially, his
girlfriend and his
best friend.
And the whole movie is them
going around the city getting
into wacky misadventures while
the principal tries to catch
him playing hooky because
he hates him.
AUDIENCE: That is awesome.
AUDIENCE: It is incredible.
PROFESSOR: So actually that
white board would be--
AUDIENCE: Has anyone heard the
Fight Club theory on Ferris
Bueller's Day Off?
AUDIENCE: No.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Ferris Bueller
and his best friend.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Yeah, Cameron.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: I'm going to
stand at this screen.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Wait, who hasn't
seen Fight Club.
AUDIENCE: Oh, Fight Club.
That's a pretty good movie.
AUDIENCE: Has everyone
seen Fight Club?
That's another one.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: --because I think,
that game would have
benefitted from the exercise
that we're about to do.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Like do
both controllers
control the same character?
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: That's some Metal Gear
Solid stuff right there.
AUDIENCE: Psycho
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So I just got to
bring out the note pad thing.
And I want people to start
thinking about verbs.
What are the verbs that
make Ferris Bueller's
Day Off kind of unique?
Or really that's what you think
of when you think of
Ferris Bueller's Day Off?
AUDIENCE: Verbs?
PROFESSOR: Yeah, verbs.
What do they do?
What do the characters do?
AUDIENCE: Bad karoake.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Bad Karoake.
AUDIENCE: Sing.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Let me make sure
we've got [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Live life.
AUDIENCE: Lie.
They lie.
PROFESSOR: OK.
So they sing.
They deceive or lie.
AUDIENCE: They run.
PROFESSOR: They run?
AUDIENCE: Elude.
[LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: They definitely
elude.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: They drive.
AUDIENCE: Destroy.
AUDIENCE: They
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
They trick.
AUDIENCE: They trick?
That's deceive.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
be spontaneous.
PROFESSOR: They be
spontaneous.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: They improvise.
AUDIENCE: They get in trouble.
PROFESSOR: They get
in trouble.
There's not a real
verb for that.
AUDIENCE: And get
out of trouble.
AUDIENCE: They mischief.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Well, mischief
is a word that should
probably be in there.
That might be an actually a back
of the box or tagline.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
What else?
Anything else they do there?
AUDIENCE: They hide.
PROFESSOR: They hide?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Hide, run, elude.
Those kind of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Exploit maybe?
PROFESSOR: Exploit?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, they
take advantage.
PROFESSOR: OK.
They exploit [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: They impress.
PROFESSOR: They impress.
AUDIENCE: Relax.
AUDIENCE: That's good.
At some point they relax.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES.
PROFESSOR: One guy
is very relaxed.
AUDIENCE: They kiss.
PROFESSOR: They kiss.
AUDIENCE: They hack.
PROFESSOR: Do they hack
into a computer?
AUDIENCE: Into the
school computer.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Oh yeah.
I forgot about that.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It's going to take
a little bit more interest.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: The school has
a [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
That's too easy.
There's a movie about that.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: That's War Games.
AUDIENCE: You ruined it.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Let's see.
What else?
AUDIENCE: It's a classic line.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Do they ever
support each other?
Or do they just stress
each other out?
AUDIENCE: They may just
stress each other out.
AUDIENCE: They plan.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Scheme.
No, they scheme.
AUDIENCE: Scheme is so much
better than plan.
AUDIENCE: I don't like these
negative words for him.
PROFESSOR: This may not be what
the main characters do,
but they campaign.
They run a campaign
to save Ferris.
So the idea is that Ferris is
basically pretending that he's
deathly ill.
And so a bunch of the students
in the school are running a
campaign to raise funds for
his medical expenses.
AUDIENCE: Well, everyone
says it.
Like the police station says,
tell your brother feel better.
And also the water tower has
Save Ferris printed on it.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
And you can think about what
those verbs associated with
like putting signs
up and painting.
And if you look at this
list, the list can
probably get much longer.
But this is a fairly
unique collection.
Maybe it's all unique if you
compare it to other, sort of,
hijinks movies.
But it's not like we've had
a lot of video games, in
particular, that are
in that game.
And we probably should have
because it sounds like it's
going to be a heck
of a lot of fun.
Actually, the one theme that
reminds me of this is actually
Bully, which was released
by Rockstar.
Where you sort of
do these things.
But it's much more vengeful.
It's much more I'm going to show
the other bullies in the
school how [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Whereas this one is kind
of more good natured.
They parade.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
is also part of the
singing badly part.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You get the girlfriend
and then they sing
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: But singing badly
wouldn't have the same impact
if there wasn't a brass
band behind him.
So you can think about how any
of these verbs-- and we've
done this exercise by taking
verbs and turning them into
game mechanics before.
And you can think about how
any of these verbs could
actually be turned
into a game.
Kiss might be a goal or it might
be a rule, a mechanic,
to be able to accomplish
something.
Parade might be a setting.
Campaign might be a collection
of mechanics that feed off
each other.
It could be a whole system that
tells you how successful
your Save Ferris campaign
is going.
You could make a game that's
just all about saving Ferris,
as opposed to playing Ferris
Bueller himself.
And that's kind of one exercise
that you can do when
you're thinking about your
reward systems and all the
systems that you guys have
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] as far as I
can recall.
You don't have to worry about
licensing the idea.
But you're basically working
with a real live franchise.
And if you're doing something
based on political diplomacy
or something like that, then
there are real life source
material things that you're
trying to be faithful to.
And going through
this exercise--
OK.
What are all the verbs in this
idea that we're working with?
This isn't going to work--
What do people actually do?
It's a good exercise to be able
to try to be faithful to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And then, you don't have to pick
all of them, of course.
You're just going
to cherry pick.
And you want to prioritize
a little bit.
OK.
What things can we get rid of
and very still clearly be
Ferris Bueller game.
Running.
I think as long as we have some
kind of evation think,
physical running may
not be necessary.
You could do something like as
long as they're not in one
location where the principal
is at any given
time, you're good.
But you don't have to physically
move through
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] basically
in all that.
AUDIENCE: Drive, probably.
PROFESSOR: Driving.
Yeah.
It's such a minor part
of the film.
Yeah.
The actual driving is such a
minor part of the film that
you can probably do
without that.
And you might actually want to
think about what if instead of
this being Ferris Bueller's day
off into Ferris Bueller's
multiple days off.
Maybe just play each
day differently.
And just trying to stay out
more and more days.
Maybe a score or number
of days you don't go
to school or something.
So that's an idea.
That's one approach that you
can use in your projects.
Before we hit two, I just want
to touch on another point.
Before I transition,
any questions about
dealing with IP ?
There is a point that Brenda
makes in her book--
the Brenda [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
book-- that if you go
professionally in the game
industry, you will most likely
at some point in time,
probably many times in
your career, work
with a licensed product.
And it can be painful because
you do not have greater
control yet trying to be
faithful to what you're
working with.
And if you succeed, you
make a lot of money.
And maybe you get enough
money to start
working on your own projects.
But it's a reality because
franchises do sell.
And they're a lot lower risk
than dealing with a
completely new idea.
By the way, if you haven't
played the new Tomb Raider
game, which is actually kind
of interesting because it's
like Tomb Raider meets Diablo.
If people have never...
Whose played or seen some one
play Tomb Raider before?
OK.
Who knows about this latest game
that I'm talking about.
It's kind of like 3/4
isometric view.
Yeah.
It is Tomb Raider meets Diablo
but it still keeps in with the
puzzle solving.
It's cooperative.
It's a very, very different
game in terms of
how you play it.
But it will be an interesting
exercise to sort
of play that game.
Maybe I'll load it
up here sometime.
And you can take a look and
how does that resemble the
Tomb Raider franchise so that
people who look at the game
and still say, yeah that's Tomb
Raider even though it's a
very new game.
You can imagine like a Tomb
Raider board game, for
instance, and how would
that be different.
And how could that still
be faithful?
That's World of Warcraft games
and Starcraft board
games that we invent.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
But I'd love to try it out.
Let's see.
So the other point I want
to get to is kind of the
legalistic definition of IP.
And I don't want to spend an
entire class on this because I
know you will all fall asleep.
I just want to point out that
there's quite a lot of
different ways that
intellectual property is protected.
People who are creating stuff
professionally, creatively,
want to make sure that they can
finish their product, they
can make sequels of their
product, they can maybe even
license their ideas
to someone else.
Make IP for some company without
having ideas copied
outright and not seeing any
compensation for that.
If it is copyrights, there's
trademarks, there's patents.
I feel like I'm missing
something.
I guess we have those
three first.
And if anything--
those are definitely
the three big ones.
Copyright.
Copyright basically protects
an expression of an idea.
The idea, itself, is
not protected.
If your basic idea is in a
world where aliens are
attacked by space marines,
the idea, itself, is not
protected, which is a relief
because a lot of people have
many games on that idea.
But the actual expression is.
So the actual--
say that you're an artist.
And you're creating concept
art based on that theme.
That piece of concept art is
copyrighted to either you or
if you're an employee of a
company then you've probably
signed over your rights
to the company.
That whatever you're creating
on their dime
belongs to the company.
And that's defensible
in court.
It's actually an automatic
protection.
But it's one of those things
where it helps to be able to
document that you've actually
created something.
There's a copyright office that
you can send things to.
But for the most part, internal
company documentation
saying, this piece of art was
created on the so and so date
by so and so person.
It's usually good enough to
stand up in court if there's
ever a dispute.
So the same thing goes
for writing.
The same thing goes for
audio and music.
A lot of music is protected
under copyright.
So if somebody creates a piece
of music that sounds an awful
lot like your piece of music.
There are specific rules that
allow for that to happen.
But I think, if you completely
reperform the piece, you are
allowed to do that.
But you may have to pay the
original composers the
royalties from the music.
This means that if person A
composes a song, then B
performs a song and releases
an album, then C could
actually reperform that song.
And the only royalties goes
back to the composer.
It doesn't necessarily go back
to Band B. However, Band B--
it depends on really how close
they sound to each other.
And, of course, if Band B
happens to be also the
composers, then they're going
to get royalties and win.
But you see this idea that
copyright protects the
expression of an idea.
The composers, at some point in
time, had to write down the
music, the notes,
and the lyrics.
And that is what is protected.
And you can't just copy that
without entering into some
sort of contract saying
that you can.
We have systems like Creative
Commons for instance that
basically, people who are
creating your IP say, under
these conditions, I am letting
people do whatever
they want with it.
And there are different kinds of
Creative Commons licensing.
Some of them that you do--
literally whatever
you want with it.
They're like open
source licenses.
And in some cases, it's like
well, you can do whatever you
want with it as long as it's for
non-commercial use and you
have to credit the origin
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
So that's why Creative
Commons evolved.
So to enable people to freely
do stuff without necessarily
having to pay and enter into
separate contracts with
everybody who is creating IP.
So the problem is with code.
If code and game mechanics
actually for this class is
something I want to consider.
Because you can think
of code in two ways.
One, you can think of it
as a chunk of text.
It's a chunk of ASCII symbols
that you type into a
development environment
and you compile it.
And that's an expression
of an idea.
But the other way that you can
think of it is it's a machine.
It's a bunch of instructions
that you feed into a machine
for it to operate in
a certain way.
And those things, machines,
inventions basically, can be
protected by patents.
That's pretty much what the
patent system is designed for.
Patent system is a lot slower
because you actually have to
apply to central US Patent
Office to be able to secure
those, assuming that you're
looking for patent
protection in the US.
Every single country, every
single region has it's own
patent office and it's
own process.
It's really expensive.
What it does is basically give
you a temporary monopoly on
that invention.
At least, that's what they were
originally designed for.
You make an invention, and
you've got like 25 years or
something to be able to
capitalize on it before anyone
can use your idea.
And the whole reason why it was
invented is that you now
have an incentive to be able
to come up with inventions.
You might make some
profit off it.
And after the patent expires--
25 years or something--
because you've released your
information to the patent
office, now, all of society
can benefit.
Can make derivatives
of your invention.
So in a sense, it was invented
to eventually release great
monopolies.
I got this idea, and I am going
to be upfront and very
clear about how I make
this thing work.
Say Amazon patents 1-click.
And I'm going to say for the
next 25 years, Amazon now has
this lock on 1-click shipping
and purchasing, which is
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] but it's
been [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But after 25 years, anyone
can do 1-click shipping.
But that's the problem, right?
25 years is a heck
of a long time.
And by then, whatever is
invented is kind of obsolete.
And a lot of the ideas that tend
to get approved by the
patent office are pretty
damn obvious.
I'm not going to discourage the
amount of work that Amazon
has actually put into
1-click shipping.
It's actually a really
complex process.
But I am going to discourage,
say there is a patent on the
giant floating arrow that
tells you where you're
supposed to go next.
They have a patent on this.
Namco has a patent on mini games
that you play while your
game is loading.
That's why only Namco games
have mini games in those
screens because they have
a patent on that.
When it comes to game ideas
and game mechanics, I find
this really annoying.
It's a personal rant because I
think that's [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
creation is that opening it up
is really, really tough.
I don't really think game
mechanics fit in the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Apple has is on all
the touching.
On their gestures, a lot
of people can't get
off the same thing.
PROFESSOR: A lot of people have
the same issue that I
have with game mechanics, with
software, in general.
Software happens so quickly that
this kind of temporary
monopoly basically means a real
monopoly over that idea.
AUDIENCE: I thought that game
rules were not patented or
covered by a copyright.
I seem to remember hearing
that somewhere.
And this was an issue which came
up when Scrabulous and
Scrabble were at loggerheads
with one another.
There's some weird technical
detail that I don't really
know, but it kind of comes down
to the actual rules of
Scrabble, the actual game
rules themselves
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] are
not copyrightable.
But somehow, the look and
feel of your game is.
Do you know what the specific
details are?
PROFESSOR: I don't know
the specific details.
But how you outlined it is one
very clear way on how someone
who's created a game can
protect a game without
necessarily being protective
of the rules.
And Scrabble can protect the
layout of their board.
Because in order to come to
design the layout, they had to
express the idea of what the
board was with graphic design.
It's like here's where all the
triple word scores are.
Here are where the double
word scores.
That's an image.
Images can be copyrighted.
And that's protected under
copyrighting law, not under
patent law.
AUDIENCE: And I think
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] of copyrights
and trademarks, it comes down
to like confusion, right?
Like if someone could-- if
Scrabulous was similar enough
to Scrabble, superficially,
that if someone could use
their products.
I think that is like a major
criteria, right?
And then again, it comes down
to things like font, colors,
titles, [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: It's even more
specific when it comes to
trademarks.
If you can claim that the image
or a particular saying
or something is closely
associated with your company's
core brand, you can defend that
as a trademark if you
registered it with the
trademark office.
GAMBIT, the Singapore
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] game lab is
actually a registered trademark
in Singapore.
And actually, we had some
trouble registering that
because well, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
not the first company to come
along with the word GAMBIT.
There's actually another MIT
product called GAMBIT.
It's a game theory
modeling system.
So we actually had to negotiate
some fine words to
be able to separate what we were
doing was not going to be
confused with what
they were doing.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: Are copyrights and
trademarks also for 25 years?
Or are they different?
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Copyrights last as
long as Walt Disney is dead.
That is because the Disney
corp keeps lobbying the
various branches of the United
States to extend copyrights so
that they can lock
down Mickey.
That's the easiest way to
tell exactly how long.
In other words, right now,
you've got something
copyrighted, it's in perpetuity
until Disney loses.
This is actually really
annoying.
Which means there's a whole
bunch of works, literature
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
that date back to the elite 20th
century that by all means
really should be public
domain at this point.
And then, they will pass
into public use.
But they aren't.
I know one thing for sure.
H.P. Lovecraft is definitely
in public domain.
That's why there are so
many games based on
H.P. Lovecraft material.
Whatever is based on Disney
material, has
to be made by Disney.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
of the copyright law.
Images.
If the Scrabble board is
identified as being key to the
Scrabble brand, you
might be able to
protect it under trademark.
And trademark is one of those
things where all you're saying
is that this is how our company
is identifying ourselves.
And if that is confused with
somebody else's product, that
product is now hurting
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
to make money.
So there are a lot of steps to
allow you to fight that.
The problem with trademark
is that you have to
keep fighting back.
So Xerox, for instance,
constantly fights to keep
Xerox as a trademark because
people keep using the word,
Xerox, to mean photocopy, which
is a great problem for a
company to have.
But it's actually a cash
drain as well.
Because everyone's associating
your company's name--
you're thinking Google, right?
AUDIENCE: I think
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Too many people or lose it.
Band-aid would for sure.
PROFESSOR: So you have
to fight it.
AUDIENCE: And Kleenex, yeah.
PROFESSOR: As long as you keep
fighting it, you stand a
chance of hanging onto it.
Like [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
you blink.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: I remember hearing
about this, so I was looking
to find it.
But Richard Garfield, who
created Magic, has a patent on
methods of play for trading
card games.
PROFESSOR: Like the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], for instance?
AUDIENCE: And the one who owns
the patent is playing a card
in a certain orientation and
then changing it's orientation
in the game field choosing to
buy a different state of that
character's embodiment.
AUDIENCE: What?
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: That is stupid.
AUDIENCE: He has a patent
on tapping cards?
AUDIENCE: He has a patent on
tapping cards, among many
other things that
are basically--
So I suspect that he doesn't
enforce this patent or that it
is not enforceable because if
you try to enforce it, it gets
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: It is possible, but
it's not [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: I heard
that the actual
manifestation of that is that--
I don't know whether
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] contested
people over it.
But definitely, they're
anti anyone else
using the term tap.
So which is why whenever you
go to look at Legend of the
Five Rings or whatever, they
have the turned sideways
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But it's called bowing.
And the same is true in any
collectible card game that has
a tap mechanic, they're not
allowed to use the word, tap.
AUDIENCE: But that's
a copyright.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, it's
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So I don't know it's
been tested because I don't
know if that patent has
been contested.
AUDIENCE: I would suspect not.
AUDIENCE: Probably not.
But it's interesting.
If you look at any of the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], so
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Pokemon and I don't recall
what the others are.
They all use the term tap.
But because of the copyright
in which they hold, they're
allowed to do it, but
nobody else--
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: The copyright
violation probably gives
evidence for a patent
violation.
So if you can stay clear of the
copyright violation, the
case that Wizards has to be
able to contest the same
mechanic that's under
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But they might still
have a case.
AUDIENCE: I suspect that they
think that their patent is not
enforceable.
PROFESSOR: It's possible.
AUDIENCE: Otherwise, you
wouldn't even be able to get
away with not even calling
it tapping.
As long as you turn a card,
you'd be able to say, hey, do
you have a method?
AUDIENCE: It's so ridiculous.
AUDIENCE: Entering
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
the first orientation at
the player's option.
Turning the trick card
another orientation
on the playing surface.
It doesn't even say
for any reason.
AUDIENCE: In Naval Battles,
you have to turn the card
upside down.
Like submarine cards, you can
put them upside down to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: --method of playing
games when two or more players
blah, blah, blah.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So you can see how
this gets annoying quick.
But there's actually an,
unfortunately, good reason why
things like game mechanics and
more often implementation of
game mechanisms code are
protected by patents.
Is in that because there are
already so many out there, if
your company is just trying to
make a game, the likelihood
that you're going to run into a
pile of patents is actually
pretty high.
So what do you do?
If you've got something that you
know that you created, a
lot of companies just
go and patent that.
In the event that it turns out
to be a case that you run
afoul of a different patent,
they might actually look at
the company that's suing them
and say, but you were running
to file our patents because we
just also patented something
pretty obvious.
EA, Activision what?
AUDIENCE: It's all just mutually
assured destruction.
PROFESSOR: Exactly.
I mean, well, it's
not destruction.
It's what they do is they
trade licenses.
It's like we will let you use
these patents if you will let
us use that patent and thus,
avoid a legal fight.
Final costs.
Lawyers are getting paid
throughout this entire process.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: It's cheaper
than actually
bringing it to court because--
AUDIENCE: Your patent isn't
validated if you can be shown
someone else came up with
it and patented
it earlier in time.
You have to be the first person
to come up with it.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: And that's why I'm
sure that Wizard has never
tried to use their patent
against people because they
suspect that it's not going to
hold up [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: It's possible.
You may not want to fight it.
But sometimes, the threat
of a lawsuit is
a big enough threat.
It's like you don't even have
to be able to win it.
You just-- we are
a big company.
We have lawyers.
And we can pay them.
Do you?
So that's one reason I mean
why companies that are
otherwise opposed to legal
patents will still secure
patents to protect themselves.
It's kind of sad.
It's like one of those things
where in a city where everyone
owns a gun, you want
to own one, too.
So that's patents.
We talked about trademarks.
We talked about copyright.
One last thing I kind of want
to talk about is fair use.
Fair use is kind of the defense
that a lot of schools
fall back on.
The idea that if you're doing
something, or if you're
appropriating some sort of
material, or some sort of IP
for political or educational
reasons, you have a defense.
Should the case be brought to
court, you might be able to
defend yourself and win that
case by saying well, this was
the reason.
So am I doing something for
satirical purposes.
Am I doing something
to teach people
about games, for instance.
I'm going to reprint
rules or something.
And you guys can look at it.
And you guys can sue me.
And I can claim fair use.
I may not win.
That's the problem.
Fair use is only a defense.
Fair use is not a law that
automatically protects you
from being taken to court.
So lawyer's fees.
Who pays the lawyers' fees
depends on the case.
But frankly, I would rather not
be put in that position.
So there is that chilling
effect.
Just keep that in mind of the
games you guys are making for
the class assignments.
But, of course, we don't expect
you to be say, copying
text verbatim from
other rule sets.
In fact, I doubt any of you
would be particularly
interested in doing so.
Certainly not copying art.
But also, keep in mind that also
applies for things like
art that you find online.
You could protect yourself
under fair use.
This is for a class assignment,
darnit.
And for the most part, no one
is really going to notice.
But, of course, if you want to
take these games a little bit
further, maybe sell them in
the future, you'll want to
rethink about every single piece
of art, every single
piece of text that you're
using in your games.
Is that coming from somewhere
else or can we claim that we
invented that?
AUDIENCE: Have any past students
or groups tried to
pitch their games anywhere?
PROFESSOR: Oh, you mean like
turn it commercial?
Not to my knowledge.
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Yeah, do it.
I mean, based on the games that
we played on Tuesday,
absolutely.
Actually, one of the pieces of
feedback that we got from the
GAMBIT [UNINTELLIGIBLE] every
single one of those games has
something they have not seen
before in a card game.
Every one of those
projects had a
really interesting mechanic.
And as far as I can
tell, they've
all really been tested.
All right.
OK.
So I'm not going anymore
into IP discussions.
I spend too much time talking
to IP lawyers because we
create IP in this lab.
We create games.
And if anyone happens
to be interested.
I was considering
a career in law.
I'll be happy to go into
greater detail.
But for now, anymore
questions?
OK.
Let's just play games.