PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
So for the first part of this
course, we've learned
basically the ins and
outs of solving
linear systems of equations.
Today we're going to
do a little review
of the basic concepts.
Hopefully we'll see a few of
them in the following problem.
We're given a square matrix A--
a three by three square
matrix A-- where the last
entry is a parameter k.
And this parameter will vary.
And we'll see what happens to
the system of equations--
Ax equal to 2 3 7, for which k
it has a unique solution, for
which k it has infinitely
many solutions.
Then we'll find the
LU decomposition.
And finally, we'll write
down the complete
solution, the system.
So I'll give you a few
minutes to work this
problem on your own.
And then please come back
and see how I do it.
All right, welcome back.
So let's start with part A. For
which k does this system,
Ax equal 2, 3, 7 have
a unique solution?
So what do we know about square
systems of linear equations?
They have a unique solution
when the matrix A is
invertible.
So now when is A invertible?
It is invertible when
it is a full rank.
And how do we figure this out?
We do it by performing
row operations.
We do it by doing eliminations
on the matrix.
But since we want to simulate
in exam setting, It always
pays off to see what tasks
lie ahead of us.
So in part C, we're asked to
find the LU decomposition.
This means that when we do row
operations, we'd better keep
track what row operations
we're doing exactly.
In particular, we'll
write them down
as elementary matrices.
And in part D, we'll
be asked to compute
the complete solution.
And therefore it's good to
do row operations on the
augmented matrix A.
So let's do this.
I'm going to write this.
The augmented matrix A is the
following beast, 1, 1, 1, 1,
2, 3, 3, 4, k, and
then 2, 3, 7.
So first thing, we subtract
a multiple of row
one from row two.
And it's exactly negative
1 times the first
row plus the second.
Let me write down the
corresponding elementary
matrix that does this.
It's E, 2, 1.
And it's lower diagonal with
1's on the diagonal.
And it's going to be exactly
minus 1 in the first entry of
the second row.
So we get 1, 1, 1,
2, 0, 1, 2, 1.
And we copy down
the third row.
Now we subtract a multiple
of the first row
from the third one.
And let me write this here.
Yeah, we'll multiply the first
row by negative 3, and add it
to the third one.
This is accomplished by the
elementary matrix E, 3 1,
which is 1, 1, 1, negative
three, and then 0, 0.
OK, 1, 1, 1, 2, 0, 1, 2, 1.
We copy the first two rows.
And then the third one will be
0, 1, k minus 3, and 7 minus 3
times 2, 7 minus 6, 1.
We have essentially one last
row operation to perform.
Let me do it here.
So we'll subtract the second
row from the third one.
And we'll get 1, 1, 1, 2,
0, 1, 2, 1, 0, 0, k
minus 5, and then 0.
And this was achieved by the
elementary matrix E, 3, 2,
which was 1, 1, 1, and
then negative 1.
Because we multiplied the second
row by negative 1 and
added it to the third one.
So we got two matrix, which
is upper triangular.
And we want to figure out for
which value of the parameter k
is this matrix a full rank.
This is a pivot.
And we want this one to
be a pivot as well.
And that happens when
k minus 5 is not 0.
So when k is different from 5,
the matrix A is a full rank.
And therefore the system
Ax equals to 2, 3, 7
has a unique solution.
Now part B. For which
k do we have
infinitely many solutions?
So when are we in such
a situation?
We are in such a situation when
the null space of the
matrix A is nontrivial.
So the null space will be
nontrivial when this k minus 5
number here, which is what's
the pivot in the
first case, is 0.
So k minus 5 equals to 0.
You see there's a little
caveat here.
When k is equal to 5, we get the
third row of the augmented
matrix, 0, 0, 0, equal to 0.
This means that the matrix is
actually consistent, and we
indeed have a solution But if
this entry were non 0, then we
would get no solutions.
Now off to part C. We want to
compute the LU decomposition.
Well, we already got what the
matrix U is through performing
row operations.
It's this guy here.
Let me write it down--
1, 1, 1, 0, 1, 2,
0, 0, k minus 5.
And when k is equal to 4,
this entry's negative 1.
And now what about
the matrix L?
Well, how did we
get to this U?
We had the matrix A. We got the
matrix U. And what we did
was first we applied E, 2, 1.
Then we applied E, 3,
1 and then E, 3, 2.
We get A by inverting
this equation.
So it's going to be E, 2, 1
inverse E, 3, 1 inverse, E, 3,
2 inverse times U. And this is
our matrix L. And we know it's
fairly easy to invert these
elementary matrices E. We flip
the signs of the diagonal
entries.
I'm not going to write
down again the
inverses of these guys.
I'm just going to write the
product of the inverses.
And that's also very
easy to compute.
Because one, we invert
the signs.
We just send the numbers and
their corresponding entry of
L. I mean the following thing.
So minus 1 becomes a 1.
And it comes here, it's
respective entry.
For E, 3, 1, we flip the
sign, first 3, and
we plug it in here.
And for E, 3, 2, we flip
the sign of this guy.
It comes 1, and we
plug it in here.
So give me a few moments to
erase the board, and then I'll
do part four.
We're back, and we're going
to do part D now.
So we need to find the complete
solution of the
system for all k.
And we solved it for
k equal to 5.
The system had many,
many solutions.
And for k not equal to
5, it had only one.
So first let's look at the case
k not equal to 5 when the
matrix A was invertible.
It's not hard to see what
the solution of
the system then is.
It's going to be--let me
just write it down.
So when k is not equal
to 5, this was non 0.
Therefore, x3 needs to be 0.
When x3 is 0, we have
x2 plus 2 times x3.
So x2 plus 0 equals 1.
Therefore x2 is 1.
And then we go back
to the first row.
We have x1 plus x2
plus x3 equals 2.
So x1 plus 1 plus 0 equals 2.
So x1 plus 1 equals 2.
And therefore x1 is 1.
Good.
Now what about k
equalled to 5?
Then we see that x3 is
a free variable.
So the solution will
be x1, x2, x3.
x3 can be any number c.
From the second row, we'll
get the value of x2.
It's 1 minus 2 times x3.
So 1 minus 2 times c.
And x1 is 2 minus x2 minus x3.
So let me rewrite this.
It's 2 minus x2 is 1 minus--
aah, chalk--
2c minus c, 1 minus 2c, c.
So we'll decompose this vector
here into a component which is
independent of c and a
component which is
a multiple of c.
So this is 2 minus 1.
It should be 1, 1,
0 plus c times--
we'll have two c minus
c c, so c times 1.
Here we'll have minus
2c so negative 2.
And here we'll have 1.
And thus we get the particular
solution for the system and
the special solution
for the system.
We're kind of done here.
If you're at an exam, you should
immediately start the
next problem.
Good luck, and Ill
see you later.