PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video, what I'd like
us to do is answer the
following question.
Suppose that f is a continuous,
differentiable function.
And if it's derivative, if f
prime is never 0, and a is not
equal to b, then show that f of
a is not equal to f of b.
I'm going to let you think about
it for a while, see if
you can come up with a good
reason for that, and then I'll
be back to explain my reasons.
OK.
Our object, again, is to show,
if f is a continuous and
differentiable and its
derivative is never 0 and
you're looking at two x values
that are different, show that
their y values have
to be different.
Show that if the inputs are
different, the outputs have to
be different.
Now, this might remind you of
something you saw in lecture
about if the derivative has a
sign, show the function, if
the derivative is positive, show
the function is always
increasing, or if the derivative
is negative, show
the function is always
decreasing.
So this is a similar type
of problem to that.
So what we're going
to use is actually
the mean value theorem.
If you'll notice, I have f.
It does satisfy the mean
value theorem on an
interval from a to b.
I haven't even specified which
is bigger, a or b.
But it doesn't matter
in this case.
So what do we know?
The mean value theorem tells us
that if we look at-- well,
let's just write it out-- f of
b minus f of a over b minus a
is equal to f prime of c--
and what do we know-- for
c between a and b.
So we want to know whether
or not f of b minus f of
a can ever be 0.
We're trying to show that
it cannot be 0.
So we're going to isolate this
expression and show that this
subtraction cannot be 0.
Well, how do we do that?
Let me come over here to give
us a little more room.
I'm going to rewrite the
mean value theorem.
I'm going to multiply through
by b minus a.
So we get f prime of
c time b minus a.
Now, we just want to show,
again, that f of b minus f of
a cannot be 0.
What's the only thing-- well,
not only thing, we know two
things-- what two things
do we know?
We know f prime of c is not 0.
That was given to you.
f prime is never 0, so certainly
at any fixed value,
f prime of c is not 0.
So we know this term is not 0.
We also know that b is not equal
to a, so we know b minus
a is not 0.
The only way to get a product
of two numbers to be 0 is if
one of them is 0.
So this in fact, this product
is not equal to 0.
The fact that this product is
not equal to 0 tells us f of b
minus f of a is not
equal to 0.
And that alone is enough to
conclude that f of b is not
equal to f of a.
So, again, let me just point
out of this is probably
reminds you very much of the
type of thing you've seen
where you were showing if f
prime had a sign, then you
could determine whether f was
increasing or decreasing.
It's the same type of
problem as that.
It's exploiting what the mean
value theorem tells you.
So I think we'll stop there.