PROFESSOR: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, I'd like to tackle
a problem in numerical
integration of ODEs
specifically on Euler's method.
And the problem we're interested
in considering
today is the ODE y prime equals
y squared minus xy.
And we're interested in
integrating the solution that
starts at y of zero is equal
to negative 1 using a step
size of 0.5.
And we want to integrate
it to y of 1.
And then for the second part,
we're interested in if our
first step of integration
either overestimates or
underestimates the
exact solution.
So I'll let you think about
this and work it out for
yourself, and I'll come
back in a moment.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So as I mentioned before, this
is a problem in numerics.
And specifically, whenever
you're given an ODE, you can
almost always numerically
integrate it on a computer.
And this is quite possibly the
simplest algorithm for
numerical integration.
So specifically, what we do is
we take the left-hand side,
the derivative, y prime, and we
approximate it using a very
simple finite difference
formula.
So if I take y prime and
approximate it as y of n plus
1 minus y of n divided by h,
where h is the step size, then
I can approximate the continuous
ODE using this
simple formula.
So here h as I mentioned
is the step size.
F in this case is the right-hand
side of the ODE And
we see that y of n plus 1 minus
y of n divided by h is
an approximation to y prime.
In addition, we can also write
down x of n plus 1 is just
equal to x of n plus h.
And I'm using subscripts n here
just to denote the step
of the algorithm.
So for part A, we're asked to
integrate the solution.
It starts at y of zero is equal
to negative 1 to y of 1.
So what this means for part A
is we want x of zero to be
zero, and we want y of zero
to be negative 1.
Now to further integrate this
equation, the quickest way to
do it, especially if you're
in a test scenario,
is to build a table.
So a nice table to build is
one that has a column n,
x of n, y of n.
I'm going to write f of n.
F of n is to denote
f evaluated at x
of n and y of n.
And then, it's also useful to
write down h times f of n
because the quantity h times f
of n comes up in the addition
of y of n plus 1 is equal to
y of n plus h times f of n.
And in the problem under
consideration, I'm just going
to fill in the first two columns
because they're the
easiest. We have n is equal
to zero, 1 and 2.
X of n is starting
off at zero.
So x of zero is zero.
X of 1 is going to be 0.5.
And then, x of 2
is equal to 1.
In addition, we're also told
that y of zero is equal to
negative 1.
And now for f of n, I'll just
use the side here, what's f of
zero going to be?
Well, it's going to be
y of zero minus x
of zero y of zero.
So this gives us 1 and zero.
So we can fill in a 0.1 here,
which means that h times f of
1 is going to be 0.5.
And now with h of f of n,
we can fill in y of 1.
So y of 1 is just going to
be y of zero plus 0.5.
And y of zero is negative 1.
So this is going to
be negative 0.5.
Now, we need to fill
in f of 1.
So this is going to be y of 1
squared minus x of 1 y of 1.
Now y of 1 squared, this is
negative 0.5 squared.
X of 1 is 0.5.
And y of 1 is again,
negative 0.5.
So this gives us one quarter
plus one quarter, which
together is just 0.5.
So we have 0.5 in
this square now.
And then h times 0.5 is 0.5
squared, which is just 0.25.
Now y of 2 is just going to be
y of 1 plus h times f of 1.
So we know h of f of 1 is
0.25, and y of 1 is just
negative 0.5.
So this is going to
be negative 0.25.
And we note that this is the
answer we're looking for.
So just to conclude our
approximation y of 2, which is
approximately y evaluated
at 1, is going
to be negative 0.25.
So for part B, we're asked
does our approximation
negative 0.25 overestimate or
underestimate the actual exact
solution of the ODE?
Now, in general, what you want
to do is you want to take the
second derivative.
However, for this problem, we're
only going to consider
the first step.
So our first step, does it
overestimate or underestimate
the exact solution?
And to do this, what we want
to do is we want to take a
look at the concavity.
So we want to look at
y double prime.
So y double prime is going
to be d by dx of y prime.
And we know from the ODE y prime
is y squared minus xy.
So I can work this out to be
2y y prime, just using the
chain rule, minus y
minus xy prime.
And at the first step, we're
interested in evaluating this
quantity at the point
x equals zero, y is
equal to negative 1.
So this is the first step.
So at x is equal to zero, y is
equal to negative 1, this
simplifies to minus
2y prime plus 1.
This term right here
drops off.
And y prime specifically
is going to be y
squared minus xy.
So we get 2.
Y squared is going to be
1 minus zero plus 1.
So together, this is going
to give us minus 1.
And we note that this
is less than zero.
So we've just shown that the
concavity at our starting
point, x equals zero, y
is equal to negative 1
is less than zero.
So what this means is that our
initial approximation is going
to overestimate the solution.
We can see that it's going to
overestimate it just by a
quick sketch.
For example, if I were to plot y
and x, we're starting off at
this point, x is equal
to zero, y is
equal to negative 1.
So this is y zero is equal
to negative 1.
We know the exact solutions
increasing, and it's concave
down because the second
derivative is negative 1.
And by Euler's formula, what
we're doing is we're
approximating the solution
using a tangent
line at this point.
So we can see that our
approximate solution when we
take one step to go from here to
here, so this is x of zero,
this is x of 1, our solution
which is now going to be y of
1 here is going to overestimate
the curve.
And the reason it overestimates
it, I'll just
reiterate again is because our
solution is concave down.
So this concludes the problem.
And just to reiterate, when
dealing with Euler's method,
the best thing to do is just
to build a table like this.
And you can quickly
work it out.
Secondly, if you're asked
questions on if your numerical
solution overestimates or
underestimates the exact
solution, typically what you
want to do is you want to look
at the concavity.
And then, you can always just
sketch a quick diagram on the
back of a notepad to see if the
solution overestimates or
underestimates the
exact solution.
So I'd like to conclude here.
And I'll see you next time.