The Euler's method applet helps
us understand numerical
methods for approximating
solutions to
differential equations.
I can choose the differential
equation using this pull down
menu, and I've selected the
equation y prime equals y
squared minus x, the same
equation that we used in the
isocline applet.
The graphing window shows a
slope field, the slope field
of this equation.
And the value of the slope
field can be read off by
rolling over the window.
It's read off on the right hand
side here. f of xy is
various values depending
on where I'm located.
I've also chosen an initial
condition, initial value, of x
equals x, zero is zero,
and y zero is minus 1.
I can see the actual solution
with that initial condition by
pressing Actual from this set
of boxes and checking Start.
Now a curve is drawing on
the graphing plane.
This is the solution with
that initial condition.
And a table of values shows
up in this left table.
We can see that this is one of
the solutions which is sucked
into the funnel.
So we understand the values
of y of x quite
well when x is large.
But what if I want to know
the value of y of 1?
According to the table over
here, the value is
approximately minus 0.83.
But how do we know that?
Euler's method is the simplest
numerical method.
It uses the tangent line
approximation.
If I set the step size to be 1,
I can then click Start, and
this will draw a tangent line
segment with delta x equal to
1 starting at my initial
condition, and with slope
given by the slope field
at that point.
So the tangent line
approximation to y of 1 is the
value zero.
Well, that's not very good.
But I can improve things by
using a smaller step size.
So let's go down to a step
size of 1/4, start again.
Now I've drawn a tangent line
segment, but the horizontal
distance is only 1/4.
Let's see what if we can see
this more clearly by pressing
the zoom key.
This will zoom in on the same
picture that we had before.
I can measure the slope field at
the end point of this green
line segment.
It seems to be about 0.32.
And by pressing Next Step, I can
draw a line segment moving
off with that slope.
So this now, it produces a
polygon, the Euler polygon,
which will stay closer to the
actual curve than the simple
tangent line approximation
did.
I can continue this process by
continuing to say Next Step.
The table of values appears on
the left, and we discover that
the Euler approximation to y
of 1 with step size 1/4, is
minus 0.75.
Much better than the earlier
value we had.
And I can improve things still
further by choosing a
smaller step size.
In fact, you get as close as
you want to the actual
solution by selecting
sufficiently small step sizes.
Let's do one more example
with step size of 1/8.
Now I will click 8 times to
produce an Euler polygon with
8 segments.
And I have an estimate
of minus 0.8.
All of these estimates
are too large.
All of these curves, these
polygons, lie above the actual
solution curve.
Let's see if we can
see why this is.
You'll notice that the slope
field is given by the formula
y squared minus x.
So as x increases, the slope
field decreases in value.
So as we're moving out along one
of these Euler struts, the
slope field is decreasing
under it.
And that causes the actual
solution to fall below the
Euler polygon.
And that process will
continue as I
iterate the Euler process.
So the general rule is, if the
direction field is decreasing
in the x direction, you should
expect the actual solution to
be less than the
Euler estimate.
There are lots of things that
can go wrong in this kind of
numerical work.
To see one of them,
let's unzoom.
Zoom back, clear the screen,
redraw the actual solution,
and choose step size 1.
Now instead of wanting to
compute y of 1, suppose that I
wanted to compute the value of
the solution at x equals 6.
Well if I try doing this
using step size of 1,
let's see what happens.
So I begin.
I have the same strut
I had before.
It's too large, but now the
slope field has a negative
value so that comes back down.
Things are looking better.
In the next step,
I've overshot.
And if I take another step, then
I've overshot again in
the other direction,
more dramatically.
And now the slow feels
even more negative.
So when I take the next step,
I've overshot yet again, more
dramatically.
And if I take the next step,
now my estimate for the
solution, which is down here at
x equals 6 is the value 7,
this is in the range where the
slope field continues to
increase forever.
And so my estimated solution
will zoom off towards
infinity, while the actual
curve is down here.
I call this catastrophic
overshoot.
It's just one of a number of
different things that can go
wrong when you try to use
these numerical methods.