The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
Some content in this audio is
not covered under a Creative
Commons license.
For more information see the
course materials on the MIT
OpenCourseWare website.
PROFESSOR: All right.
So this, of course, does not
actually mean that you have
more time for assignment
three.
In fact it eats a little
bit of your time
for assignment three.
Sorry about that, but
I think this is a
net gain for everyone.
Right.
With that out of the
way, Mia Consalvo.
Actually, a lot of you probably
are already familiar,
you might have taken
any of her classes.
She is the visiting lecturer--
visiting professor, visiting
professor--
here at GAMBIT.
Are you teaching something
in the spring?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
Cheating and ethics in games.
Brian can tell you
all about it.
PROFESSOR: You can take this
as the sneak preview--
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
This is a taster of a little
bit of what we do.
Thanks.
OK.
So it sounds like you all
have lots of opinions,
which will be good.
So to get started-- and
actually, I don't like the
term lecturer because I don't
get to lecture very much--
I'm going to start by handing
around some index cards and I
want you to take a few minutes
and generate some examples of
ethical elements, procedures,
episodes, games, the more
specific you can
be the better.
And I'm actually going to
collect these at the end
because, as Phil mentioned, I'm
teaching this ethics and
games class and I want
to bring in more
examples of this stuff.
So this will actually
be useful for me.
AUDIENCE: Talking
about in games.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
So we were just talking about
Fable, but if you could think
of a more specific example from
it, a level, different
choices that you get with
characters in certain games,
whatever you can come up with
in terms of are there
interesting ethical dilemmas,
situations.
AUDIENCE: Wait.
Is this within the context of
the game, or are we talking
about in a multiplayer game
your conduct with other
players, and this
kind of thing?
AUDIENCE: Or, when I was in
Owen's office whether or not
to steal the swag.
GUEST SPEAKER: You can do it
within MMOs as well, or a
multiplayer game.
You can continue to write
examples [UNINTELLIGIBLE] if
you can think of them.
But just to get you started--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Well then
you can start by
giving me an example.
AUDIENCE: Sure.
OK.
So I have a couple.
Fighting games, obviously,
there's always kind of
questions and debate about
whether something's cheap or
viable or should you be
allowed to do it.
Yeah, so if maybe--
I'm trying to think how to
describe it-- so, people who
play casually will tend to say,
oh, if you do this with
this character then it's cheap
and you shouldn't do that,
whereas the community at large
and people who play seriously
tend to say, well, if you can
do something you should be
allowed to do it, and if
you can't overcome it
that's your own fault.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
So violating a community norm?
AUDIENCE: Yeah
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: Even if it's
allowed in the rules but it's
against a community norm.
OK.
It's like using
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
You hadn't thought about that.
Evan?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, sorry.
AUDIENCE: I have a bunch of
stuff, which is related to
griefing just generally.
So let's just go for the one
which is one of my favorites.
So this is griefing for comic
effect, or role playing
griefing but doing it in a way
which you are then going to
write a blog about.
And from your character's
perspective the
griefing makes sense.
So there is a particular player
that played EverQuest.
His name is Fansy
the Famous Bard.
He was on the good team's side
and he griefed evil because
evil is bad.
So people who had played evil
characters, he would run
around and annoy in a really
frustrating way, which
eventually caused the makers
of EverQuest to change the
rules of the server so that
people could kill him, where
previously they weren't
allowed to.
GUEST SPEAKER: What did he do?
AUDIENCE: There was this
mechanic in EverQuest where if
you were close to a monster
it became aggressive
and attacked you.
So he had a low level character
who was able to run
really fast and--
GUEST SPEAKER: I have
heard of him.
AUDIENCE: --he would run around
and then run over the
top of evil people, and then the
monsters would detach from
him and then kill them.
Oh yeah, and the catch
was that the server
was a mobile server.
Aside from-- that is why-- so
you can't complain to GMs
about a player's behavior,
aside from there was a
built-in protection for players
so that if they're
level four or below-- so a very
low level-- they can't be
killed by higher
level players.
And so he just sat on
the cusp of that.
Yet there's still a way to use
his ability to go around and
grief people from
a higher level.
It was pretty great.
And he did it all totally in
character as well, which is
what makes this a good grief.
AUDIENCE: Is that me?
OK.
I think of Portal when they ask
you to use your portable
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
You get to burn up the Cube.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
You don't want to, and
they make you.
And you've tried to leave
without it a few times and you
try to break the machine
and it doesn't work.
It's very sad.
GUEST SPEAKER: I feel bad.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
How about you?
AUDIENCE: I thought of Jason
Rohrer's Sleep Is Death.
GUEST SPEAKER: What
is that like?
AUDIENCE: It's a more of like a
story telling tool where you
have one player that can control
the 2D world and then
you have one player who is
the player, and they can
interact with it.
And each player has 30 seconds
to make some kind of action,
and then you make a story
going back and forth.
And what happens is--
you can play online with people,
and the controller
character or player will have
some kind of story that they
want to tell.
And so it's up to the player
whether or not they want to go
along with the story and act
like a character in that world
or try and break the story.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
What's the name of it again?
AUDIENCE: Sleep Is Death.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
I forgot what it's called.
GUEST SPEAKER: Actually that's
more griefing, would you say?
AUDIENCE: Kind of.
AUDIENCE: Is that by the same
person as [INAUDIBLE]
Passage?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
AUDIENCE: In Ocarina of Time
there's the treasure box
gambling game.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] achieve if
you use the Lens of Truth.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
So there's a built-in mechanic
that allows you to cheat.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
legit.
AUDIENCE: Yeah [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
use it anyway so it's not
like a [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I just like include
the [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Lucky man.
AUDIENCE: So in Civ IV for each
and every sector there's
some sort of slavery mechanic,
but I guess in Civ IV's
example I know.
Many players don't seem to mind
the fact that what is
considered slavery is ethically
wrong, but in the
game it's affectionately called
whipping, and it's
considered a very efficient
way of converting food--
GUEST SPEAKER: What's
it called?
AUDIENCE: Whipping.
AUDIENCE: You whip and then
you [INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
So it's efficient but
it's slavery.
AUDIENCE: You use granaries to
offset the population loss,
and if you [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
farms it becomes a very
effective way to produce,
especially in the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
a lot of people that way.
AUDIENCE: So in The
Sims [INAUDIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: But you
have to watch them
flail around and die.
AUDIENCE: And they get
tired and [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: A more obscure example
that goes along with
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] griefing is
discussions over the point in
the game the community
is in MMOs.
Specifically, there was
apparently a huge problem in
an obscure MMO called Skyress
where a large community of the
players was there to basically
anthropomorph and RP.
A large community of the players
was there to play to
win because it had a large
combat economy system.
And this, tactically, almost
tore the game apart because it
was such a small number of
people over what should be the
point to this game when,
mechanically, somebody thinks
they're alive.
Also in Canara Rey you can blow
up people, and they'll
even put the star.
It was traumatizing.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but they're in
a giant ball of awesome.
AUDIENCE: That's true.
GUEST SPEAKER: Well, it's
not really murder but--
AUDIENCE: I didn't want
to get starred.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It's starification.
AUDIENCE: If they don't
suffocate on the inside of the
kevlar first.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: It's like the
Borg, once you're in there you
know it's a better way
of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
You're grateful.
AUDIENCE: So in F.E.A.R there's
a nail gun, and when
you kill people with it the game
does a really good job of
spectacularly nailing them to
surfaces in the environment.
So if someone jumps and you
shoot them in the shoulder you
can nail them up
to the ceiling.
And if you nail them multiple
times you can have them
hanging by a hand, and by their
head, and by a foot from
the ceiling or from the wall.
Anyway, [INTERPOSING VOICES]
on forums there were entire
threads devoted to sharing
screenshots of your most
spectacular nails, just the
absolutely, most gruesome--
five nails to the eye suspending
a guy from
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
kind of thing.
And it's pretty--
Anyway, and there's a lot of
debate on these threads
because most people will be
like, yeah, look at this
picture this one's awesome and
everything it has blood
spatters everywhere
and all that.
But every third or fourth post
it would be like, you guys are
so messed up, this is wrong.
And it's not real, you idiot,
but that fact that you like it
is still real.
And people would argue at
great lengths over this.
And I remember chancing upon
these forums and being like,
is this messed up?
I'm not sure.
GUEST SPEAKER: So is it more
efficient in the game to use
the nail gun to kill
people than other
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It's a hell
of a lot more fun.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
But it's not like the game
forces you to do it if you
would not want to.
AUDIENCE: No it doesn't.
You could use other guns, but
at some point, if you don't
have enough ammo for the other
guns you would switch to the
nail gun, I guess.
it's a good gun.
Shotgun is fun too.
It disintegrates people
at short range.
AUDIENCE: I've now heard they're
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE] turn
people into skeletons.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
That one was in the expansion.
Yes. that was the original,
though.
The sniper rifle is a rail
gun that shoots a beam of
electricity and turns people
into big [UNINTELLIGIBLE] of
flesh off of their bones.
AUDIENCE: Delightful.
Grand Theft Auto, you can
get a prostitute for
money, you get help.
And then eventually you kill the
prostitute, and get your
money back.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: And then some of the
ones related to that is
BioShock where you can either
kill the little sisters and
harvest them for lots of good,
or lots of points, rather, or
save them and get a small amount
of points but you feel
better about yourself, which
actually in the end, ends us
being the better way to go.
GUEST SPEAKER: It's like you
get more if you save them?
AUDIENCE: If you kill them and
harvest them you get 10
points, let's say.
If you save them you
get five points.
But then after 10 saves you
get a bonus of 100 points.
So it ends up being more
efficient in the long run to
save them, more efficient in
the short run to kill them.
GUEST SPEAKER: And also if
you're going to kill them you
should kill them all.
Don't just knock off one.
AUDIENCE: In Age of Empires III
when you are colonizing
your colony you have the option
of exploiting the
native people to
help you fight.
They just help you fight.
GUEST SPEAKER: How is this
presented to exploit natives?
AUDIENCE: You establish an
outpost inside of their
residence area and you
supposedly train with them.
There's nothing really there
in the game, you just
literally put a house of yours
inside of their colony.
AUDIENCE: Also Microsoft's
selling that for $0.10.
AUDIENCE: Empires III?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Why?
AUDIENCE: I think it
was just yesterday.
I'm not sure.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: In inFAMOUS you can
choose whether to be bad or
good, and [UNINTELLIGIBLE] other
people or to help them
survive in a post-apocalyptic
world.
And I guess you can do the
same thing in Fallout.
GUEST SPEAKER: Well
also, inFAMOUS
forces you more to choose.
Remember Ash was playing
that in our class?
And she said you really
had to go one way or
the other to get--
on either end of the spectrum
there were special abilities.
If you stayed in the middle
you got nothing.
Although there are certain
things you can build off of.
AUDIENCE: So there's also
getting a following.
You can gain people that
travel with you.
Like based off if you're
good, neutral, or bad.
AUDIENCE: I'm sorry.
I was going to say, in Fallout
3 there's one particularly
really good example where you
get trapped in this dream
world that this guy is creating
for you and a bunch
of other people, which you don't
know that it's a dream
world at first.
You know it's a dream or
something but you don't know
that these are real people and
they're dreaming with you.
And he tells you to kill the
other people in the dream in
order to let you get out because
he is in complete
control of it.
You can kill them and you'll
get out fine and all the
people will be dead.
Or there's ways that aren't--
you're not told but there are
ways to just go around all of
it and just get out without
killing anyone.
AUDIENCE: They stole
that from--
in Baldur's Gate 2 there's
a similar thing.
AUDIENCE: I was actually going
to talk [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So the first
thing I would mention
is a Emerald Items.
GUEST SPEAKER: Just one thing.
AUDIENCE: God of War,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], how so many
times you'll be fighting
monsters and all of a sudden a
bunch of civilians come by and
you just let them go, but
there's no fun there.
If you kill them you get life
and experience so it's--
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
reward you for killing them?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Oh that's bizarre.
AUDIENCE: You get
your life back.
AUDIENCE: Maybe some
[INTERPOSING VOICES] do that
in the story.
AUDIENCE: Huh?
AUDIENCE: You're Kratos.
AUDIENCE: Oh, you are
the God of War.
AUDIENCE: Well, you become the
God of-- well, pretty much you
just go around killing,
hacking and slashing
everything up.
AUDIENCE: OK.
So these are just civilians
who are doing nothing.
AUDIENCE: Yes, they're just
running away from everybody
for their lives from scary
monsters, and then you come
and just hack them
all into pieces.
Also in the game, the second
one, in order to pass on you
have to translate something.
And to translate it you smash
your head into it and then
they say you have to sacrifice
it in blood so you just smash
them into pieces until they
have the blood sacrifice.
GUEST SPEAKER: It
feels so good.
AUDIENCE: Do you have
to do that?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Oh, OK.
AUDIENCE: In Indigo Prophecy you
switch between different
sets of characters.
And one of them is a guy who
commited a murder, and then
you switch to the cops who
are trying to catch him.
In one of the earlier scenes you
play as a cop you bring in
a witness and you're trying to
make up the artist rendering
of what the murderer
looks like.
And so you can choose whether
or not to make a faithful
rendering and bring the cops
closer to catching him or to
make one that looks nothing like
him so you can evade them
when you play as
the other guy.
GUEST SPEAKER: Interesting.
If you make it not look
like you as killer--
AUDIENCE: Then there are other
clues he has to find in order
to finally track him down.
GUEST SPEAKER: Can you--
AUDIENCE: How do you
win this game?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
events.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: I mean is the
goal to catch the killer, or
for the killer to get
away, or you just--
AUDIENCE: It's actually an
adventure game so the goal is
to maintain the story.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
Philip.
AUDIENCE: In a LARP that I
played a long time ago I was
allowed to draw one item from
a location every hour.
The game ran from noon to
midnight on three different
days but I couldn't play
before 2:00 PM.
So I come in at 2:00 PM.
How many items was I allowed to
draw when I came into the
game given that I already missed
two hours of the game?
And if the answer is, well, I
can make that up, then what
happens if I miss an hour
half way through the--
and if I forget.
No one's looking into the box.
GUEST SPEAKER: What
did you do?
AUDIENCE: What did I do?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
I think I drew more than one
item at the beginning of the
game and I made sure
I never forgot.
So, honor system.
A lot of LARPs are based
on the honor system.
AUDIENCE: So in Final Fantasy
VII, like a lot of Japanese
RPGs, you get used to the idea
of walking into people's
houses and just digging in the
items you find, except in FF
VII they actually mix it
up a couple of times.
There are a couple of instances
where you go in
there and do that and maybe it's
fairly insignificant, you
could buy it easily with a
couple pieces of gold or gil
or whatever it is.
And then the person walks out of
their kitchen or something,
and it's, did you just
take my item?
And you have the option
saying yes or no.
And if you say no then you get
to keep it but if you say yes
they're, what the hell?
Give it back.
I thought it was interesting.
AUDIENCE: I have something
that hasn't really been
touched on.
When you're running a very large
scale Guild in an MMO
you reach a point where you need
to distribute from these
high end The community optimal
thing to do is for the people
who are in charge of the Guild
to allocate who gets what so
that you can, for instance, kick
out the characters that's
most important for the Guild
to have for the [? game ?]
to progress.
But for the most part, actual
members of the Guild don't
really like that because you
would like to receive some
kind of reward for having put
in time to the Guild.
And going a long time without
ever having gotten anything is
really frustrating, so people
come up with these intricate
systems for DKP for distributing
your resources,
essentially, to try to balance
the interests of the
individual and the interest
of the community.
GUEST SPEAKER: How many of you
are unsure what DKP is?
Dragon Kill Points.
There are these sometimes
elaborate schemes for if you
participate in these raids,
you get so many points.
And the idea is the Guild claims
everything that drops
physically.
And you build up points, and at
some point you have enough
to buy a certain item.
So let's say you're on a raid
and you just got something
really cool last time.
If something drops this time
that you could really use,
even though you're there you
don't necessarily get it
because you just spent
all your DKP.
And there's lots of Guild drama
over how these DKPs--
AUDIENCE: Primary source
of Guild drama.
AUDIENCE: Have you
been playing?
GUEST SPEAKER: Hm?
AUDIENCE: Dan, have you
been playing this?
AUDIENCE: You end up by
raids and then you
catch them before breakfast.
GUEST SPEAKER: And there
are black out dates.
AUDIENCE: Running one of these
things is actually
surprisingly complicated and
hard, particularly--
so my little experience,
I ran a Guild which
incorporated this.
One problem that happens is if
you have fixed prices for
things then you get DKP
inflation as prices change.
And what happens is-- and it's
incredibly complicated-- to
where, now, you have to reprice
everything constantly.
So instead we went for an
auction-based system where
people bid on things.
And then prices correct
themselves.
However, people can collude in
auctions, which then causes a
resentment in people who aren't
in on the collusion,
and the whole thing is
just a nightmare.
And now I don't run a Guild
anymore and I'm really happy.
AUDIENCE: In games like Pokemon
or Animal Crossing you
can decide whether or not
to change the time on
your DNS or game cube.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] score
came out I was like
10 I had a bed time.
I didn't have a lot of time
to catch up on Pokemon.
AUDIENCE: You can do that too
and manipulate the RNG and get
the stats you want.
Perfect for
[INTERPOSING VOICES].
AUDIENCE: There's also-- besides
whenever you do the
random number generator hacks
in games in order to get a
certain drop that's normally 1%
but you can increase it to
up to almost 100--
but what I was going to say was
that in Fallout 3 you can
pickpocket people.
And something you do when you
pickpocket people, as long as
you don't get caught, you can
take a grenade from your
inventory and place it in their
pocket, and all of a
sudden they're, oh my god,
there's a grenade, run away.
And it will blow up inside
their pocket
and they will explode.
AUDIENCE: What game?
AUDIENCE: Fallout 3.
And the funny thing is that
that's actually an achievement
to blow someone up.
GUEST SPEAKER: Do
you get, other
than the joy and giggles--
AUDIENCE: Well besides from
the joy and giggles,
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
you can pick their pockets,
whatever they have in their
pocket you can get.
AUDIENCE: That is still left.
AUDIENCE: Well you take
it out as you're
putting the grenade in.
AUDIENCE: You wouldn't want
their [UNINTELLIGIBLE] to be
damaged by the grenade.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you're
just putting them
in at the same time.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: And it can
be a little tricky.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
Anybody have any representative
examples we
haven't touched on?
AUDIENCE: I used to play a lot
of [UNINTELLIGIBLE] online and
they had a bunch of really
sophisticated rules that
applied in certain situations.
So there were a lot of times
in the game where you just
flat out lie to people and have
them go into situations
that were unsafe for them.
For example, if people were in
your house-- in an urban
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] game if people
are inside your house
they are automatically flagged
as attackable by you because
they're in your house and you
might not have let them in.
And they can run outside their
house and they'll be
unattackable by you.
But you can also put a trash
barrel in front of your door,
which only you can destroy and
nobody else can destroy, and
they can't run through that.
So you would invite them in
to trade them something or
enjoying your meal.
And they're in your house, then
you put a trash barrel
there so they can never leave
and just kill them.
GUEST SPEAKER: Or just leave
them there, right?
AUDIENCE: Or just leave them.
There are tons and
tons of rules.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
It's really bad, It's
really bad.
I was part of the Guild that
did this to me and then I
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I was like, that
is pretty sick.
There are a bunch of way to
steal tons and tons of money
from people and they didn't
realize that you did.
GUEST SPEAKER: Did you get
that [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Yes.
But I feel like just blatantly
lying to people as a tactic
instead of just being
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: The question about
real world money for in game
items especially for competitive
games whether or
not it's allowed by the GMs.
Those are two different
questions.
One is the ethical question from
the player's standpoint.
And the other is what does it
mean in terms of the player
character relation
in the game.
AUDIENCE: I was going to say
one thing that comes up
especially in board games that
have a lot of positive
feedback, it's called
king making.
Good examples are like
in Monopoly,
or Settlers or Munchkin.
And how it works, let's say you
and Owen and I are playing
Settlers and typically what
will happen is say Owen is
winning but I'm typically really
far behind, or someone
is going to be in a position
where they have
no chance of winning.
So if I decide he's winning and
you're close second and
I'm distant third, what people
do is say, hey Mia, I will
give you everything for your one
little card and then you
can win because I'm
mad at Owen.
And then it comes up, like you
said, in Monopoly there's this
question of is that a really
jerky thing to do?
The rules don't disallow it.
It's an ongoing debate.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Don't do that.
AUDIENCE: Similarly in Monopoly,
the rules don't
specifically allow If I have
two [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
we'll exchange that and promise
each other immunity on
our properties or something
that you're not allowed to
actually promise each other.
Or if [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
will always do it to you and
will promise me half the
profits or something like that
where clearly the third person
is now shut out of the game
and can't win because
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
advantage even though we're
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] with things
that aren't explicitly
allowed in the rules.
GUEST SPEAKER: How many of you
have played Dragon Age?
AUDIENCE: I've seen it played.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
I've just, I'm playing
through it right now.
I've been thinking about
these issues a lot.
Actually on my first play
through there's a scene where
there's a kid possessed
by a demon.
You have the choice whether
you kill him or not.
The first time I killed
him and--
I thought everybody did.
I had no compunction about it.
It was like die demon,
demon die.
It turns out everybody really
hated that, all the other
characters, my companions.
And this play time through
I was I'll try it.
And it was all this extra
work involved.
But it seems like in the game
whether you want to do the
good thing or not it generally
works to your advantage to do
the good thing because you get
more stuff, either better
approval ratings from your
companions who then unlock
bonuses or you get stuff.
Whereas, being the jerk--
AUDIENCE: It kind of depends
on who your companions are.
GUEST SPEAKER: Does it?
Who approves?
AUDIENCE: People like the--
AUDIENCE: Like Elven assassin,
I can't remember
what his name is.
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, Zevran.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
but she likes all the
jerky things.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
I didn't have Zevran the
first time through.
That's why [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Also that one
guy, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
that can spot
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
No, no, another guy.
I think you can get him
on your team at least.
He's in the temple where there's
that big dragon and
where you're doing some ash
quest or something.
And he wants you to pour
dragon blood on
the ashes or something.
I'm pretty sure you can
get him on your team.
Am I right or am I wrong?
But I think you can get them
as part of your final army.
And they're pretty good,
and they're bad.
GUEST SPEAKER: I just chose
poorly, apparently, my
companions [INAUDIBLE]
moralistic ones like
kill a kid.
OK.
In the reading you did
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
talks about different choices
and the way that game
designers are putting
games together.
And he talks about two different
categories, the open
and the closed ethical
systems.
The open was more letting
players determine for
themselves [UNINTELLIGIBLE] they
want to take and kind of
seeing how that goes through,
whereas the closed is the
system that forces a
particular way of
playing upon you.
And so, just kind of going
through these here, where do
you see them falling in terms
of closed and open?
AUDIENCE: Wait.
You confused me with those
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
You said open means that you
have the decision on how to
value actions or
on what to do?
GUEST SPEAKER: Well he says, for
example, in The Sims with
drowning, he mentions The Sims
is an open game where you can
do what you want and think
about what happens.
AUDIENCE: A definitely closed
example, it's not up there,
but I'll give you a closed
example up there
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
In the first Modern Warfare
game they have a flashback
sequence where you have to snipe
the featured bad guy,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And even though in the game
story he survives your attempt
to kill him, if you don't
actually hit him with the
bullet the game won't
let you progress.
So you have to go and basically
snipe this dude no
matter what, the game
won't let you do it.
And that's just part
of the story,
that's just how it works.
And it's dubiously moral that
you should be meddling with
such affairs but you know.
And it actually comes back to
bite you later in the game
because you're at the place
where it's causing problems
for you the fact that you
tried snipe this guy.
And they had you play
the flashback but
you have to do it.
And it's all directed
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Isn't like the Cube
murder closed as well because
you don't have a choice.
You have to kill
him to move on.
GUEST SPEAKER: The what?
AUDIENCE: The Cube murder
in [INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, the Cube.
I'm thinking Q. Yeah, that would
be closed because you
simply can't move on, and you
just have to deal with your--
AUDIENCE: But that's the joke.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, yeah.
Exactly.
AUDIENCE: Starification
is fairly closed.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
You can bad mouth those people
you just can't play
Katamari I'm sorry.
AUDIENCE: I have a question
actually about when we passed
Sleep Is Death griefing.
It seems to me that was
intended by design.
GUEST SPEAKER: Which one?
AUDIENCE: The Sleep Is Death
griefing directly under
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Like the idea that I am a GM,
you're a player, and part of
the challenge is not knowing
whether your player is going
to play along with you.
But that's part of the game.
So I don't know that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
closed or open.
That tension's intended.
GUEST SPEAKER: I don't know.
AUDIENCE: It's still
open, right?
GUEST SPEAKER: I would say this
one is open, I guess,
because you are allowed
to do what you want.
The example he gives for closed
ended is-- one of
them-- is Manhunt where you have
to kill the bull and the
more grisly you kill them
the better in some ways
you don't like it.
There's just no way to
get through the game.
The other example
he also gives is
Shadow of the Colossus.
And that one, especially, it's
ambiguous in terms of, OK, I
have to kill these things, and
if you play through you
realize well, wait a minute,
they're just hanging out
they're not really doing
anything necessarily bad but I
have to keep killing
them anyhow.
And you can start to feel guilty
but it's what you have
to do to play the game.
So you would say that's
a closed system.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE] and
Indigo Prophecy might be
closed because you have to go on
with the story, you have to
make decisions such in
order to progress on.
AUDIENCE: I feel like it
isn't-- is that right?
AUDIENCE: I think the idea is
that closed would be you don't
get to make decisions.
Closed is like if you want to
play the game you have to make
this moral decision-- you don't
have a choice in the
moral decision, you
have to be evil.
And that's one thing.
And another game could be you
have to be good but if you
have the decision between both
paths then that's open, I
believe, right?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
AUDIENCE: The premise behind
Inidgo Prophecy was that you
can choose to do any action in
the game it would just have a
different ending as a result.
But in practice it only had a
few endings but the premise
was that it would have countless
endings depending on
your actions.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE] and
Age of Empires III is going to
have some closed--
Maid exploitation because for
the campaigns at least
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
there are conditions for
completing a scenario
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, so you have
to do [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: The [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
is open.
[? QTA ?] is open.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Most of the
rest are open.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
Fallout 3 is definitely open.
AUDIENCE: The western
style one.
AUDIENCE: The F.E.A.R nail
gun is actually--
GUEST SPEAKER: The
nail gun is what?
AUDIENCE: I don't know of anyone
who's gotten through
F.E.A.R without killing someone
with a nail gun at
some point.
AUDIENCE: But is that
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Can you
punch things?
AUDIENCE: Yeah you can.
AUDIENCE: You can't
run at that level.
AUDIENCE: You can actually kung
fu kick things, which is
pretty cool, in slow mo.
AUDIENCE: In fact, I don't
say all the rest
of them seem open.
GUEST SPEAKER: Pretty
open, yeah.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
kicking people.
GUEST SPEAKER: You don't
have to do this at
any point, do you?
AUDIENCE: No.
[INAUDIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: OK.
So most of these-- what, do we
say about [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: Oh.
AUDIENCE: Open.
AUDIENCE: Regarding BioShock,
would that be open or closed?
AUDIENCE: Well [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
open--
AUDIENCE: You have a choice
but it's in your best
interests to do one
or the other.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So if you have only
one thing you can do it's
fairly closed.
If you have only two things
you can do that are very
clearly defined is it really an
open system or is it just a
closed system with two paths.
AUDIENCE: I was under
the impression that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
because you weren't self-guiding
the system was
determining whether what you
were doing was good or bad.
AUDIENCE: I was thinking
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I thought inFAMOUS
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
would also be closed.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I didn't get the difference
between only having one option
and the system telling
you which option
is the right option.
So in that case some of these
turn from open to close.
AUDIENCE: Like this one.
{INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: BioShock would
then be closed.
Fallout 3 The Dream Land,
would that be closed?
AUDIENCE: It isn't telling
you which choice
is the right option.
You needn't be morally
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: What
do you think?
Do you think he's saying--
I know what you're saying
because he also mentioned Ice
Field Republic as
a closed option.
Is it that there are two
discrete, like good or evil,
like the Jedi or
the dark path?
Is Fallout that concrete?
Fallout 3.
I know inFAMOUS is.
You're either going one
way or the other.
But I'm not as sure, and I'm
just asking people who've
played it, is Fallout 3 that
particular in is it setting up
a dichotomy of the good
character versus
evil, or is it much--
AUDIENCE: It's much more
of a gradient.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: In Baldur's Gate
there's two things.
There's your alignment,
which you pick at the
beginning of the game.
It's more like D&D style
but it's fixed.
But then there's this thing
that's your reputation, which
can be decreased if you do
certain things, from the game
point of view, in view others.
So you can get into doing bad
stuff sometimes without
actually decreasing
your reputation.
You can also just pick a evil
alignment and then do only
good things, and that's
just very weird.
So I don't exactly remember
how the alignment really
factors into game play.
But there's a moment, for
example, in the game, there's
a big story for--
it rejoins it afterwards-- but
you you have to ally yourself
with either the Thieves Guild
or the vampires in town who
are competing affections.
So you have the thieves
against the vampires.
If it's the thieves against the
vampires you got to pick
one to help you raid a certain
area, and you don't really
have other choices.
And one doesn't make you
gooder or eviler.
They're both kind of bad.
But you have to do it to
find the person that
you're trying to get.
That's kind of closed.
AUDIENCE: So in terms of
Baldur's Gate II, I would say,
one, there's the reputation
stats, which I've found never
really into the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], which is
some type of metric for your--
AUDIENCE: That's not true.
AUDIENCE: You kill everyone
and you have to go
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] to do that.
People in your party can duel
you for your honor if they get
upset at you.
Kaldor dueled me, left my
party, and then tried to
attack me because
I was too evil.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I stood out.
Like very, very specific actions
that will affect your
alignment, and there aren't
very many of those.
In addition you have these cut
scene decisions, which are
also very black or white,
good or evil.
But I would say there's a lot of
decisions in the game that
don't [UNINTELLIGIBLE], that
have both that ethical choice
but not nearly as much of
a mechanical impact.
GUEST SPEAKER: One of the things
he also mentions in
relation to the open system,
going back to The Sims, is
that you can do what you want
and the game doesn't
necessarily punish you.
You can murder and you can drown
your Sims, and the rest
of the Sims in the house don't
move away in fear or
disapprove of your action.
It's just up to you whether
you want to feel
bad about it or not.
Or the game has no larger
response other than let a Sim
die once the site lit
a Sim on fire.
And I wish they rolled for his
life and got a zombie back.
It turns out the only way
zombies happen in the game is
if you make somebody
else unhappy.
So then I had to
kill a zombie.
It was sad.
So that was another
element to it.
One of the things that he talks
about in general in
relation to all of this, and a
lot of these fit is ethics to
your statistics.
That somehow ethical systems are
on this point or sliding
scale and that you're heading
towards good or you're heading
towards evil.
We were even mentioning this
before class started that you
can blow up an entire town but
then if you give three beggars
$0.50 cents each suddenly you're
back at neutral because
of the way that these sliding
systems work in bizzarely
mechanical ways.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you can
buy reputation back
by stoning two temples.
AUDIENCE: It's like
indulgences.
AUDIENCE: Yeah it is, exactly.
AUDIENCE: Indulgences
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I have to close this
now because I'm getting high
off of marker fumes.
I wanted to show you an example
of one that we haven't
talked about yet.
Somebody mentioned
Call of Duty.
This one is actually
from last year.
It's not Castro, which
is the new one, but--
AUDIENCE: Is it the Russian
hostage thing?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
It's the new Russian level--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: From Modern
Warfare 2.
AUDIENCE: It's like
a competition.
GUEST SPEAKER: So this was last
year's Call of Duty, and
this was the optional level.
You did not have to play it.
And of course it caused a big
storm when it was released.
I'm just going to play it and
then we can talk about it
afterwards.
Has anyone played this?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: Want to provide
a little context or explain
the a little bit more?
AUDIENCE: So the convoluted plot
is that this is a false
flag attack, which is staged by
a terrorist organization,
which is meant to frame the
CIA to start a war between
Russia and the US.
And so the idea here is that
you are playing a character
who is undercover as part of
the CIA who is part of this
terrorist organization.
And then you end up being double
crossed because they,
as it was just revealed at the
end, they knew you were a CIA
agent and they're trying to
pin the attack on America.
So that's the--
AUDIENCE: Do you have the option
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
of shooting Makarov
in the back or--
AUDIENCE: No, I don't
believe so.
AUDIENCE: If you tried and shoot
Makarov then the level
ends with a fail, and you have
to arrest him again.
If you try and get through the
level without shooting any
civilians the level also ends.
Makarov decides that you're a
traitor and shoots you before
doing anything else--
AUDIENCE: Before he's supposed
to shoot you later.
AUDIENCE: Before he's
supposed to shoot
you, I seem to remember.
AUDIENCE: I think you can get
through the mission by not
shooting any civilians but you
can't get through without
shooting any of the cops.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, there's--
AUDIENCE: If you don't shoot
the cops then you can't
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah
that's true.
[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Although that guy was
incredibly diligent about
killing civilians.
I did not play that
level that way.
AUDIENCE: Oh, god.
I did.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, that guy
took his work to heart.
I don't think that I would
have-- like Owen says--
I haven't played Modern Warfare
2 yet or Black Ops,
for that matter-- but I don't
feel like it would come to me
that it was really necessary to
just hunt down every last
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: He's thorough.
He's very thorough.
But it is also interesting
that you--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
and that's all right-- that you
think, well, I'm killing
all of these people--
AUDIENCE: So that I
can then kill him,
probably, or something.
GUEST SPEAKER: Right, or it's
for a greater good, right,
that I'm going to get in with
this group and help bring down
this terrorist cell, whereas,
ha, ha, not so much.
Call of Duty, has anyone
played Black Ops?
AUDIENCE: Not yet.
GUEST SPEAKER: There's a scene
in it, another level where you
can assassinate Castro.
And I was just watching it--
AUDIENCE: It pissed
off Castro.
GUEST SPEAKER: --this morning.
AUDIENCE: It did.
They--
GUEST SPEAKER: No the Cuba
objected to the video game.
I watched that level.
It's not nearly as exciting
as this one.
Although it's interesting in
that you infiltrate his
compound, you get up to-- he's
in his bedroom with his
whatever she is--
and you shoot him.
And in this clip the guy shot
him in the head and it slows
down to bullet time actually,
and you see it enter his
forehead and he falls over.
And then the enraged lover
grabs the machine gun and
starts firing at you
in her negligee.
So you have to kill her too.
And, yeah, Cuba is
the operation.
But I don't think it takes a
lot to get Cuba mad at the
United States anyway.
AUDIENCE: Can you score that?
I don't see the statistics,
the like statistics.
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
see if I dislike.
AUDIENCE: It's pretty
high [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: In the previous
Modern Warfare
game there's actually--
I haven't seen anyone draw this
parallel, but there is a
level where you are in the
middle of a firefight, a US
Marine in some Middle Eastern
war zone, and you are told to
shoot at enemies who are coming
onto your center but at
such a range that you cannot
tell friend from foe.
That it's absolutely certain
that whatever it is you can
get there's a 50% chance
that there's
actually one of your allies.
AUDIENCE: There's also
the really creepy--
PROFESSOR: Gunship sequence.
AUDIENCE: --the gunship
sequence, which is--
PROFESSOR: Which gets most
of the attention.
But I was surprised by the
subtlety of the sequence where
you are just in the middle of a
firefight in Modern Warfare
1 because it has that situation
of you are being
told to kill but you may not,
even though everyone that you
might be shooting at is a
combatant, you may not want to
shoot everyone in this space.
I felt that made a more
interesting, subtle point
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
That's kind of what the
situation of being in the
Middle East right now is like,
as far as you can tell.
GUEST SPEAKER: I was thinking
about this because I actually
did an interview last week, two
weeks ago, with some radio
people and it was about Black
Ops being released because
it's the best selling
entertainment media ever.
And they introduced it, of
course, on the segment as the
ultra violent video game,
Call of Duty.
AUDIENCE: That's pretty
accurate.
GUEST SPEAKER: It is please.
And one of the questions that
each affiliate asked over and
over is they mentioned the
Castro level and they said,
have video games gone too far?
Is there a line that shouldn't
be crossed?
And I'm sure if they had-- none
of these people actually
played video games
so they were just
reading their scripts--
this might have even fit
even better in terms of
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I'm surprised
this got through.
GUEST SPEAKER: Well it's
an optional level.
You don't have to do it.
Interesting comment
right there.
If it was JFK airport
or US citizens--
But leaving aside just the knee
jerk gamer defense, well,
it's just for fun or it's just
a video game, how do you
answer that question?
I know what I spew to them but
I'm just curious in terms of
what does it mean beyond just
games as statistics for the
good or the dark side?
Is there a point you think
where it can go too
far with the game?
What's the assumption behind
that question?
AUDIENCE: There's a really
disturbing news report I was
reading about this Japanese
game called RapeLay.
And for me it was clear this is
totally messed up, I can't
believe this exists.
But the part that was disturbing
was the defense put
forth by the developers.
And they were saying who are you
guys to be telling us this
is messed up.
You Americans, you make games
all the time where you have to
kill people.
Murder is a much worse
crime than rape.
Our game is not nearly
as bad as, say, this.
And I was, wait, no, but
that's more messed up.
But, what?
And I don't know what
to think of it.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: What?
AUDIENCE: In a South Park
episode they address it
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Actually, just
online on that game in
particular there was a backlash
that I heard in Japan
about RapeLay mainly because
the game had been out for
maybe two years and gone
completely unnoticed until,
basically, the West heard about
it, American and Europe.
Because I think it showed up on
Amazon.com or something at
some point.
And of course, there was
a gigantic controversy.
The media blew it
up completely,
and so then, in Japan--
was it banned in
Japan, I think?
AUDIENCE: No.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: But it had been out
for a while and no one had
paid attention.
All of a sudden--
AUDIENCE: Apparently Japanese
politicians started cracking
down on these types of games.
And a lot of fans got really
angry and they said this is
just like your Western
Euro-centric view, and why is
this backlashing onto
us kind of thing.
PROFESSOR: The only reason why
there was a backlash was
because of political
attention not
necessarily because of moral--
AUDIENCE: A lot of our
moral framework is
Judeo-Christian in nature.
I read an entire Wikipedia
article on such things
afterwards.
Child pornography, as long as
it doesn't actually show the
actors, so representations,
animated, 3D, whatever is not
illegal in Japan.
And there's no real
political pressure
either to make it illegal.
It's just not part of the public
consciousness that it's
something that needs
to be made illegal.
And the point is not a weird
point, completely crazy, that
killing people is probably
the worst crime.
And the West makes games that
advocate that all the time.
AUDIENCE: So the question
of [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Would there
probably be a radio
interview with that answer?
AUDIENCE: In terms of the
question of whether or not a
game crosses the line first
assumes that there is a line
to be crossed.
And second, I guess, my answer
would be yes there is a line
but that line is basically
whether or not
people buy the game.
If people buy the game
the game hasn't
really crossed the line.
AUDIENCE: So [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
the video reminds me of the
game of 9/11, where you
are a person on
one of the top floors--
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, and
you could jump.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Well, that's the only
way to end the game.
You can go any way you want
but there's no escape.
And so the only way to end the
game is to jump out a window.
GUEST SPEAKER: That had
the same response.
AUDIENCE: I was just going to
say, back on the point of is
there a line or not?
I think the line is not
a line on whether it
becomes OK or not.
It's a line between--
I know we mentioned this
before, but-- between
pornography and art.
There's ways to take pictures of
naked human bodies and it's
artful and people respect
it and all that.
And there's ways in games to
represent killing and rape and
all that kind of stuff in a way
that provides a message
within this framework
that makes it OK.
And there's games where--
I think Manhunt is one of
these-- where there's no real
point other than just displaying
just terrible,
terrible images for the sake
of displaying that.
In my mind it's very, very
similar to the discussion of
is that image pornography
or art?
AUDIENCE: See, I think that's
the right way to go with this
kind of a thing in particular.
I feel that there's this
question of is it doing
anything meaningful in the game
other than just being
gratuitous?
And in this case it's
definitely, yes.
It progresses the plot, it makes
you think, I guess, a
bit about the characters
that are involved.
There's character development
with Makarov here, it's
showing the shady dealings
of the CIA and all
this kind of business.
It's also making a political
statement at the same time.
So yeah, it's not just nailing
people's eyes to the ceiling
with a nail gun and
what have you.
AUDIENCE: I was thinking,
are there any games that
are over the line?
I could definitely imagine
a game that
would be over the line.
You could imagine in RapeLay, or
whatever it's called, there
were a customizable character
thing that you were
advertising, rape your
neighbors or
something like that.
I would be uncomfortable with
I almost wanted to say that
there is no line if people buy
it, but I feel like there are
some things that they would be
over the line regardless of
whether people buy it or not.
GUEST SPEAKER: People might even
buy it because they are
over this line.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, of course.
That's why you would buy that.
GUEST SPEAKER: How many of you
have played or seen Super
Columbine Massacre RPG?
How many of you have
heard of it?
OK.
Does that game cross the line?
AUDIENCE: Can somebody
describe this?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I mean, I get the
idea. from the title.
GUEST SPEAKER: Somebody
want to?
PROFESSOR: It's kind of a Super
Nintendo US-style RPG.
It has you walking around in
this sort of Final Fantasy
with Nintendo era kind of
graphics with quotes and
dialogue that have been
collected from the actual news
reports of the [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
diaries and stuff like that.
And yeah, it is largely about
the events leading up to and
the massacre itself.
Yes, and you do go around-- and
I can't remember whether
you actually--
GUEST SPEAKER: You
do everything.
PROFESSOR: You shoot
everybody.
GUEST SPEAKER: You have to
sneak into the school.
I forget which one you start off
as, it's either Kinkel or
Harris, but you pick
up your friend.
It's very RPGish in the
beginning where you're in the
room because you touch objects
and it gives flashbacks to
your friendship with this guy
like learning how to make pipe
bombs behind the convenience
store.
And you pick him up, you
go to the school.
You have to sneak in and
plant some bombs.
And after those go off then you
move through the school
and you're shooting.
And it's interesting
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I've showed it to a class once
in Ohio, my old school, and
I'm sneaking into the school,
right, and there are security
cameras you have to avoid.
And students, you can't be
seen by them either.
And there's a point where I'm
trying to manipulate the
character and everyone
in class is like, oh,
that way, that way.
Oh, oh, you blew it, you got
seen, you got kicked out.
And it was like this moment
of typical gaming,
like, oh, you did it.
And then you realize, I got
kicked out of the school
because I was trying
to plant a bomb.
And this was based on
something that really happened.
And it was that moment of like
you were saying with the
friendly fire and not sure
who you're shooting.
And it was like, wow, this is
something that made me think
about what about all those other
games where I'm happy to
kill people, and I don't
really think about the
consequences.
And this is a game where
you are forced to.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE] a
really interesting parallel in
a film that I could think of,
The Battle of Algiers.
I don't know if you've seen this
but there's this scene
where you are following the
insurgents who are these two
women who've managed to smuggle
bombs into a cafe they
think leaders of the civilians
hang out, which is largely
frequented by the ruling
class French
section of society there.
And there's this incredibly
tense scene where they're
trying to leave their bombs
in the cafe without being
detected and get out of there.
And you're like, oh my god,
are they going to be
able to make it?
I hope that they can
bomb this cafe.
What am I thinking?
This is terrible.
And you definitely have that
same kind of tension.
AUDIENCE: I feel like people
devote too much emotional
energy into getting offended.
They pour their heart
and souls into
getting offended by things.
And the line for me is is it
does it advocate and is it
instructional?
If it's not either of those two
things it doesn't affect
me really, and if you really
want to go out and play some
messed up shit it's none
of my business.
And my line is not going to be
the same as your line, it's
not going to be the same
as someone else's line.
And because there is no human
definable line it really
scares me that someone
could define a line.
And since I don't like that idea
I'd rather say that as
long as it's not like and then
you pull back the safety, and
here's how you sneak into the
airport, and then here's how
you shoot this.
As long as it's not something
like that, and now please go
do it, here's why you
should because
America is evil, or whatever.
That would scare me because I
think that would be increasing
the chances that someone shoots
me up at an airport.
But otherwise, because my
attitudes are so liberal and
someone else's attitude is going
to be so conservative,
and oh god, someone else's
attitude is going to be even
more liberal than mine and be OK
with things that I wouldn't
feel comfortable with.
If I was allowed to draw a line,
someone else could draw
that somewhere else, either
before or after, and that
would just mess everything up.
And so that's how
I feel about it.
And I think that the environment
right now kind of
tends towards that in that--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: Huh?
AUDIENCE: The line drawing?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, in that--
AUDIENCE: Depends on
which line drawing?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
People who make games are not
intrinsically, on average,
really messed up, and so tend
to make stuff that they feel
generally comfortable with.
And those who are messed up,
you just draw attention to
them, really, by giving
them publicity anyway.
For every person
who says that--
Diablo 2 got an M rating
because of violence.
Now if you look at it today
it's like little sprites
whacking at each other.
But that was the
line back then.
And if that's the line today
then this stuff is absolutely
horrendous and should
not be disseminated.
But I think it should be, and
someone else might think what
I think is OK is not OK.
It's just going to be what
I think is not OK is OK.
It's very complicated.
GUEST SPEAKER: This guy
got death threats.
Apparently seen this game.
PROFESSOR: I'd strongly like
to agree with the a lot of
effort being put into the line
drawing especially the public
display of, hey, I'm drawing
the line here, mostly by
politicians but also by people
with some sort of possibly,
often self-interested agenda.
And both by the game industry
and by people who
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] the
game industry.
It seems like there's more
effort either being used to
figure out what is offensive and
what is not offensive than
to discuss the need
that some things
should be able to offend.
That we should have stuff that
needs [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
There needs to be some stuff
that crosses because maybe the
line [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: And it's a method to
sensitize adults to violence.
There's so much violence these
days it'd be better if you
didn't freak out at
every little--
AUDIENCE: I think it's
totally OK to be
freaked out at things.
I think that you should
definitely say when you're
offended by something, and I
think that should be open to
debate like whether something
is a decent artistic
expression or
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
So there's a difference between
staging that you find
something offensive and
attempting to have these
things banned or
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I agree.
AUDIENCE: I'm totally fine with
people wasting words on
saying whether it's--
AUDIENCE: No clearly.
But as long as because you are
offended you think I shouldn't
be able to look at it,
that's the problem.
AUDIENCE: OK.
I think it's--
PROFESSOR: Or even better, if
by being offended you get to
now make your point.
This is why it is offensive
to me and these are
my reasons for it.
It might be more informative
and actually better for
society to get those ideas
out into the open.
AUDIENCE: Suppose you get
offended by proxy?
It doesn't offend me but I can
see how it offends others.
GUEST SPEAKER: I think there's
also a conflation of taking
offense and discomfort because
playing these games might be
uncomfortable.
And I don't think that's
necessarily a bad thing if it
makes you think about, like
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] was saying,
or like [UNINTELLIGIBLE] game,
this Super Columbine Massacre,
if it makes you think about
things in a different way, or
like that film.
And especially games have the
ability to provoke that in you
to make you think because
you're the one.
Especially these games
that force you
to do certain things.
It's like, well, I don't even
think about is there a game
that you absolutely refuse
to play because there was
something in it that you just
really did not want to do?
PROFESSOR: That's fine.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK?
I think we'll end there.