So, to begin with permutations.
Can I just -- so these
permutations,
those are matrices P and they
execute row exchanges.
And we may need them.
We may have a perfectly good
matrix, a perfect matrix A
that's invertible that we can
solve A x=b, but to do it --
I've got to allow myself that
extra freedom that if a zero
shows up in the pivot position I
move it away.
I get a non-zero.
I get a proper pivot there by
exchanging from a row below.
And you've seen that already,
and I just want to collect the
ideas together.
And principle,
I could even have to do that
two times, or more times.
So I have to allow -- to
complete the -- the theory,
the possibility that I take my
matrix A, I start elimination,
I find out that I need row
exchanges and I do it and
continue and I finish.
Okay.
Then all I want to do is say --
and I won't make a big project
out of this -- what happens to A
equal L U?
So A equal L U -- this was a
matrix L with ones on the
diagonal and zeroes above and
multipliers below,
and this U we know,
with zeroes down here.
That's only possible.
That description of elimination
assumes that we don't have a P,
that we don't have any row
exchanges.
And now I just want to say,
okay, how do I account for row
exchanges?
Because that doesn't.
The P in this factorization is
the identity matrix.
The rows were in a good order,
we left them there.
Maybe I'll just add a little
moment of reality,
too, about how Matlab actually
does elimination.
Matlab not only checks whether
that pivot is not zero,
as every human would do.
It checks for is that pivot big
enough, because it doesn't like
very, very small pivots.
Pivots close to zero are
numerically bad.
So actually if we ask Matlab to
solve a system,
it will do some elimination
some row exchanges,
which we don't think are
necessary.
Algebra doesn't say they're
necessary, but accuracy --
numerical accuracy says they
are.
Well, we're doing algebra,
so here we will say,
well, what do row exchanges do,
but we won't do them unless we
have to.
But we may have to.
And then, the result is -- it's
hiding here.
It's the main fact.
This is the description of
elimination with row exchanges.
So A equal L U becomes P A
equal L U.
So this P is the matrix that
does the row exchanges,
and actually it does them -- it
gets the rows into the right
order, into the good order where
pivots will not --
where zeroes won't appear in
the pivot position,
where L and U will come out
right as up here.
So, that's the point.
Actually, I don't want to labor
that point, that a permutation
matrix -- and you remember what
those were.
I'll remind you from last time
of what the main points about
permutation matrices were -- and
then just leave this
factorization as the general
case.
This is -- any invertible A we
get this.
For almost every one,
we don't need a P.
But there's that handful that
do need row exchanges,
and if we do need them,
there they are.
Okay, finally,
just to remember what P was.
So permutations,
P is the identity matrix with
reordered rows.
I include in reordering the
possibility that you just leave
them the same.
So the identity matrix is --
okay.
That's, like,
your basic permutation matrix
-- your do-nothing permutation
matrix is the identity.
And then there are the ones
that exchange two rows and then
the ones that exchange three
rows and then then ones that
exchange four -- well,
it gets a little -- it gets
more interesting algebraically
if you've got four rows,
you might exchange them all in
one big cycle.
One to two, two to three,
three to four,
four to one.
Or you might have -- exchange
one and two and three and four.
Lots of possibilities there.
In fact, how many
possibilities?
The answer was (n)factorial.
This is n(n-1)(n-2)...
(3)(2)(1).
That's the number of -- this
counts the reorderings,
the possible reorderings.
So it counts all the n by n
permutations.
And all those matrices have
these --
have this nice property that
they're all invertible,
because we can bring those rows
back into the normal order.
And the matrix that does that
is just P -- is just the same as
the transpose.
You might take a permutation
matrix, multiply by its
transpose and you will see how
--
that the ones hit the ones and
give the ones in the identity
matrix.
So this is a -- we'll be highly
interested in matrices that have
nice properties.
And one property that -- maybe
I could rewrite that as P
transpose P is the identity.
That tells me in other words
that this is the inverse of
that.
Okay.
We'll be interested in matrices
that have P transpose P equal
the identity.
There are more of them than
just permutations,
but my point right now is that
permutations are like a little
group in the middle -- in the
center of these special
matrices.
Okay.
So now we know how many there
are.
Twenty four in the case of --
there are twenty four four by
four permutations,
there are five factorial which
is a hundred and twenty,
five times twenty four would
bump us up to a hundred and
twenty --
so listing all the five by five
permutations would be not so
much fun.
Okay.
So that's permutations.
Now also in section two seven
is some discussion of
transposes.
And can I just complete that
discussion.
First of all,
I haven't even transposed a
matrix on the board here,
have I?
So I'd better do it.
So suppose I take a matrix like
(1 2 4; 3 3 1).
It's a rectangular matrix,
three by two.
And I want to transpose it.
So what's -- I'll use a T,
also Matlab would use a prime.
And the result will be -- I'll
right it here,
because this was three rows and
two columns, this was a three by
two matrix.
The transpose will be two rows
and three columns,
two by three.
So it's short and wider.
And, of course,
that row -- that column becomes
a row --
that column becomes the other
row.
And at the same time,
that row became a column.
This row became a column.
Oh, what's the general formula
for the transpose?
So the transpose -- you see it
in numbers.
What I'm going to write is the
same thing in symbols.
The numbers are the clearest,
of course.
But in symbols,
if I take A transpose and I ask
what number is in row I and
column J of A transpose?
Well, it came out of A.
It came out A by this flip
across the main diagonal.
And, actually,
it was the number in A which
was in row J,
column I.
So the row and column -- the
row and column numbers just get
reversed.
The row number becomes the
column number,
the column number becomes the
row number.
No problem.
Okay.
Now, a special -- the best
matrices, we could say.
In a lot of applications,
symmetric matrices show up.
So can I just call attention to
symmetric matrices?
What does that mean?
What does that word symmetric
mean?
It means that this transposing
doesn't change the matrix.
A transpose equals A.
And an example.
So, let's take a matrix that's
symmetric, so whatever is
sitting on the diagonal -- but
now what's above the diagonal,
like a one, had better be
there, a seven had better be
here, a nine had better be
there.
There's a symmetric matrix.
I happened to use all positive
numbers as its entries.
That's not the point.
The point is that if I
transpose that matrix,
I get it back again.
So symmetric matrices have this
property A transpose equals A.
I guess at this point --
I'm just asking you to notice
this family of matrices that are
unchanged by transposing.
And they're easy to identify,
of course.
You know, it's not maybe so
easy before we had a case where
the transpose gave the inverse.
That's highly important,
but not so simple to see.
This is the case where the
transpose gives the same matrix
back again.
That's totally simple to see.
Okay.
Could actually -- maybe I could
even say when would we get such
a matrix?
For example,
this -- that matrix is
absolutely far from symmetric,
right?
The transpose isn't even the
same shape --
because it's rectangular,
it turns the -- lies down on
its side.
But let me tell you a way to
get a symmetric matrix out of
this.
Multiply those together.
If I multiply this rectangular,
shall I call it R for
rectangular?
So let that be R for
rectangular matrix and let that
be R transpose,
which it is.
Then I think that if I multiply
those together,
I get a symmetric matrix.
Can I just do it with the
numbers and then ask you why,
how did I know it would be
symmetric?
So my point is that R transpose
R is always symmetric.
Okay?
And I'm going to do it for that
particular R transpose R which
was -- let's see,
the column was one two four
three three one.
I called that one R transpose,
didn't I, and I called this guy
one two four three three one.
I called that R.
Shall we just do that
multiplication?
Okay, so up here I'm getting a
ten.
Next to it I'm getting two,
a nine, I'm getting an eleven.
Next to that I'm getting four
and three, a seven.
Now what do I get there?
This eleven came from one three
times two three,
right?
Row one, column two.
What goes here?
Row two, column one.
But no difference.
One three two three or two
three one three,
same thing.
It's going to be an eleven.
That's the symmetry.
I can continue to fill it out.
What -- oh, let's get that
seven.
That seven will show up down
here, too, and then four more
numbers.
That seven will show up here
because one three times four one
gave the seven,
but also four one times one
three will give that seven.
Do you see that it works?
Actually, do you want to see it
work also in matrix language?
I mean, that's quite
convincing, right?
That seven is no accident.
The eleven is no accident.
But just tell me how do I know
if I transpose this guy --
How do I know it's symmetric?
Well, I'm going to transpose
it.
And when I transpose it,
I'm hoping I get the matrix
back again.
So can I transpose R transpose
R?
So just -- so,
why?
Well, my suggestion is take the
transpose.
That's the only way to show
it's symmetric.
Take the transpose and see that
it didn't change.
Okay, so I take the transpose
of R transpose R.
Okay.
How do I do that?
This is our little practice on
the rules for transposes.
So the rule for transposes is
the order gets reversed.
Just like inverses,
which we did prove,
same rule for transposes and --
which we'll now use.
So the order gets reversed.
It's the transpose of that that
comes first, and the transpose
of this that comes -- no.
Is that -- yeah.
That's what I have to write,
right?
This is a product of two
matrices and I want its
transpose.
So I put the matrices in the
opposite order and I transpose
them.
But what have I got here?
What is R transpose transpose?
Well, don't all speak at once.
R transpose transpose,
I flipped over the diagonal,
I flipped over the diagonal
again, so I've got R.
And that's just my point,
that if I started with this
matrix, I transposed it,
I got it back again.
So that's the check,
without using numbers,
but with --
it checked in two lines that I
always get symmetric matrices
this way.
And actually,
that's where they come from in
so many practical applications.
Okay.
So now I've said something
today about permutations and
about transposes and about
symmetry and I'm ready for
chapter three.
Can we take a breath -- the
tape won't take a breath,
but the lecturer will,
because to tell you about
vector spaces is -- we really
have to start now and think,
okay, listen up.
What are vector spaces?
And what are sub-spaces?
Okay.
So, the point is,
The main operations that we do
-- what do we do with vectors?
We add them.
We know how to add two vectors.
We multiply them by numbers,
usually called scalers.
If we have a vector,
we know what three V is.
If we have a vector V and W,
we know what V plus W is.
Those are the two operations
that we've got to be able to do.
To legitimately talk about a
space of vectors,
the requirement is that we
should be able to add the things
and multiply by numbers and that
there should be some decent
rules satisfied.
Okay.
So let me start with examples.
So I'm talking now about vector
spaces.
And I'm going to start with
examples.
Let me say again what this word
space is meaning.
When I say that word space,
that means to me that I've got
a bunch of vectors,
a space of vectors.
But not just any bunch of
vectors.
It has to be a space of vectors
-- has to allow me to do the
operations that vectors are for.
I have to be able to add
vectors and multiply by numbers.
I have to be able to take
linear combinations.
Well, where did we meet linear
combinations?
We met them back in,
say in R^2.
So there's a vector space.
What's that vector space?
So R two is telling me I'm
talking about real numbers and
I'm talking about two real
numbers.
So this is all two dimensional
vectors -- real,
such as -- well,
I'm not going to be able to
list them all.
But let me put a few down.
|3; 2|, |0;0|,
|pi; e|.
So on.
And it's natural -- okay.
Let's see, I guess I should do
algebra first.
Algebra means what can I do to
these vectors?
I can add them.
I can add that to that.
And how do I do it?
A component at a time,
of course.
Three two added to zero zero
gives me, three two.
Sorry about that.
Three two added to pi e gives
me three plus pi,
two plus e.
Oh, you know what it does.
And you know the picture that
goes with it.
There's the vector three two.
And often, the picture has an
arrow.
The vector zero zero,
which is a highly important
vector -- it's got,
like, the most important here
-- is there.
And of course there's not much
of an arrow.
Pi -- I'll have to remember --
pi is about three and a little
more, e is about two and a
little more.
So maybe there's pi e.
I never drew pi e before.
It's just natural to -- this is
the first component on the
horizontal and this is the
second component,
going up the vertical.
Okay.
And the whole plane is R two.
So R two is,
we could say,
the plane.
The xy plane.
That's what everybody thinks.
But the point is it's a vector
space because all those vectors
are in there.
If I removed one of them --
Suppose I removed zero zero.
Suppose I tried to take the --
considered the X Y plane with a
puncture, with a point removed.
Like the origin.
That would be,
like, awful to take the origin
away.
Why is that?
Why do I need the origin there?
Because I have to be allowed --
if I had these other vectors,
I have to be allowed to
multiply three two -- this was
three two -- by anything,
by any scaler,
including zero.
I've got to be allowed to
multiply by zero and the
result's got to be there.
I can't do without that point.
And I have to be able to add
three two to the opposite guy,
minus three minus two.
And if I add those I'm back to
the origin again.
No way I can do without the
origin.
Every vector space has got that
zero vector in it.
Okay, that's an easy vector
space, because we have a natural
picture of it.
Okay.
Similarly easy is R^3.
This would be all -- let me go
up a little here.
This would be -- R three would
be all three dimensional vectors
--
or shall I say vectors with
three real components.
Okay.
Let me just to be sure we're
together, let me take the vector
three two zero.
Is that a vector in R^2 or R^3?
Definitely it's in R^3.
It's got three components.
One of them happens to be zero,
but that's a perfectly okay
number.
So that's a vector in R^3.
We don't want to mix up the --
I mean, keep these vectors
straight and keep R^n straight.
So what's R^n?
R^n.
So this is our big example,
is all vectors with n
components.
And I'm making these darn
things column vectors.
Can I try to follow that
convention, that they'll be
column vectors,
and their components should be
real numbers.
Later we'll need complex
numbers and complex vectors,
but much later.
Okay.
So that's a vector space.
Now, let's see.
What do I have to tell you
about vector spaces?
I said the most important
thing, which is that we can add
any two of these and we -- still
in R^2.
We can multiply by any number
and we're still in R^2.
We can take any combination and
we're still in R^2.
And same goes for R^n.
It's -- honesty requires me to
mention that these operations of
adding and multiplying have to
obey a few rules.
Like, we can't just arbitrarily
say, okay, the sum of three two
and pi e is zero zero.
It's not.
The sum of three two and minus
three two is zero zero.
So -- oh, I'm not going to --
the book, actually,
lists the eight rules that the
addition and multiplication have
to satisfy, but they do.
They certainly satisfy it in
R^n and usually it's not those
eight rules that are in doubt.
What's -- the question is,
can we do those additions and
do we stay in the space?
Let me show you a case where
you can't.
So suppose this is going to be
not a vector space.
Suppose I take the xy plane --
so there's R^2.
That is a vector space.
Now suppose I just take part of
it.
Just this.
Just this one -- this is one
quarter of the vector space.
All the vectors with positive
or at least not negative
components.
Can I add those safely?
Yes.
If I add a vector with,
like, two -- three two to
another vector like five six,
I'm still up in this quarter,
no problem with adding.
But there's a heck of a problem
with multiplying by scalers,
because there's a lot of
scalers that will take me out of
this quarter plane,
like negative ones.
If I took three two and I
multiplied by minus five,
I'm way down here.
So that's not a vector space,
because it's not -- closed is
the right word.
It's not closed under
multiplication by all real
numbers.
So a vector space has to be
closed under multiplication and
addition of vectors.
In other words,
linear combinations.
It -- so, it means that if I
give you a few vectors -- yeah
look, here's an important --
here -- now we're getting to
some really important vector
spaces.
Well, R^n -- like,
they are the most important.
But we will be interested in
so- in vector spaces that are
inside R^n.
Vector spaces that follow the
rules, but they -- we don't need
all of -- see,
there we started with R^2 here,
and took part of it and messed
it up.
What we got was not a vector
space.
Now tell me a vector space that
is part of R^2 and is still
safely --
we can multiply,
we can add and we stay in this
smaller vector space.
So it's going to be called a
subspace.
So I'm going to change this bad
example to a good one.
Okay.
So I'm going to start again
with R^2, but I'm going to take
an example --
it is a vector space,
so it'll be a vector space
inside R^2.
And we'll call that a subspace
of R^2.
Okay.
What can I do?
It's got something in it.
Suppose it's got this vector in
it.
Okay.
If that vector's in my little
subspace and it's a true
subspace, then there's got to be
some more in it,
right?
I have to be able to multiply
that by two, and that double
vector has to be included.
Have to be able to multiply by
zero, that vector,
or by half, or by three
quarters.
All these vectors.
Or by minus a half,
or by minus one.
I have to be able to multiply
by any number.
So that is going to say that I
have to have that whole line.
Do you see that?
Once I get a vector in there --
I've got the whole line of all
multiples of that vector.
I can't have a vector space
without extending to get those
multiples in there.
Now I still have to check
addition.
But that comes out okay.
This line is going to work,
because I could add something
on the line to something else on
the line and I'm still on the
line.
So, example.
So this is all examples of a
subspace -- our example is a
line in R^2 actually -- not just
any line.
If I took this line,
would that -- so all the
vectors on that line.
So that vector and that vector
and this vector and this vector
-- in lighter type,
I'm drawing something that
doesn't work.
It's not a subspace.
The line in R^2 -- to be a
subspace, the line in R^2 must
go through the zero vector.
Because -- why is this line no
good?
Let me do a dashed line.
Because if I multiplied that
vector on the dashed line by
zero, then I'm down here,
I'm not on the dashed line.
Z- zero's got to be.
Every subspace has got to
contain zero --
because I must be allowed to
multiply by zero and that will
always give me the zero vector.
Okay.
Now, I was going to make --
create some subspaces.
Oh, while I'm in R^2,
why don't we think of all the
possibilities.
R two, there can't be that
many.
So what are the possible
subspaces of R^2?
Let me list them.
So I'm listing now the
subspaces of R^2.
And one possibility that we
always allow is all of R two,
the whole thing,
the whole space.
That counts as a subspace of
itself.
You always want to allow that.
Then the others are lines --
any line, meaning infinitely far
in both directions through the
zero.
So that's like the whole space
-- that's like whole two D
space.
This is like one dimension.
Is this line the same as R^1 ?
No.
You could say it looks a lot
like R^1.
R^1 was just a line and this is
a line.
But this is a line inside R^2.
The vectors here have two
components.
So that's not the same as R^1,
because there the vectors only
have one component.
Very close, you could say,
but not the same.
Okay.
And now there's a third
possibility.
There's a third subspace that's
-- of R^2 that's not the whole
thing, and it's not a line.
It's even less.
It's just the zero vector
alone.
The zero vector alone,
only.
I'll often call this subspace
Z, just for zero.
Here's a line,
L.
Here's a plane,
all of R^2.
So, do you see that the zero
vector's okay?
You would just -- to understand
subspaces, we have to know the
rules --
and knowing the rules means
that we have to see that yes,
the zero vector by itself,
just this guy alone satisfies
the rules.
Why's that?
Oh, it's too dumb to tell you.
If I took that and added it to
itself, I'm still there.
If I took that and multiplied
by seventeen,
I'm still there.
So I've done the operations,
adding and multiplying by
numbers, that are required,
and I didn't go outside this
one point space.
So that's always -- that's the
littlest subspace.
And the largest subspace is the
whole thing and in-between come
all -- whatever's in between.
Okay.
So for example,
what's in between for R^3?
So if I'm in ordinary three
dimensions, the subspace is R,
all of R^3 at one extreme,
the zero vector at the bottom.
And then a plane,
a plane through the origin.
Or a line, a line through the
origin.
So with R^3,
the subspaces were R^3,
plane through the origin,
line through the origin and a
zero vector by itself,
zero zero zero,
just that single vector.
Okay, you've got the idea.
But, now comes -- the reality
is -- what are these -- where do
these subspaces come -- how do
they come out of matrices?
And I want to take this matrix
-- oh, let me take that matrix.
So I want to create some
subspaces out of that matrix.
Well, one subspace is from the
columns.
Okay.
So this is the important
subspace, the first important
subspace that comes from that
matrix -- I'm going to -- let me
call it A again.
Back to -- okay.
I'm looking at the columns of
A.
Those are vectors in R^3.
So the columns are in R^3.
The columns are in R^3.
So I want those columns to be
in my subspace.
Now I can't just put two
columns in my subspace and call
it a subspace.
What do I have to throw in --
if I'm going to put those two
columns in, what else has got to
be there to have a subspace?
I must be able to add those
things.
So the sum of those columns --
so these columns are in R^3,
and I have to be able -- I'm,
you know, I want that to be in
my subspace, I want that to be
in my subspace,
but therefore I have to be able
to multiply them by anything.
Zero zero zero has got to be in
my subspace.
I have to be able to add them
so that four five five is in the
subspace.
I've got to be able to add one
of these plus three of these.
That'll give me some other
vector.
I have to be able to take all
the linear combinations.
So these are columns in R^3 and
all there linear combinations
form a subspace.
What do I mean by linear
combinations?
I mean multiply that by
something, multiply that by
something and add.
The two operations of linear
algebra, multiplying by numbers
and adding vectors.
And, if I include all the
results, then I'm guaranteed to
have a subspace.
I've done the job.
And we'll give it a name -- the
column space.
Column space.
And maybe I'll call it C of A.
C for column space.
There's an idea there that --
Like, the central idea for
today's lecture is -- got a few
vectors.
Not satisfied with a few
vectors, we want a space of
vectors.
The vectors,
they're in -- these vectors in
-- are in R^3 ,
so our space of vectors will be
vectors in R^3.
The key idea's --
we have to be able to take
their combinations.
So tell me, geometrically,
if I drew all these things --
like if I drew one two four,
that would be somewhere maybe
there.
If I drew three three one,
who knows, might be -- I don't
know, I'll say there.
There's column one,
there's column two.
What else -- what's in the
whole column space?
How do I draw the whole column
space now?
I take all combinations of
those two vectors.
Do I get -- well,
I guess I actually listed the
possibilities.
Do I get the whole space?
Do I get a plane?
I get more than a line,
that's for sure.
And I certainly get more than
the zero vector,
but I do get the zero vector
included.
What do I get if I combine --
take all the combinations of
two vectors in R^3 ?
So I've got all this stuff on
-- that whole line gets filled
out, that whole line gets filled
out, but all in-between gets
filled out -- between the two
lines because I --
I allowed to add something from
one line, something from the
other.
You see what's coming?
I'm getting a plane.
That's my -- and it's through
the origin.
Those two vectors,
namely one two four and three
three one, when I take all their
combinations,
I fill out a whole plane.
Please think about that.
That's the picture you have to
see.
You sure have to see it in R^3
, because we're going to do it
in R^10, and we may take a
combination of five vectors in
R^10, and what will we have?
God knows.
It's some subspace.
We'll have five vectors.
They'll all have ten
components.
We take their combinations.
We don't have R^5 ,
because our vectors have ten
components.
And we possibly have,
like, some five dimensional
flat thing going through the
origin for sure.
Well, of course,
if those five vectors were all
on the line, then we would only
get that line.
So, you see,
there are, like,
other possibilities here.
It depends what --
it depends on those five
vectors.
Just like if our two columns
had been on the same line,
then the column space would
have been only a line.
Here it was a plane.
Okay.
I'm going to stop at that
point.
That's the central idea of --
the great example of how to
create a subspace from a matrix.
Take its columns,
take their combinations,
all their linear combinations
and you get the column space.
And that's the central sort of
-- we're looking at linear
algebra at a higher level.
When I look at A -- now,
I want to look at Ax=b.
That'll be the first thing in
the next lecture.
How do I understand Ax=b in
this language -- in this new
language of vector spaces and
column spaces.
And what are other subspaces?
So the column space is a big
one, there are others to come.
Okay, thanks.