PROFESSOR: Hi, welcome
back to recitation.
In the lecture, we've learned
very important concepts--
linear space and linear
subspace.
Well, as you can imagine, if
we call something a space,
we're putting a lot of things, a
lot of objects into one set.
But for linear space, we want to
put them in according to a
particular manner.
So can you recall what are the
conditions for a set to be a
linear space?
You take any two elements
from that set,
take the sum of them.
You want the sum to be still
in the same set.
That's the first condition.
Second, you take any multiple of
any element from that set,
the result will still
be in that set.
That's the second condition.
And if within a linear space
you can find a subset which
also satisfies the two
conditions, that will give you
a subspace.
Today, we're going to look at
this example to review these
two important properties of
linear space and subspace.
I have two vectors, x1 and x2.
Both of them are
vectors in R3.
So as you can see, I've
drawn them here.
This is x1, and this is x2.
So first, we want to find the
subspace generated by x1.
I call it v1.
Let me say a word about
this generated by.
So what do I mean by a subspace
generated by x1?
I'm looking for the smallest
subspace that contains x1, as
small as you can get.
Similarly, I want to find out
the subspace generated by x2,
call it v2.
Then we want to say something
about the
intersection of v1 and v2.
That's the first question.
And the second question, we want
to put vector x1 and x2
together and look at the
subspace generated by x1 and
x2 at the same time.
So I call it v3.
And a good question to be asked
here is what is the
relation of v3 to v1 union v2.
Do you think they're equal?
Within the second question, I
would also like you to find a
subspace, call it s of v3,
such that neither x1
nor x2 is in s.
And the last question is I'd
like you to say something
about the intersection of
v3 with the xy plane.
So notice that, of course,
xy plane is also
a subspace of R3.
So again, I'm looking at the
intersection of two subspaces.
All right, why don't you hit
the pause now, and try to
solve these three problems
on your own.
And I'd like you to identify
your answers in this picture
whenever you can.
I'll come back later and
continue working with you.
OK, how did your drawing go?
Let's look at this together.
First, we want to find subspace
generated by x1.
So here is x1.
Let's keep in mind the two
conditions that a subspace has
to satisfy.
Well, if I want to obtain the
subspace, at least I have to
be able to take any multiple
of x1, right?
So that means at least I have
to include the straight line
that contains x1.
So I'm going to try to draw
the straight line here.
So I'm just simply going to
extend this x1 along to both
directions.
So x1, I will try very hard
to make it straight.
But to be honest, it's really
hard for me to draw a straight
line from the board.
Is that straight?
Seems fine.
All right, so this entire
line contains x1.
So at least this line
has to be in v1.
Is there anything else
beyond this line?
Now let's turn to the
second condition.
The second condition says that
we have to be able to take any
two elements, take the
sum, and the sum will
remain in that set.
Does it work for this line?
You take any two vectors on this
line or you can say any
two points on this line, and
then you take to sum of them.
Of course, you still get
something on this line.
You won't be able to
escape from it.
Which means this line is a
perfect set that satisfies the
two conditions.
So this line simply
gives me v1.
That is the smallest subspace
that contains x1.
So in other words, the subspace
generated by x1 is v1.
So similarly, let's
look at x2.
What is the subspace
generated by x2?
Again you get the entire
straight line
that contains x2.
So I'm going to extend x2
in both directions.
I hope it's straight.
Not too bad.
That will give me v2.
All right, v1, v2.
Both of them are subspaces
of R3.
Now let's look at the
intersection of v1 and v2.
So we know that both of them
are straight lines.
And clearly they're not
parallel, because x1 and x2
are not parallel.
So what is the intersection
of v1 and v2?
The intersection of v1 and v2
is the only point at which
they cross.
And where's that point?
It's here, right
at the origin.
Because both of them
pass the origin.
I'm going to use o to denote.
That's the intersection
of v1 and v2.
This is a set with
only one element.
What can you say
about this set?
I claim this is also
a subspace of R3.
By saying space, we
usually mean a
lot of objects together.
But look at this set.
This set fits perfectly into
the conditions of being a
linear space.
You take any multiple of
0, again you get 0--
0 plus 0, you get 0.
So that's a perfectly
fine subspace of R3.
All right, so what we have
got here is I take the
intersection of v1 and v2, and
the result, again, becomes a
subspace, which only contains
the origin.
That completes the
first question.
Let's look at the second one.
In the second question, I want
to put x1 and x2 together, and
look at the subspace generated
by x1 and x2.
And I would also like you to
say something about the
relation between v1 union
v2 to the subspace
generated by x1 x2.
Let's try to answer the second
question first. Is there a
chance that v1 union
v2 equal to v3?
OK, so what is v1 union v2?
That's clearly just
two lines, right?
This line union this line.
Is there a chance that this
union will be a subspace?
Let's check the two
conditions.
First, you take any multiple of
the elements in this union.
It's either on this line
or on this line.
Seems that the multiple
is still going to
stay inside the union.
So the first condition is
actually satisfied.
What about the second one?
The second one says that I have
to be able to take any
sum, the sum of any
two elements,
from these two lines.
Let's just try a simple
sum, x1 plus x2.
So what is x1 plus x2?
You just sum up each
coordinate.
That will give you 2, 5, 3.
In this picture, can I draw
it in this picture?
It's going to be
somewhere here.
That's x1 plus x3.
Did you notice something?
You clearly have got
out of this union.
So this sum is not inside
v1 union v2.
Which means v1 union v2
is not a subspace.
Then it's impossible that this
union will equal to v3.
So the answer to the second
question is no, v3 is not
equal to v1 union v2.
Now let's identify v3.
Well, as you can see, since we
have seen from this argument
that we have to be able
to include this
diagonal vector here.
But in fact, as you can see
since we can take any elements
from these two lines, we're
actually including every
vector on the plane spanned
by v1 and v2.
So in other words, I'm actually
looking at this huge
plane that is spanned
by v1 and v2.
That will give me v3.
So that's reasonable.
I'm looking at the subspace
generated by two lines in R3.
And that two line will be able
to span a plane in R3.
Now for the last part of
question two, I want to find a
subspace s of v3.
So I want to find a subspace
of this plane such
that x1 is not s.
x2 is not in s either.
So I want to stay away from
this line and this line.
Can you find such a
subspace of v3?
It's right here.
Because if you look at this
vector, x1 plus x2-- sorry,
that should be x2.
If you look at this vector,
and if you look at the
subspace generated by this
vector, again you know it's
going to be a line.
And this line is right here.
This line forms a perfect
subspace of v3.
But neither x1 nor x2 is
inside this subspace.
So let's just make it
S. Of course, the
choice is not unique.
You can take twice x1 plus
x2 or x1 plus twice x2.
OK, we have completed
the second problem.
The last problems ask us to find
the intersection of v3
with xy plane.
Well, just think about that.
We've identified v3 as
this plane spanned
by line v1 and v2.
And xy is also a plane.
So we're talking about
the intersection of
two planes in R3.
What would that be?
So you have two planes
intersect.
The intersection will be a
straight line again, right?
So let's locate that
straight line.
We want to find something that
is inside of v3 and xy plane
at the same time.
What can you say about the
points in xy plane?
The z-coordinate has to be 0.
And at the same time, we
know that at least x1
and x2 are in v3.
So did you notice that?
x2 is a vector that
lies in v3.
But at the same time, the
z-coordinate of x2 is 0.
That is what we're
looking for.
So the intersection of v3 with
xy plane will simply be the
line that contains x2.
And here we've identified
that as v2.
That's it.
This is a subspace of R3.
And this is the subspace
of R3.
The intersection is again
a subspace of R3.
I hope you've learned a way to
somehow visualize this linear
space and subspace through
this exercise.
Thank you for watching, and
I'll see you next time.