27-24.
We charge a capacitor 'C', and
we charge it to 15 volts.
Then we discharge it through
a resistor 'R'.
So here is that capacitor, it's
fully charged, switch
here, resistor here, 'R', throw
the switch-- at first
there is +15 volts here--
we throw the switch, current
is going to flow until the
capacitor is completely
discharged.
Now this 'R' is part
of a voltmeter.
I shall call it 'Rv', and that
is 2.25 times 10 to the sixth
ohms. And what the voltmeter
indicates--
this is really a voltmeter--
is, of course, the product of
the current through the
voltmeter times the resistance
of the voltmeter.
So that's what the reading
will show you.
You start throwing the switch.
What do you see?
15 volts, of course.
Now you wait 5 seconds
and what do you see?
You only see 1/3 of 15 volts.
You only see 5 volts.
At least that's a given.
Well, if you look in your book
at page 848 you see in detail
how we set up the differential
equations for this circuit.
It's extremely simple.
And you'll find then that the
current through this circuit,
going in this direction, has a
function of time equals 'i0'
times 'e' to the ''- t'
divided by 'RC''.
Sometimes 'RC' is called the
discharge time, which is, of
course, a little bit
of a jargon.
Because it takes infinitely long
for the whole thing to be
discharged.
You have to wait for t
infinitely long for the
current to become 0.
Now, the voltmeter reads
'i' times 'R'.
But since you have the 'R' on
the right side as well as on
the left side, that's fine.
You can ignore that.
What you do know, however, is
that after 5 seconds it over
'i0' is 1/3.
So 1/3 equals 'e' to the
''- t' over 'RC'.
't' is 5 seconds over 'RC'.
Well, you know 'R'.
2.25 megaohms. So
out pops 'C'.
And I found that 'C' equals
2 microfarads.
If you make a curve of the
current as a function of time,
that would look like this.
This is the current, this is the
time, you start off with
some current 'i0', and it
discharges in exponential
fashion, and by the time it is
down to 'i0' over 'e', which
is somewhere here, the
time 't' equals 'RC'.
That's why it's often called the
'RC' time of the circuit.