Today I'm going to work with
you on a new concept and that is
the concept of what we call
electric field.
We spend the whole lecture on
electric fields.
If I have a -- a charge,
I just choose Q,
capital Q and plus at a
particular location and at
another location
I have another charge little Q,
I think of that as my test
charge.
And there is a separation
between the two which is R.
The unit vector from capital Q
to li- little Q is this vector.
And so now I know that the two
charges if they were positive --
let's suppose that little Q is
positive, they would repel each
other.
Little Q is negative they would
attract each other.
And let this force be F and
last time we introduced
Coulomb's law that force equals
little Q times capital Q times
Coulomb's constant divided by R
squared in the direction of R
roof.
The two have the same sign.
It's in this direction.
If they have opposite sign it's
in the other direction.
And now I introduce the idea of
electric field for which we
write
the symbol capital E.
And capital E at that location
P where I have my test charge
little Q at that location P is
simply the force that a test
charge experienced divided by
that test charge.
So I eliminate the test charge.
So I get something that looks
quite similar but it doesn't
have the little Q in it anymore.
And it is also a vector.
And by convention,
we choose the force such that
if this is a positive test
charge then we say the E field
is away from Q if Q is positive,
if Q is negative the force is
in the other direction,
and therefore E is in the other
direction.
So we adopt the convention that
the E field is always in the
direction that the force is on a
positive test charge.
What you have gained now is
that you
have taken out the little Q.
In other words the force here
depends on little Q.
Electric field does not.
The electric field is a
representation for what happens
around the charge plus Q.
This could be a very
complicated charge
configuration.
An electric field tells you
something about that charge
configuration.
The unit for electric field you
can see is newtons divided by
coulombs.
In SI units and normally we
won't even indicate the um the
unit,
we just leave that as it is.
Now we have graphical
representations for the electric
field.
Electric field is a vector.
So you expect arrows and I have
here an example of a -- a charge
plus three.
So by convention the arrows are
pointing away from the charge in
the same direction that a
positive test
charge would experience the
force.
And you notice that very close
to the charge the arrows are
larger than farther away.
That it that sort of represents
is trying to represent the
inverse R square relationship.
Of course it cannot be very
quantitative.
But the basic idea is this is
of course spherically symmetric,
if this is a point charge.
The basic idea is here you see
the field vectors and the
direction of the arrow tells you
in which direction the force
would be.
If it is a positive test
charge.
And the length of the vector
give you an idea of the
magnitude.
And here I have another charge
minus one.
Doesn't matter whether it is
minus one coulomb or minus
microcoulomb.
Just it's a relative
representation.
And you see now that the E
field vectors are reversed in
direction.
They're pointing towards the
minus charge by convention.
And when you go further out
they are smaller and you have to
go all
the way to infinity of course
for the field to become zero.
Because the one over R square
field falls off and you have to
be infinitely far away for you
to not experience at least in
principle any effect from the
from the charge.
What do we do now when we have
more than one charge?
Well, if we have several
charges -- here we have Q one
and here we have Q two and here
we have Q three and let's say
here we
have Q of I,
we have I charges.
And now we want to know what is
the electric field at point P.
So it's independent of the test
charge that I put here.
You can think of it if you want
to as the the force per unit
charge.
You've divided out the charge.
So now I can say what is the E
field due to Q one alone?
Well, that would be if Q one
were
positive then this might be a
representation for E one.
If Q two were negative,
this might be a representation
for E two, pointing towards the
negative charge.
And if this one were negative,
then I would have here a
contribution E three,
and so on.
And now we use the
superposition principle as we
did last time with Coulomb's
law, that the
net electric field at point P
as a vector is E one in
reference of charge Q one plus
the vector E two plus E three
and so on and if you have I
charges it is the sum of all I
charges of the individual E
vectors.
Is it obvious that the
superposition principle works?
No.
Does it work?
Yes.
How do we
know it works?
Because it's consistent with
all our experimental results.
So we take the superposition
principle for granted and that
is acceptable.
But it's not obvious.
If you tell me what the
electric field at this point is
which is the vectorial sum of
the individual E field vectors
then I can always tell you what
the force will be if I bring a
charge at that location.
I take any charge that I always
would carry in my pocket,
I take it out of my pocket and
I put it at that location.
And the charge that I have in
my pocket is little Q.
Then the force on that charge
is always Q times E.
Doesn't matter whether Q is
positive.
Then it will be in the same
direction as E.
If it is negative it will be in
the opposite direction as E.
If Q is large the force will be
large.
If Q is small the force will be
small.
So once you know the E
field it could be the result of
very complicated charge
configurations,
the real secret behind the
concept of an E field is that
you bring any charge at that
location and you know what force
acts at that point on that
charge.
If we try to be a little bit
more quantitative,
suppose I had here a charge
plus three and here I had a
charge minus one.
Here's minus one.
And I want to know what the
field configuration is as a
result of these two charges.
So you can go to any particular
point.
You get an E vector which is
going away from the plus three,
you get one that goes to minus
one, and you have to vectorially
add the two.
If you are very close to minus
one, it's very clear because of
the inverse R square
relationship that the minus one
is probably
going to win.
Let's in our mind take a plus
test charge now.
And we put a plus test charge
very close to minus one,
say put it here,
even though plus three is
trying to push it out,
clearly minus one is most
likely to win.
And so there will probably be a
force on my test charge in this
direction.
The net result of the effects
of the two.
Suppose I take the same
positive test charge and I put
it here, very far away,
much farther away than this
separation.
What do you think now is the
direction of the force on my
plus charge?
Very far away.
Excuse me.
Why do you think it's to the
left?
Do you think minus one wins?
A: [inaudible].
Do you really think the minus
one is stronger than the plus
three because the plus three
will push it out and
the minus one tries to lure it
in, right, if the test charge is
positive.
A:
plus two.
So if you're far away from a
configuration like this,
even if you were here,
or if you were there,
or if you're way there,
clearly the field is like a
plus two charge.
And falls off as one over R
squared.
So therefore if you're far away
the force is in this direction.
And now look,
what is very interesting.
Here if you're close to the
minus one, the force is in this
direction.
Here when you're very far away,
maybe I should be all the way
here, it's in that direction.
So that means there must be
somewhere here
the point where the E field is
zero.
Because if the force is here in
this direction but ultimately
turns over in that direction,
there must be somewhere a point
where E is zero.
And that is part of your
assignment.
I want you to find that point
for a particular charge
configuration.
So let's now go to some
graphical representations of a
situation which is actually plus
three minus one,
try to improve on the light
situation.
And let's see how these
electric vectors,
how they show up in the
vicinity of these two charges.
So here you see the plus three
and the minus one,
relative units,
and let's take a look at this
in some detail.
First of all the length of the
arrows again indicates the
strength.
It gives you a feeling for the
It's not very quantitative of
course.
And so let's first look at the
plus three, which is very
powerful.
You see that these arrows all
go away from the plus three and
when you're closer to the plus
three, they're stronger,
which is a representation of
the inverse R square field.
If you're very close to the
minus one, ah the arrows are
pointing in towards the minus
one, because the one over R
square, the minus one wins.
And so you see
they're clearly going into the
direction of the minus one.
Well, if you're in between the
plus and the minus on this line,
always the E field will be
pointing from the plus to the
minus.
Because the plus is pushing out
and the minus is sucking in.
So the two support each other.
But now if you go very far away
from this charge configuration,
anywhere but very far away,
much farther than the distance
between the two charges,
so somewhere here,
or somewhere there,
or here, notice that always the
arrows are pointing away.
And the reason is that plus
three and minus one is as good
as a plus two if you're very
very far away.
But of course when you're very
close in, then the field
configuration can be very very
complicated.
But you see very clearly that
these arrows are all pointing
outwards.
None of them come back to the
minus one.
None of them point to the minus
one direction.
And that's because the plus
three is more powerful and then
there is here
this point and only point
whereby the electric field is
zero, if you put a positive test
charge here, the minus will
attract it, the plus will repel
it, and therefore there comes a
point where the two cancel each
other exactly.
Now there is another way of
electric field representation
which is more organized.
And we call these field lines.
So you see again the plus three
and
you see there the minus one.
If I release right here or I
place here a positive test
charge all I know is that the
force will be tangential to the
field lines.
That is the meaning of these
lines.
So if I'm here the force will
be in this direction.
If I put a positive test charge
here, the force will be in this
direction, and of course,
if it's a negative charge the
force flips over.
So the meaning of the field
lines are that it always tells
you in which direction a charge
experiences a force.
A force a positive charge
always in the direction of the
arrows, tangentially to the
field lines and a negative
charge in the opposite
direction.
How many field lines are there
in space?
Well of course there are an
infinite number.
Just like these little arrows
that we had before,
we only sprinkled in a few but
of
course in every single point
there is an electric field and
so you can put in an infinite
number of field lines and that
would make this a representation
of course useless.
So we always limit ourselves to
a certain number.
If you look very close to the
minus one notice that all the
field lines come in on the minus
one.
We understand that of course
because a positive charge would
want to go to the minus one.
If you're very close to the
plus and they all go away from
the plus because they're being
repelled.
You can sort of think as these
field lines if you want to
imagine the configuration that
the plus charges blow out air
like a hairdryer,
and that the minus suck in air
like a vacuum cleaner,
and then you get a feeling for
there is on this left side here
this hairdryer which wants to
blow out stuff and then there is
that little sucker that wants to
suck something in and it
succeeds to some degree,
it's not as powerful as the
plus
three, though.
Have we lost all information
about field strength?
We had earlier with these
arrows, we had the length of the
arrow, the magnitude of the
field was represented.
Yeah, you have lost that,
but there is still some
information on field strength.
If the lines are closer
together, the density of the
lines is high,
the electric field is stronger
than when the density becomes
low.
So if you look for instance
here, look how many lines there
are per few millimeters,
and when you go further out
these
lines spread out,
that tells you the E field is
going down, the strength of the
E field is going down.
It's the one over R square
field of course.
If you want to make these
drawings what you could do to
make them look good,
you can make three times more
field lines going out from the
plus in this case than return to
the minus one.
So the field lines are very
powerful and we will often think
in terms of electric fields and
the line configurations and you
will have
several homework problems that
deal with electric fields and
with the electric field lines.
If an electric field line is
straight, so I have electric
fields, get some red chalk,
say we have fields that are
like this, straight E field
lines, and I release a charge
there, for instance a positive
charge,
then the positive charge would
experience a force exactly in
the same direction as the field
lines, because the tangential
now is in the direction of the
field line, it would become
accelerated in this direction
and would always stay on the
field lines.
If I release it with zero
speed, start to accelerate and
it would stay on the field
lines.
In a similar way,
if we think of the earth as
having a gravitational field,
with eight oh one we may never
have used that word,
gravitational field,
but in physics
we think of the -- of gravity
also being a field.
If I have here a piece of chalk
the um the field lines,
the gravitational field lines,
here in twenty-six one hundred,
nicely parallel and straight
and if I release this piece of
chalk at zero speed it will
begin to move in the direction
of the field lines,
and it will stay on the field
lines.
So now you can ask yourself the
question if I release a charge
would it always follow the field
lines?
And the answer is no.
Only in this very special case.
But suppose now that the field
lines are curved.
So here are field lines as you
have seen in those
configurations.
It's very common.
If now I release a -- a charge
in here, say I have a point
charge here, it will experience
a force in this direction.
So it will get an acceleration
in this direction,
so it will immediately abandon
that
field line.
And so if now you ask me what
is the trajectory of that
charge, well,
it could become very
complicated, I really don't
know.
Maybe it's going like this,
and by the time it reaches this
point, what I do know that then
the force will be tangential to
this field line,
so will be in this direction.
And so as it marches out and
picks up speed,
locally it will experience
forces representative of those
field lines and so the
trajectory can be rather
complicated.
So field lines are not
trajectories,
and not even when you release a
charge with uh with zero speed.
Only in case that the field
lines are straight lines.
Let's now look at a field
configuration which Maxwell
himself, the great maestro,
in some of his publications put
there.
And it's a ratio one to four
and whether it is plus four plus
one or minus four minus one
is not important because that's
just a matter of the direction
of the arrows.
But uh Maxwell didn't put
arrows in.
So I leave it up to you.
If it's plus four and plus one
you have to put arrows going
outwards.
And what you see now here is
this airblower effect.
Think of them as both being
positive.
So there is the plus four
trying to blow air out like a
hairdryer and the plus one is
trying to do its own thing and
so you get a field
configuration,
field lines,
which are sort of not
perhaps easy but you can sort
of imagine why it has this
peculiar shape.
If you um put a plus test
charge in between the one and
the four, then the four will
repel it but the one will also
repel it and so there's going to
be a point somewhere,
probably close to one,
whereby the two forces exactly
cancel out.
Therefore E will be zero there.
In a similar way between the
moon and the earth,
there is a point not too far
away from the moon where the
gravitational attraction from
the earth and the gravitational
attraction from the moon exactly
cancel each other out.
That's not too dissimilar from
this situation.
So when you have charges of the
same polarity,
you always find in between
somewhere a point where the
electric field is zero.
Let's now go to a very special
case whereby I make the two
charges equal in magnitude but
opposite in sign
and we have a name for that,
we call that a dipole.
The plus charge is here and the
minus charge is there.
Situation is extremely
symmetric, as you would expect,
because they have equal power.
There's one airblower upstairs
and one vacuum cleaner
downstairs.
If you're close to the plus
charge notice that all the field
lines go away from the plus.
And if you're close to the
minus, notice that all the field
lines come
in on the minus,
you expect that.
If you are far away from this
dipole, now you have a problem.
Before we had a plus three and
a minus one and when you're far
away the plus three wins.
So it's like having a plus two
charge.
If you're far away you always
expect the electric field then
to be pointing away from the
equivalent charge of plus two.
But if you add up plus and
minus and they have equal
magnitude,
let's say plus one and minus
one, you get zero,
so neither one wins if you're
far away, and notice carefully
if you're very far away,
indeed you do not see arrows
either pointing out nor pointing
in.
Nature cannot decide,
there isn't one that is
stronger than the other.
And that makes dipole fields
very very special.
In the case of the plus three
and the minus one,
if you're very far away,
it's like having a plus two
charge and the E field when you
go further and further out will
fall off as one
over R squared.
With a dipole your intuition
sort of tells you that it will
probably fall off faster than
one over R squared.
And that is part of a homework
assignment that you have this
week.
In fact I can already give you
the answer.
You have to prove it.
If you're far away from an
electric dipole the electric
field falls off as one over R
cubed.
It goes faster than one over R
squared.
There is not a single point in
space where the electric
field is zero.
And you can think about that
why that is the case.
So these field configurations
can be rather complicated and
can be very interesting and each
one has its own applications.
Are dipoles rare in physics?
Not at all.
In fact, they're extremely
common.
You cannot avoid them.
Remember last time,
I told you if you have a
spherical atom or we have a
spherical molecule,
and you bring that close to a
charge -- let's now think of it
you bring it in an electric
field, it's another way of
saying the same thing.
So we have a nice spherical
atom or a nice spherical
molecule and we bring it in an
electric field.
The electrons want to go
upstream the electric field
vectors, they go against the
direction of the electric field.
And the positive charge wants
to go in the direction,
wants to go downstream.
And so what are you going to
do?
The electrons will spend a
little bit more time on one side
of the nucleus than they would
in the absence of that electric
field.
And therefore you are through
induction turning that atom,
turning that molecule,
in becoming a dipole.
If you have a little bit more
charge on this side,
averaged over time,
you have the same amount of
extra charge plus on that side
averaged over time.
So you make dipoles very often
whether you like it or not.
And later in this course we
will learn more about the
polarization of
atoms and molecules creating
dipoles when when we talk about
dielectrics.
And you will see that it will
have an en- can have an enormous
impact on the properties of the
material.
Could I make you a dipole here
in class?
Oh yeah, that's very easy.
To make one of nonconductors is
not so easy in class.
To make one of conductors is
very easy.
And I'm going to do that with
these two spheres that you have.
Look at these two metal
spheres.
Conductors.
Free electrons.
It's very easy for them to
move.
And I'm going to bring this
rubber rod which I will rub and
becomes I think negatively
charged if I remember correctly,
and I will bring that so close
to these two which are touching
each other.
So here is this one metal
sphere and here is the other
metal sphere and here comes the
rubber.
Negatively charged.
Ah!
What's going to happen?
The electrons want to go away,
so this becomes negatively
charged, and therefore this
remains a little bit positively
charged.
For every one electron that has
is excess here,
when I start it's neutral,
there will be a positive excess
there because charge is
conserved.
You can't create charge out of
nothing.
And now what I do,
while this rubber is still
here, while that rubber rod is
there, I separate them,
so here the- they're in contact
with each other first,
they
have to be in contact,
wow, we get some visitors.
[clap-clap] Don't be late,
that means you,
pretty boy.
I'm impressed.
Thank you.
Um so what I do now is while
this rubber rod is still in
place, I take them apart,
and when I take them apart this
negative charge is trapped and
this positive charge is trapped.
And so I have thereby created
negative charge on this one.
Positive on this one and it's
equal in magnitude,
so I have a dipole.
What I want to demonstrate to
you is that indeed I have
positive charged here and
negative here,
that there is a difference in
polarity between these two,
and that's the way that I will
do the experiment.
I will not show you that the
amount of charge is exactly the
same on each,
which of course it has to be.
So let me give you some better
light, or we have to get the uh
view graph off,
the overhead,
you see there for the first
time an electroscope,
we discussed it last time,
it is a piece of aluminum foil,
very thin, with a metal rod
next to it, and when I put
charge on the rod it will also
go into the aluminum foil,
and they will repel each other,
and so the -- the aluminum
tinsel will go to the right and
the more charge there is on it,
the farther it goes to the
right.
So let me first put these two
together, make sure they are
completely discharged,
and now I'm going to bring
these two into an electric field
which is produced by this rubber
rod, I have to rub with the cat
fur, and I believe it was
negative but if you -- you'd
never have to remember whether
it's negative or positive of
course, that is not so
important, what is in a name,
after all.
But it did happen to be
negative.
OK.
So now we go here.
I bring it here,
I hope that no sparks will fly
over because that
ruins the demonstration.
And now notice what I do.
While the -- while the rod is
here I separate them.
So as I was holding it there,
things were going on in there
that you and I couldn't see but
electrons, the rubber rod is
negative, electrons were
shifting in this direction and
this is now positive and that is
now negative.
If I take this one and I touch
it with the electroscope,
you clearly see that there is
charge on this.
How can I show you now that
there is
charge of different polarity on
the other one?
Well, the way I will do that is
I will approach this
electroscope by bring this
sphere very close to it.
And if this charge is different
than the charge that is on it
the electroscope will -- the
reading will become smaller.
And why is that?
Why will the reading become
smaller?
Well, here is the situation of
the
electroscope now.
And here is that ball that you
see on top, this is upside-down
there, if this is all negative,
that's why it is apart,
if now I approach this here
with an object which is
positively charged and I claim
that this one now is positively
charged, because this one was
negatively charged,
then electrons are afraid of
the positive charge,
so more will go -- excuse me,
electrons love the positive
charge, so the electrons want to
come to the positive charge,
so these electrons drift down
again, and so if they come down,
fewer will be here,
and so you will see this.
If however I put here a
negative rod,
then the electrons which are
here want to go further away,
they will stream up,
and therefore the reading will
become larger.
So you can always through
induction test what the polarity
is of your charge.
Let's hope that this one is
still holding its charge while I
was talking.
So I claim now that if this
polarity is different and if
it's still there when I approach
the electroscope,
come very close,
that the reading should become
a little smaller without even
touching it.
Let's see whether that works.
You see, it goes down.
Goes down.
So through induction I have
demonstrated that this has
indeed a different polarity from
this one.
If I approached it with this
one, it would go further out,
unless it
already is at the maximum,
let's try that,
you see, it goes further out.
So not only have I demonstrated
that I created a dipole,
but you've also seen that by
means of induction that you can
demonstrate uh that the --
there's a difference in polarity
between the two spheres.
If I create a dipole and I put
that dipole in a --
in an electric field,
the dipole will start to
rotate.
Let's first talk about it.
Why it rotates.
And then I will try to
demonstrate that by making a
dipole, a big one,
this big.
Right in front of you,
almost as big as the one there.
So let's have a -- an electric
field like so.
And I bring in this electric
field a dipole,
a biggie, here,
this is the one I'm going to
use for this demonstration.
Ping Pong balls on either side,
they are conducting,
and they are con- connected
with a rod which is not
conducting.
And so here is this dipole.
To this rod is not conducting.
And this is a conducting and
this is a conductor.
And let's suppose this is
positive and this is negative
for now.
And I'll show you how we get
the charge on it.
Well, the positive charge will
experience a force in this
direction, always in the
direction of the electric field,
and the negative charge will
experience a force always
upstream.
And now there is a torque on
this and there is a torque on
this dipole.
It will start to rotate
clockwise.
And of course if it overshoots
the field lines when it is in
this direction the torque will
reverse.
It's very easy to see.
And so what you will see,
it's going to oscillate and if
there is enough damping it will
come to a halt more or less in
the direction of the field
lines.
And this is something that I
can demonstrate.
First I have to make a dipole
of this kind and the way I will
do that is the following.
This is a metal bar,
it's this insulator,
and here is this -- are these
two Ping Pong balls,
the one on this side has a
yellow marker,
the one on that side has an
orange marker,
and I'm going to attach them
holding them up against this
metal bar.
In other words,
here is this dipole,
it's not a dipole yet,
metal metal and here is a metal
bar, this is a conductor which
connects them.
I'm going to turn on the
VandeGraaff here,
and the VandeGraaff creates an
electric field,
so we have the VandeGraaff
here.
And let's suppose that this
VandeGraaff creates a positive
charge.
Sometimes a VandeGraaff creates
positive charge on the dome,
others can be designed to
create negative charge on the
dome.
And remember for now I assume
that's positive.
What will happen now?
Electrons want to go in this
direction.
So this becomes negative.
Protons positive charge stays
behind.
So that becomes through
induction a dipole.
Because I have them
connected.
I have them connected with this
metal bar.
So these electrons can flow
through this bar and end up
here.
Now I remove the bar.
And so when I remove the bar I
have created now a dipole.
I have here an insulating
thread and I have a fishing rod
and at the end of my fishing rod
I have now a permanent dipole.
With that permanent dipole I'm
now going to probe the electric
field around this VandeGraaff.
I could have chosen the same
VandeGraaff but there's a
reason why I picked this one and
as I walk around this
VandeGraaff you will see that
this fishing rod at the end is
this dipole, that the dipole
always wants to go radially
inwards or outwards depending on
how you look at it of this
field, so I can probe this field
and make you see for the first
time that there is indeed
somewhere here a strong radial
field going in or out of the
VandeGraaff.
And now comes something very
interesting,
which I found out this morning
for the first time when I did
this experiment.
If the other VandeGraaff there
is also positive when I run it,
how do you think this dipole is
going to align then if I walk
into it?
Will the negative ball be
closer to the VandeGraaff or
will the positive one go closer
to the VandeGraaff?
So I give you thirty seconds to
think about it,
so I make the dipole as it is
here, let's assume this one is
positive, this VandeGraaff.
So this side becomes minus,
I call that A,
and this side become positive,
that's B.
I now walk with this dipole,
I bring it in this field.
And let's assume that one is
also positive.
We don't know that yet.
How will the dipole align now?
Will A go inwards or will A go
outwards?
Who thinks A goes inwards?
Very good.
Who says A goes outwards?
OK.
A will go inwards.
If the two VandeGraaffs have
the same polarity.
So if that doesn't happen tha-
that doesn't mean that physics
doesn't work,
it means the two VandeGraaffs
have different polarities.
And we'll see what happens.
So let me first then create a
dipole.
So here is the -- the dipole.
It's shorted out now.
I turn on the -- this
VandeGraaff.
So induction takes place.
Remember that the yellow is
pointing towards the VandeGraaff
and that the orange is away from
the
VandeGraaff.
OK.
So I induce a dipole.
Oh.
I really should redo that.
I don't know what happens when
it -- I have to remove the field
first.
OK.
The yellow was inside,
right, was that the way it was?
OK.
Yellow inside.
There we go.
So now it's creating a dipole
through this metal bar.
And I break contact and this
should now be a dipole.
Now I turn on the field of the
-- so if the polarity is the
same, yellow will go in.
I will try to swing it a
little.
Notice two things.
It's going to line up
beautifully radially but the
yellow is not in,
the yellow is out.
So the two VandeGraaffs have
different polarities.
But you will see they rotate
nicely.
And they end up beautifully
radial and when I go all the way
around here again they may swing
a little, they may oscillate a
little, but through damping they
will come to a halt and look,
the field is indeed beautifully
radial and the yellow is so to
speak on the wrong side.
The two VandeGraaffs have
different
polarities.
So you see how we can create a
dipole and you've also seen how
we often can make statements
about uh the specific polarity.
I can probe an electric field
using grass seeds in oil.
Grass seeds are elongated
and when I put a grass seed in
the electric field it will
become polarized,
there's nothing you can do
about it.
Here is a grass seed and the
electric field is like so.
And so the electrons want to go
as far away in this direction as
they can through induction.
And so this side remains
positive, and so what is this
grass seed going to do?
It's going to rotate.
It's going to line up with the
electric field.
And this is the way that I'm
going to show you now field
configurations
in the vicinity of a dipole.
And I will also show you then
field configurations in a
vicinity of two charges which
have equal polarity.
You may have seen this in high
school with magnetic fields,
with iron files,
that's kid stuff.
That's the easiest thing to do.
This is the real thing,
this is the electric fields,
I bet you you've never seen
electric fields which are traced
by these mysterious seeds.
So I'll give you some light
that may optimize the
demonstration.
These seeds first have to be
oriented in a way so that it is
chaos.
The first thing you see is I'm
going to make this -- I believe
it's going to be a dipole first.
Almost certain.
So I'm going to charge one
positive and charge the other
negative.
And then we'll see how these
grass seeds will form each
other.
Watch closely.
There you go.
My goodness.
That is a wonderful dipole
field.
Of course we don't know which
one is plus or minus because the
grass seeds have no arrows on
them.
But you clearly see these
incredible lines radially
inwards or outwards on each one
of the charges and then you see
these nice arcs in between.
Who could see it easily?
OK, you got something worth for
your twenty thousand dollars'
tuition.
Put a little bit more charge on
maybe.
Very clear.
And now which is perhaps more
interesting, I'd like to show
you the field surrounding two
charges but now the charges are
both the same polarity.
So we have to undo the -- the
memory of the grass seeds.
OK, now we'll try to make them
both
the same polarity.
And then watch this hairblower
effect that I told you about.
Maybe not make -- I'm not sure
they made contact.
OK, we'll try it again.
Come on.
It's very funny,
you know, it looks like there
is
some -- some charge hidden
because it doesn't look as
beautiful as we had earlier on
the Maxwell view graph.
It seems like there is
something here on the side which
it prefers.
And therefore the electric
field is being distorted.
Let me try to discharge it.
I'm a reasonable conductor,
so I should be able to take any
stray charges off.
Oh, wait a minute.
Ha!
I had it upside-down.
[laughter] Oh my goodness.
Can happen to anyone.
All right.
So they were never really in
good contact,
we ready now?
Ah, look at that.
Great.
Now you really cle- clearly see
these -- these field lines,
and you see in between how the
two airblowers are competing
with each other.
Very impressive.
All right, so that's the way
you see field lines now,
electric field lines.
And some of you may have seen
with iron files uh magnetic
field lines.
If I have the VandeGraaff and I
have the VandeGraaff here,
and let's suppose the
VandeGraaff is positive,
I don't know whether it's
positive or negative,
let's suppose it's,
I'm going to use the one over
there, and I'm going to stand
here, on the ground,
Walter Lewin,
what is going to happen with
me?
Through induction,
the electrons being sucked out
of the earth and coming up
because they want to go close to
the positive charge.
So I will become negatively
charged.
What will the field lines do?
Oh, they will be extremely
complicated.
Very complicated.
But something like this maybe.
Maybe something like this.
Uh some may come out here.
Some may end up on my neck
here.
Some may go here.
Like so.
Very complicated field
configurations.
But I want to probe that field.
Somehow, a little.
Get a feeling for how that --
what that field is like.
And the way I'm going to do
that is I'm going to put a
charged balloon.
There you see the balloon.
It's a conductor.
I'm going to put a charged
balloon and put it here say.
Well if it is a positively
charged balloon it will take off
in that direction.
Right?
The force is always tangential
to the field lines.
It will abandon the field
lines, it won't stay on the
field lines, there's a lot of
damping on the balloon,
that's why I chose the balloon,
so it will move relatively
slowly, and it'll ultimately
maybe end up on my head,
right here.
Once it ends up on my head
there, so it comes in maybe like
this, now it will get the
negative charge from my head and
so it will become immediately
negatively charged and so the
force now will reverse and will
be in this direction,
tangential to this field line,
and so it will go back.
When it hits the VandeGraaff
again it will get positive
charge, reverse its polarity,
and it will go back.
And so it will b- bounce back
and forth between me and the
VandeGraaff and it gives you
some rough feeling of what this
field configuration is about,
although I want to remind you
that the charge does not follow
exactly field lines.
So I'm going to sit here and I
will be part of this,
so that's probably going to be
positive, I will automatically
become negative,
there's nothing I have to do,
all I turn is the VandeGraaff
and we have to put a little bit
of charge on that balloon.
It will probably do that by
itself, but I can always give it
a little kick so that it goes to
the VandeGraaff,
there it goes.
[laughter] Oh [inaudible]
because my -- my glasses are a
good insulator,
so I better take my glasses
off, so that every time it hits
me.
[laughter] Changes polarity.
[laughter] So this is a way you
can do physics and have fun at
the same time.
See you Monday.
[applause]