Creative Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or to view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: So, Professor
Jerison is relaxing in sunny
London, Ontario today and sent
me in as his substitute again.
I'm glad to the here
and see you all again.
He said that he'd already
talked about power series and
Taylor's formula oh on last
week right, on Friday?
So I'm going to go a little
further with that and show you
some examples, show you some
applications, and then I have
this course evaluation survey
that I'll hand out in the last
10 minutes or so of the class.
I also have this handout that
he made that says 18.01
end of term, 2007.
If you didn't pick this up
coming in, grab it going out.
People tend not to pick it up
when they walk in, I see.
So grab this when
you're going out.
There's some things
missing from it.
He has not decided when
his office hours will
be at the end of term.
He will have them, just
hasn't decided when.
So, check the website
for that information.
And we're looking forward
to the final exam, which
is [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Any questions about
this technical stuff?
All right, let's talk about
power series for a little bit.
So I thought I should review
for you what the story
with power series is.
OK, could I have your
attention please?
So, power series is a way of
writing a function as a sum
of interval powers of x.
These a, 0, a1, and
so on, are numbers.
An example of a power
series is a polynomial.
Not to be forgotten, one type
of power series is one which
goes on for a finite number of
terms and then ends, so that
all of the all the higher
a sub i's are all 0.
This is a perfectly good
example of a power series
it's a very special
kind of power series.
Part of what I want to tell you
today is that power series
behave, if almost exactly
like, polynomials.
There's just one thing that you
have to be careful about when
you're using power series
that isn't a concern for
polynomials, and I'll show you
what that is in a minute.
So, you should think of them
as generalized polynomials.
The one thing that you have
to be careful about is that
there's a number, which I'll
call r, where r can be between
0 and it can also be ifninity.
It's a number between 0 and
infinity, inclusive, so that
when the absolute value
of x is less than r.
So when x is smaller than r
in size, the sum converges.
that's sum converges
to a finite value.
And when x is bigger than
r in absolute value,
the sum diverges.
This r is called the
radius of convergence.
So we'll see some examples of
what the radius of convergence
is in various powers series as
well, and how you find it also.
Let me go on and give you a few
more of the properties about
power series which I think
that professor Jerison
talked about earlier.
So one of them is there's
a radius of convergence.
Here's another one.
If you're inside of the radius
convergence, then the function
has all it's derivatives.
It has all it's derivatives,
just like a polynomial does.
You can differentiate it
over and over again.
In terms of those derivatives,
the number a sub n in the power
series can be expressed in
terms of the value of
the derivative at 0.
And this is called
Taylor's formula.
So I'm saying that inside of
this radius of convergence, the
function that we're looking at,
this f of x, can be written as
the value of the function at 0,
that's a sub 0, plus the
value of the derivative.
This bracket n means you take
the derivative n times.
So, when n is one, you take the
derivative once at 0 divided
by one factorial, which is
one, and multiplied by x.
That's the linear term
in the power series.
Then, the qaudratic term is you
take the second derivative.
Remember to divide by 2
factorial which is 2.
Multiply that by x
squared and so on out.
So, the coefficients in the
power series just record the
values of derivatives of the
function at x equals 0.
They Can be computed
that way also.
Let's see.
I think that's a end of
my summary of things
that he talked about.
I think he did one example,
and I'll repeat that
example of a power series.
This example wasn't due
to David Jerison; it was
due to Leonard Euler.
It's the example of where the
function is the exponential
function e to the x.
So, let's see.
I will just repeat for you the
computations of the power
series for e to the x,
just because it's such an
important thing to do.
So, in order to do that, I have
to know what the derivative of
e to the x is, and what the
second derivative of e to the x
is, and so on, because that
comes into the Taylor formula
for the coefficients.
But we know what the
derivaative of e to the x is,
it's just e to the x again, and
it's that way all the way down.
All the derivatives are e to
the x over and over again.
So when I evaluate this at x
equal 0, well, the value of e
to the x is one, the value of e
to the x is one and x equals 0.
You get a value of one
all the way down.
So all these derivatives
at 0 have the value one.
And now, when I plug into this
formula, I find e to the x is
1, plus 1 times x, plus 1 over
2 factorial times x squared
plus 1 over 3 factorial
times x cubed and so on.
So all of these numbers are
one, and all you wind up
with is the factorials
and the denominators.
That's the power series
for e to the x.
This was a discovery
of Leonhard Euler in
1740 or something.
Yes Ma'am.
AUDIENCE: When your writing out
the power series, how far do
you have to write it out?
PROFESSOR: How far do you have
to write the power series
before it becomes well defined?
Before its a satisfactory
solution to an exam problem,
I suppose, is another way
to phrase the question.
Write until you can see
what the pattern is.
I can see what the pattern is.
Is there anyone who's in
doubt about what the
next term might be?
Some people would tell you
that you have to write the
summation convention thing.
Don't believe them.
If you right out enough
terms to make it clear,
that's good enough.
OK?
Is that an answer for you?
AUDIENCE: Yes, Thank you.
PROFESSOR: OK, so that's
a basic example.
Let's do another basic
example of a powers series.
Oh yes, and by the way,
whenever you write out a power
series, you should say what the
readius of convergence is.
For now, I will just to tell
you that the radius of
convergence of this power
series is infiinity; that is,
this sum always convergence
for any value of x.
I'll say a little more about
that in a few minutes.
AUDIENCE: Which functions can
be written as power series?
PROFESSOR: Which functions can
That's an excellent question.
Any function that has a
reasonable expression can be
written as a power series.
I'm not giving you a very good
answer because the true answer
is a little bit complicated.
But any of the functions that
occur in Calculus like sines
cosines, tangents, they all
have power series
expansions, OK?
We'll see more examples
Let's do another example.
Here's another example.
I guess this was example one.
So, this example, I think, was
due to Newton, not Euler.
Let's find the power series
expansion of this function,
1 over 1 plus x.
Well, I think that somewhere
along the line, you learned
about the geometric series
which tells you what the
answer to this is, and
I'll just write it out.
The geometric series tells you
that this function can be
written as an alternating
sum of powers of x.
You may wonder where
these minuses came from.
Well, if you really think about
the geometric series, as you
probably remembered, there was
a minus sign here, and
that gets replaced by
these minus signs.
I think maybe Jerison
talked about this also.
Anyway, here's another
basic example.
Remember what the graph of
this function looks like when
x is equal to minus one.
There's a little problem here
because the denominator
become 0, so the graph
has a poll there.
It goes up to infinity at x
equals minus one, and that's an
indication that the radius of
convergence is not infinity.
If you try to converge to this
infinite number by putting
in x equals minus one here,
you'll have a big problem.
In fact, you see when you put
in x equals minus one, you keep
getting one in every term, and
it gets bigger and bigger
and does not converge.
In this example, the radius
of convergence is one.
OK, so, let's do a
new example now.
Oh, and by the way, I should
say you can calculate these
numbers using Taylor's formula.
If you haven't seen
it, check it out.
Calculate The iterated
derivatives of this function
and plug in x equals 0 and see
that you get plus one, minus
one, plus one, minus
one, and so on.
Yes sir.
AUDIENCE: Per the radius of
convergence as stated, if you
do minus one it'll fall out.
If you put in one though,
seems like it would be fine.
PROFESSOR: The questions is I
can see that there's a problem
at x equals minus one, why is
there also a problem at x
equals one where the graph
is perfectly smooth and
innocuous and finite.
That's another
excellent question.
The problem is, that if you go
off to a radius of one in any
direction and there's
a problem, that's it.
That's what the radius
of convergence is.
Here, what does happen if I
put an x equals plus one?
So, let' look at
the partial sums.
Do x equals plus one
in your mind here.
So I'll get a partial sum
one, then 0, then one,
then 0, then one.
So even though it doesn't go
up to infinity, it still
does not converge.
AUDIENCE: And
anything in between?
PROFESSOR: Any of these other
things will also fail to
converge in this example.
Well, that's the only two
real numbers at the edge.
OK, let's do a
different example now.
How about a trig function?
I'm going to compute the power
series expansion for the sine
of x, and I'm going to do
it using Taylor's formula.
So Taylor's formula says that
I have to start computing
derivatives of the sine of x.
Sounds like it's going
to be a lot of work.
Let's see, the derivative
of the sine is the cosine.
and the derivative of the
cosine, the second derivative
of the sine, is what?
Remember the minus,
it's minus sine of x.
OK, now I want to take the
third derivative of the sine,
which is the derivative of
sine, prime, prime, so it's
the derivative of this.
And we just decided to
derivative of sine is cosine,
so I get cosine, but I have
this minus sign in front.
And now I want to differentiate
again, so the cosine becomes a
minus sine, and that minus sine
cancels with this minus
sine to give me sine.
of x.
You follow that?
It's a lot of minus one's
canceling out there.
So, all of a sudden, I'm right
back where I started; these two
are the same and the
pattern will now repeat
forever and ever.
Higher and higher derivatives
of sines are just plus or
minus sines and cosines.
Now Taylor's formula says I
should now substitute x equals
0 into this and see what
happens, so let's do that.
When x is equals to 0, the sine
is 0 and the cosine is one.
The sine is 0, so
minus 0 is also 0.
The cosine is one, but now
there's a minus one, and now
I'm back where I started, and
so the pattern will repeat.
OK, so the values of the
derivatives are all 0es and
plus and minus ones and they go
through that pattern, four-fold
periodicity, over
and over again.
So we can write out what
the sine of x is using
Taylor's formula.
So I put in the value at
0 which is 0, then I put
in the derivative which
is 1 multiplied by x.
Then, I have the second
derivative divided by 2
factorial, but the second
derivatve at 0 is 0.
So I'm going to drop
that term out.
Now I have the third derivative
which is minus one.
Remember the 3 factorial
in the denominator.
That's the coefficient
of x cubed.
What's the fourth derivative?
Well, here we are, it's
on the board, it's 0.
So I drop that term out
go up to the fifth term,
the fifth power of x.
It's derivative is now one.
We've gone through the pattern
and we're back at plus one as
the value of the iterated
derivative, so now I get 1/5
factorial times x to the fifth.
Now, you tell me, have we
done enough terms to see
what the pattern is?
I guess an x term will be
a minus 1/7 factorial
x to the seventh.
Let me write this out
again just so we have it.
So it's x minus x cubed over
3 factorial plus x to the
fifth over 5 factorial.
You guessed it, and so on.
That's the power series
expansion for the
sine of x, OK?
So, the sines alternate,
and these denominators
get very big, don't they?
Factorials grow very fast.
Let me make a remark.
r is infinity here.
The radius of convergence of
this power series again is
infinity, and let
me just say why.
The general term is going to be
like x to the 2n plus 1 divided
by 2n plus one factorial,
an odd number I can
write as 2n plus 1.
And what I want to say is about
what happens to the size of
this as n goes to infinity.
So let's just think about this.
For a fixed x, let's
fix the number of x.
Look at powers of x and think
about the size of this
expression when n
gets to be large.
Let's just do that
for a second.
So, for x to the 2n plus 1
over 2n plus 1 factorial,
I can write out like this.
It's x over one times x over x
over 3, times x over 2n plus 1.
I've multiplied x by itself 2n
plus 1 times in the numerator,
and I've multiplied the numbers
1, 2, 3, 4, and so on, by each
other in the denominator, and
that gives me the factorial.
So I've just written
this out like this.
Now x is fixed, so maybe
it's a million, OK?
It's big, but fixed.
What happens to these numbers?
Well at first,
they're pretty big.
This is a million over 2,
this is a million over 3.
But when n gets to be maybe
a million, then this
is about one half.
If n is a billion, then this
is about 1/2,000, right?
The denominator just keep
getting bigger and bigger,
but the numerators stay the
same; they're always x.
So when I take the product, if
I go far enough out, I'm going
to be multiplying, by very,
very small numbers and
more and more of them.
And so no matter what
x is, these numbers
will converge to 0.
They'll get smaller and smaller
as x gets to be bigger.
That's the sign that
x is inside of the
radius of convergence.
This is the sign for you
that this series converges
for that value of x.
And because I could do this
for any x, this works.
This convergence to
0 for any fixed s.
That's what tells you that
the raidus of convergence
is infinity because of the
formula that the radius of
convergence talks about.
If r is equal infinity,
this is no condition on x.
Every number is less than
infinity in absolute value, So
if this covergence to 0 of
the general term works for
every x, then radius of
convergence is infinity.
Well that was kind of fast, but
I think that you've heard
something about that
earlier as well.
Anyway, so we've got the sine
function, a new function
with its own power series.
It's a way of
computing sine of x.
If you take enough terms you'll
a good evaluation of the
sine of x for any x.
This tells you a lot about
the function sine of x but
not everything at all.
For example, from this formula,
it's very hard to see that
the sine of x is periodic.
I'ts not obvious at all.
Somewhere hidden away in this
expression is that number
pi, the half of the period.
But that's not clear from
the power series at all.
So the power series are
very good for some things,
but they hide other
properties of functions.
So I want to spend a few
minutes telling you about what
you can do with a power series
once you have one to get
new power series, and new
power series from old.
This is also called
operations on power series.
So what are the things that
we can do to a power series?
Well one of the things
you can do is multiply.
For example, what if I want to
compute a power series for
x times the sine of x.
Well I a power series for the
sine of x, I just did it.
How about a power series for x?
Actually, I did that here too.
The function x is a very
simple polynomial.
It's a polynomial where, about
0, a1 is 1, and all the
other coefficients are 0.
So x itself is a power
series, a very simple one.
The sine of x is
a powers series.
What I want to encourage you
to do is treat power series
just like polynomials and
multiply them together.
We'll see other operations too.
So, to compute the power series
for x times the sine of x, I
just take this one and
multiply it by x.
It distributes through x
squared minus x to the fourth
over 3 factorial plus
x to the sixth over 5
factorial, and so on.
Again, the radius of
convergence is going to be
the smaller of the two
radii of convergence here.
So it's r equals
infinity in this case.
OK, you can multiply
power series together.
It can be a pain if the power
series are very long, but
if one of them is x,
it's pretty simple.
OK, it's one thing I can do.
Notice something by the way.
You know that even
an odd functions?
So, sine is an odd function, x
is an odd function, and the
product of two large functions
is an even function.
That's reflected in the fact
that all the powers that occur
in the power series are even.
For an odd function, like the
sine, all the powers that
occur are odd powers of x.
That's always true.
OK, we can multiply, and I
can also differentiate.
Let's just do a case of that
and use the process of
differentiation to find out
what the power series for the
cosine of x is by writing
the cosine of x as the
derivative of the sine and
differentiating term by term.
So, I'll take this expression
for the power series of the
sine and differentiate it term
by term, and I'll get the
power series for cosine.
So, let's see.
The derivative of x is one.
The derivative of x cubed is 3x
squared, and then there's a 3
factorial in the denominator.
The derivative of x to the
fifth is 5x to the fourth, and
there's a 5 factorial in the
denominator, and
so on and so on.
And know some
cancellation happens.
So this is one minus, well, the
3 cancels with the last factor
in this 3 factorial and
leaves you with 2 factorial.
The 5 cancels with the last
factor in the 5 factorial and
leaves you with a 4 factorial
in the denominator.
So, there you go, there's
the power series
expansion for the cosine.
It's got all even powers of x
they alternate, and you have
factorials in the denominator.
And of course, you could derive
that expression by using
Taylor's formula by the same
kind of calculation you did
here, taking higher and higher
derivatives of the cosine.
You get the same periodic
pattern of derivatives and
values of derivatives
at x equals 0.
But here's a cleaner, simpler
way to do it because
we already knew the
derivative of the sine.
When you differentiate,
you keep the same
radius of convergence.
OK, so we can multiply, and I
can add to and multiply that
constant, things like that.
How about integrating?
That's what half of this
course was about isn't it?
So, let's integrate something.
So, the integration I'm going
to do is this one: the
integral from 0 to x
of dt over one plus x.
What is that integral
as a function?
So, when I find the
anti-derivative of this, I get
the natural log of 1 plus t,
and then when I evaluate that
at t equals x, I get the
natural log of 1 plus x.
And when I evaluate the natural
log at 0, I get the natural
log of one, which is 0, so
this is what you get, OK?
This is really valid, by
the way, for x bigger
than minus one.
But you don't want to think
about this quite like this
when x is smaller than that.
Now, I'm going to try to apply
power series methods here and
use this integral to find a
power series for the natural
log, and I'll do it by plugging
in to this expression what the
power series for
1/1 plus t was.
I know what that is because
I wrote it down on
the board up here.
Change the variable from x to
t there, and so 1/1 plus t is
1 minus t, plus t squared,
minust t cubed, and so on.
So that's the thing in the in
inside of the integral, and now
it's legal to integrate that
term by term, so let's do that.
I'm going to get something
which I will then
evaluate at x and at 0.
So, when I integrate one
I get x, and when they
integrate t, I get t.
Intergrating t, I get t squared
over 2, and t squared gives me
t cubed over 3, and
so on and so on.
Then, when I put in t equals x,
while I just replace all the
t's by x's, and when I put
in t equals 0, I get 0.
So this equals x.
So, I've discovered that the
natural log of 1 plus x is x
minus x squared over 2, plus x
cubed over 3 minus x to the
fourth over 4, and
so on and so on.
There's the power series
expansion for the natural
log of 1 plus x.
Because I began with a power
series who's radius of
convergence was just one, I
began with this power series,
the radius of convergence of
this is also going to be one.
Also, because this function as
I just pointed out, this
function goes bad when x
becomes less than minus one, so
some problem happens, and
that's reflected in the
radius of convergence.
Cool, so, you can integrate.
That is the correct power
series expansion for the
natural log of 1 plus x, and
another victory of Euler's was
to use this kind of power
series expansion to calculate
natural algorithms in a much
more efficient way than
people had done before.
OK, one more property, what
are we at here, 3 or 4?
Substitute, very appropriate
for me as a substitute teacher
to tell you about substitution.
So I'm going to try to find
the power series expansion
of e to the minus t squared.
And the way I'll do that is by
taking the power series
expansion for e to the x, which
we have up there, and make the
substitution x equals minus t
squared in the expansion
for x to the x.
Did you have a question?
AUDIENCE: Well, it's just
concerning the radius
of convergence.
You can't define x so that is
always positive, and if so, it
wouldn't have a radius
of convergence, right?
PROFESSOR: Like I say, again
the worry is this natural log
of 1 plus x function
is perfectly well
behaved for large x.
Why does the power series fail
to converge for large x?
Well suppose that x is bigger
than one, then here you get
bigger and bigger powers of x,
which will grow to infinity,
and they grow large faster than
the numbers 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
They grow exponentially, and
these just grow linearly.
So, again, when x is bigger
than one, the general term will
go off to infinity, even though
the function that you're
talking about, log of net of 1
plus x is perfectly good.
So the power series is
not good outside of the
radius of convergence.
It's just a fact of life.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Talk to
me after class.
The question is why is it
the smaller of the two
radii of convergence?
The basic answer is, well, you
can't expect it to be bigger
than that smaller one, because
the power series only gives you
information inside of that
range about the function, so.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Well, in this
case, both of the radii of
convergence are infinity.
x has radius of convergence
infinity for sure, and
sine of x does too.
So you get insanity
in that case, OK?
Let's just do this, and then
I'm going to integrate this and
that'll be the end of what
I have time for today.
What's the power series
expansion for this?
The power series expansion of
this is going to be a function
of t, right, because
the variable here is t.
I get it by taking my expansion
for x to the x and putting
in what x is in terms of t.
I just put in minus t squared
in place of x there in the
series expansion
for e to the x.
I can work this out a
little bit better.
minus t squared is what it is.
This is going to give me a t
to the fourth and the minus
squared is going to give me
a plus, so I get t to the
fourth over 2 factorial.
Then I get minus t quantity
cubed, so there'll be a minus
sign and a t to the sixth and
the denominator 3 factorial.
So the signs are going to
alternate, the powers are all
even, and the denominators
are these factorials.
Several times as this course
has gone on, the error function
has made an appearance.
The error function gets
normalized by putting a 2 over
the square root of pi in front,
and it's the integral of e to
the minus t squared
d t from 0 to x.
This normalization is here
because as x gets to the
large the value becomes one.
So this error function is
very important in the
theory of probability.
I think you calculated
this fact at some
point in the course.
This is the standard definition
of the error function, you
put a 2 over the square
root of pi in front.
Let's calculate it's
power series expansion.
So there's a 2 over the
score root of pi that hurts
nobody here in the front.
And now I want to integrate
either the minus t squared, and
I'm going to use this power
series expansion for that
to see what you get.
I'm just going to write
this out I think.
I did it out carefully
in another example over
there so I'll do it a
little quicker now.
intergrate this terms by term,
you're just integrating powers
of t so it's pretty simple, and
then I'm evaluating
at and then 0.
So I get x minus x cubed over
3, plus x to the fifth over 5
times 2 factorial, 5 from
integrating the t's of the
fourth, and the 2 factorial
from this denominator
that we already had.
And then there's an a minus x
to the seventh over 7 times 3
factorial, and plus, and so
on, and you can imagine
how they go on from there.
I guess to get this exactly
in the form that we began
talking about, I should
multiply through.
So the coeifficient of x is 2
over the square root of pi, and
the coefficient of x cubed is
minus 2/3 times the square
root of pi, and so on.
But this is a perfectly good
way to write this power
series expansion as well.
And, this is a very good
way to compute the value
of the error function.
It's a new function
in our experience.
Your calculator probably
calculates it, and your
calculator probably does
it by this method.
OK, so that's my sermon on
examples of things you can
do with power series.
So, we're going to do the
CEG thing in just a minute.
Professor Jerison wanted me
to make an ad for 18.02.
Just in case you were thinking
of not taking it next term,
you really should take it.
It will put a lot of things
in this course into
context, for one thing.
It's about vector
calculus and so on.
So you'll learn about vectors
and things like that.
But it comes back and explains
some things in this course that
might have been a little bit
strange, like these strange
formulas for the product rule
and the quotient rule and these
sort of random formulas.
Well, one of the things you
learn in 18.02 is that
they're all special
cases of the chain rule.
And just to drive that point
home, he wanted me to show you
this poem of his that really
drives the points home
forcefully, I think.