Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or to view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses visit
MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Today we
are continuing with
improper integrals.
I still have a little bit
more to tell you about them.
What we were discussing at
the very end of last time
was improper integrals.
Now and these are going
to be improper integrals
of the second kind.
By second kind I mean if
they have a singularity
at a finite place.
That would be
something like this.
So here's the definition
if you like.
Same sort of thing as we
did when the singularity
was an infinity.
So if you have the integral
from 0 to 1 of f of x.
This is going to be the
same thing as the limit.
As a goes to 0 from above.
The integral from 8
to 1 of f of x d x.
The idea here is the same one
that we had at infinity.
Let me draw a picture of it.
You have imagine a function
which is coming down like
this and here's the point 1.
And we don't know whether the
area enclosed is going to be
infinite or finite until we
cut it off at someplace a.
And we let a go
to 0 from above.
So really it's 0 plus.
So we're coming in
from the right here.
And we're counting up
the area in this chunk.
And we're seeing as it expands
whether it goes to infinity or
whether it tends to
some finite limit.
Right so this is the example
and this is the definition.
And just as we did for the
other kind of improper
integral, we say that this
converges-- so that's the key
word here --if the limit is
finite, exists maybe I should
just say and diverges if not.
Let's just take care of
the basic examples.
First of all I wrote this
one down last time.
We're going to
evaluate this one.
The integral from 0 to 1 of 1
over the square root of x.
You almost don't notice the
fact that it goes to infinity.
This goes to infinity
as x goes to 0.
But if you evaluate it --
first of all we always
write this as a power.
Right?
To get evaluation.
And then I'm not even going
to replace the 0 by an a.
I'm just going to
leave it as 0.
The antiderivative here
is x to the 1/2 times 2.
And then I evaluate
that at 0 and 1.
And I get 2.
2 minus 0, which is 2.
All right so this
one is convergent.
And not only is it convergent
but we can evaluate it.
The second example being not
systematic but really giving
you the principal examples
that we'll be thinking about.
Is this one here d x over x
And this one gives you the
antiderivative as
the logarithm.
Valuated at 0 and 1.
And now again you have to have
this thought process in your
mind that your really
taking the limit.
But this is going to be the
log of 1 minus the log of 0.
Really the log of 0 from above.
There is no such thing as
the log 0 from below.
And this is minus infinity.
So it's 0 minus minus infinity,
which is plus infinity.
And so this one diverges.
All right so what's
the general?
So more or less in general for
powers anyway, if you work out
this thing for d x over
x to the p from 0 to 1.
What you're going to find is
that it's 1 over 1 minus p.
When p is less than one.
And it diverges for p
bigger than or equal to 1.
Now that's the final result.
If you carry out this
integration it's not difficult.
All right so now I just
want to try to help
you to remember this.
And to think about how you
should think about it.
So I'm going to say it
in a few more ways.
All right just repeat what I've
said already but try to get it
to percolate and absorb itself.
And in order to do that I have
to make the contrast between
the kind of improper integral
that I was dealing with before.
Which was not as x goes to
0 here but as x goes to
infinity, the other side.
Let's make this contrast.
First of all, if I look at the
angle that we have been paying
attention to right now.
We've just considered
things like this.
1 over x to the 1 half.
Which is a lot smaller
than one over x.
Which is a lot smaller than
say 1 over x squared.
Which would be another example.
This is as x goes to 0.
So this once the smallest one.
This one next smallest one.
And this one is very large.
On the other hand it goes
the other way at infinity.
As x tends to infinity.
All right so try to
keep that in mind.
And now I'm going to put
a little box around
the bad guys here.
This one is divergent.
And this one is divergent.
When the cross over
point is 1 over x.
When we get smaller than
that, we get to things
which are convergent.
When we get smaller than
it on this other scale,
it's convergent.
All right so these
guys are divergent.
So they are associated
with divergent integrals.
The functions themselves are
just tending towards-- well
these tend to infinity,
and these tend toward 0.
So I'm not talking about
the functions themselves
but the integrals.
Now I want to draw this again
here, not small enough.
I want to try this again.
So I'm just going to draw
a picture of what it
is that I have here.
But I'm going to combine
these two pictures.
So here's the picture for
example of y equals 1 over x.
All right.
That's y equals 1 over x.
And that picture
is very balanced.
It's symmetric on the two ends.
If I cut it in half then what
I get here is 2 halves.
And this one has
an infinite area.
That corresponds to the
integral from 1 to infinity,
d x over x being infinite.
And the other piece--
which this one we
calculated last time.
This is the one that we just
calculated over here at example
2 has the same property.
It's infinite.
And that's the fact that
the integral from 0
to 1 is infinite.
Right we lose on both ends.
On the other hand if I take
something like-- I'm drawing it
the same way but it's really
not the same --y equals 1 over
the square root of x. y equals
one over x to the 1 half.
And if I cut that in half here
then the x to the 1 half is
actually bigger than this guy.
So this piece is infinite.
And this part over here
actually is going to give
us an honest number.
In fact this one is finite.
And we just checked
what the number is.
It actually happens
to have area 2.
And what's happening here is if
you would superimpose this
graph on the other graph what
you would see is
that they cross.
And this one sits on top.
So if I drew this one in let's
have another color here
--orange let's say.
If this were orange if I
set it on top here it
would go this way.
OK and underneath the
orange is still infinite.
So both of these are infinite.
On here on the other hand
underneath the orange is
infinite but underneath
where the green is finite.
That's a smaller quantity.
Infinity is a lot
bigger than 2.
2 is a lot less than infinity.
All right so that's reflected
in these comparisons here.
Now if you like if I want
to do these in green.
This guy good and
this guy is good.
Well let me just repeat that
idea over here in this sort
of reversed picture with y
equals 1 over x squared.
If I chop that in half then the
good part is this end here.
It's finite.
And the bad part is this
part of here which is
way more singular.
And it's infinite.
All right so again what I've
just tried to do is to give
you some geometric sense and
also some visceral sense.
This guy it's tail as it goes
out to infinity is much lower.
It's much smaller
than 1 over x.
And these guys trapped an
infinite amount of area.
This one traps only a
finite amount of area.
All right so now I'm just going
to give one last example which
combines these two
types of pictures.
It's really practically
the same as what I said
before but I-- oh have
to erase this one too.
So here's another example
if you're in so let's take
the following example.
This is somewhat related
to the first one that
I gave last time.
If you take a function y equals
1 over x minus 3 squared.
And you think about
it's integral.
So let's think about the
integral from 0 to infinity,
d x over x minus 3 squared.
And suppose you were faced
with this integral.
In order to understand what
it's doing you have to pay
attention just two places
where it can go wrong.
We're going to split
into two pieces.
I'm going say break it up
into this one here up to 5,
for the sake of argument.
And say from 5 to infinity.
All right.
So these are the two chunks.
Now why did I break it up
into those two pieces?
Because what's happening with
this function is that it's
going up like this at 3.
And so if I look at
the two halves here.
I'm going to draw them again
and I'm going to illustrate
with what colors we've chosen--
which are I guess red and green
--what you'll discover is that
this one here which corresponds
to this piece here is infinite.
And it's infinite because
there's a square in
the denominator.
And as x goes to 3 this
is very much like we
shifted the 3 to 0.
Very much like this 1
over x squared here.
But not in this context.
In the other context where
it's going to infinity.
This is the same as at the
picture directly above with
the infinite part in red.
All right.
And this part here
This part is finite.
All right.
So since we have an infinite
part plus a finite part
the conclusion is that
this guy converges.
And this one diverges.
But the total
unfortunately diverges.
Right because it's got
1 infinity in it.
So this thing diverges.
And that's what happened
last time when we
got a crazy number.
If you integrated this you
would get some negative number.
If you wrote down the
formulas carelessly.
And the reason is
that the calculation
actually is nonsense.
So you've gotta be aware if you
encounter a singularity in
the middle not to ignore it.
Yeah.
Question.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: Why do we say that
the whole thing diverges?
The reason why we say that
is the area under the
whole curve is infinite.
It's the sum of this
piece plus this piece.
And so the total is infinite.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: We're stuck.
This is an ill
defined integral.
It's one where you're
red flashing warning
sign should be on.
Because you're not going
to get the right answer
by computing it.
You'll never get an answer.
Similarly you'll never
get an answer with this.
And you will get an
answer with that.
OK?
Yeah another question.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: So the question is
if you have a little glance at
an integral, how are you going
to decide where you
should be heading?
So I'm going to
answer that orally.
Although you know but I'll
say one little hint here.
So you always have to check x
going to infinity and x going
to minus infinity, if
they're in there.
And you also have to check any
singularity, like x going
to 3 for sure in this case.
You have to pay attention
all the places where
the thing is infinite.
And then you want to focus
in on each one separately.
And decide what's going on it
at that particular place.
When it's a negative power.
So remember d x over x
as x goes to 0 is bad.
And d x over x squared is bad.
D x over x cubed is bad.
All of them are even worse.
So anything of this form is
bad and equals 1, 2, 3.
These are the red box kind.
All right.
That means that any of the
integrals that we did in
partial fractions which had a
root, which had a factor of
something, the denominator
Those are all divergent
integrals if you cross
the singularly.
Not a single one of them makes
sense across the singularity.
If you have square roots and
things like that then you can
repair things like that.
And there's some interesting
examples of that.
Such as with the arc sign
function and so forth.
Where you have an improper
integral which is really OK.
All right.
So that's the best I can do.
It's obviously something
you get experience with.
All right.
Now I'm going to move
on and this is more or
less our last topic.
Yay but not quite.
Well it's our
penultimate topic.
Right because we have
one more lecture.
All right.
So that our next
topic is series.
Now we'll do it in a sort
of a concrete way today.
And then we'll do what are
known as power series tomorrow.
So let me tell you
about series.
Remember we're talking
about infinity and
dealing with infinity.
So we're not just talking
about any old series.
We're talking about
infinite series.
There is one infinite series
which is probably, which is
without question the most
important and useful series.
And that's the geometric series
but I'm going to introduce it
concretely first in
a particular case.
If I draw a picture
of this sum.
Which in principle
goes on forever.
You can see that it go
someplace fairly easily by
marking out what's happening
on the number line.
The first step takes
us to 1 from 0.
And then if I add this
half, I get to 3 halves.
Right, so the first step was 1
and the second step was a half.
Now see if I add this quarter
in which is the next piece
then I get some place here.
But what I want to observe is
that I can look at it from
the other point of view.
When I move this quarter I
got half way to 2 here.
I'm putting 2 in green because
I want you to think of it
as being the good kind.
Right.
The kind that has a number.
And not one of the red kind.
We're getting there and
we're almost there.
So the next stage we
get half way again.
That's the eighth and so forth.
And eventually we get to 2.
So this sum we
write equals two.
All right that's kind
of a paradox because
we never get to 2.
This is the paradox
that Zeno fussed with.
And his conclusion with
the rabbit and the hare.
Oh no the rabbit
and the tortoise.
Sorry hare chasing-- anyway the
rabbit chasing the tortoise.
His conclusion-- I don't know
if you're aware of this --but
he understood this paradox.
And he said you know it doesn't
look like it ever gets there
because they're infinitely many
time between the time-- you
know that the tortoise is
always behind, always behind,
always behind, always behind.
So therefore it's impossible
that the tortoise
catches up right.
So do you know what
his conclusion was?
Time does not exist.
That was actually
literally his conclusion.
Because he didn't understand
the possibility of a
continuum of time.
Because there were infinitely
many things that happened
before the tortoise caught up.
So that was the reasoning.
I mean it's a long time ago
but you know he didn't
believe in continuum.
All right.
So anyway that's a small point.
Now the general case here of
geometric series is where
I put in a number a
instead of a half here.
So what we had before.
So that's 1 plus a
plus a squared.
Isn't quite the most
general but anyway
I'll write this down.
And your certainly going to
want to remember that the
formula for this in the
limit is 1 over 1 minus a.
And I remind you that there's
only works when the absolute
value is strictly less than 1.
In other words when minus
1 is strictly less
than a is less than 1.
And that's really the issue
that we're going to want
to worry about now.
What we're worrying about is
this notion of convergence.
And what goes wrong when there
isn't convergence, when
there's a divergence.
So let me illustrate
divergence before going on.
And this is what we have
to avoid if we're going
to understand series.
So here's an example
when a is equal to 1.
You get 1 plus 1 plus
1 plus et cetera.
And that's equal to
1 over 1 minus 1.
Which is 1 over 0.
So this is not bad.
It's almost right.
It's sort of infinity
equals infinity.
At the edge here we managed
to get something which
is sort of almost right.
But you know it's we don't
consider this to be logically
to make complete sense.
So it's a little dangerous
And so we just say
that it diverges.
And we get rid of this.
So we're still
putting it in red.
All right.
The bad guy here so
this one diverges.
Similarly if I take a equals
minus 1, I get 1 minus 1 plus 1
minus one plus 1 because the
odd and even powers in that
formula alternate sign.
And this bounces
back and forth.
It never settles down.
It starts at 1.
And then it gets down to 0
and then comes back up to
1, down to 0, back up to 1.
It doesn't settle down.
It bounces back and forth.
It oscillates.
On the other hand if you
compare the right hand side.
What's the right hand side?
It's 1 over 1 minus minus 1.
which is a half.
All right.
So if you just paid
attention to the formula.
Which is what we were doing
when we integrated without
thinking too hard about this.
You get a number here but
in fact that's wrong.
Actually it's kind of
an interesting number.
It's halfway between
the 2 between 0 1.
So again there's some sort of
vague sense in which this is
trying to be this answer.
All right.
It's not so bad but we're still
going to put this in a red box.
All right.
because this is what
we called divergence.
So both of these
cases are divergent.
It only really works
when a is less than 1.
I'm going to add one more case
just to see that mathematicians
are slightly curious about
what goes on in other cases.
So this is 1 plus 2
plus 2 squared plus
2 to cube plus etc..
And that should be equal to--
according to this formula
--1 over 1 minus 2.
Which is negative 1.
All right.
Now this one it
clearly wrong, right?
This one it's totally Wrong
It certainly diverges.
The left hand side is
obviously infinite.
The right hand side is way off.
It's negative 1.
On the other hand it turns out
actually that mathematicians
have ways of making
sense out of these.
In number theory there's
a strange system where
this is actually true.
And what happens in that system
is that what you have to throw
out is the idea that 0
is less than you 1.
There is no such thing
as negative numbers.
So this number exists.
And it's the additive
inverse of 1.
It has this arithmetic property
but the statement that 1 is
bigger than 0 does
not make sense.
So you have your choice either
this diverges or you have to
throw out something like this.
So that's a very curious
thing in higher mathematics.
Which if you get to number
theory there's fun stuff there.
All right.
OK but for our purposes
these things are all out.
All right.
They're gone.
We're not considering them.
Only a between
negative 1 and 1.
All right.
Now I want to do
something systematic.
And it's more or less on the
lines of the powers that
I'm erasing right now.
I want to tell you
about series.
Which are kind of
borderline convergent.
And then next time when we talk
about powers series we'll come
back to this very important
series which is the
most important one.
So now let's talk about some
series general notations.
And this will help you
with the last bit.
This is going to be pretty
much the same as what we
did for improper integrals.
First of all I'm going to have
capital S N which is the sum of
a n, n equals 0 to capital N.
And this is what we're
calling a partial sum.
And then the full limit which
is capital S, if you like, and
N equals 0 to infinity is just
the limit as N goes to
infinity of the Sn.
And then we have the same kind
of notation that we had before.
Which is there these two
choices which is that
if the limit exists.
That's the green choice.
And we say it converges.
So we say the series converges.
And then the other case which
is limit does not exist.
And we can say the
series diverges.
Question.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: The question was
how did I get to this?
And I will do that next time
but in fact of course you've
seen in high school.
Right this a-- Yeah.
Yeah.
We'll do that next time.
The question was how do we
arrive-- sorry I didn't tell
you the question --the question
was how do we arrive at this
formula on the right
hand side here.
But we'll talk about
that next time.
All right.
So here's the basic definition
and what we're going to
recognize about series.
And I'm going to give you a
few examples and then we'll
do something systematic.
So the first example-- well the
first example is the geometric
series But the first example
that I'm going to discuss now
and in a little bit of detail
is this sum 1 over n squared
N equals 1 to infinity.
It turns out that this series
is very analogous-- and we'll
develop this analogy carefully
--the integral from 1 to
x d x over x squared.
And we're going to develop
this analogy in detail
later in this lecture.
And this one is one of the
ones-- so now you have to go
back and actually remember
this is one of the ones you
really want to memorize.
And you should especially
pay attention to the ones
with an infinity in them.
This one is convergent.
And this series convergent.
Now it turns out that
evaluating this is very easy.
This is 1.
It's easy to calculation.
Evaluating this is very tricky.
And Euler did it.
And the answer with
pie squared over 6.
That's amazing calculation.
And it was done very early in
the history of mathematics.
If you look at another
example-- so maybe example
two here -if you look
at 1 over n cubed.
n equals-- well you can't
start here at 0 by the way.
I get to start where ever
I want in these series.
Here I start with 0.
Here I started with 1.
And notice the reason why it
was a bad idea to start with 0
was that 1 over 0 is undefined.
Right so I'm just starting
where it's convenient for me.
And since I'm interested mostly
in the tale behavior it doesn't
matter to me so much
where I start.
Although if I want an exact
answer I need to start
exactly at n equals 1.
All right.
This one is similar to
this integral here.
All right.
Which is convergent again.
So there's a number
that you get.
And let's see what is it
something like 2 thirds or
something like that for
this for this number.
Or a third.
What is it?
No a half.
I guess it's a half.
This one is a half.
You check that I'm not positive
but anyway just doing it
in my head quickly it
seems to be a half.
Anyway it's an easy
number to calculate.
This one over here
stumped mathematicians
basically for all time.
It doesn't have any kind of
elementary form like this.
And it was only very recently
proved to be rational.
People couldn't even couldn't
even decide whether this was
a rational number or not.
But anyway that's been resolved
it is an irrational number
which is what people suspected.
Yeah question.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Yeah sorry.
OK I violated a rule of
mathematics-- you said
why is this similar?
I thought that similar
was something else.
And you're absolutely right.
And I violated a rule
of mathematics.
Which is that I uses
this symbol for two
different things.
I should have written
this symbol here.
All right.
I'll create a new symbol here.
The question of whether this
converges or this converges.
These are this the same
type of question.
And we'll see why they're
the same question it
in a few minutes.
But in fact the wiggle I use
similar I used for the
connection between functions.
The things that are really
similar are that 1 over n
resembles 1 over x squared.
So I apologize I didn't--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: Oh you thought
that this was the
definition of that.
That's actually the
reason why these things
correspond so closely.
That is that the Riemann's
sum is close to this.
But that doesn't
mean they're equal.
The Riemann's sum only works
when the delta x goes to 0.
The way that we're going to get
a connection between these two
as, we will just a second,
is with a Riemann sum with.
What we're going to use
is a Riemann's sum
with delta x equals 1.
All right and then that will
be the connection between.
Right that's absolutely right.
All right.
So in order to illustrate
exactly this idea that
you've just come up with.
And in fact that
we're going to use.
We'll do the same thing but
we're going to do it on
the example sum 1 over n.
So here's example 3 and it's
going to be sum 1 over n,
n equals 1 to infinity.
And what we're now going to
see is that it corresponds
to this integral here.
And we're going to show
therefore that thing diverges.
But we're going to
do more carefully.
We're going to do this in some
detail so that you see what the
correspondence is between
these quantities.
And the same sort of
reasoning applies to
these other examples.
So here we go.
I'm going to take the integral
and draw the picture
of the Riemann's sum.
So here's the level one
and here's the function
y equals 1 over x.
And I'm going to take
the Riemann's sum.
With delta x equals 1.
And that's going to be
closely connected to
the series that I have.
But now I have to decide
whether I want to lower
Riemann's sum or an
upper Riemann's sum.
And actually I'm going to check
both of them because both
of them are illuminating.
First will do the
upper Riemann's sum.
Now that's this staircase here.
So we'll call this the
upper Riemann's sum.
And let's check what
it's levels are.
This is not to scale.
This level should be a half.
So if this is 1 and this is 2
and that level was supposed to
be a half then this next
level should be a third.
That's how the Riemann's
sums are working out.
And now I have the
following phenomenon.
Let's cut it off at the n.
So that means that the integral
if from 1 to n d x over x.
And the Riemann's sum
is something that's
bigger than it.
Because the areas are enclosing
the area of the curved region.
And that's going to be the area
of the first box which is 1,
plus the area of the second box
which is a half plus the
area of the third box
which is a third.
All the way up the last one
but the last one starts
today n minus 1.
So it has 1 over n minus 1.
There are not n boxes here.
They're only n minus 1 boxes.
Because the distance between
1 n is n minus one.
Right so this is n
minus one terms.
However if I use a
notation for partial sum.
Which is 1 plus 1 over 2 plus
all the way up to n over n
minus one plus 1 over n.
In other words I go out to
the n one which is what
I would ordinarily do.
Then this sum that I have here
certainly is less than sn.
Because there's one
more term there.
And so here I have an
integral which is
underneath this sum s n.
Now this is going to allow
us to prove conclusively
that the sum diverges.
Why is that?
Because this term here
we can calculate.
This is the log x
evaluated at 1 and n.
Which is the same thing
as log n minus 0.
All right the quantity log
n minus log 1 which is 0.
And so what we have here is
that log n is less than s n.
All right and clearly this
goes to infinity right.
As n goes to infinity this
thing goes to infinity.
So we're done.
All right we've
shown divergence.
The way I'm going to use the
lower Riemann's sum is to
recognize that we've captured
the rate appropriately.
That is not only do have a
lower bound like this but
I have an upper bound
which is very similar.
So if I use the upper--
remind oh sorry --the
lower Riemann's sum again
with delta x equals 1.
Then I have that the integral
from 1 to n of d x over x is
bigger than-- Well what are
the terms going to be if
fit sit them underneath?
If I fit them underneath I'm
missing the first term.
That is the box is going
to be half height.
It's going to be
this lower piece.
So I'm missing this first term.
So it'll be a half plus a third
plus it will keep on going.
But now the last one instead
of being 1 over n minus 1.
It's going to be 1 over n.
This is again a total of
the n minus 1 terms.
This is the lower
Riemann's sum.
And now we can recognize that
this is exactly equal to s n
minus 1 minus the first term.
So we missed the first term but
we got all the rest of them.
So if I put this to the
other side remember
this is the log n.
All right.
If I put this to the other
side I have the other
side of this bound.
I have that f n is less than
if I reverse it log n plus 1.
And so I've trapped it
on the other side.
And here I have
the lower bound.
So I'm going to combine
those together.
So all hold I have this
correspondence here.
It is the size of a log n is
trapped between the size of f n
which is relatively hard to
calculate and understand
exactly is trapped between
log n and log n plus 1.
Yeah question.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: This step here
is the step that you're
concerned about.
So this step is a geometric
argument which is
analogous to this step.
All right it's the same
type of argument.
And in this case it's that the
rectangle is on top and so the
area represented on the right
hand side is less than the area
represented on this side.
And this is the same type
of thing except that the
rectangle is underneath.
So the sum of the areas of
the rectangle is less than
the area under the curve.
All right.
So I've now trapped
this quantity.
And I'm now going to state
the sort of general results.
So here's what's known
as integral comparison.
It's this double arrow
correspondence in the general
case, for a very general case.
There is actually even more
cases where it works.
But this is a good
case and convenient.
And this is called
integral comparison.
And it comes with hypothesis
but it follows the same
argument that I just gave.
If f of x is decreasing and
it's positive then the sum f n,
n equals 1 to infinity minus
the integral from 1 to infinity
of f of x d x is less
than half of 1.
That's basically
what we showed.
We showed that the difference
between s n and log
n was at most 1.
All right.
And the sum and the integral
converge or diverge together.
That is they either both
converge or both diverge.
This is the type of test that
we like because then we can
just convert the question of
convergence over here to this
question of convergence
over on the other side.
Now I remind you that
it's incredibly hard to
calculate these numbers.
Whereas these numbers are
easier to calculate.
Our goal is to reduce
things to simpler things.
In this case sums, infinite
sums are much harder
than infinite integrals.
All right so that the
integral comparison.
And now I have one last
bit on comparisons that I
need to tell you about.
And this is very much like
what we did with integrals.
Which is so called
limit comparison.
The limits comparison says
the following if f of n
is similar to g of n.
You will recall that means f
of n over g of n tends to
1 as n goes to infinity.
And we're in the positive case.
So let's just say
g n is positive.
Then sum f n sum g n same
this as above, either both
converge or both diverge.
All right.
This is just saying that if
they behave the same way in the
tail, which is all we really
care about, then they have
similar behavior, similar
convergence properties.
And let me give you
a couple examples.
So here's one example if
you take the sum 1 over n
squared plus 1 square root.
This is going to be replaced
by something simpler.
Which is the main term here.
Which is 1 over square root of
n squared which we recognize as
sum 1 over n which diverges.
So this guy is one
of the red guys.
On the red team now we
have another example.
Which is let's say the square
root of n to the fifth
minus n squared.
Now if you have something
where it's negative in the
denominator you kind of
do have to watch out that
denominator makes sense.
It isn't 0.
So we're going to be careful
and start this at n equals 2.
I don't like 1 over 0 as
a term in my series.
So I'm just going to be a
little careful about how-- as I
said I was kind of lazy here.
I could have started this
one at 0 for instance.
All right.
So here's the picture.
Now this I just replace by it's
main term which is 1 over n
to the fifth square root.
Which is sum 1 over n to the
five halves which converges.
All right.
The power is bigger than 1.
1 is the divider for these
things and it just misses.
This one converges.
All right so these are the
typical ways in which these
convergence processes are used.
All right.
So I have one more
thing for you.
Which is an advertisement
for next time.
And I have this demo
here which I will grab.
But you will see
this next time.
So here's a question for you to
think about overnight but don't
ask friends you have to
think about yourself.
So here's the problem.
Here are some blocks
which I acquired when
my kids left home.
Anyway yeah that'll happen to
you too in about four years.
So now here you are
these are blocks.
So now here's the question
that we're going to
deal with next time.
I'm going to build it, maybe
I'll put it over here
because I want to have some
room to head this way.
I want to stack them up
so that-- oh didn't work
--going to stack them up
in the following way.
I want to do it so that the
top one is completely to the
right of the bottom one.
That's the question
can I do that?
Can I build this up?
So what's let's see here.
I just seem to be missing-- but
anyway what I'm going to do is
I'm going to try to build this
and we're going to see how far
we can get with this next time.