Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or to view
additional materials for
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
mitopencourseware@ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Last time we left
off with a question having to
do with playing with blocks.
And this is supposed to give us
a visceral feel for something
anyway, having to
do with series.
And the question was whether I
could stack these blocks, build
up a stack so that I'm
going to try here up.
I'm already off
balance here, see.
The question is can I build
this so that the-- let's draw
a picture of it so that the
first block is like this.
The next block is like this.
And maybe the next
block is like this.
And notice there is
no visible means of
support for this block.
It's completely to the
left of the first block.
And the question is,
will this fall down?
Or at least, or more precisely,
eventually we'll ask you
know, how far can we go?
Now before you answer this
question, the claim is it that
this is a kind of a natural,
physical question, which
involves some important answer.
No matter whether the answer
is, you can do it or you can't.
So this is a good kind of math
question where no matter what
the answer is, when you figure
out the answer, you're
going to get something
interesting out of it.
Because they're two
possibilities.
Either there is a limit to how
far to the left we can go-- in
which case that's a very
interesting number-- or
else there is no limit.
You can go arbitrarily far.
And that's also
interesting and curious.
And that's the difference
between convergence and
divergence, the thing that
we were talking about up
to now concerning series.
So my first question is, do you
think that I can get it so that
this thing doesn't fall down
with, well you see I have about
eight blocks here or so.
So you can vote now.
How many in favor that I can
succeed in doing this sort of
thing with maybe more
than three blocks.
How many in favor?
All right somebody
is voting twice.
That's good.
I like that.
How about opposed?
So that was really
close to a tie.
All right.
But I think the there was
slightly more opposed.
I don't know.
You guys who are in the
back maybe could tell.
Anyway it was pretty close.
All right.
So now I'm going-- because this
is a real life thing-- I'm
going to try to do it.
All right?
All right.
So now I'm going to tell
you what the trick is.
The trick is to
do it backwards.
When most people are playing
with blocks, they decide to
build it from the bottom up.
Right?
But we're going to build
it from the top down,
from the top down.
And that's going to make it
possible for us to do the
optimal thing at each stage.
So when I build it from the
top down, the best I can do
is well, it'll fall off.
I need to have it you
know, halfway across.
That's the best I can do.
So the top one I'm going
to build like that.
I'm going to take it as
far to the left as I can.
And then I'm going to put
the next one down as far
to the left as I can.
And then the next one as
far to the left as I can.
That was a little too far.
And then I'm going to
do the next one as far
to the left as I can.
And then I'm going to do the
next one-- well let's line it
up first-- as far to
the left as I can.
OK?
And then the next one as
far to the left as I can.
All right.
Now those of you who are
in this line can see,
all right, I succeeded.
All right, that's
over the edge.
All right?
So it can be done.
All right.
So now we know that we can
get farther than you know,
we can make it overflow.
So the question now is,
how far can I get?
OK.
Do you think I can get to here?
Can I get to the end over here?
So how many people think I can
get this far over to here?
How many people think
I can get this far?
Well you know, remember.
I'm going to have to use more
than just this one more
block that I've got.
Right?
Obviously I'm thinking,
actually I do have some
more blocks at home.
But, OK.
We're not going to.
But anyway, do you think
I can get over to here?
How many people say yes?
And how many people say no?
More people said no then yes.
All right.
So maybe the stopping
place is some mysterious
number in between here.
All right?
Well OK.
So now we're going to
do the arithmetic.
And we're going to figure out
what happens with this problem.
OK?
So let's do it.
All right, so now again the
idea is, the idea is we're
going to start with the
top, the top block.
We'll call that
block number one.
And then the farthest if you
like to the right, that you
can put a block underneath
it, is exactly halfway.
All right well, that's
the best job I can do.
Now in order to make my units
work out easily, I'm going
to decide to call the
length of the block 2.
All right?
And that means if I start
at location 0, then the
first place where I am is
supposed to be halfway.
And that will be 1.
OK so the first step in the
process is 1 more to the right.
Or if you like, if I were
building up-- which is what you
would actually have to do in
real life-- it would
be 1 to the left.
OK now the next one.
Now here is the way that
you start figuring
out the arithmetic.
The next one is based on
a physical principle.
Which is that the farthest I
can stick this next block
underneath is what's called the
center of mass of these two,
which is exactly halfway here.
That is there's 1/4 of this
guy, and a 1/4 of that
guy balancing each other.
Right?
So that's as far as I can go.
If I go farther than
that, it'll fall over.
So that's the absolute
farthest I can do.
So the next block is
going to be over here.
And 1/4 of 2 is 1/2.
So this is 3/2 here.
All right so we went to 1.
We went to it 3/2 here.
And then I'm going to keep on
going with this eventually.
All right so we're going to
figure out what happens
with this stack.
Question?
AUDIENCE: How do you know
that this is the best
way to optimize?
PROFESSOR: The question is
how do I know that this is
the best way to optimize?
I can't answer that question.
But I can tell you that it's
the best way if I start
with a top like this, and
the next one like this.
Right, because I'm doing
the farthest possible
at each stage.
That actually has a name in
computer science that's
called the greedy algorithm.
I'm trying to do the best
possible at each stage.
The greedy algorithm starting
from the bottom, is an
extremely bad strategy.
Because when you do that,
you stack it this way,
and it almost falls over.
And then the next time
you can't do anything.
So the greedy algorithm is
terrible from the bottom.
This is the greedy algorithm
starting from the top, and it
turns out to do much better
then the greedy algorithm
starting from the bottom.
But of course I'm not
addressing whether there might
not be some other incredibly
clever strategy where I wiggle
around and make it go up.
I'm not addressing
that question.
It turns out this is
the best you can do.
But that's not clear.
All right so now, here
we have this thing.
And now I have to figure out
what the arithmetic pattern is,
so that I can figure out what I
was doing with those shapes.
So let's figure out a
thought experiment here.
All right?
Now the thought experiment I
want to imagine for you is,
you've got a stack of a bunch
of blocks, and this is
the first N blocks.
All right?
And now we're going to
put one underneath it.
And what we're going to figure
out is the center of mass of
those N blocks, which I'm
going to call C sub N.
OK.
And that's the place where
I'm going to put this
very next block.
I'll put it in a
different color here.
Here's the new,
next block over.
And the next block over
is the N plus 1st block.
And now I want you to think
about what's going on here.
If the center of mass of the
first N blocks is this number,
this new one, it's of length 2.
And its center of mass is
1 further to the right
than the center of mass
that we had before.
So in other words, I've added
to this configuration of N
blocks, 1 more block,
which is shifted.
Whose center mass is not lined
up with the center of mass of
this, but actually over
farther to the right.
All right so the new center of
mass of this new block-- and
this is the extra piece of
information that I want to
observe-- is that this thing
has a center of mass
at C sub N plus 1.
It's 1 unit over because
this total length is 2.
So right in the middle there is
1 over, according to my units.
All right now this is going to
make it possible for me to
figure out what the new
center of mass is.
So C sub N plus 1 is the center
of mass of N plus 1 blocks.
Now this is really only in the
horizontal variable, right?
I'm not keeping track
of the center of mass.
Actually this thing is hard
to build because the center
of mass is also rising.
It's getting higher and higher.
But I'm only keeping track
of its left and right
characteristic.
So this is the
x-coordinate of it.
All right so now
here's the idea.
I'm combining the white ones,
the N blocks, with the
pink one, which is the
one on the bottom.
And there are N of
the white ones.
And there's 1 of the pink one.
And so in order to get the
center of mass of the whole,
I have to take the weighted
average of the two.
That's N times C sub N plus 1,
times the center of mass of the
pink one, which is
C sub N plus 1.
And then I have to divide if
it's the weighted average of
the total of N plus 1
blocks, by N plus 1.
This is going to give me the
new center of mass of my
configuration at the
N plus 1st stage.
And now I can just do the
arithmetic and figure
out what this is.
And the two C sub Ns combine.
I get N plus 1, times C sub N
plus 1, divided by N plus 1.
And if I combine these two
things and do the cancellation,
that gives me this recurrence
formula, C sub N plus 1 is
equal to C sub N plus,
there's a little extra.
These two cancel.
That gives me the C sub N.
But then I also have
1 over N plus 1.
Well that's how much gain I
can get in the center of mass
by adding one more block.
That's how much I can shift
things over, depending on how
we're thinking of things to the
left or the right, depending on
which direction we're
building them.
All right, so now I'm going
to work out the formulas.
First of all C sub 1, that was
the center of the first block.
I put its left-ended
0, the center of the
first block is at 1.
That mean that C sub 1 is 1.
OK?
C sub 2, according to this
formula-- and actually I've
worked it out, we'll check
it in this thing-- C sub 2
is C sub 1 plus 1 over 2.
All right, so that's
the case, N equals 1.
So this is 1 plus 1/2.
That's what we already did.
That's the 3/2 number.
Now the next one is
C sub 2 plus 1/3.
That's the formula again.
And so that comes out to
be 1 plus 1/2 plus 1/3.
And now you can see
what the pattern is.
C sub N, if you just keep on
going here, C sub N is going
to be 1 plus 1/2 plus
1/3 plus 1/4 plus 1/N.
So now I would like
you to vote again.
Do you think I can-- now that
we have the formula-- do you
think I can get over to here?
How many people think I
can get over to here?
can't get over to here?
There's still a lot
of people who do.
So it's still almost 50/50.
That's amazing.
Well so we'll address
that in a few minutes.
So now let me tell
you what's going on.
This C sub N of course,
is the same as what we
called last time S sub N.
And remember that we actually
estimated the size of this guy.
This is related to what's
called the harmonic series.
And what we showed is that log
N is less than S sub N, which
is less than S sub N plus 1.
All right?
Now I'm going to call your
attention to the red part,
which is the divergence part
of this estimate, which is
this one for the time
being, all right.
Just saying that this
thing is growing.
And what this is saying is that
as N goes to infinite, log N
goes to infinite, So that means
that S sub N goes to
infinite, because of
this inequality here.
It's bigger than log N.
And so if N is big enough, we
can get as far as we like.
All right?
So I can get to here.
And at least half of you, at
least the ones who voted,
that was I don't know.
We have a quorum here,
but I'm not sure.
We certainly didn't have a
majority on either side.
Anyway this thing
does go to infinite.
So in principle, if I had
enough blocks, I could
get it over to here.
All right, and that's the
meaning of divergence
in this case.
On the other hand, I want to
discuss with you, and the
reason why I use this example,
is I want to discuss with you
also what's going on with this
other inequality here, and
what its significance is.
Which is that it's going to
take us a lot of numbers N,
a lot of blocks, to get
up to a certain level.
In other words, I can't
do it with just eight
blocks or nine blocks.
In order to get over
here, I'd have to use
quite a few of them.
So let's just see
how many it is.
So I worked this out carefully.
And let's see what I got.
So to get across the
lab tables, all right.
This distance here, I
already did this secretly.
But I don't actually even have
enough of these to show you.
Well 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 1/2.
I guess that's enough.
So it's 6 and 1/2.
So it's two lab tables
is 13 of these blocks.
All right.
So they're 13 blocks, which
is equal to 26 units.
OK, that's how far to
get across I need.
And the first one is already 2.
So it's really 26
minus 2, which is 24.
Which that's what I need.
OK.
So I need log N to be equal
to 24, roughly speaking,
in order to get that far.
So let's just see
how big that is.
All right.
I think I worked this out.
So let's see.
That means that N is equal to
either the 24th-- and if you
realize that these blocks are 3
centimeters high-- OK let's see
how many that we
would need here.
That's kind of a lot.
Let's see, it's 3 centimeters
times either the 24th, which
is about 8 times 10
to the 8th meters.
OK.
And that is twice the
distance to the moon.
So OK, I could do it maybe.
But I would need
a lot of blocks.
Right?
So that's not very
plausible here, all right.
So those of you who voted
against this were actually
sort of half right.
And in fact, if you wanted to
get it to the wall over there,
which is over 30 feet, the
height would be about
the diameter of the
observable universe.
That's kind of a long way.
There's one other thing that
I wanted to point out to
you about this shape here.
Which is that if you lean
to the left, right?
If you put your head like
this-- of course you have to be
on your side to look at it--
this curve is the shape
of a logarithmic curve.
So in other words, if you think
of the vertical as the x-axis,
and the horizontal that way, is
the vertical, is the up
direction, then this thing is
growing very, very,
very, very slowly.
If you send the x-axis all the
way up to the moon, the graph
still hasn't gotten across
the lab tables here.
It's only partway there.
If you go twice the distance to
the moon up that way, it's
gotten finally to that end.
All right so that's how
slowly the logarithm grows.
It grows very, very slowly.
And if you look at it another
way, if you stand on your
head, you can see an
exponential curve.
So you get some sense as
to the growth properties
of these functions.
And fortunately these are
protecting us from all kinds of
stuff that would happen if
there weren't exponentially
small tails in the world.
Like you know, I could walk
through this wall which
I wouldn't like doing.
OK, now so this is
our last example.
And the important number,
unfortunately we didn't
discover another
important number.
There wasn't an amazing number
place where this stopped.
All we discovered again is
some property of infinite.
So infinite is still
a nice number.
And the theme here is just that
infinite isn't just one thing,
it has a character which
is a rate of growth.
And you shouldn't just
think of there being
one order of infinite.
There are lots of
different orders.
And some of them have different
meaning from others.
All right so that's the theme I
wanted to do, and just have a
visceral example of infinite.
Now, we're going to move
on now to some other
kinds of techniques.
And this is going to
be our last subject.
What we're going to
talk about is what are
known as power series.
And we've already seen
our first power series.
And I'm going to
remind you of that.
Here we are with power series.
Our first series was this one.
And we mentioned last time
that it was equal to 1 over 1
minus x, for x less than 1.
Well this one is known as
the geometric series.
You didn't use the letter x
last time, I used the letter a.
But this is known as
the geometric series.
Now I'm going to show you one
reason why this is true,
why the formula holds.
And it's just the kind of
manipulation that was done
when these things were
first introduced.
And here's the idea of a proof.
So suppose that this sum is
equal to some number x,
which is the sum of all
of these numbers here.
The first thing that
I'm going to do is I'm
going to multiply by x.
OK, so if I multiply by x--
let's think about that-- I
multiply by x on both the left
and the right-hand side.
Then on the left side, I get x
plus x-squared plus x-cubed
plus, and so forth.
And on the right side,
I get S times x.
And now I'm going to
subtract the two equations,
one from the other.
And there's a very, very
substantial cancellation.
This whole tail here
gets canceled off.
And the only thing
that's left is the 1.
So when I subtract, I get
1 on the left-hand side.
And on the right-hand side,
I get S minus S times x.
All right?
And now that can be rewritten
as S times 1 minus x.
And so I've got
my formula here.
This is 1 over 1 minus
x is equal to S.
All right.
Now this reasoning
has one flaw.
It's not complete.
And this reasoning is
basically correct.
But it's incomplete because
it requires that S exists.
For example, it doesn't
make any sense in
the case x equals 1.
So for example in the case
x equals 1, we have 1 plus
1 plus 1 plus et cetera,
equals whatever we call S.
And then when we multiply
through by 1, we get 1 plus 1
plus 1 plus, equals S times 1.
And now you see that the
subtraction gives us infinite
minus infinite is equal to
infinite minus infinite.
That's what's really
going on in the argument
in this context.
So it's just nonsense.
I mean it doesn't give
us anything meaningful.
So this argument, it's great.
And it gives us the right
answer, but not always.
And the times when it gives us
the answer, the correct answer,
is when the series
is convergent.
And that's why we care
about convergence.
Because we want manipulations
like this to be allowed.
So the good case, this is
the red case that we were
describing last time,
that's the bad case.
What we want is the good
case, the convergent case.
And that is the case
when x is less than 1.
So this is the convergent case.
Yep.
OK, so they're much more
detailed things to check
exactly what's going on.
But I'm going to just say
general words about how you
recognize convergence.
And then we're not going to
worry about so much about
convergence, because it
works very, very well.
And it's always easy to
diagnose when there's
convergence with
a power series.
All right so here's
the general setup.
The general setup is that we
have not just the coefficients
1 all the time, but any
numbers here, dot, dot, dot.
And we abbreviate that with
the summation notation.
This is the sum a n x to the
n, n equals 0 to infinite.
And that's what's known
as a power series.
Fortunately there is a very
simple rule about how
power series converge.
And it's the following.
There's a magic number R which
depends on these numbers here
such that-- and this thing is
known as a radius of
convergence-- and the
problem that we had,
it's this number 1 here.
This thing works
for x less than 1.
In our case, it's
maybe x less R.
So that's some symmetric
interval, right?
That's the same as minus R,
less then x, less than R, and
so where there's convergence.
OK, where the series converges.
And then there's the region
where every computation that
you give will give
you nonsense.
So x greater than R is the sum
a sub n x to the n, diverges.
And x equals R is very
delicate, borderline, and
will not be used by us.
OK we're going to stick inside
the radius of convergence.
Now the way you'll be
able to recognize this,
is the following.
What always happens is that
these numbers tend to 0
exponentially fast for x in R,
and doesn't even tend to 0 at
all for x greater than R.
Right so it'll be
totally obvious.
When you look at this series
here, what's happening when x
less than R is that the numbers
are getting smaller and
smaller, less than 1.
When x is bigger than 1,
the numbers are getting
bigger and bigger.
There's no chance that
the series converges.
So that's going to be the
case with all power series.
There's going to be a cut off.
And it'll be one
particular number.
And below that it'll be obvious
that you have convergence, and
you'll be able to
do computations.
And above that every
formula will be wrong
and won't make sense.
So it's a very clean thing.
There is this very subtle
borderline, but we're not going
to discuss that in this class.
And it's actually not used in
direct studies of power series.
AUDIENCE: How can you tell when
the numbers are declining
exponentially fast, whereas
just, in other words 1
over x [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: OK so, the question
is why was I able to
tell you this word here?
Why was I able to tell you not
only is it going to 0, but it's
going exponentially fast?
I'm telling you
extra information.
I'm telling you it always
goes exponentially fast.
You can identify it.
In other words, you'll see it.
And it will happen
every single time.
I'm just promising you
that it works that way.
And it's really for the same
reason that it works that way
here, that these are powers.
And what's going on over here
is there are, it's close to
powers with this a sub ns.
All right?
There's a long discussion
of radius of convergence
in many textbooks.
But really it's not necessary,
all right, for this purpose?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: How do you find R?
PROFESSOR: The question
was how do you find R?
Yes, so I just said, there's
a long discussion for how
you find the radius of
convergence in textbooks.
But we will not be
discussing that here.
And it won't be
necessary for you.
Because it will be obvious in
any given series what the R is.
It will always either
1 or infinite.
It will always work for
all x, or maybe it'll
stop at some point.
But it'll be very clear where
it stops, as it is for
the geometric series.
All right?
OK so now I need to give
you the basic facts, and
give you a few examples.
So why are we looking
at these series?
Well the answer is we're
looking at these series because
the role that they play is
exactly the reverse of
this equation here.
That is, and this is a theme
which I have tried to emphasize
throughout this course, you can
read equalities in
two directions.
Both are interesting,
typically.
You can think, I don't know
what the value of this is.
Here's a way of evaluating.
And in other words, the
right side is a formula
for the left side.
Or you can think of the left
side as being a formula
for the right side.
And the idea of series is that
they're flexible enough to
represent all of the functions
that we've encountered
in this course.
This is the tool which is very
much like the decimal
expansion which allows you to
represent numbers like
the square root of 2.
Now we're going to be
representing all the numbers,
all the functions that
we know, e to the x,
arctangent, sine, cosine.
All of those functions become
completely flexible, and
completely available to
us, and computationally
available to us directly.
So that's what this
is a tool for.
And it's just like decimal
expansions giving you handle
on all real numbers.
So here's how it works.
The rules for convergent
power series are just
like polynomials.
All of the manipulations that
you do for power series are
essentially the same
as for polynomials.
So what kinds of things do
we do with polynomials?
We add them.
We multiply them together.
We do substitutions.
Right?
We take one function
of another function.
We divide them.
OK.
And these are all really not
very surprising operations.
And we will be able to do
them with power series too.
The ones that are interesting,
really interesting for
calculus, are the last two.
We differentiate them,
and we integrate them.
And all of these operations
we'll be able to do for
power series as well.
So now let's explain the
high points of this.
Which is mainly just the
differentiation and
the integration part.
So if I take a series like this
and so forth, the formula for
it's derivative is just
like polynomials.
That's what I just said,
it's just like polynomials.
So the derivative of
the constant is 0.
The derivative of this
term is a sub 1.
This one is plus 2 a sub 2 x.
This one is 3a sub 3
x-squared, et cetera.
That's the formula.
Similarly if I integrate, well
there's an unknown constant
which I'm going to put
first rather than last.
Which corresponds sort of to
the a sub 0, term which is
going to get wiped out.
That a sub 0 term suddenly
becomes a sub 0 x.
And the anti-derivative of
this next term is a sub
1 x-squared over 2.
And the next term is a sub 2
x-cubed over 3, and so forth.
Yeah, question?
AUDIENCE: Is that a
series or a polynomial?
PROFESSOR: Is this a
Good question.
It's a polynomial if it ends.
If it goes on infinitely
far, then it's a series.
They look practically the
same, polynomials and series.
There's this little
dot, dot, dot here.
Is this a series
or a polynomial?
It's the same rule.
If it stops at a finite
stage, this one stops
at a finite stage.
If it goes on forever,
it goes on forever.
AUDIENCE: So I thought that the
series add up finite numbers.
You can add up terms
of x in series?
PROFESSOR: So an
interesting question.
So the question that was just
asked is I thought that a
series added up finite numbers.
You could add up x?
That was what you said, right?
OK now notice that I pulled
that off on you by changing the
letter a to the letter x at the
very beginning of this
commentary here.
This is a series.
For each individual value
of x, it's a number.
So in other words, it I plug in
here x equals 1/2, I'm going to
add 1 plus 1/2 plus 1/4 plus
1/8; and I'll get a
number which is 2.
And I'll plug in a number over
here, and I'll get a number.
On the other hand, I can do
this for each value of x.
So the interpretation of this
is that it's a function of x.
And similarly this
is a function of x.
It works when you plug in
the possible values x
between minus 1 and 1.
So there's really no
distinction there, just I
slipped it passed you.
These are functions of x.
And the notion of a power
series is this idea that you
put coefficients on a series,
but then you allow yourself
the flexibility to
stick powers here.
And that's exactly
what we're doing.
OK there are other kinds if
series where you stick other
interesting functions in here
like sines and cosines.
There are lots of other
series that people study.
And these are the
simplest ones.
And all those examples are
extremely helpful for
representing functions.
But we're only going to
do this example here.
All right, so here
are the two rules.
And now there's only one other
complication here which I have
to explain to you before giving
you a bunch of examples to show
you that this works
extremely well.
And the last thing that I have
to do for you is explain to
you something called
Taylor's formula.
Taylor's formula is the way you
get from the representations
that we're used to a functions,
to a representation in the
form of these coefficients.
When I gave you the function
e to the x, it didn't
look like a polynomial.
And we have to figure out which
of these guys it is, if it's
going to fall into
our category here.
And here's the formula.
I'll explain to you how
it works in a second.
So the formula is f of x, turns
out there's a formula in terms
of the derivatives of f.
Namely, you differentiate n
times, and you evaluate it
at 0, and you divide by n
factorial, and multiply
by x to the n.
So here's Taylor's formula.
This tells you what
the Taylor series is.
Now about half of our job for
the next few minutes is going
to be to give examples of this.
But let me just explain to
you why this has to be.
If you pick out this number
here, this is the a sub n, the
magic number a sub n here.
So let's just illustrate it.
If f of x happens to be a sub
zero plus a sub 1 x plus a sub
2 x-squared plus a sub 2
x-cubed plus dot, dot, dot.
And now I differentiate
it, right?
I get a sub 1 plus 2 sub a
2x plus 3 a sub 3 x If I
differentiate it another time,
I get 2 a sub 2, plus 3 times 2
a sub 3 x plus dot, dot, dot.
And now a third time, I get 3
times 2 a sub 3 plus et cetera.
So this next term is really
in disguise, 4 times
3 times 2 a sub 4x.
That's what really comes
down if I kept track of
the fourth term there.
So now here is my function.
But now you see if I plug
in x equals 0, I can
pick off the third term.
f triple prime of 0 is equal
to 3 times 2 times a sub 3.
Right, because all the rest
of those terms when I
plug in 0 are just 0.
Here's the formula.
And so the pattern
here is this.
And what's really going on here
is this is really 3 times
2 times 1 equals a sub 3.
And in general a sub n is equal
to f to the nth derivative
divided by n factorial.
And of course, n factorial, I
remind you, is n times n minus
1 times n minus 2,
all the way down.
Now there's one more
crazy convention
which is always used.
Which is that there's something
very strange here down at 0,
which is that 0 factorials
turns out, have to
be set equal to 1.
All right, so that's what
you do in order to make
this formula work out.
And that's one of the reasons
for this convention.
All right.
So my next goal is to
give you some examples.
And let's do a couple.
So here's, well you know, I'm
going to have to let you see
a few of them next time.
But let me just tell you
this one, which is by
far the most impressive.
So what happens with e to the
x, if a function of f of x is
e to the x, is that it's
derivative is also x to the x.
And its second derivative
is also e to the x.
And it just keeps
on going that way.
They're all the same.
So that means that these
numbers in Taylor's formula,
in the numerator, the nth
derivative is very
easy to evaluate.
It's just e to the x.
And if I evaluated at x
equals 0, I just get 1.
So all of those
numerators are 1.
So the formula here, is the sum
n equals 0 to infinite, of 1
divided by n factorial
x to the n.
In particular, we now have
an honest formula for
e to the first power.
Which is just e.
Which if I plug it in,
x equals 1, I get 1.
This is the n equals
0 term plus 1.
This is the n equals 1 term
plus 1 over 2 factorial plus
1 over 3 factorial plus
1 over 4 factorial.
Right?
So this is our first
honest formula for e.
And also, this is
how you compute the
exponential function.
Finally if you take a function
like sine x, what you'll
discover is that we can
complete the sort of strange
business that we did at the
beginning of the course-- or
cosine x-- where we took the
linear and quadratic
approximations.
Now we're going to get complete
formulas for these functions.
Sine x turns out to be equal to
x minus x-cubed over 3
factorial plus x to the 5th
over 5 factorial minus x to the
7th over 7 factorial,
et cetera.
And cosine x is equal to 1,
minus x-squared over 2
factorial-- that's the same as
this 2 here-- plus x to the 4th
over 4 factorial minus x to the
6th over 6 factorial,
plus et cetera.
Now these may feel like they're
hard to memorize because I've
just pulled them out of a hat.
I do expect you to know them.
They're actually extremely
similar formulas.
The exponential here just has
this collection of factorials.
The sine is all the odd powers
with alternating sines.
And the cosine is all the even
powers with alternating sines.
So all three of them form
part of the same family.
So this will actually make it
easier for you to remember,
rather than harder.
And so with that, I'll leave
the practice on differentiation
for next time.
And good luck, everybody.
I'll talk to individually.