The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or to view
additional material from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Right now, we're
finishing up with the first
unit, and I'd like to continue
in this lecture, lecture seven,
with some final remarks
about exponents.
So what I'd like to do is just
review something that I did
quickly last time, and make a
few philosophical
remarks about it.
I think that the steps involved
were maybe a little tricky, and
so I'd like to go through
it one more time.
Remember, that we were
talking about this
number ak, which is (1
1/k)^k.
And what we showed was that
the limit as k goes to
infinity of ak was e.
So the first thing that I'd
like to do is just explain the
proof a little bit more clearly
than I did last time with fewer
symbols, or at least with this
abbreviation of the symbol
here, to show you what
we actually did.
So I'll just remind you of what
we did last time, and the first
observation was to check,
rather than the limit of
this function, but to
take the ln first.
And this is typically what's
done when you have an
exponential, when you
have an exponent.
And what we found was that
the limit here was 1
as k goes to infinity.
So last time, this
is what we did.
And I just wanted to be
careful and show you exactly
what the next step is.
If you exponentiate this fact;
you take e to this power,
that's going to tend to
e ^ 1, which is just e.
And then, we just observe
that this is the same as ak.
So the basic ingredient
here is that e ^ ln a = a.
That's because the ln function
is the inverse of the
exponential function.
Yes, question?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: So the question was,
wouldn't the log of this be 0
because ak is tending to 1.
But ak isn't tending to 1.
Who said it was?
If you take the logarithm,
which is what we did last
time, logarithm of ak is
indeed k(ln(1 + 1/k)).
That does not tend to 0.
This part of it tends to 0, and
this part tends to infinity.
And they balance each
other, 0 times infinity.
We don't really know yet from
this expression, in fact we did
some cleverness with limits and
derivatives, to figure
out this limit.
It was a very subtle thing.
It turned out to be 1.
All right?
Now, the thing that I'd like to
say - I'm sorry I'm going to
erase this aside here - but you
need to go back to your notes
and remember that this is
what we did last time.
Because I want to have room for
the next comment that I want to
make on this little
blackboard here.
What we just derived was this
property here, but I made a
claim yesterday, and I just
want to emphasize it again so
that we realized what it
is that we're doing.
I looked at this backwards.
One way you can think of this
is we're evaluating this
limit and getting an answer.
But all equalities can be
read both directions.
And we can write it the other
way: e = the limit, as k goes
to infinity, of this
expression here.
So that's just the same thing.
And if we read it backwards,
what we're saying is that this
limit is a formula for e.
So this is very typical
of mathematics.
You want to always reverse your
perspective all the time.
Equations work both ways, and
in this case, we have two
different things here.
This e was what we defined as
the base, which when you graph
e ^ x, you get slope 1 at 0.
And then it turns out to be
equal to this limit, which we
can calculate numerically.
If you do this on your
calculators, you, of course,
will have a way of programming
in this number and
evaluating it for each k.
And you'll have another button
available to evaluate this one.
So another way of saying it is
it that there's a relationship
between these two things.
And all of Calculus is a matter
of getting these relationships.
So we can look at these things
in several different ways.
And indeed, that's what we're
going to be doing at least at
the end of today in talking
about derivatives.
A lot of times when we talk
about derivative, we're trying
to look at them from several
perspectives at once.
Okay, so I have to keep on
going with exponents, because
I have one loose end.
One loose end that I
did not cover yet.
There's one very important
formula that's left, and it's
the derivative of the powers.
We actually didn't do this
- well we did it for
rational numbers r.
So this is the formula here.
But now we're going to check
this for all real numbers, r.
So including all the
irrational ones as well.
This is also good practice
for using base e and using
logarithmic differentiation.
So let me do this by our two
methods that we can use to
handle exponential
type problems.
So method one was base e.
So if I just rewrite this base
e again, that's just this
formula over here. x ^ r =
(e^ln x)^r, which
is e ^ r ln x.
Okay, so now I can
differentiate this.
So I get that d / dx (x^r), now
I'm going to use prime
notation, because I don't want
to keep on writing that d /
dx here; e ^ (r ln x)'.
And now, what I can do is
I can use the chain rule.
The chain rule says that it's
the derivative of a this times
the derivative of the function.
So the derivative of the
exponential is just itself.
And the derivative of this
guy here, well I'll write
it out once, is (r ln x)'.
So what's that equal to?
Well, each of the r ln
x's is just x ^ r.
And this derivative here is...
Well the derivative of r is 0.
This is a constant.
It just factors out.
And ln x now the derivative...
What's the derivative of ln x?
1 / x, so this is going
to be times r / x.
And now, we rewrite it in the
customary form, which is r, we
put the r in front,
x ^ (r - 1).
Ok?
So I just derived the
formula for you.
And it didn't matter whether r
was rational or irrational,
it's the same proof.
Okay so now I have to show you
how method two works as well.
So let's do method two,
which we called logarithmic
differentiation.
And so here I'll use a
symbol, say u for x ^ r, and
I'll take its logarithm.
That's r ln x.
And now I differentiate it.
I'll leave that in the middle,
because I want to remember
the key property of
logarithmic differention.
But first I'll
differentiate it.
Later on, what I'm going
to use is that this
is the same as u'/u.
This is one way of evaluating
a logarithmic derivative.
And then the other is to
differentiate the explicit
function that we
have over here.
And that is just,
as we said, r /x.
So now, I multiply through,
and I get u' = u(r/x), which
is just x^r(r/x), which is
just what we did before.
It's r x ^ (r - 1).
Again, you can now see by
comparing these two pieces
of arithmetic that they're
basically the same.
Pretty much every time you
convert to base c or you do
logarithmic differentiation,
it'll amount to the same
thing, provided you
don't get mixed up.
You generally have to
introduce a new symbol here.
On the other hand, you're
dealing with exponents there.
It's worth it to know
both points of view.
All right, so now I want to
make one last remark before
we finish with exponents.
And, I'll try to sell this to
you in a lot of ways as the
court goes on, but one thing
that I want to try to
emphasize is that the natural
logarithm really is natural.
So, I claim that the
natural log is natural.
And the example that we're
going to use for this
illustration is economics.
Okay?
So let me explain to why the
natural log is the one that's
natural for economics.
If you are imagining the price
of a stock that you own goes
down by a dollar, that's a
totally meaningless statement.
It depends on a lot of things.
In particular, it depends on
whether the original price
was a dollar or 100 dollars.
So there's not much meaning
to these absolute numbers.
It's always the
ratios that matter.
So, for example, I just looked
up an hour ago, the London
Exchange close, and it was down
27.9, which as I said, is
pretty meaningless unless
you know what the actual
total of this index is.
It turns out it was 6,432.
So the change in the price,
divided by the price, which
in this case is 27.9 /
6,432, is what matters.
And, in this case, it
happens to be 0.43%.
All right?
That's what happened today.
And similarly, if you take the
infinitessimal of this, people
think of days as being
relatively small increments
when you're investing in a
stock, you would be interested
in the infinitessimal
sense, p'/p.
The derivative of p / p.
That's just (ln p)'.
So this is the - let me put a
little box around it - the
formula of logarithmic
differentiation.
But let me just emphasize that
it has an actual significance,
and it's the one that's used by
economists and people who
are modeling prices of
things all the time.
They never use absolute prices
when there are large swings.
They always use the
log of the price.
And there's no point in using
log base 10, or log base 2.
Those give you junk.
They give you an extra
factor of log 2.
It's the natural log that's
the obvious one to use.
It's completely straightforward
that this is a simpler
expression than using log base
10 and having a factor of
natural log of 10 there, which
would just mess everything up.
All right, so this is
just one illustration.
Anything that has to do
with ratios is going to
encounter logarithms.
All right, so that's
pretty much it.
That's all I want to
say for now anyway.
There's lots more to say, but
we'll be saying it when we do
applications of derivatives
in the second unit.
So now, what I'd like to
do is to start a review.
I'm just going to run through
what we did in this unit.
I'll tell you approximately
what I expect from you on the
test that's coming up tomorrow.
And, well, so let's get
started with that.
So this is a review
of Unit One.
And I'm just going to put on
the board all of the things
that you need to think about,
anyway, keep in your head.
And there what are
called general formulas
for derivatives.
And then there are
the specific ones.
And let me just remind you what
the general formulas are.
There's what you do to
differentiate a sum, a multiple
of a function, the product
rule, the quotient rule.
Those are several
general formulas.
And then there's one more,
which is the chain rule, which
I'm going to say just a
little bit more about.
So the derivative of a function
of a function is the derivative
of the function times the
derivative of the
other function.
So here, I've
abbreviated u = u(x).
Right, so this is one of
two ways of writing it.
The other way is also one that
you can keep in mind and you
might find easier to remember.
It's probably a good idea
to remember both formulas.
And then the last type of
general formula that we did
was implicit differentiation.
Okay?
So when you do implicit
differentiation, you have an
equation and you don't try to
solve for the unknown function.
You just put it in its simplest
form and you differentiate.
So, we actually did this, in
particular, for inverses.
That was a very, very key
method for calculating the
inverses of functions.
And it's also true that
logarithmic differentiation
is of this type.
This is a transformation.
We're differentiating
something else.
We're transforming the equation
by taking its logarithm
and then differentiating.
Ok, so there are a number of
different ways this is applied.
It can also be applied, anyway,
these are two of them.
So maybe in parenthesis.
These are just examples.
All right.
I'll try to give examples
of at least a few of
these rules later.
So now, the specific functions
that you know how to
differentiate: well you know
how to differentiate now x ^ r
thanks to what I just did.
We have the sine and the cosine
functions, which you're
responsible for knowing what
their derivatives are.
And then other trig functions
like tan and secant.
We generally don't bother with
cosecants and cotangents,
because everything can be
expressed in terms
of these anyway.
Actually, you can really
express everything in terms
of sines and cosines.
But what you'll find is that
it's much more convenient to
remember the derivatives
of these as well.
So memorize all of these.
All right, and then
we had e^x and ln x.
And we had the inverses
of the trig functions.
These were the two that we did:
the arctangent and the arcsin.
So those are the ones
you're responsible for.
You should have enough time,
anyway, to work out anything
else, if you know these.
All right, so basically the
idea is you have a bunch
of special formulas.
You have a bunch of
general formulas.
You put them together,
and you can generate
pretty much anything.
Okay, so let's do a few
examples before going
on with the review.
Okay, so I do want to do a few
examples in sort of increasing
level of difficulty and how you
would combine these
things together.
So first of all, you should
remember that if you
differentiate the secant
function, that's just - oh I
just realized that I wanted
to say something else
before - so forget that.
We'll do that in a second.
I wanted to make some
general remarks.
So there's one rule that you
discussed in my absence,
which is the chain rule.
And I do want to make just a
couple of remarks about the
chain rule now to remind you
of what it is, and also to
present some consequences.
So, a little bit of extra
on the chain rule.
The first thing that I want
say is that we didn't really
fully explain why it's true.
And I do want to just explain
it by example, okay?
So imagine that you have a
function which is, say, 10x
b.
All right?
So y = 10x
b.
Then obviously, y is changing
10 times as fast as b, right?
The issue is this number
here, dy / dx = 10.
And now if x is a function of
something, say t, shifted
by some other constant
here, then dx/dt = 5.
Now all the chain rule is
saying is that if y is going 10
times as fast as t, I'm sorry
as x, and x is going 5 times as
fast as t, then y is going
50 times as fast as t.
And algebraically, all this
means is if I plug in and
substitute, which is what the
composition of the two
functions amounts to, 10(5t +
a) + b and I multiply
it out, I get 50t
10a b.
Now these terms don't matter.
The constant terms
don't matter.
The rate is 50.
And so the consequence, if we
put them together, is that
dy/dt = 10*5, which is 50.
All right, so this is
in a nutshell why the
chain rule works.
And why these rates multiply.
The second thing that I wanted
to say about the chain rule is
that it has a few consequences
that make some of the other
rules a little easier to
remember or possibly to avoid.
The messiest rule in my humble
opinion is the quotient
rule, which is kind of
a nuisance to remember.
So let me just remind you, if
you take just the reciprocal
of a function, and you
differentiate it, there's
another way of looking at this.
And it's actually the way that
I use, so I want to encourage
you to think about
it this way too.
This is the same as
(v^-1)' power .
And now instead of using the
quotient rule, which we
could've used, we can use the
chain rule here with the
power -1, which works
by the power law.
So what is this equal to?
This is equal to (-v^-2)(v').
So here, I've applied the
chain rule rather than
the quotient rule.
And similarly, suppose
I wanted to derive the
full quotient rule.
Well, now this may or
may not be easier.
But this is one way of
remembering what's going on.
If you convert it to (uv^-1)
and you differentiate
that, now I can use the
product rule on this.
Of course, I have to
use the chain rule and
this rule as well.
So what do I get?
I get u' , the inverse,
u, and then I have to
differentiate the v inverse.
That's the formula
right up here.
That's (-v^-2)(v').
So that's one way of doing it.
This actually explains the
funny minus sign when you
differentiate v in the formula.
The other formula, the other
way that we did it, was by
putting this over a
common denominator.
The common denominator was v^2.
This comes from this v ^ -2.
And then the second
term is - u v'.
And the first term, we have to
multiply by an extra factor of
v, because we have a v^2
in the denominator.
So it's u'v.
All right, so this is the
quotient rule as we wrote it
down in lecture, and this is
just another way of remembering
it or deriving it without
remembering it, if you just
remember the chain rule
and the product rule.
Okay, so you'll find that in
many contexts, it's easier
to do one or the other.
Okay, so now i'm ready to
differentiate the secant
and a few such functions.
So we'll do some
examples here here.
So here's the secant function,
and I want to use that formula
up there for the reciprocal.
This is the way I think of it.
This is the cos x ^ -1.
And so, the formula
here is just what?
It's just - (cos
x) ^ -2 (-sin x).
So now this is usually written
in a different fashion, so
that's why I'm doing this
for a reason actually.
Which is although there are
several formulas for things,
with trig functions, there
are usually five ways
of writing something.
So I'm writing this one down so
that you know what the standard
way of presenting it is.
So what happens here is
that we have two minus
signs cancelling.
And we get sin x / cos^2 x.
That's a perfectly acceptable
answer, but there's a customary
way in which is written.
It's written (1 / cos
x) (sin x / cos x).
And then we get rid of the
denominators by rewriting
it in terms of secant and
tangent, so sec x tan x.
So this is the form that's
generally used when
you see these formulas
written in textbooks.
And so you know, you need to
watch out, because if you ever
want to use this kind of
Calculus, you'll have not
be put off by all the
secants and tangents.
All right, so getting slightly
more complicated, how about if
we differentiate ln(sec x)?
If you differentiate the
natural log, that's just going
to be (sec x)' / sec x.
And plugging in the formula
that we had before, that's
(sec x) (tan x) / sec
x, which is tan x.
So this one also has
a very nice form.
And you might say that this is
kind of an ugly function, but
the strange thing is that the
natural log was invented before
the exponential by a guy named
Napier, exactly in order to
evaluate functions like this.
These are the functions
that people cared about
a lot, because they were
used in navigation.
You wanted to multiply
sines and cosines together
to do navigation.
And the multiplication he
encoded using a logarithm.
So these were invented
long before people even
knew about exponents.
And it was a surprise,
actually, that it was
connected to exponents.
So the natural log was invented
before the log base 10 and
everything else, exactly
for this kind of purpose.
Anyway, so this is a nice
function, which was very
important, so that your ships
wouldn't crash into the reef.
Okay, let's continue here.
So there's another kind
of function that I want
to discuss with you.
And these are the kinds in
which there's a choice as to
which of these rules to apply.
And I'll just give a couple
of examples of that.
There usually is a better
and a worse way, so let
me illustrate that.
Okay, yet another example.
I hope you've seen
some of these before.
Say (x ^ 10
+ 8x) ^ 6.
So it's a little bit more
complicated than what we had
before, because there were
several more symbols here.
So what should we
do at this point?
There's one choice which I
claim is a bad idea, and
that is to expand this
out to the 6th power.
That's a bad idea,
because it's very long.
And then your answer
will also be very long.
It will fill the entire
exam paper, for instance.
Yeah?
STUDENT: Can you use
the chain rule?
PROFESSOR: Chain rule.
That's it.
We use the chain rule.
So fortunately, this is
relatively easy using
the chain rule.
We just think of this box
as being the function.
And we take 6 times this guy to
the 5th, times the derivative
of this guy, which is 10x ^ 9
8.
And this is, feeling this
in, it's x^10 + 8x.
And that's it.
That's all you need to do
differentiate things like this.
The chain rule is
very effective.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: That's
a good question.
So I'm not really willing to
answer too many questions about
what's going to be on the exam.
But the question that was just
asked is exactly the kind of
question I'm very
happy to answer.
Ok the question was, in what
form is an acceptable answer?
Now in real life, that is a
really serious question.
When you ask a computer a
question and it gives you
500 million sheets of
printout, it's useless.
And you really care what form
answers are in, and indeed,
somebody might really care what
this thing to the 6th power is,
and then you would be forced
to discuss things in terms of
that other functional form.
For the purposes of this
exam, this is okay form.
And, in fact, any correct
form is an okay form.
I recommend strongly that you
not try to simplify things
unless we tell you to.
Sometimes it will be to your
advantage to simplify things.
Sometimes we'll say simplify.
It takes a good deal of
experience to know when
it's really worth it to
simplify expressions.
Yes?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Right, so
turning to this example.
The question is what
is this derivative?
And here's an answer.
That's the end of the problem.
This is a more customary form.
But this is answer is ok.
Same issue.
That's exactly the point.
Yes?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: The question is, do
you have to show the work?
Do you have to show the work?
Well if I ask you what is d/dx
of sec x, then if you wrote
down this answer or you wrote
down this answer showing no
work, that would be acceptable.
If the question was derive the
formula for this from the
formula for the derivative of
the cosine or something like
that, then it would
not be acceptable.
You'd have to carry
out this arithmetic.
So, in other words, typically
this will come up, for
instance, in various contexts.
You just basically have
to follow directions.
Yes?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: The next question
is, are you expected to be able
to prove what the derivative
of the sine function is?
The short answer
to that is yes.
But I will be getting to that
when I discuss the rest
of the material here.
We're almost there.
Okay, so let me just
finish these examples
with one last one.
And then we'll talk about this
question of things like the
derivative of the sine
function, and deriving it.
So the last example that I'd
like to write down is the one
that I promised you in the
first lecture, namely to
differentiate e ^ x arctan x.
Basically you're supposed to
be able to differentiate
any function.
So this is the one that we
mentioned at the beginning.
So here it is.
Let's do it.
So what is it?
Well, it's just equal to -
I have to differentiate.
I have to use the chain rule -
it's equal to the exponential
times the derivative of
this expression here.
That's the chain rule.
That's the first step.
And now I have to apply
the product rule here.
So I have e ^ x arctan x.
And I differentiate the first
factor, so I get arctan x.
Add to it what happens when
I differentiate the second
factor, leaving alone the x.
So that's x / 1
x^2.
And that's it.
That's the end of the problem.
It wasn't that hard.
Of course, it requires you to
remember all of the rules, and
a lot of formulas
underlying them.
So that's consistent with
what I just told you.
I told you that you
wanted to know this.
I told you that you needed
to know this product rule,
and that you needed to
know the chain rule.
And I guess there was one more
thing, the derivative of e to
the x came into play there.
So of these formulas, we
used four of them in
this one calculation.
Okay, so now what other things
did we talk about in Unit One?
So the main other thing that
we talked about was the
definition of a derivative.
And also there was sort of a
goal which was to get to the
meaning of the derivative.
So these are things - so we had
a couple of ways of looking at
it, or at least a couple
that I'm going to
emphasize right now.
But first, let me remind
you what the formula is.
The derivative is the limit as
delta x goes to 0 of (f(x
delta x) - f(x)) / delta x.
So that's it, and this is
certainly going to be
a central focus here.
And you want to be able to
recognize this formula
in a number of ways.
So, how do we use this?
Well one thing we did was
we calculated a bunch of
these rates of change.
In fact, more or less,
they're the ones which are
written right over here.
This list of functions here.
Now, which ones did we start
out with just straight
from the definition here?
Which of these things?
There were a whole
bunch of them.
So we started out with
a function 1 / x.
We did x^n.
We did sine x.
We did cosine x.
Now there was a little
bit of subtlety with
sine x and cosine x.
We got them using
something else.
We didn't quite get
them all the way.
We got them using
the case x = 0.
We got them from the derivative
at x = 0, we got the formulas
for the derivatives
of sine and cosine.
But that was an argument which
involved plug in sine x
delta x, and running through.
So that's one example.
We also did a ^ x.
And that may be it.
Oh yeah, I think
that's about it.
That may be about it.
No.
It isn't.
Ok, so let me make a connection
here which you probably haven't
yet made, which is that
we did it for (u v)'.
And we also did
it for (u / v)'.
So sorry, I shouldn't write
primes, because that's
not consistent.
I differentiated the product;
I differentiated the
quotient using the
same delta x notation.
I guess I forgot that because I
wasn't there when it happened.
So look, these are the
ones that you do by this.
And, of course, you might have
to reduce them to other things.
These involve using
something else.
This one involves using the
slope of this function at 0,
just the way the sine
and the cosine did.
This one involves the
slopes of the individual
functions, u and v.
And this one also
involves the individual.
So, in other words, it doesn't
get you all the way through to
the end, but it's expressed in
terms of something simpler
in each of these cases.
And I could go on.
We didn't do these in class,
but you're certainly... e ^ x
is a perfectly okay one
on one of the exams.
We ask you for 1 / x^2.
In other words, I'm not
claiming that it's going to
be one on this list, but
it certainly can be
any one of these.
But we're not going to ask you
to go all the way through to
the beginning in
these formulas.
There are also some fundamental
limits that I certainly
want you to know about.
And these you can
derive in reverse.
So I will describe that now.
So let me also emphasize the
following thing: I want to
read this backwards now.
This is the theme from the very
beginning of this lecture.
Namely, if you're given
the function f, you can
figure out its derivative
by its formula here.
That is the formula for
this in terms of what's
on the right hand side.
On the other hand, you can
also use the formula in that
direction, and if you know the
slope of something, you can
figure out what the limit is.
For example, I'll use
the letter x here, even
though it's cheating.
Maybe I'll call it delta x
so it's clearer to you.
Maybe I'll call it u.
Suppose you look at
this limit here.
Well, I claim that you should
recognize that is the
derivative with respect to u
of the function e^u at u =
0, which of course
we know to be 1.
So this is reading this
formula in reverse.
It's recognizing that one of
these limits - let me rewrite
this again here - one of these
so-called difference quotient
limits is a derivative.
And since we know a formula
for that derivative,
we can evaluate it.
And lastly, there's one
other type of thing which
I think you should know.
These are the ones you do
with difference quotients.
There are also other
formulas that you want
to be able to drive.
You want to be able to
derive formulas by
implicit differentiation.
In other words, the basic idea
is to take whatever equation
you've got and simplify it as
much as possible, without
insisting that you solve for y.
That's not necessarily the
most appropriate way to
get the rate of change.
The much simpler
formula is sin y = x.
And that one is easier to
differentiate implicitly.
So I should say, do
this kind of thing.
So that's, if you like,
a typical derivation
that you might see.
And then there's one last type
of problem that you'll face,
and it's the other thing
that I claim we discussed.
And it goes all the way
back to the first lecture.
So the last thing that we'll be
talking about is tangent lines.
All right?
The geometric point of
view of a derivative.
And we'll be doing more of
this in next the unit.
So first of all, you'll be
expected to be able to
compute the tangent line.
That's often fairly
straightforward.
And the second thing is to
graph y' , the derivative
of a function.
And the third thing, which I'm
going to throw in here, because
I regard it in a sort of
geometric vein, although it's
got an analytical aspect to it.
So this is a picture.
This is a computation.
And if you combine the
two together, you
get something else.
And so this is to recognize
differentiable functions.
Alright, so how do you do this?
Well, we really only have
one way of doing it.
We're going to check the
left and right tangents.
They must be equal.
So again, this is a property
that you should be familiar
with from some of
your exercises.
And the idea is simply, that if
the tangent line exists, it's
the same from the right
and from the left.
Ok, now I'm going to just do
one example here from this sort
of qualitative sketching skill
to give you an example here.
And what I'm going to do is
I'm going to draw a graph
of a function like this.
And what I want to do
underneath is draw the
graph of the derivative.
So this is the function y =
f(x), and here I'm going to
draw the graph of the function
y = f'(x) right underneath it.
So now, let's think about what
it's supposed to look like.
And the one step that you need
to make in order to do this, is
to draw a few tangent lines.
I'm just going to
draw one down here.
And I'm going to
draw one up here.
Now, the tangent lines here -
noticed that the slope of these
tangent lines are all positive.
So everything I draw down
here is going to be
above the x-axis.
Furthermore,, as I go further
to the left, they get
steeper and steeper.
So they're getting
higher and higher.
So the function is
coming down like this.
It starts up there.
Maybe I'll draw it in green to
illustrate the graph here.
So that's this function here.
As we get farther out, it's
getting flatter and flatter.
So it's leveling off, but
above the axis like that.
So one of the things to
emphasize is, you should not
expect the derivative to
look like the function.
It's totally different.
It's keeping track at each
point of its tangent line.
On the other hand, you should
get some kind of physical feel
for it, and we'll be practicing
this more in the next unit.
So let me give you an
example of a function
which does exactly this.
And it's the function y = ln x.
If you differentiate it,
you get y' = 1 / x.
And this plot above is, roughly
speaking, the logarithm.
And this plot underneath
is the function 1 / x.
We still have time
for one question.
And so, fire away.
Yes?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: The question is,
can you show how you derive
the inverse tangent of x.
So that's in a lecture.
I'm happy to do it right
now, but it's going to make
me a whole two minutes.
So, here's how you do
it. y = arctan x.
And now this is hopeless
to differentiate, so I
rewrite it as tan y = x.
And now I have to
differentiate that.
So when I differentiate it, I
get the derivative of tan y
with respect to x, so
with respect to y.
That's (1 / 1
y^2 )y'.
So this is a hard step.
That's the chain rule.
And on the left side I get 1.
So I'm doing this super
fast because we have
thirty seconds left.
But this is the hard
step right here.
And it needs for you to know
that d/dy (tan y) = sec^2 y.
So here's the identity.
So you need have known
this in advance.
And that's the input
into this equation.
So now, what we have is that
y' = 1 / sec^2 y, which is
the same thing as cos^2 y.
Now, the last bit of the
problem is to rewrite
this in terms of x.
And that you have to do
with a right triangle.
If this is x and this is 1,
then the angle is y, because
the tangent of y is x.
So this expresses the fact
that the tangent of y is x.
And then the hypoteneuse
is the square root of 1
x^2.
And so the cosine is
1 divided by that.
So this thing is 1 divided
by the square root of 1
x^2, the quantity squared.
So, and then the last little
bit here, since I'm racing
along, is that it's 1 / 1
+ x^2, squared, which I
incorrectly wrote over here.
OK, so good luck on the text.
See you tomorrow.