DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
So in this problem, we're
considering a function f of
three variables f of x, y, z,
and it's differentiable, and
we're not told a
formula for f.
We just know that it's
differential at this point P,
which is 1 minus 1, 1, and we're
told that the gradient
of f at that point is this
particular vector 2i plus j
minus 3k at that point P. So all
we understand about f is
how it looks around
the point P.
Now, we also have this
relation between the
variables, so x, y and
z aren't unrelated.
They're related by this
constraint that z is x squared
plus y plus 1.
So with this information, we
want to compute the gradient
of a new function g, and the new
function g is a function
of two variables, and this
function g is obtained from f
by just plugging in our
relation for y.
So we can use our constraint to
solve for y, and then this
function g is just f with
that constraint applied.
And what we really want to
do is we want to find the
gradient of g at
the point 1, 1.
So notice that when g is equal
to 1, 1, that means that--
sorry, when the input of g is 1,
1, that means the input of
f is P. OK?
So why don't you pause
the video and work
this out for yourself.
Check back with me and we'll
work it out together.
OK, welcome back.
So let's get started.
So this problem may not look
like it's a problem about
partial derivatives with
constraints, but that's what
it's really going to boil down
to, which is to say that when
we want to compute--
so when we want to answer this
question by computing the
gradient, the first thing we're
going to want to do is
compute the partial derivative
of g and its variable x.
And from the way we set up the
problem, that's just the same
as computing the partial
derivative of f with respect
to x and keeping z constant.
Now, remember, when we do
partial derivatives with
constraints, what's important
about the
notation is what's missing.
The variable y is missing, and
that's because we are going to
use the constraint to get rid of
it, and that's exactly how
we define g, so this is
the key observation.
So computing the gradient of g
is just going to be computing
these partial derivatives
with constraints.
So we'll do that in a moment,
and I'll also just write that
the partial derivative of g in
the z-direction is partial f
partial z, now keeping
x constrained.
All right, so we need to
compute these partial
derivatives with constraints.
And so you remember
how this goes.
The way that I prefer to do this
is to compute the total
differentials.
So let's compute over here.
The total differential df is--
the total differential of f is
just the partials of f in the
x-direction, f in the
y-direction, f in the
z-direction, and each of these
is multiplied by the
corresponding differential.
And we don't know f, so we
can't compute the partial
derivatives of it in general,
but we do know these partial
derivatives at this point.
And so in the problem, we were
given that this is 2dx
plus dy minus 3dz.
So this is just using the fact
that the gradient of f we were
given is 2, 1 minus 3, OK?
So that's the total differential
of f, and now we
have this constraint.
And remember, when we do these
partial derivatives with
constraints, the trick is to
take the differential of the
constraint.
So we had this equation z equals
x squared plus y plus
1, and what we need to do is
take its differential.
So we have dz is
2x dx plus dy.
So that's our constraint.
Now here we have this variable
x, but we're not varying x in
this problem.
We're only focused on the
point P, and at the
point P, x is 1.
So, in fact, dz is just
2dx plus dy, OK?
So now what we need to do is
we need to combine the
constraint equation and the
total differential for f into
one equation, and so this is
just linear algebra now.
So I'll just come over here.
So we can rewrite our total
differential for the
constraint as saying that dy is
equal to dz minus 2dx, and
then we can plug that
back into our total
differential for f.
And so we get that df is
equal to 2dx plus--
now I plug in dy here--
so dz minus 2dx, and then
finally, minus 3dz.
So altogether, I get a
minus 2dz, because
this and this cancel.
OK.
We get a minus 2dz.
So what does that tell us
about the gradient?
So remember that the
differential now of g and its
variables is partial
g partial x dx plus
partial g partial z dz.
And remember, the trick about
partial derivatives and their
relation to total differentials
is that the
partial derivative is just
this coefficient.
So the fact that we computed
df and we found that it was
minus 2dz, that tells
us that dg--
so the thing that we need to
use is that g, remember, is
just the specialization of f.
So dg is equal to df in this
case, because g is just a
special case of f with
constraints.
So when we computed df here, we
were imposing exactly the
constraints that we used to
define dg, and so what this
tells us is that we can just
compare the coefficients here
and so our gradient
is 0 minus 2.
So the 0 is because there is no
dependence anymore on x at
this point.
There wasn't a dx term.
There could have been
and there wasn't.
And the minus 2 is because
that's the dependence on z.
OK, so this is a bit
complicated, so why don't we
review what we did.
So going back over to the
problem statement, we first
needed to realize that saying
that g was a special case of f
where we use our constraints
to solve for y, that's what
put us in the context of
problems with constraints.
So the fact that the dependence
on y was so simple
that we could just use
the constraint.
OK.
So then, what that allowed us to
do is it allowed us to say
that the partial derivative of
g in the x-direction is just
the partial derivative in the
x-direction subject to the
constraint, and that's
what we did here.
And so then, the next steps that
we did are the same steps
that we would always do to
compute partial derivatives
with constraints, and so we
finally got a relationship
that said that, subject to these
constraints, df is equal
to minus 2dz.
And the point is that g is just
the function f with those
constraints imposed, and so dg
and df are the same, and so,
in particular, dg
is minus 2dz.
And then, we remember that you
can always read off partial
derivatives from the
total differential.
They're just the coefficients.
And so in the end, we got that
the gradient was 0 minus 2.
And I think I'll leave
it at that.