JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
You've been learning in lecture
about matrices and
their various applications, and
one of them is to solving
systems of linear equations.
So I have here a system
of three linear
equations for you.
2x plus cz equals 4, x minus y
plus 2z equals pi, and x minus
2y plus 2z equals minus 12.
So what I'd like you to
do is the following.
Find the value of c--
or all values of c--
for which, first of all, there's
a unique solution to
this system.
Second of all, for which the
corresponding homogeneous
system has a unique solution.
So remember that the
corresponding homogeneous
system is the system where you
just replace these constants
on the right by 0.
So it's a very similar-looking
system.
The left-hand sides are all the
same, but the right-hand
sides are replaced with 0.
So you want to find the value of
c for which this system has
a unique solution, the value
of c for which the
corresponding homogeneous system
has a unique solution,
and also the values of c for
which the corresponding
homogeneous system has
infinitely many solutions.
Note that I'm not asking you
to solve this system of
equations, although you're
welcome to do so if you like.
Although, of course, whether you
can or not might depend on
the value of c.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a little while to
work out the solutions to these
three questions, come
back, and we can work
it out together.
So hopefully you have some
luck working out these
problems. Let's start working
through them together.
So I'm actually going to
take parts a and b
together at the same time.
And the reason that I'm going
to do that is that one thing
you've learned is that a system
has a unique solution
for, on the right-hand
side-- sorry--
a system has a unique solution,
like this, a square
system of linear equations has
a unique solution if and only
if it has a unique solution
regardless of what the
right-hand side is.
So in particular, the answer to
a and the answer to b are
exactly the same.
So values of c for which this
system has a unique solution
are exactly the same as values
of c for which the homogeneous
system has a unique solution.
Now the solutions will be
different, of course.
But the value of c--
or the value of c--
that make it solvable uniquely,
make it solvable
uniquely for all right-hand
sides.
And so which values
of c are those?
Well, those are the values of
c for which the coefficient
matrix on the left-hand
side is invertible.
So if the coefficient matrix
on the left-hand side is
invertible, then we can solve
this system and we get a
unique solution.
If it's not invertible, then
either we can't solve this
system-- like there
are no solutions--
or we can solve this system,
but there are
infinitely many solutions.
So in both questions a and b,
we're asking for the value of
c for which the coefficient
matrix of the left-hand side
is invertible, and that
will be when we
have a unique solution.
So how do we know when a
matrix is invertible?
Well, let's write down what the
matrix is first of all.
So this matrix M that we're
after is equal to the
matrix 2, 0, c.
1, minus 1, 2.
1, minus 2, 2.
So this is the coefficient
matrix M of that system, and
we want to know for which values
of c is it invertible.
Well, when is a matrix
invertible?
A matrix is invertible-- square
matrix is invertible--
precisely when it has non-zero
determinant.
So we just need to look at the
determinant of this matrix.
So you've learned how to
compute determinants of
matrices, I think.
So let's, in this case, we have
the det M. So it's a sum
or difference of six different
terms, and you could get it,
for example, by the Laplace
expansion if you wanted to.
So I'm just going to write out
what the six terms are.
So it's 2 times minus 1 times
2, plus 0 times 2 times 1,
plus c times 1 times minus 2,
minus c times minus 1 times 1,
minus 2 times minus 2 times 2,
minus 0 times 1 times 2.
So this is the determinant
of this matrix.
You can get it either just by
remembering which terms are
which and which get a plus sign
and which get a minus
sign, or by doing the Laplace
expansion, or by whatever
other tricks you might
happen to know.
So now we need to know whether
or not this determinant is 0.
So let's work out
what this is.
So this is-- let me start
simplifying it.
So this is minus 4
plus 0 minus 2c--
this is minus minus c--
so plus c--
this is minus minus 8--
so plus 8, which is equal
to 4 minus c.
So the determinant-- right, two
of those terms are 0, and
so I just get to
leave them out.
So the determinant of this
matrix is 4 minus c.
And what we're interested
in is when this
determinant is non-zero.
So in particular, for c not
equal to 0-- sorry, for c not
equal to 4, when c is not 4--
the determinant of M is not 0.
So when c is not 4, determinant
of M is not 0, so
both systems-- both the original
system and the
corresponding homogeneous
system--
have a unique solution.
So when c is not 4--
so for most values of c--
the determinant is not
0, and the system
has a unique solution.
So when c is equal to
4, what happens?
Well, when c is equal to 4,
we're in the bottom case.
We're in the case where the
homogeneous system has
infinitely many solutions.
OK?
So let me write that
over here.
When c equals 4--
I'm going to abbreviate
again--
the homogeneous system has--
I'm going to use this symbol--
this sort of sideways eight
symbol means infinity, so I'm
going to use it for infinitely
many solutions.
So when c is 4, the homogeneous
system has
infinitely many solutions.
And you might be curious-- well,
so let me say one more
thing about that.
We know when the coefficient
matrix isn't invertible that
the system either has 0 or
infinitely many solutions.
But the homogeneous system
always has a solution.
It always has the solution where
everything is all 0.
Right?
So that's why we know that it's
infinitely many here.
And one thing you might ask is
can you find any others?
Can you find any solutions
that aren't just 0, 0, 0?
And the answer is yes.
So this is now going beyond when
I asked you to do, but I
think it's, you know, an
interesting thing to see.
So if you wanted
to find another
solution, what do you know?
Well, let's go back to the
equations that we had.
So when we're dealing with
a homogeneous system, the
right-hand sides are 0.
So I'm just going to cross out
these right-hand sides and
replace them with 0 so we
don't get confused.
So this is 0, 0, and 0.
So we're dealing with this
system: 2x plus cz equals 0, x
minus y plus 2z equals 0, and
x minus 2y plus 2z equals 0.
OK, so if you want
a solution--
x, y, z--
to this system, what
do you know?
Well, from the second equation,
you know that the
vector xyz is orthogonal to
the vector 1, minus 1, 2.
How do you know that?
Because this left-hand side, x
minus y plus 2z, is equal to
xyz dot 1, minus 1, 2.
And similarly from the third
equation, you know that the
vector xyz is orthogonal to
the vector 1, minus 2, 2,
because this left-hand
side is equal to xyz
dot 1, minus 2, 2.
Yeah?
And that's equal to 0.
So from the second and third
equations, you know that
you're looking for a vector
that's orthogonal to both x--
or sorry-- both 1, minus 1,
2, and 1, minus 2, 2.
How do you get a vector
perpendicular
to two known vectors?
Well, you just take their
cross product.
So let's go back over here.
So to find one, you take a cross
product of two rows of
the coefficient matrix.
So in this case, for example,
we can take these rows 1,
minus 1, 2, and 1, minus 2, 2.
So, for example, the vector
1, minus 1, 2--
OK--
cross the vector
1, minus 2, 2.
Now I've kind of run out of
board space, so I'm not going
to work out precisely what
this vector is for you.
But if you like, you can
certainly check.
You can compute this cross
product out with our nice
formula for the cross product.
It will give you some vector,
and then you can check that
that vector is indeed
a solution of
the homogeneous system.
So that will give us a
second solution of
the homogeneous system.
Nontrivial we say, because it's
not just the 0 solution.
So to quickly recap, we had a
system of linear equations.
I've now crossed out what the
original right-hand side was.
We had a system of linear
equations, and we were looking
for a choice of c for which
that system had a unique
solution and for which the
corresponding homogeneous
system had a unique solution.
And the values of c that make
that work are precisely the
values of c such that the
coefficient matrix has a
non-zero determinant.
So that's true for both
parts a and b.
And for part c, when we were
looking for what values of c
give the homogeneous system
infinitely many solutions, the
answer is any other
value of c.
Any value of c for which the
coefficient matrix does have 0
determinant will give you
infinitely many solutions in
the homogeneous case, and in
non-homogeneous cases will
either give you 0 solutions or
infinitely many solutions.
And then we also at the end, we
briefly discussed one way
to find nontrivial solutions in
the homogeneous case when
there are infinitely
many solutions.
So I'll end there.