JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, among other things,
you've been learning
about computing components of
one vector in the direction of
another vector.
So I have a straightforward
problem about
that for you here.
So we've got two vectors.
The vector 2i minus 2j plus k.
And we've got the vector
i plus j plus k.
And so what I'd like you to do
for me is to compute the
component of this first vector
in the direction
of the second vector.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to work
that out, come back, and we
can work on it together.
Welcome back.
So hopefully you had some
luck with this problem.
Now this problem is pretty
straightforward.
Really all you have to do is
remember what the definition
of component is.
And after that, it's
smooth sailing.
So in particular, the component
of one vector in the
direction of another is the
length of what you get when
you project this vector
onto that one, well,
plus a sign, right?
So if the projection is in the
same direction, then it's
positive, or if it's
in the opposite
direction, it's negative.
So let me draw a picture
of what I mean by that.
So if you have a vector V and
you have another vector W,
then the projection of V onto W
is what you get if you make
a, drop a perpendicular line
there, and then it's just this
vector here.
So that's the projection.
And then the component is the
length of that projection.
Again, with the sign
if necessary.
And so we can see since this
is going to be a right
triangle here, we can see that
this vector has length that's
just given by the length of V.
So the length-- rather-- the
component of V in direction
W is, so it's just the
length of V, right.
That's the length of
the hypotenuse--
times the cosine of the
angle between them--
so it's times cosine of theta.
Now this length of V times
cosine theta, this should
remind you of something.
This looks very much like this
formula we had for the dot
product, right?
So another way of writing this
is to say that this is equal
to V dot W.
So V dot W is the length of V
times the length of W times
the cosine of the angle.
And so here we just have the
length of V times the cosine
of the angle.
So we have to divide this
through by the length of W. So
this is what the component is,
and this is the simple formula
for it if you're given V and
W in some easy-to-use form.
And indeed in this problem,
we're given V and W just in
they're nice coordinate forms.
So we're given that our vector
V that we want the component
of is 2i minus 2j plus k.
And the direction W that we're
looking at is i plus j plus k.
So in our case, we just have to
compute these expressions V
dot W and the length of W in
order to put them into this
formula, and then
we'll be done.
So in our case, V dot W-- well,
that's straightforward
because we're given V and
W in coordinates--
so this is just 2 times
1 plus minus 2 times 1
plus 1 times 1.
So that's, OK, 2 minus
2 plus 1 is 1.
And the length of W-- well, you
know, it's just your usual
length formula--
is 1 squared plus 1 squared
plus 1 squared, the whole
thing is square rooted,
which is equal to the
square root of 3.
So we've got V dot W and we have
the length of W, and so
then we just need to put them
right into this formula.
That the component of V in the
direction of W is given by
this expression.
So the component of--
I'm not going to write it out
with i's, j's, and k's, I'm
going to write--
2, minus 2, 1.
And direction 1, 1, 1 is, well
we just have to divide the dot
product by the length of
the direction vector.
So that's 1 divided by
the square root of 3.
So that's that, I'll
end there.