JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about line integrals
and computing them around curves
and closed curves and
in various different ways.
So here I have some problems
on line integrals for you.
So in all cases I want C to
be the circle of radius b.
So b is some constant, some
positive constant.
It's the circle of radius b
centered at the origin, and I
want to orient it
counterclockwise.
And then what I'd like you
to do is for each of the
following vector fields F, I'd
like you to compute the line
integral around C of F dot dr.
So in the first case, where
F is xi plus yj.
In the second, where F is
g(xy) times (xi + yj).
So here g of xy is some
scalar function.
But you don't know a formula
for this function.
So your answer might be in
terms of g, for example.
You can assume it's a
continuous, differentiable
nice function.
And then the third one,
F is -yi plus xj.
Now before you start, I want
to give you a little
suggestion, which is often
when we're given a line
integral like this, the first
thing you want to do is jump
in and do a parameterization
right away for the curve, and
then you get a normal single
variable integral.
So what I'd like you to do for
these problems is to think
about the setup and think about
whether you can do this
without ever parameterizing C,
so without ever substituting
in cosine and sine
or whatever.
So for all three parts
of this problem.
So if you can use some sort of
geometric reasoning to save
yourself a little bit of work
without ever going to the
parameterization.
So why don't you pause the
video, spend some time, work
that out, come back, and we
can work it out together.
Hopefully you had some luck
working on these problems.
Let's get started.
So let's do the first problem
first. Let's think about what
this vector field
F looks like.
This first vector field.
So let me just draw a little
picture over here.
So here's our circle
of radius b.
And this vector field F given by
xi plus yj, at every point
(x,y), the vector F is the same
as the position vector of
that point.
So over here the vector's
like that.
Over here, the vector's
Up here, the vector
is like that.
So these are just a few little
values of F that
I've drawn in there.
And so down here, say,
F is like that.
So in particular, so that's just
sort of, you know, if you
wanted, you could draw in some
more vectors, get a full
vector field picture.
So the thing to observe here is
that a circle is a really
nice curve.
So the circle has the property
that the position vector at a
point is orthogonal to the
tangent vector to the circle.
At every point on the circle,
the tangent vector to the
circle is perpendicular to
the position vector.
So that means it's perpendicular
to F, because F
is the same, in fact,
but is parallel to
the position vector.
So in Part a, you have that F
dot the tangent vector to your
curve is equal to zero
at every point
on the entire curve.
All right?
So your field F dot your tangent
vector is always zero.
So that means that the integral
around C of F dot dr,
well, we know that dr is T ds.
So this is F dot T ds.
But that's just zero.
It's just an integral and the
integrand is zero everywhere.
And whenever you take a definite
integral of something
that's zero everywhere,
you get zero.
So this is just zero
right away.
We didn't have to parameterize
the curve or anything.
We just had to look at this
picture to sort of understand
that this kind of field, it's
called a radial vector field,
where the vector F is always
pointed directly outwards.
When you integrate a radial
vector field around a circle
centered at the origin, you
get zero, because the
contribution at every
point is zero.
So that's Part a.
Part b is actually
exactly the same.
If we look back at our formula
over here in Part b, we have
that F is given by some
function g(xy) times
(xi hat + yj hat).
Well, what is this
g of xy doing?
It's just rescaling.
It's telling you every point you
can scale that vector by
some amount.
So if we looked over at this
picture, maybe over here you
would scale some of these
vectors to be longer, and over
here they might be shorter, or
you might switch them to be
negative, but you don't change
the direction of any vector in
the field from Part a.
You just change their length.
So you still have a radial
vector field.
And you still have the property
that at every point
on our curve, the tangent
vector to the curve is
orthogonal to the vector F.
So the tangent vector is
orthogonal to F, so that means
you again have F dot T is
equal to zero.
And so F dot dr is also equal
to 0 ds, and so when you
integrate that, you
just get zero.
So that's also what
happens in Part b.
So Part b, I'm just going
to write ditto.
The exact same reasoning
applies in Part b as
applied in Part a.
And you also get zero as your
integral without having to
parameterize, without having
to do any tricky
calculations at all.
All right.
So let's now look at Part c.
I'm going to draw another
little picture.
So in Part c, there's
your curve.
At the point (x,y)--
so I'm going to draw some
choices of F again.
So in Part c, at the point
(x,y), your vector field F is
-y i hat plus x j hat.
Now if you draw that on the
picture here, over there
that's that vector.
Over here, so at the point
(0,1), say, that gives you the
vector .
So that's horizontal
to the left.
Here are some more.
There's one there, there's
one there.
There's another one over
here and so on.
In fact, what you'll notice is
that this vector F is just
parallel to the tangent vector
of the circle everywhere.
This field is a tangential
field.
It's always pointing parallel
to the curve.
OK?
It's perpendicular to
the position vector.
It's in the same direction
as the tangent
vector at every point.
So this is something that you've
seen before, I think.
That this vector field is giving
you a sort of nice
rotating motion.
You know, at every point it's
circulating counterclockwise.
So what does that mean?
Well, again, it's not exactly
the same as Part a and b, but
again we'll be able to compute
this integral without
parameterizing.
Why?
Because F dot T in this case--
well, so, let's see.
What is the norm of F?
The magnitude of F is just the
square root of (x squared plus
y squared).
So on our circle of radius
b, that means the
magnitude of F is b.
And the magnitude of T, the unit
tangent vector, is 1, and
they point in the
same direction.
So when you have two vectors
that point in the same
direction, their dot product is
just the product of their
magnitudes.
So that means F dot
T is equal to b.
This is a constant.
F dot T is equal to b.
So when you integrate around
the circle, F dot dr, well,
this is equal to the integral
around a circle of F dot the
tangent vector with respect
to arc length.
But this integrand, F dot the
tangent vector, is this
constant b.
So you're integrating
over the curve b ds.
And when you integrate a
constant ds, well, that just
gives you the total
arc length.
So this is b times the
total arc length.
And this is a circle
of radius b.
So that's b times 2 pi b, which
we could also write as 2
pi b squared.
So there you go.
So in this third case,
you have a nice
tangential vector field.
So that means the integrand
actually
works out to be constant.
Because the integrand is
constant, we don't ever have
to parameterize the curve.
We can just use the fact that we
already know its arc length
in order to compute
this integral.
Again, we could do all of these
integrals if we wanted
by parameterizing the circle,
by x equals b cosine T, y
equals b sine T, and going
through and writing this as an
integral from T equals
0 to 2 pi, and so on.
But these are examples of
problems where it's helpful to
think about what's going on
first, see if you can
understand the geometry
of your situation.
And sometimes you'll
have a problem
like this where you'll--
either in this class or
elsewhere in your life--
where something that might seem
complicated has a simple
geometric explanation.
And so when that does happen,
it's nice when you can take
advantage of it.
Sometimes that won't happen and
sometimes you'll have to
do the parameterization
and the computation.
But in these cases we have
these nice three examples
where with a radial vector
field, you get that the
integrand is always zero, or
with a tangential vector
field, you have that the
integrand is constant.
All right.
So, I'll stop there.