The second lecture in linear
algebra, and I've put below my
main topics for today.
I put right there a system of
equations that's going to be our
example to work with.
But what are we going to do
with it?
We're going to solve it.
And the method of solution will
not be determinants.
Determinants are something that
will come later.
The method we'll use is called
elimination.
And it's the way every software
package solves equations.
And elimination,
well, if it succeeds,
it gets the answer.
And normally it does succeed.
If the matrix A that's coming
into that system is a good
matrix, and I think this one is,
then elimination will work.
We'll get the answer in an
efficient way.
But why don't we,
as long as we're sort of seeing
how elimination works -- it's
always good to ask how could it
fail?
So at the same time,
we'll see how elimination
decides whether the matrix is a
good one or has problems.
Then to complete the answer,
there's an obvious step of back
substitution.
In fact, the idea of
elimination is -- you would have
thought of it,
right?
I mean Gauss thought of it
before we did,
but only because he was born
earlier.
It's a natural idea...
and died earlier,
too.
Okay, and you've seen the idea.
But now, the part that I want
to show you is elimination
expressed in matrix language,
because the whole course --
all the key ideas get expressed
as matrix operations,
not as words.
And one of the operations,
of course, that we'll meet is
how do we multiply matrices and
why?
Okay, so there's a system of
equations.
Three equations and three
unknowns.
And there's the matrix,
the three by three matrix -- so
this is the system Ax = b.
This is our system to solve,
Ax equal -- and the right-hand
side is that vector 2,
12, 2.
Okay.
Now, when I describe
elimination -- it gets to be a
pain to keep writing the equal
signs and the pluses and so on.
It's that matrix that totally
matters.
Everything is in that matrix.
But behind it is those
equations.
So what does elimination do?
What's the first step of
elimination?
We accept the first equation,
it's okay.
I'm going to multiply that
equation by the right number,
the right multiplier and I'm
going to subtract it from the
second equation.
With what purpose?
So that will decide what the
multiplier should be.
Our purpose is to knock out the
x part of equation two.
So our purpose is to eliminate
x.
So what do I multiply -- and
again, I'll do it with this
matrix, because I can do it
short.
What's the multiplier here?
What do I multiply -- equation
one and subtract.
Notice I'm saying that word
subtract.
I'd like to stick to that
convention.
I'll do a subtraction.
First of all this is the key
number that I'm starting with.
And that's called the pivot.
I'll put a box around it and
write its name down.
That's the first pivot.
The first pivot.
Okay.
So I'm going to use -- that's
sort of like the key number in
that equation.
And now what's the multiplier?
So I'm going to -- my first row
won't change,
that's the pivot row.
But I'm going to use it -- and
now, finally,
let me ask you what the
multiplier is.
Yes?
3 times that first equation
will knock out that 3.
Okay.
So what will it leave?
So the multiplier is 3.
3 times that will make that 0.
That was our purpose.
3 2s away from the 8 will leave
a 2 and three 1s away from 1
will leave a minus 2.
And this guy didn't change.
Okay.
Now the next step -- this is
forward elimination and that
step's completed.
Oh, well, you could say wait a
minute, what about the right
hand side?
Shall I carry -- the right-hand
side gets carried along.
Actually MatLab finishes up
with the left side before -- and
then just goes back to do the
right side.
Maybe I'll be MatLab for a
moment and do that.
Okay.
I'm leaving a room for a column
of b, the right-hand side.
But I'll fill it in later.
Okay.
Now the next step of
elimination is what?
Well, strictly speaking...
this position that I cleaned up
was like the 2,
1 position, row 2,
column 1.
So I got a 0 in the 2,
1 position.
I'll use 2,1 as the index of
that step.
The next step should be to
finish the column and get a 0 in
that position.
So the next step is really the
3,1 step, row three,
column one.
But of course,
I already have 0.
Okay.
So the multiplier is 0.
I take 0 of this equation away
from this one and I'm all set.
So I won't repeat that,
but there was a step there
which, MatLab would have to look
-- it would look at this number
and, do that step,
unless you told it in advance
that it was 0.
Okay.
Now what?
Now we can see the second
pivot, which is what?
The second pivot -- see,
we've eliminated -- x is now
gone from this equation,
right?
We're down to two equations in
y and z.
And so now I just do it again.
Like, everything's very cursive
at this -- this is like --
such a basic algorithm and
you've seen it,
but carry me through one last
step.
So this is still the first
pivot.
Now the second pivot is this
guy, who has appeared there.
And what's the multiplier,
the appropriate multiplier now?
And what's my purpose?
Is it to wipe out the 3,
2 position, right?
This was the 2,
1 step.
And now I'm going to take the
3, 2 step.
So this all stays the same,
1 2 1, 0 2 -1 and the pivots
are there.
Now I'm using this pivot,
so what's the multiplier?
2 times this equation,
this row, gets subtracted from
this row and makes that a 0.
So it's 0, 0 and is it a 5?
Yeah, I guess it's a 5,
is that right?
Because I have a one there and
I'm subtracting twice of twice
this, so I think it's a 5 there.
There's the third pivot.
So let me put a box around all
three pivots.
Is there a -- oh,
did I just invent a negative
one?
I'm sorry that the tape can't,
correct that as easily as I
can.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
You get an A in the course now.
Is that correct?
Is it correct now?
Okay.
So the three pivots are there
-- I know right away a lot about
this matrix.
This elimination step from A --
this matrix I'm going to call U.
U for upper triangular.
So the whole purpose of
elimination was to get from A to
U.
And, literally,
that's the most common
calculation in scientific
computing.
And people think of how could I
do that faster?
Because it's a major,
major thing.
But we're doing it the
straightforward way.
We found three pivots,
and by the way,
I didn't say this,
pivots can't be 0.
I don't accept 0 as a pivot.
And I didn't get 0.
So this matrix is great.
It gave me three pivots,
I didn't have to do anything
special, I just followed the
rules and, and the pivots are 1,
2 and 5.
By the way, just because I
always anticipate stuff from a
later day, if I wanted to know
the determinant of this matrix
--
which I never do want to know,
but I would just multiply the
pivots.
The determinant is 10.
So even things like the
determinant are here.
Okay.
Now -- oh, let me talk about
failure for a moment,
and then --
and then come back to success.
How could this have failed?
How could -- by fail,
I mean to come up with three
pivots.
I mean, there are a couple of
points.
I would have already been in
trouble if this very first
number here was 0.
If it was a 0 there -- suppose
that had been a 0,
there were no Xs in that
equation -- first equation.
Does that mean I can't solve
the problem?
Does that mean I quit?
No.
What do I do?
I switch rows.
I exchange rows.
So in case of a 0,
I will not say 0 pivot.
I will never be heard to utter
those words, 0 pivot.
But if there's a 0 in the pivot
position, maybe I can say that,
I would try to exchange for a
lower equation and get a proper
pivot up there.
Okay.
Now, for example,
this second pivot came out two.
Could it have come out 0?
What -- actually,
if I change that 8 a little
bit, I would have got a little
trouble.
What should I change that 8 to
so that I run into trouble?
A 6.
If that had been a 6,
then this would have been 0 and
I couldn't have used that as the
pivot.
But I could have exchanged
again.
In this case.
In this case,
because when can I get out of
trouble?
I can get out of trouble if
there's a non-0 below this
troublesome 0.
And there is here.
So I would be okay in this
case.
If this was a 6,
I would survive by a row
exchange.
Now -- of course,
it might have happened that I
couldn't do the row,
that -- that there was 0s below
it, but here there wasn't.
Now, I could also have got in
trouble if this number 1 was a
little different.
See, that 1 became a 5,
I guess, by the end.
So can you see what number
there would have got me trouble
that I really couldn't get out
of?
Trouble that I couldn't get out
of would mean if 0 is in the
pivot position and I've got no
place to exchange.
So there must be some number
which if I had had here it would
have meant failure.
Negative 4, good.
If it was a negative 4 here --
if it happened to be a negative
4, I'll temporarily put it up
here.
If this had been a negative 4
z, then I would have gone
through the same steps.
This would have been a minus 4,
it still would have been a
minus 4.
But at the last minute it would
have become 0.
And there wouldn't have been a
third pivot.
The matrix would have not been
invertible.
Well, of course,
the inverse of a matrix is
coming next week,
but, you've heard these words
before.
So, that's how we identify
failure.
There's temporary failure when
we can do a row exchange --
and get out of it,
or there's complete failure
when we get a 0 and -- and
there's nothing below that we
can use.
Okay.
Let's stay with -- back to
success now.
In fact, I guess the next topic
is back substitution.
So what's back substitution?
Well, now I'd better bring the
right-hand side in.
So what would MatLab do and
what should we do?
Let me bring in the right-hand
side as an extra column.
So there comes B.
So it's 2, 12,
I would call this the augmented
matrix.
"Augment" means you've tacked
something on.
I've tacked on this extra
column.
Because, when I'm working with
equations, I do the same thing
to both sides.
So, at this step,
I subtracted 2 of the first
equation away from the second
equation so that this augmented
-- I even brought some colored
chalk, but I don't know if it
shows up.
So this is like the augmented
-- no!
Damn, circled the wrong thing.
Okay.
Here is b.
Okay, that's the extra column.
Okay.
So what happened to that extra
column, the right-hand side of
the equations,
when I did the first step?
So that was 3 of this away from
this, so it took -- the 2 stayed
the same, but three 2s got taken
away from 12,
leaving 6, and that 2 stayed
the same.
So this is how it's looking
halfway along.
And let me just carry to the
end.
The 2 and the 6 stay the same,
but -- what do I have here?
Oh, gosh.
Help me out,
now.
What -- so now I'm --
This is still like forward
elimination.
I got to this point,
which I think is right,
and now what did I do at this
step?
I multiplied that pivot by 2 or
that whole equation by 2 and
subtracted from that,
so I think I take two 6s,
which is 12,
away from the 2.
Do you think minus 10 is my
final right-hand side -- the
right-hand side that goes with
U, and let me call that once and
forever the vector c.
So c is what happens to b,
and U is what happens to A.
Okay.
There you've seen elimination
clean.
Okay.
Oh, what's back substitution?
So what are my final equations,
then?
Can I copy these equations?
x+2y+z=2 is still there and
2y-2z=6 is there,
and 5z=-10.
Okay.
Those are the equations that
these numbers are telling me
about.
Those are the equations U x
equals c.
Okay, how do I solve them?
What one do I solve for first?
z.
I see immediately that the
correct value of z is negative
And what do I do next?
I go back upwards.
I now know z here.
So, if z is negative 2,
that's 4 there,
is that right?
And so 2 y plus a 4 is 6,
maybe y is 1.
Going -- this is back
substitution.
We're doing it on the fly
because it's so easy.
And then x is --
so x -- 2y is 2 minus 2,
maybe x is 2?
So you see what back
substitution is.
It's the simple step solving
the equations in reverse order
because the system is
triangular.
Okay.
Good.
So that's elimination and back
substitution,
and I kept the right-hand side
along.
Okay, now what do I -- that,
like, is first piece of the
lecture.
What's the second piece?
Matrices are going to get in.
So I wrote stuff with x,
y-s and z-s in there,
then I really,
got the right shorthand,
just writing the matrix
entries, and now I want to write
the operations that I did in
matrices, right?
I've carried the matrices
along, but I haven't said the
operation those elimination
steps, I now want to express as
matrices.
Okay.
Here they come.
So now this is elimination
matrices.
Okay.
Let me take that first step,
which took me from 1 2 1 3 8 1
0 4 1.
I want to operate on that -- I
want to do elimination on that.
Okay.
Okay, now I'm remembering a
point I want to single out as
especially important.
Let me move the board up for
that.
Because when we do matrix
operations, we've got to,
like, be able to see the big
picture.
Okay.
Last time, I spoke about the
big picture of -- when I
multiply a matrix by a
right-hand side.
If I have some matrix there and
I multiply it by 3 4 5,
let's say -- so here's a matrix
--
what did I say -- well,
I guess I only said it on the
videotape, but -- do you
remember how I look at that
matrix multiplication?
The result of multiplying a
matrix by some vector is a
combination of the columns of
the matrix.
It's 3 times the first column.
It's 3 times column one plus 4
times column two plus 5 times
column three.
Okay.
I'm going to come back to that
multiple times.
What I wanted to do now was to
emphasize the parallel thing
with rows.
Why?
Because all our operations here
for this two weeks of the course
are row operations.
So this isn't what I need for
row operations.
Let me do a row operation.
Suppose I have my matrix again
and suppose I multiply on the
left by some -- let's say 1 2 7.
Again, I'm just,
like, saying what the result
is.
And then we'll say how matrix
multiplication works and we'll
see that it's true.
Okay.
But maybe already I'm making --
I'm sort of bringing up -- the
central idea of linear algebra
is how these matrices work by
rows as well as by columns.
Okay.
How does it work by rows?
What -- so that's a row vector.
I could say that's a one by
three matrix,
a row vector multiplying a
three by three matrix.
What's the output?
What's the product of a row
times a matrix?
And -- okay,
it's a row.
A row -- a column -- I'm sorry.
A matrix times a column is a
column.
So matrix times a -- yeah.
Matrix times a column is a
column.
And we know what column it is.
Over here, I'm doing a row
times a matrix.
And what's the answer?
It's one of that first row,
so it's 1 times -- 1 times row
one, plus 2 times row two plus 7
times row three.
When -- as we do matrix
multiplication,
keep your eye on what it's
doing with whole vectors.
And what it's doing -- what
it's doing in this case is it's
combining the rows.
And we have a combination,
a linear combination of the
rows.
Okay, I want to use that.
Okay, so my question is what's
the matrix that does this first
step, that takes -- subtracts 3
of equation one from equation
two?
That's what I want to do.
So this is going to be a matrix
that's going to subtract 3 times
row one from row two,
and leaves the other rows the
same.
Just in -- I mean,
the answer is going to be that.
So whatever matrix this is --
and you're going to,
like, tell me what matrix will
do it, it's the matrix that
leaves the first row unchanged,
leaves the last row unchanged,
but takes 3 of these away from
this so it puts a 0 there,
a 2 there and a minus 2.
Good.
What matrix will do it?
It's these.
It should be a pretty simple
matrix, because we're doing a
very simple step.
We're just doing this step that
changes row two.
So actually,
row one is not changing.
So tell me how the matrix
should begin.
One -- the first row of the
matrix will be 1 0 0,
because that's just the right
thing that takes one of that row
and none of the other rows,
and that's what we want.
What's the last row of the
matrix?
0 0 1, because that takes one
of the third row and none of the
other rows, that's great.
Okay.
Now, suppose I didn't want to
do anything at all.
Suppose my row -- well,
I guess maybe I had a case here
when I already had a 0 and,
didn't have to do anything.
What matrix does nothing,
like, just leaves you where you
were?
If I put in -- if I put in 0 1
0, that would be -- that would
be -- that's the matrix --
what's the name of that matrix?
The identity matrix,
right.
So it does absolutely nothing.
It just multiplies everything
and leaves it where it is.
It's like a one,
like the number one,
for matrices.
But that's not what we want,
because we want to change this
row to -- so what's the correct
--
what should I put in here now
to do it right?
I want to get -- what do I
want?
What I -- I'm after -- I want 3
of row one to get subtracted
off.
So what's the right matrix,
finish that matrix for me.
Negative 3 goes here?
And what goes here?
That 1.
The 0.
That's the good matrix.
That's the matrix that takes
minus 3 of row one plus the row
two and gives the new row 2.
Should we just,
like, check some particular
entry?
How do I check a particular
entry of a matrix in matrix
multiplication?
Like, suppose I wanted to check
the entry here that's in row
two, column three.
So where does the entry in row
two, column three come from?
I would look at row two of this
guy and column three of this one
to get that number.
That number comes from the
second row and the third column
and I just take this dot product
minus 3 -- I'm multiplying --
minus 3 plus 1 and 0 gives the
minus 2.
Yeah.
It works.
So we got various ways to
multiply matrices now.
We're sort of,
like -- informally.
We've got by columns,
we've got -- well,
we will have by columns,
by rows, by each entry at a
time.
But it's good to see that
matrix multiplication when one
of the matrices is so simple.
So this guy is our elementary
matrix.
Let's call it E for elementary
or elimination.
And let me put the indexes 2 1,
because it's the matrix that we
needed to fix the 2 1 position.
It's the matrix that we needed
to get this 2 1 position to be
Okay.
Good enough.
So what do I do next?
I need another matrix,
right?
I need to -- there's another
step here.
And I want to express the whole
elimination process in matrix
language.
So tell me what -- so next
step, step two,
which was what?
Subtract -- what was -- what
was the actual step that we did?
I think I subtracted -- do you
remember?
I had a 2 in the pivot and a 4
below it, so I subtracted two
times -- times row two from row
three.
From row three.
Tell me the matrix that will do
that.
And tell me its name.
Okay, it's going to be E,
for elementary or elimination
matrix and what's the index
number that I used to tell me
what E -- 3, 2,
right?
Because it's fixing this 3 2
position.
And what's the matrix,
now?
Okay, you remember -- so E 3 2
is supposed to multiply my guy
that I have and it's supposed to
produce the right result,
which was -- it leaves -- it's
supposed to leave the first row,
it's supposed to leave the
second row and it's supposed to
straighten out that third row to
this.
And what's the matrix that does
that?
1 0 0, right?
Because we don't change the
first row and the next row we
don't change either,
and the last row is the one we
do change.
And what do I do?
Let's see, I subtract two times
-- so what's this row?
What's this here?
0, right, because the first
row's not involved.
It's just in the 3 2 position,
isn't it?
This the key number is this
minus the multiplier that goes
-- sitting there in that 3 2
position.
Is it a minus 2 to subtract 2
and then this is a 1 so that --
the overall effect is to take
minus 2 of this row plus 1 of
that.
Okay.
So, I've now given you the
pieces, the elimination
matrices, the elementary
matrices that take each step.
So now what?
Now the next point in the
lecture is to put those steps
together into a matrix that does
it all and see how it all
happens.
So now I'm going to express the
whole -- everything we did today
so far on A was to start with A,
we multiplied it by E 2 1,
that was the first step --
and then we multiplied that
result by E 3 2 and that led us
to this thing and what was that
matrix?
U.
You see why I like matrix
notation, because there in,
like, little space -- a few
bits when its compressed on the
web -- is everything -- is this
whole lecture.
Okay.
Now there -- there are
important facts about matrix
multiplication.
And we're close to maybe the
most important.
And that is this.
Suppose I ask you this
question.
Suppose I start with a matrix A
and I want to end with a matrix
U and I want to say what matrix
does the whole job?
What matrix takes me from A to
U, using the letters I've got?
And the answer is simple.
I'm not asking this as -- but
it's highly important.
How would I create the matrix
that does the whole job at once,
that does all of elimination in
one shot?
It would be -- I would just put
these together,
right?
In other words,
this is the thing I'm
struggling to say.
I can move those parentheses.
If I keep the matrices in order
-- I can't mess around with the
order of the matrices,
but I can change the order that
I do the multiplications.
I can multiply these two first
-- in other words,
you see what those parentheses
are doing?
It's saying -- multiply the Es
first and that gives you the
matrix that does everything at
once.
Okay.
So this fact,
that this is automatically the
same as this -- for every matrix
multiplication,
which I'm conscious of still
not telling you in every detail,
but, like, you're seeing how it
works -- and this is highly
important --
and maybe tell me the long word
that describes this law for
matrices, that you can move the
parentheses?
It's called the associative
law.
I think you can now forget
that.
But don't forget the law.
I mean, like,
forget the word associative.
I don't know.
But don't forget the law.
Because actually,
we'll see so many steps in
linear algebra,
so many proofs,
even, of main fact come from
just moving the parentheses.
And it's not that easy to prove
that this is correct,
you have to go into the gory
details of matrix
multiplication,
do it both ways and see that
you come out the same.
Maybe I'll leave the author to
do that.
Okay.
So there we go.
So there's a single matrix,
I could call it E -- while
we're talking about these
matrices, tell me one other --
there's another type of
elementary matrix,
and we already said why we
might need it.
We didn't need it in this case.
But it's the matrix that
exchanges two rows.
It's called a permutation
matrix.
Can you just,
like, tell me what that would
be?
So I'm just -- like,
this is a slight digression and
we'll --
yes, so let me get some -- let
me figure out where I'm going to
put a permutation matrix.
You'll see I'm always squeezing
stuff in.
So permutation.
Or, in fact this one you'll,
like, exchange rows -- shall I
exchange rows one and two,
just to make life easy?
So if I had my matrix -- no,
let -- let me just do two by
two.
|a b; c d|.
Suppose I want to find the
matrix that exchanges those
rows.
What is it?
So the matrix that exchanges
those rows -- the row I want is
c d and it's there.
So I better take one of it.
And the row I want here is up
top, so I'll take one of that.
So actually,
I'm just -- the easy way --
this is my matrix that I'll call
P, for permutation.
It's the matrix -- actually,
the easy way to find it is just
do the thing to the identity
matrix.
Exchange the rows of the
identity matrix and then that's
the matrix that will do row
exchanges for you.
Suppose I wanted to exchange
columns instead.
Columns have hardly got into
today's lecture,
but they certainly are going to
be around.
How could I -- if I started
with this matrix |a b;
c d| then I wouldn't -- I'm not
even going to write this down,
I'm just going to ask you,
because in elimination,
we're doing rows.
But suppose we wanted to
exchange the columns of a
matrix.
How would I do that?
What matrix multiplication
would do that job?
Actually, why not?
I'll write it down.
So this is -- I'll write it
under here and then hide it
again.
Okay.
Suppose I had my matrix |a b;
c d| and I want to get to a c
over here and b d here.
What matrix does that job?
Can I multiply -- can I cook up
some matrix that produces that
answer?
You can see from where I put my
hand I was really asking can I
put a matrix here on the left
that will exchange columns?
And the answer is no.
I'm just bringing out again
this point that when I multiply
on the left, I'm doing row
operations.
So if I want to do a column
operation, where do I put that
permutation matrix?
On the right.
If I put it here,
where I just barely left room
for it -- so I'll exchange the
two columns of the identity.
Then it comes out right,
because now I'm multiplying a
column at a time.
This is the first column and
says take one --
take none of that column,
one of this one and then you
got it.
Over here, take one of this
one, none of this one and you've
got a c.
So, in short,
to do column operations,
the matrix multiplies on the
right.
To do row operations,
it multiplies on the left.
Okay, okay, and it's row
operations that we're really
doing.
Okay.
And of course,
I mentioned in passing,
but I better say it very
clearly that you can't exchange
the orders of matrices.
And that's just the point I was
making again here.
A times B is not the same as B
times A.
You have to keep these matrices
in their Gauss given order here,
right?
But you can move the
parentheses, so that,
in other words,
the commutative law,
which would allow you to take
it in the other order is false.
So we have to keep it in that
order.
Okay.
So what next?
I could do this multiplication.
I could do E 32.
So let me come back to see what
that was.
Here was E 2 1.
And here is E 3 2.
And if I multiply those two
matrices together -- E 3 2 and
then E 2 1, I'll get a single
matrix that does elimination.
I don't want to do it that --
if I do that multiplication --
there -- there's a better way
to do this.
And so in this last few minutes
of today's lecture,
can I anticipate that better
way?
The better way is to think not
how do I get from A to U,
but how do I get from U back to
A?
So reversing steps is going to
come in.
Inverse -- I'll use the word
inverse here.
Okay.
So let me make the first step
at what's the inverse matrix?
All the matrices you've seen on
this board have inverses.
I didn't write any bad matrices
down.
We spoke about possible
failure, and for a moment,
we put in a matrix that would
fail.
But right now,
all these matrices are good,
they're all invertible.
And let's take the inverse --
well, let me say first what does
the inverse mean and find it?
Okay.
So we're getting a little leg
up on inverses.
Okay, so this is the final
moments of today.
Sorry, he's still there.
Okay.
Inverses.
Okay, and I'm just going to
take one example and then we're
done.
The example I'll take will be
that E.
So my matrix is 1 0 0 minus 3 1
0 0 0 1.
And I want to find the matrix
that undoes that step.
So what was that step?
The step was subtract 3 times
row one from row two.
So what matrix will get me
back?
What matrix will bring back --
you know, if I started with a 2
12 2 and I changed it to a 2 6 2
because of this guy,
I want to get back to the 2 12
I want to find the matrix which
-- which undoes elimination,
the matrix which multiplies
this to give the identity.
And you can tell me what I
should do in words first,
and then we'll write down the
matrix that does it.
If this step subtracted 3 times
row 1 from row 2,
what's the inverse step?
I add 3 times row one to row
two, right?
I add it back.
The -- what I subtracted away,
I add back.
So the inverse matrix in this
case is --
I now want to add 3 times row
one to row two,
so I won't change row one,
I won't change row three and
I'll add 3 times row one to row
two.
That's a case where the inverse
is clear.
It's clear in words what to do,
because what this did was
simple to express.
It just changed row two by
subtracting 3 of row one.
So to invert it,
I go that way.
And if you -- if we do that
calculation, 3 times this row
plus 1 times this row,
comes out the right row of the
identity.
Okay, so inverses are an -- so
if this matrix was E and this
matrix is I for identity,
then what's the notation for
this guy?
E to the minus one.
E inverse.
Okay.
Let's stop there for today.
That's a little jump on what's
coming on Monday.
So, see you Monday.