PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome to recitation.
My name is Martina, and I'll be
your recitation instructor
for some of these linear
algebra videos.
Today's problem is a
straightforward solve the
following linear system with
four equations and four
unknowns, using the method
of elimination.
The system is x minus y minus z
plus u equals 0, 2x plus 2z
equals 8, minus y minus 2z
equals -8, and 3x minus 3y
minus 2z plus 4u equals 7.
And although you might know
different ways to solve the
system at this point, the method
of elimination is going
to show up a million times
during these videos, so it's
really important to
get it right.
So I suggest you try solving
this system now, using the
method of elimination as it
was described in class.
I'm going to leave you alone
with the problem.
You should pause the video,
solve it yourself, and then
come back and compare your
solution with mine.
And we're back.
So the method of elimination, if
you remember it from class,
consisted of replacing this
system with an equivalent
system-- equivalent meaning they
have the same solution--
by a series of row operations.
Row operations are not supposed
to change the
solution to the system and
there, for example, exchange
the order of two equations.
Multiply an equation with a
non-0 number, and add a non-0
multiple of one equation
to the other.
So let's do that.
As we're going to do this
series of arithmetic
operations, we don't really want
to copy the names of the
variables and the equality
signs every time.
So we're going to keep the
important information which
are these numbers.
these coefficients here, we're
going to keep that information
in a matrix.
So let's write a matrix.
Each row is going to grasp onto
an equation, and each
column is going to correspond
to an unknown.
So the first row is
1, -1, -1, 1.
The second row responding
to the second
equation is 2, 0, 2, 0.
And you want to be very careful
to put 0s on the right
spots here.
The third equation is 0--
I haven't left myself
enough room--
0, -1, -2, 0.
And the fourth row corresponding
to the fourth
equation is 3, -3, -2, 4.
And as we care about the right
hand side as well, we're going
to copy this information as
well, and get the augmented
matrix of the system.
0, 8, -8, 7.
OK, and now let's try reducing
this matrix to an upper
triangular one.
We start with the first column,
and we're going to use
this number called a pivot to
get rid of all the numbers
under it, so to get
0s here and here.
A way to do it is--
well, to get rid of this 2, I
have to multiply the first row
by -2, and add it to
the second one.
Writing this here is not
strictly necessary, but I like
to do a bit of bookkeeping,
because I'm prone to make a
lot of errors while doing this
simple arithmetic operations.
And then if I get to the end,
figure out I made a mistake
somewhere, this bookkeeping
makes it easier to backtrack
and find the place where
I made this mistake.
So we replace this matrix
with another matrix.
The first row stays the same.
1, -1, -1, 1, 0.
The second row gets replaced
by a second row, -2
times the first row.
The aim of that is to get a
0 here, so that's good.
Next on this position here, we
get -2 times -1, which is 2
plus 0 which is 2.
-1 times -2, which is 2
plus 2, which is 4.
-2 plus 0 which is -2.
And 8 ,-2 times 0 which is 8.
The third row already has
a 0 here, so I can
just copy it over.
0, -1, -2, 0, -8.
And to get a 0 here, I'm going
to multiply the first row by
-3 and add it to the fourth
row and get 0, -3 times
-1 is 3 -3 is 0.
-3 minus 1--
oh, sorry--
3 -2 is 1, and -3 plus 4 is 1.
And there we go.
The first column looks like
a first column of an upper
triangular matrix.
Now let's do the same to
the second column.
This is going to be our pivot,
the number that we use to get
rid of numbers under it.
And we see that to get rid of
this number here, we will need
to multiply it with 1/2.
So multiply the whole second
row with 1/2, and add it to
the third row.
The matrix that we get will have
the first row the same.
It stays the same.
1, -1, -1, 1, 0.
The second row stays the same.
0, 2, 4, -2, 8.
The third row gets replaced by
the third row plus 1/2 times
the second row and becomes 0, 0,
2 -2 which is 0, -1 plus 0
which is -1, and 4
-8 which is -4.
And the fourth row already
has a 0 here so I
just copy it over.
0, 0, 1, 1, 7.
And now let's look
at this matrix.
It has the first two columns as
they're supposed to be, 0s
under the diagonal.
And now we want to
get a 0 here.
Normally what I would do is to
circle this number here,
multiply it by something so that
I get a -1, and add it to
this row to get a 0 here.
But that's not going to work.
You might remember from
lecture that 0s
can never be pivots.
Or you can just try finding a
number such that 0 times this
number equals -1, and seeing
that such a number doesn't
exist, because you're always
going to get 0.
So we can proceed as
we did until now.
But is there another way
to get a 0 here?
There is a very simple row
operation, which consists just
of switching the third
and the fourth row.
It certainly doesn't change the
solution of the system.
So let's do that.
And let's get the next matrix
which is 1, -1, -1, 1, 0.
0, 2, 4, -2, 8.
Then we put the fourth
row here.
0, 0, 1, 1, 7.
And we put the third row
here, 0, 0, 0, -1, -4.
And there it is.
This is an upper triangular
matrix.
So in the same way as at the
beginning, we had a system and
then wrote the matrix
representing it, this matrix
also represents a system.
And this system has the same
solutions as the initial
system but is much
easier to solve.
Now let's write this back as a
system, and let me do that not
starting from the first
equation, but starting from
the last equation.
So the last equation here reads
-u equals -4, which is,
as equations go, a pretty
easy one to solve.
The solution is u equals 4.
Now let's go back to
the third equation.
The third equation reads y--
no, I'm sorry-- z--
the third column corresponds
to z--
plus u equals 7.
But we know what's u now.
So, it reads z plus 4
equals 7, which just
becomes z equals 3.
The second equation is 2 times
y plus 4 times z, but z is 3,
minus 2 times u, but
you is 4, equals 8.
And from this, one can easily
compute that y is equal to 2.
And finally the first equation
reads x minus y minus z plus u
equals 0 or x equals 1.
And this is our solution.
x, y, z, and u equal
1, 2, 3, and 4.
This finishes the problem,
but I would very strongly
encourage you now to take this
solution and plug it back into
the original system and check
if it's really a solution.
And that's all I wanted
to say today.