The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or to view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses visit
MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
Okay so I'd like to begin the
second lecture by reminding
you what we did last time.
So last time, we defined the
derivative as the slope
of a tangent line.
So that was our geometric point
of view and we also did a
couple of computations.
We worked out that the
derivative of 1 /
x was -1 / x^2.
And we also computed the
derivative of x ^ nth power for
n = 1, 2, etc., and that turned
out to be x, I'm
sorry, nx^(n-1).
So that's what we did last
time, and today I want to
finish up with other points of
view on what a derivative is.
So this is extremely important,
it's almost the most important
thing I'll be saying
in the class.
But you'll have to think about
it again when you start over
and start using calculus
in the real world.
So again we're talking about
what is a derivative and this
is just a continuation
of last time.
So, as I said last time, we
talked about geometric
interpretations, and today what
we're gonna talk about is rate
of change as an interpretation
of the derivative.
So remember we drew graphs of
functions, y = f(x) and we
kept track of the change in x
and here the change
in y, let's say.
And then from this new point of
view a rate of change, keeping
track of the rate of change of
x and the rate of change of y,
it's the relative rate of
change we're interested in, and
that's delta y / delta x and
that has another
interpretation.
This is the average change.
Usually we would think of that,
if x were measuring time and so
the average and that's when
this becomes a rate, and
the average is over the
time interval delta x.
And then the limiting value is
denoted dy/dx and so this one
is the average rate of change
and this one is the
instantaneous rate.
Okay, so that's the point of
view that I'd like to discuss
now and give you just
a couple of examples.
So, let's see.
Well, first of all, maybe some
examples from physics here.
So q is usually the name for
a charge, and then dq/dt is
what's known as current.
So that's one physical example.
A second example, which is
probably the most tangible one,
is we could denote know the
letter s by distance and
then the rate of change is
that what we call speed.
So those are the two typical
examples and I just want to
illustrate the second example
in a little bit more detail
because I think it's important
to have some visceral
sense of this notion of
instantaneous speed.
And I get to use the example of
this very building to do that.
Probably you know, or maybe
you don't, that on Halloween
there's an event that takes
place in this building or
really from the top of this
building which is called
the pumpkin drop.
So let's illustrates this
idea of rate of change
with the pumpkin drop.
So what happens is this
building, well let's see here's
the building, and here's the
dot, that's the beautiful grass
out on this side of the
building, and then there's some
people up here and very small
objects, well they're not that
small when you're close to
them, that get dumped
over the side there.
And they fall down.
You know everything at MIT
or a lot of things at MIT
are physics experiments.
That's the pumpkin drop.
So roughly speaking, the
building is about 300 feet
high, we're down here on
the first usable floor.
And so we're going to use
instead of 300 feet, just for
convenience purposes we'll use
80 meters because that makes
the numbers come out simply.
So we have the height which
starts out at 80 meters at time
0 and then the acceleration due
to gravity gives you this
formula for h, this
is the height.
So at time t = 0, we're up
at the top, h is 80 meters,
the units here are meters.
And at time t = 4 you
notice, (5 * 4^2) is 80.
I picked these numbers
conveniently so that we're
down at the bottom.
Okay, so this notion of average
change here, so the average
change, or the average speed
here, maybe we'll call it the
average speed since that's,
over this time that it takes
for the pumpkin to drop is
going to be the change
in h / the change in t.
Which starts out at, what
does it start out as?
It starts out as 80, right?
And it ends at 0.
So actually we have
to do it backwards.
We have to take 0 - 80 because
the first value is the final
position and the second value
is the initial position.
And that's divided by 4
- 0; times 4 seconds
minus times 0 seconds.
And so that of course is
-20 meters per second.
So the average speed of this
guy is 20 meters a second.
Now, so why did I
pick this example?
Because, of course, the
average, although interesting,
is not really what anybody
cares about who actually
goes to the event.
All we really care about is the
instantaneous speed when it
hits the pavement and so that's
can be calculated
at the bottom.
So what's the
instantaneous speed?
That's the derivative, or maybe
to be consistent with the
notation I've been using
so far, that's d/dt of h.
All right?
So that's d/dt of h.
Now remember we have
formulas for these things.
We can differentiate
this function now.
We did that yesterday.
So we're gonna take the rate of
change and if you take a look
at it, it's just the rate of
change of 80 is 0, minus
the rate change for this
-5t^2, that's minus 10t.
So that's using the fact that
d/dt of 80 is equal to 0 and
d/dt of t^2 is equal to 2t.
The special case...
Well I'm cheating here,
but there's a special
case that's obvious.
I didn't throw it in over here.
The case n = 2 is that
second case there.
But the case n = 0 also works.
Because that's constants.
The derivative of
a constant is 0.
And then the factor n there's
0 and that's consistent.
And actually if you look at the
formula above it you'll see
that it's the case of n = -1.
So we'll get a larger pattern
soon enough with the powers.
Okay anyway.
Back over here we have
our rate of change and
this is what it is.
And at the bottom, at that
point of impact, we have t
= 4 and so h' which is the
derivative is equal to
-40 meters per second.
So twice as fast as the average
speed here, and if you need
to convert that, that's
about 90 miles an hour.
Which is why the police are
there at midnight on Halloween
to make sure you're all safe
and also why when you come you
have to be prepared to
clean up afterwards.
So anyway that's what happens,
it's 90 miles an hour.
It's actually the buildings a
little taller, there's air
resistance and I'm sure you
can do a much more thorough
study of this example.
All right so now I want to give
you a couple of more examples
because time and these kinds of
parameters and variables are
not the only ones that are
important for calculus.
If it were only this kind of
physics that was involved, then
this would be a much more
specialized subject than it.
Is And so I want to give you a
couple of examples that don't
involved time as a variable.
So the third example
I'll give here is.
The letter t often denotes
temperature, and then dt/dx
would be what is known as
the temperature gradient.
Which we really care about a
lot when we're predicting the
weather because it's that
temperature difference
that causes air flows and
causes things to change.
And then there's another theme
which is throughout the
sciences and engineering which
I'm going to talk about under
the heading of sensitivity
of measurements.
So let me explain this.
I don't want to belabor it
because I just am doing this in
order to introduce you to the
ideas on your problem set which
are the first case of this.
So on problem set one you have
an example which is based on a
simplified model of GPS, sort
of the Flat Earth Model.
And in that situation, well, if
the Earth is flat it's just
a horizontal line like this.
And then you have a satellite,
which is over here, preferably
above the earth, and the
satellite or the system knows
exactly where the point
directly below the
satellite is.
So this point is
treated as known.
And I'm sitting here with
my little GPS device and I
want to know where I am.
And the way I locate where I am
is I communicate with this
satellite by radio signals and
I can measure this distance
here which is called h.
And then system will
computer this horizontal
distance which is L.
So in other words what is
measured, so h measured by
radios, radio waves and a
clock, or various clocks.
And then L is deduced from h.
And what's critical in all of
these systems is that you
don't know h exactly.
There's an error in h which
will denote delta h.
There's some degree
of uncertainty.
The main uncertainty in GPS
is from the ionosphere.
But there are lots of
corrections that are
made of all kinds.
And also if you're inside
a building it's a
problem to measure it.
But it's an extremely
important issue, as I'll
explain in a second.
So the idea is we then get at
delta L is estimated by
considering this ratio delta
L/delta h which is going to be
approximately the same as
the derivative of L
with respect to h.
So this is the thing
that's easy because of
course it's calculus.
Calculus is the easy part and
that allows us to deduce
something about the real world
that's close by over here.
So the reason why you should
care about this quite a bit
is that it's used all the
time to land airplanes.
So you really do care that they
actually know to within a few
feet or even closer where
your plane is and how high
up it is and so forth.
All right.
So that's it for the general
introduction of what
a derivative is.
I'm sure you'll be getting used
to this in a lot of different
contexts throughout the course.
And now we have to get back
down to some rigorous details.
Ok, everybody happy with
what we've got so far?
Yeah?
Student: How did you get
the equation for height?
Professor: Ah good
question question.
The question was how did I get
this equation for height?
I just made it up because it's
the formula from physics that
you will learn when you take
8.01 and, in fact, it has to do
with the fact that this is the
speed if you differentiate
another time you get
acceleration and acceleration
due to gravity is 10
meters per second.
Which happens to be the
second derivative of this.
But anyway I just pulled
it out of a hat from
your physics class.
So you can just say see 8.01 .
All right, other questions?
All right, so let's go on now.
Now I have to be a little bit
more systematic about limits.
So let's do that now.
So now what I'd like to talk
about is limits and continuity.
And this is a warm up for
deriving all the rest of the
formulas, all the rest of
the formulas that I'm going
to need to differentiate
every function you know.
Remember, that's our goal and
we only have about a week left
so we'd better get started.
So first of all there is what
I will call easy limits.
So what's an easy limit?
An easy limit is something like
the limit as x goes to 4 of (x
3 / x^2
1).
And with this kind of limit all
I have to do to evaluate it is
to plug in x = 4 because,
so what I get here
is 4 + 3 / (4^2
1).
And that's just 7 / 17.
And that's the end of it.
So those are the easy limits.
The second kind of limit, well
so this isn't the only second
kind of limit but I just want
to point this out, it's very
important is that:
derivatives are are always
harder than this.
You can't get away
with nothing here.
So, why is that?
Well, when you take a
derivative, you're taking the
limit as x goes to x0 of f(x),
well we'll write it all
out in all its glory.
Here's the formula
for the derivative.
Now notice that if you plug in
x = x0, always gives 0 / 0.
So it just basically
never works.
So we always are going to need
some cancellation to make
sense out of the limit.
Now in order to make things a
little easier for myself to
explain what's going on with
limits I need to introduce just
one more piece of notation.
What I'm gonna introduce
here is what's known as a
left-hand and a right limit.
If I take the limit as
x tends to x0 with a
sign here of some function,
this is what's known as
the right hand limit.
And I can display it visually.
So what does this mean?
It means practically the same
thing as x tends to x0 except
there is one more restriction
which has to do with this
sign, which is we're going
from the plus side of x0.
That means x is bigger than x0.
And I say right-hand, so there
should be a hyphen here,
right-hand limit because on the
number line, if x zero is over
here the x is to the right.
All right?
So that's the right-hand limit.
And then this being the left
side of the board, I'll put on
the right side of the board
the left limit, just to
make things confusing.
So that one has the
minus sign here.
I'm just a little dyslexic
and I hope you're not.
So I may have
gotten that wrong.
So this is the left-hand
limit, and I'll draw it.
So of course that just means
x goes to x0 but x is
to the left of x0 .
And again, on the number line,
here's the x0 and the x is
on the other side of it.
Okay, so those two notations
are going to help us to
clarify a bunch of things.
It's much more convenient to
have this extra bit of
description of limits than to
just consider limits
from both sides.
Okay so I want to give
an example of this.
And also an example of how
you're going to think about
these sorts of problems.
So I'll take a function which
has two different definitions.
Say it's x + 1, when
x &gt; 0 and -x
2, when x &lt; 0.
So maybe put commas there.
So when x &gt;
0, it's x + 1.
Now I can draw a
picture of this.
It's gonna be kind of little
small because I'm gonna try to
fit it down in here, but maybe
I'll put the axis down below.
So at height 1, I have to the
right something of slope 1
so it goes up like this.
All right?
And then to the left of 0 I
have something which has slope
-1, but it hits the axis
at 2 so it's up here.
So I had this sort of
strange antennae figure
here is my graph.
Maybe I should draw these in
another color to depict that.
And then if I calculate these
two limits here, what I see is
that the limit as x goes to 0
from above of f(x), that's the
same as the limit as x goes to
0 of the formula here, x + 1.
Which turns out to be 1.
And if I take the limit, so
that's the left-hand limit.
Sorry, I told you
I was dyslexic.
This is the right, so
it's that right-hand.
Here we go.
So now I'm going from the left,
and it's f(x) again, but now
because I'm on that side the
thing I need to plug is the
other formula, -x + 2, and
that's gonna give us 2.
Now, notice that the left and
right limits, and this is one
little tiny subtlety and it's
almost the only thing that I
need you to really pay
attention to a little bit right
now, is that this, we did
not need x = 0 value.
In fact I never even told
you what f(0) was here.
If we stick it in we
could stick it in.
Okay let's say we stick
it in on this side.
Let's make it be that
it's on this side.
So that means that this point
is in and this point is out.
So that's a typical notation:
this little open circle
and this closed dot for
when you include the.
So in that case the value of
f(x) happens to be the same as
its right hand limit, namely
the value is 1 here and not 2.
Okay, so that's the
first kind of example.
Questions?
Okay, so now our next
job is to introduce the
definition of continuity.
So that was the
other topic here.
So we're going to define.
So f is continuous at x0 means
that the limit of f(x) as
x tends to x0 = f(x0) .
Right?
So the reason why I spend all
this time paying attention to
the left and the right and so
on and so forth and focusing
is that I want you to pay
attention for one moment to
what the content of
this definition is.
What it's saying is the
following: continuous at x0
has various ingredients here.
So the first one is that
this limit exists.
And what that means is that
there's an honest limiting
value both from the
left and right.
And they also have
to be the same.
All right, so that's
what's going on here.
And the second property is
that f(x0) is defined.
So I can't be in one of these
situations where I haven't
even specified what f(x0)
is and they're equal.
Okay, so that's the situation.
Now again let me emphasize
a tricky part of the
definition of a limit.
This side, the left-hand side
is completely independent, is
evaluated by a procedure which
does not involve the
right-hand side.
These are separate things.
This one is, to evaluate
it, you always avoid
the limit point.
So that's if you like a
paradox, because it's exactly
the question: is it true that
if you plug in x0 you get the
same answer as if you
move in the limit?
That's the issue that
we're considering here.
We have to make that
distinction in order to say
that these are two, otherwise
this is just tautalogical.
It doesn't have any meaning.
But in fact it does have a
meaning because one thing is
evaluated separately with
reference to all the other
points and the other is
evaluated right at the
point in question.
And indeed what these
things are, are exactly
the easy limits.
That's exactly what we're
talking about here.
They're the ones you
can evaluate this way.
So we have to make
the distinction.
And these other ones are
gonna be the ones which we
can't evaluate that way.
So these are the nice ones and
that's why we care about them
why we have a whole definitions
associated with them.
All right?
So now what's next?
Well, I need to give you a a
little tour, very brief tour,
of the zoo of what are known
as discontinuous functions.
So sort of everything else
that's not continuous.
So, the first example here, let
me just write it down here.
It's jump discontinuities.
So what would a jump
discontinuity be?
Well we've actually
already seen it.
The jump discontinuity
is the example that
we had right there.
This is when the limit from
the left and right exist,
but are not equal.
Okay, so that's as
in the example.
Right?
In this example, the two
limits, one of them was
1 and of them was 2.
So that's a jump discontinuity.
And this kind of issue, of
whether something is continuous
or not, may seem a little bit
technical but it is true that
people have worried
about it a lot.
Bob Merton, who was a professor
at MIT when he did his work for
the Nobel prize in economics,
was interested in this very
issue of whether stock prices
of various kinds are continuous
from the left or right
in a certain model.
And that was a very serious
issue in developing the model
that priced things that
our hedge funds use
all the time now.
So left and right can really
mean something very different.
In this case left is the past
and right is the future and it
makes a big difference whether
things are continuous from the
left or continuous
from the right.
Right, is it true that the
point is here, here, somewhere
in the middle, somewhere else.
That's a serious issue.
So the next example that
I want to give you is a
little bit more subtle.
It's what's known as a
removable discontinuity.
And so what this means is
that the limit from left
and right are equal.
So a picture of that would be,
you have a function which is
coming along like this and
there's a hole maybe where, who
knows either the function is
undefined or maybe it's defined
up here, and then it
just continues on.
All right?
So the two limits are the same.
And then of course the function
in begging to be redefined
so that we remove that hole.
And that's why it's called
a removable discontinuity.
Now let me give you an
example of this, or actually
a couple of examples.
So these are quite important
examples which you will be
working with in a few minutes.
So the first is the function
g(x), which is sin x / x, and
the second will be the function
h(x), which is 1 - cos x / x.
So we have a problem at
g(0) , g(0) is undefined.
On the other hand it turns out
this function has what's called
a removable singularity.
Namely the limit as x goes to
0 of sin x / x does exist.
In fact it's equal to 1.
So that's a very important
limit that we will work out
either at the end of this
lecture or the beginning
of next lecture.
And similarly, the limit of 1 -
cos x / x, as x goes to 0 is 0.
Maybe I'll put that a
little farther away
so you can read it.
Okay, so these are very useful
facts that we're going
to need later on.
And what they say is that these
things have removable
singularities, sorry removable
discontinuity at x = 0.
All right so as I say, we'll
get to that in a few minutes.
Okay so are there any
questions before I move on?
Yeah?
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: The question
is: why is this true?
Is that what your question is?
The answer is it's very, very
unobvious, I haven't shown it
to you yet, and if you were
not surprised by it then that
would be very strange indeed.
So we haven't done it yet.
You have to stay
tuned until we do.
Okay?
We haven't shown it yet.
And actually even this other
statement, which maybe seems
stranger still, is also
not yet explained.
Okay, so we are going to get
there, as I said, either at
the end of this lecture or
at the beginning of next.
Other questions?
All right, so let me just
continue my tour of the
zoo of discontinuities.
And, I guess, I want to
illustrate something with the
convenience of right and left
hand limits so I'll save this
board about right and
left-hand limits.
So a third type of
discontinuity is what's known
as an infinite discontinuity.
And we've already
encountered one of these.
I'm going to draw
them over here.
Remember the function
y is 1 / x.
That's this function here.
But now I'd like to draw also
the other branch of the
hyperbola down here and
allow myself to consider
negative values of x.
So here's the graph of 1 / x.
And the convenience here of
distinguishing the left and the
right hand limits is very
important because here I
can write down that the
limit as x goes to 0
of 1 / x.
Well that's coming from the
right and it's going up.
So this limit is infinity.
Whereas, the limit in the other
direction, from the left,
that one is going down.
And so it's quite different,
it's minus infinity.
Now some people say that these
limits are undefined but
actually they're going in some
very definite direction.
So you should, whenever
possible, specify what
these limits are.
On the other hand, the
statement that the limit as
x goes to 0 of 1 / x is
infinity is simply wrong.
Okay, it's not that
people don't write this.
It's just that it's wrong.
It's not that they
don't write it down.
In fact you'll probably see it.
It's because people are
just thinking of the
right hand branch.
It's not that they're making
a mistake necessarily,
but anyway, it's sloppy.
And there's some sloppiness
that we'll endure and others
that we'll try to avoid.
So here, you want to say this,
and it does make a difference.
You know, plus infinity is an
infinite number of dollars
and minus infinity is and
infinite amount of debt.
They're actually different.
They're not the same.
So, you know, this is sloppy
and this is actually
more correct.
Okay, so now in addition,
I just want to point
out one more thing.
Remember, we calculated
the derivative, and
that was -1/x^2.
But, I want to draw the graph
of that and make a few
comments about it.
So I'm going to draw the graph
directly underneath the
graph of the function.
And notice what this graphs is.
It goes like this, it's always
negative, and it points down.
So now this may look a little
strange, that the derivative
of this thing is this guy,
but that's because of
something very important.
And you should always remember
this about derivatives.
The derivative function
looks nothing like the
function, necessarily.
So you should just forget
about that as being an idea.
Some people feel like if one
thing goes down, the other
thing has to go down.
Just forget that intuition.
It's wrong.
What we're dealing with here,
if you remember, is the slope.
So if you have a slope here,
that corresponds to just a
place over here and as the
slope gets a little bit less
steep, that's why
we're approaching the
horizontal axis.
The number is getting a little
smaller as we close in.
Now over here, the slope
is also negative.
It is going down and as we
get down here it's getting
more and more negative.
As we go here the slope, this
function is going up, but
its slope is going down.
All right, so the slope is down
on both sides and the notation
that we use for that is well
suited to this left
and right business.
Namely, the limit as x goes to
0 of -1 / x^2, that's going to
be equal to minus infinity.
And that applies
to x going to 0
and x going to 0-.
So both have this property.
Finally let me just make
one last comment about
these two graphs.
This function here is an odd
function and when you take the
derivative of an odd function
you always get an
even function.
That's closely related to the
fact that this 1 / x is an odd
power and x^1 is an odd power
and x^2 is an even power.
So all of this your intuition
should be reinforcing the fact
that these pictures look right.
Okay, now there's one last kind
of discontinuity that I want to
mention briefly, which I will
call other ugly
discontinuities.
And there are lots
and lots of them.
So one example would be
the function y = sin 1
/ x, as x goes to 0.
And that looks a
little bit like this.
Back and forth and
back and forth.
It oscillates infinitely
often as we tend to 0.
There's no left or right
limit in this case.
So there is a very large
quantity of things like that.
Fortunately we're not gonna
deal with them in this course.
A lot of times in real life
there are things that oscillate
as time goes to infinity, but
we're not going to worry
about that right now.
Okay, so that's our final
mention of a discontinuity, and
now I need to do just one more
piece of groundwork for
our formulas next time.
Namely, I want to check
for you one basic fact,
one limiting tool.
So this is going
to be a theorem.
Fortunately it's a very
short theorem and has
a very short proof.
So the theorem goes under
the name differentiable
implies continuous.
And what it says is the
following: it says that if f is
differentiable, in other words
its the derivative exists at
x0, then f is continuous at x0.
So, we're gonna need this is as
a tool, it's a key step in the
product and quotient rules.
So I'd like to prove
it right now for you.
So here is the proof.
Fortunately the proof
is just one line.
So first of all, I want to
write in just the right
way what it is that
we have to check.
So what we have to check is
that the limit, as x goes
to x0 of f(x) - f(x0) = 0.
So this is what
we want to know.
We don't know it yet, but
we're trying to check
whether this is true or not.
So that's the same as the
statement that the function is
continuous because the limit of
f(x) is supposed to be f(x0)
and so this difference
should have limit 0.
And now, the way this is
proved is just by rewriting
it by multiplying and
dividing by (x - x0).
So I'll rewrite the limit as x
goes to x0 of (f(x) - f(x0)
/ by x - x0) (x - x0).
Okay, so I wrote down the same
expression that I had here.
This is just the same limit,
but I multiplied and
divided by (x - x0).
And now when I take the limit
what happens is the limit of
the first factor is f'(x0).
That's the thing we know
exists by our assumption.
And the limit of the second
factor is 0 because the
limit as x goes to x0 of
(x - x0) is clearly 0 .
So that's it.
The answer is 0, which
is what we wanted.
So that's the proof.
Now there's something
exceedingly fishy looking about
this proof and let me just
point to it before we proceed.
Namely, you're used in limits
to setting x equal to 0.
And this looks like we're
multiplying, dividing by 0,
exactly the thing which makes
all proofs wrong in all kinds
of algebraic situations
and so on and so forth.
You've been taught that
that never works.
Right?
But somehow these limiting
tricks have found a way around
this and let me just make
explicit what it is.
In this limit we never
are using x = x0.
That's exactly the one
value of x that we don't
consider in this limit.
That's how limits
are cooked up.
And that's sort of been the
themes so far today, is that we
don't have to consider that and
so this multiplication and
division by this
number is legal.
It may be small, this number,
but it's always non-zero.
So this really works, and it's
really true, and we just
checked that a differentiable
function is continuous.
So I'm gonna have to carry out
these limits, which are very
interesting 0 / 0
limits next time.
But let's hang on for one
second to see if there any
questions before we stop.
Yeah, there is a question.
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: Repeat this
proof right here?
Just say again.
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: Okay, so there are
two steps to the proof and
the step that you're asking
about is the first step.
Right?
And what I'm saying is if
you have a number, and you
multiply it by 10 / 10
it's the same number.
If you multiply it by 3 /
3 it's the same number.
2 / 2, 1 / 1, and so on.
So it is okay to change
this to this, it's
exactly the same thing.
That's the first step.
Yes?
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: Shhhh...
The question was how does the
proof, how does this line, yeah
where the question mark is.
So what I checked was that this
number which is on the left
hand side is equal to this very
long complicated number which
is equal to this number which
is equal to this number.
And so I've checked that this
number is equal to 0 because
the last thing is 0.
This is equal to that is
equal to that is equal to 0.
And that's the proof.
Yes?
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: So that's a
different question.
Okay, so the hypothesis of
differentiability I use
because this limit is
equal to this number.
That that limit exits.
That's how I use the
hypothesis of the theorem.
The conclusion of the theorem
is the same as this because
being continuous is the same
as limit as x goes to
x0 of f(x) = f(x0).
That's the definition
of continuity.
And I subtracted f(x0) from
both sides to get this
as being the same thing.
So this claim is continuity
and it's the same as
this question here.
Last question.
Student: How did you
get the 0 [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: How did we
get the 0 from this?
So the claim that is being
made, so the claim is why
is this tending to that.
So for example, I'm going
to have to erase something
to explain that.
So the claim is that the limit
as x goes to x0 of x - x0 = 0.
That's what I'm claiming.
Okay, does that answer
your question?
Okay.
All right.
Ask me other stuff
after lecture.