Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
Today we're going to do a nice
little problem involving
computing the arc length
of a curve.
So in particular, consider the
curve given by the equation y
equals x to the 3/2.
So I have here a kind of
mediocre sketch of what that
curve looks like.
You know, it's curving upwards
not quite as fast as a
parabola would.
So I'm interested in the piece
of that curve for x between 0
and 4, which I've drawn here.
So why don't you take a minute,
pause the video,
compute the arc lengths of this
curve, come back, and we
can compute it together.
All right.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you had some
luck computing
this arc length here.
So let's set about doing it.
So I'm sure you remember that
in order to compute arc
length, first you have to
compute the little piece of
arc length ds.
And we have a couple of
different formulas for that.
So then after that, you get an
integral, and THEN hopefully
it's an integral you
can compute.
So let's remember what ds is.
So there are a couple of
different ways to remember it.
One way that I like is to write
ds equals the square
root of dx squared
plus dy squared.
So this always reminds me of the
Pythagorean theorem, so I
find it easy to remember.
And then from here, it's not
very hard to get the other
form, which is, you can divide
through by A dx squared inside
and multiply by dX outside.
So you can also write this as
the square root of 1 plus dy
dx squared dx.
And when you write it in this
form-- it's, you know, this is
the form that you can actually
use to integrate it, to
actually compute the
value in question.
So in our case, we have y as
a function of x, right?
So we just have to
compete dy dx.
So y is x to the 3/2, so dy dx
is easy to compute, y prime dy
dx is just 3/2 x to the 1/2,
or 3/2 square root of x.
So ds, then-- well, we just
have to plug it in there.
So that means ds is equal to
the square root of 1 plus--
OK.
So now you have to
square this.
Well, 3/2 squared is just 9/4,
and the square root of x
squared is x.
So this is 9/4 x dx.
So this is the thing that
we want to integrate.
And now you need bounds
of integration.
So in our case, this is dx.
We want to integrate with
respect to x, so we need
bounds on x.
And luckily we have them.
We have 0 less than or equal to
x, less than or equal to 4,
the bounds that we want.
So the arc length in question is
the integral from 0 to 4 of
square root of 1
plus 9/4 x dx.
Now, this curve has the property
that this is an
integral we actually know
how to compute.
Right?
There's a-- well, OK.
So I always lose track of my
constants when I do this, so
I'm going to do an extra
substitution, and then it'll
be really easy.
But you know, this is an
integral-- many of you can
probably do this one
in your heads,
basically, at this point.
This is unusual.
Even most polynomials that you
write down, computing their
arc length is really hard.
You get nasty things
popping up.
So, you know, I sort of
conspired to choose a one that
will have a value that we
can integrate by hand.
You don't need to resort to any
sort of numerical method.
But it happens, in this case,
that that did happen, and
that's nice.
So we can we can actually
write down what
this arc length is.
So I'm going to do the
substitution, u
equals 1 plus 9/4 x.
So with this substitution, I
get that du is equal to 9/4
dx, and since I want to
substitute it the other way, I
could write that as
dx equals 4/9 du.
And I also need to change
bounds, so when x equals 0,
that goes to u, I put the 0
here, u is equal to 1 when x
is equal to 4.
So I put 4 in here.
That goes to u equals
10, and so, OK.
With those substitutions, I get
that the arc length that
I'm interested in is the
integral from 1 to 10 of 4/9
times the square root of u du.
OK.
And so now this is, you
know, really easy.
So this is u to the 1/2, so I
integrate that, so I'm going
to get u to the 3/2
divided by 3/2.
So this is 4/9 times u to the
3/2 divided by 3/2 between u
equals 1 and u equals 10.
OK.
So I can divide here, so this
becomes 8/27 is the constant.
So this is 8 over 27 times 10
to the 3/2 minus 1 to the
3/2, is just 1.
OK.
So now if you wanted to,
you know, get a decimal
approximation for this number,
you could put this into a
calculator.
You can also kind of eyeball
what this is, because 10, the
square root of 10 is just a
little bigger than 3, so this
is, you know, bigger than 27,
so this is bigger than 26.
So this whole thing is probably
about 8 or a little
bit larger.
Probably going to be a little
bit larger than
8, would be my guess.
So that's, you know, just
rough eyeballing.
Since you're all sitting in
front of a computer, I'm sure
you can get a more precise
estimate on your own.
But there we go.
So very much just applying the
sort of straightforward tools
that we've developed for
computing arc lengths.
You know, using our formulas for
the little element of arc
length, for the differential
of arc length.
Computing a derivative,
plugging it in.
And it happens, in this case,
that we got something that we
can actually evaluate the
resulting integral in a nice
closed form.
So I'll stop there.