CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video I want to show
how we can use change of
variables to polar coordinates
in particular to evaluate an
integral that, without the
change in variables, we don't
have the techniques to do.
So I'm going to show us how to
evaluate the integral from
minus infinity to infinity of
e to the minus x squared dx.
And I'll just point out that
if you do anything in
probability you will see this
integral a great deal.
So this is a distribution and
you'll see it a great deal if
you ever do anything in
probability theory.
But how are we going
to use polar
coordinates to evaluate this?
Well, the object is going to be
to introduce a little bit
more into this integral, so that
when I actually introduce
that in I'm going to have an r
squared term in the exponent
and I'm going to have --of
course by the change of
variables in the Jacobian--
multiplied by r.
And that's what's going
to save us.
So let me actually just
get right to it.
I'm going to call this integral,
this quantity,
capital I. We'll just call this
quantity capital I. And
then what I'm going
to do is introduce
a couple more things.
So let me write it down, and
then I will justify that it's
reasonable to even look
at this thing.
And that it will give
us something useful.
OK, so I just took this integral
and what I've done is
I've now taken this quantity and
I've multiplied by an e to
the minus y squared.
And then I'm now integrating for
minus infinity to infinity
and dy also.
And what I want to point out,
that maybe isn't immediately
obvious from the way it's
written here, but will be
immediately obvious when I write
it a different way, is
that this quantity is
actually just the
square of this quantity.
So it's actually just two of
these multiplied together.
And let me point out
why that is.
Because this term right here can
be rewritten as e to the
minus x squared, e to
the minus y squared.
And then I have two integrals,
which are for minus infinity
to infinity both.
Sorry, that one looks
a little off kilter.
But those two integrals, which
the bounds are minus infinity
to infinity for both.
And then I have a dx and a dy.
Now the reason that it
is just I squared--
this quantity is just I
squared-- is because if you
notice, this first integral, the
inside integral, this is
independent of x.
So I can move it out.
So let me actually come up
here and write that down.
So I can move it out and I can
actually rewrite the integral.
And I'll put the bounds here,
because it's high up enough
that I can actually write it.
e to the minus y squared.
And then integral for minus
infinity to infinity.
e to the minus x
squared dx dy.
Right?
So let's point out
again what I did.
This quantity I circled was the
constant when I considered
x the variable.
Right?
In terms of x, this is the
constant, so I can move it in
front of that integral, which
is the dx integral.
And so now what do I see?
Well, this quantity is what
I've called I. And so now
that's a constant.
So I can move that
out to the front.
That's a constant.
That's I, as designated.
And so now I have the integral
for minus infinity to infinity
of either the minus
y squared dy.
And then that again is another
I. Because if you notice, I
mean, this was either the
minus x squared dx--
and so if I keep this as either
the minus y squared dy,
it's going to be exactly
the same value.
So this is actually equal
to I squared.
So the point I want to make, if
you come back over here to
this integral, is that this
quantity I'm going to be able
to integrate very easily.
And when I do that, if I take
the square root, I'm going to
get this value.
Because I just showed this
thing in the box
was equal to I squared.
So let me write it down.
On this last part of the board
I will write down that thing
again and then we'll actually
evaluate it and
we'll see what we get.
So let me rewrite.
This is the thing we
want to evaluate.
And I'm going to remind
myself that
that's equal to I squared.
I squared is equal
to this quantity.
And I mentioned at the beginning
that we're going to
use a trick.
We're going to change
variables into polar
coordinates.
And so notice that the region
we're integrating over is the
entire xy plane.
And in polar coordinates,
what's that going to be?
Theta is going to run from 0
all the way around to 2 pi,
and r is going to run
from 0 to infinity.
And so those will be our
bounds for r and theta.
Because if you want to get the
entire xy plane, in terms of r
and theta, that is what
you have to do.
And I want to mention also, what
is this quantity going to
become in terms of
r and theta?
Well, notice that this
is e to the minus x
squared minus y squared.
It's just really e to
the minus quantity x
squared plus y squared.
It's really e to the
minus r squared.
So what we get when
we do a change of
variables, is we do--
I'll put the theta on the
inside actually, because
that'll be easy to do first.
So the r is going
to be on the outside.
The theta is going to
be on the inside.
And then e to the minus r
squared, that's a direct
substitution.
x squared plus y squared
equals r squared.
And then I get r d theta d r.
And this comes from the Jacobian
that you computed--
I believe in lecture even--
to show how you change from xy
variables to r theta variables.
And I put the d theta first
here because I wanted to
integrate in theta first. And
the reason I want to integrate
in theta first is
notice that--
because nothing here
depends on theta--
all I pick up is a 2 pi.
I just pick up --when
I integrate--
I get a theta.
I evaluate it at 2 pi, and then
I evaluate it at 0 and I
take the difference.
And so if I do that line all
I get is-- well, I should
probably write it in front--
all I get is 2 pi from the
theta, and then the integral
from 0 to infinity.
e to the minus r squared
times r dr.
Now this is a much easier
quantity to evaluate than e to
the minus x squared dx.
Because now we have an r here.
So now it's a natural
substitution type of problem.
And we can do it right away.
I'm going to write it down and
then we'll check and make sure
I didn't make a mistake.
We should get something like e
to the minus r squared over 2
with a negative sign in front.
So let me make sure when I
take this derivative--
you could just do a substitution
to check, but you
should get exactly this
kind of thing.
When I take the derivative of
e to the minus r squared, I
get a negative 2r and then--
did I do something wrong here?
Oh yeah.
I'm good.
I get a negative 2r.
And so the negatives kill off,
the 2s divide out, and I get
my e to the minus r
squared times r.
So that's good.
And now I have to evaluate
it at the bounds.
So again, this was much easier
to evaluate if I do a
substitution and I let r--
I think I want to let
r squared equal u or
something like this.
I don't even know.
I just did the substitution
without thinking about it.
So you can figure out what
you need to substitute.
But this is what you get.
And so let me actually just
evaluate at the bounds and see
what happens.
So as r goes to infinity, I get
e to the minus r squared.
As r goes to infinity, e to the
minus r squared goes to 0.
And so the first term is
0 when I evaluate.
And then so the second term I
get is, I do 0 minus 2 pi
times-- if I evaluate at
e to the 0 I get 1--
so I get negative 1 over 2.
The negative 1 comes
from e to the 0.
And then I divide by 2
so I get my 2 there.
So a negative and a negative
gives me a positive.
2 divided by 2.
And so the whole thing
equals pi.
Whew!
Just enough room.
And so I just want to remind
us where we came from.
We came from pi--
we wanted to show was equal--
well, the pi,
where did it come from?
It's equal if we go all the
way back up to I squared.
And so we wanted to show
what I was equal to.
I then is equal to just
the square root of pi.
So I can come back over
to where I started
which is over here.
And I can say this is equal
to the square root of pi.
And again, I just want to
mention what it came down to.
It came down to introducing
a little bit more.
Essentially we took something
that was a single variable
problem, we made it a
multivariable problem.
But what that allowed us to
do is to do a change of
coordinates from xy into the
polar coordinate system.
And the trick here-- as you come
through-- the trick where
it actually happens
is right here.
Is because this is easy
to integrate now
that I have an r here.
If I didn't have-- my problem
initially was I didn't have an
x when I was trying to find
an antiderivative.
But when I do the change of
variables, I get an e to the
minus r squared.
And then with an r here, that's
much easier to find an
antiderivative.
OK.
So I think that is
where I'll stop.