Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
We've been talking about a bunch
of different integration
techniques.
Here are a couple of examples on
which you can try and pick
out the right technique
to compute these
two integrals with.
So I've got the first one, is
the indefinite integral of x
cubed times the square root
of the quantity x
squared plus 2 dx.
And the second one is
a definite integral.
It's the integral 1 to e of x
squared times the quantity ln
of x squared with
respect to x.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to
compute these two integrals,
come back, and we can compute
them together.
So hopefully you had some luck
working on these integrals.
Let's start with
the first one.
So for question A, let me
just rewrite it here.
We have the integral of x cubed
times the square root of
x squared plus 2 dx.
Now, if you look at this
integral, what you see is a
product of two terms. This
term is x cubed.
It's a nice term.
This one is the square root
of x squared plus 2.
That's not such a nice term.
There are a few different
things you might
think to try here.
So one thing you might think to
try, is this square root of
x squared plus 2 is the sort of
thing that shows up in trig
substitutions.
So that's one thing you might
have in your mind.
Another thing you might have in
your mind, is that this is
a product of two things.
So you might consider the
possibility that you're going
to do an integration
by parts here.
And the third thing you might
have in your mind, is just,
you could just, you know,
this might just be a
substitution situation.
You have this x squared plus 2
as the sort of discrete entity
that shows up there.
So you might try a regular
substitution.
Now you have to, you know, make
a choice among which of
these to try.
And it seems to me that of
those options, a regular
substitution is the
easiest to do.
And you'll find out really
quickly whether you've made
your life horribly complicated
or not.
And frequently, with integration
by parts, if you
have the option of doing a
substitution when you have
integration by parts, you know,
it won't, if do the
substitution, you still can do
integration by parts afterward.
If you do integration by parts
first, you can still do the
substitution afterward.
So trying the substitution
shouldn't hurt us for
integration by parts, and a
regular substitution will be a
lot simpler than a trig
substitution here, right?
Trig substitutions in general
are complicated, so it's a
good idea to see if there's
something simpler that can be
done first.
So if we're going to try regular
substitution, the sort
of natural thing to do, is to
set u equal x squared plus 2.
So in this case, we have
du is equal to 2x dx.
Or--
well, so OK.
So we want to substitute
these things in.
The u is going to go into
the square root term.
So that's going to
be taken care of.
And the dx part-- well, we've
got an x here to pair up with
the dx, so that's going
to give us a du.
And then we'll have x
squared left over.
So we'll need to substitute
in for x squared.
So we're going to use x squared
is equal to u minus 2,
and x dx is equal
to du over 2.
So when we make these
substitutions in here, what we
get it is that this integral is
equal to the integral of--
so it's x squared times the
square root of x squared plus
2 times x dx.
So that's u minus 2 times
the square root of u
times du over 2.
Now, having made the
substitution, we see--
OK.
So with a little bit of
rearrangement, this is just a
sum of powers of u.
Right?
We can rewrite this as the
integral of u to the 3/2 over
2 minus u to the 1/2 du.
And now, this is just
straightforward to integrate.
So it turn out we don't need
integration by parts.
We don't need a trig
substitution.
Just this regular substitution
works nicely.
So we get, well, u to the
3/2, so we compute an
antiderivative, so that
gives us u to the 5/2.
And I have to divide by 5/2, so
I have to multiply by 2/5.
And then I have a half.
So it's u to the 5/2
over 5, minus--
so u to the 1/2, so that gives
me 3/2, so I need minus 2/3 u
to the 3/2.
OK.
And now to finish this off,
I have to do my final back
substitution, and replace
u with x.
So this is going to be x squared
plus 2 over 5 to the
5/2 minus 2/3 times x squared
plus 2 to the 3/2.
All right.
Plus a constant.
Thank you, peanut gallery.
Right.
Indefinite integral, should
have had it right the very
first time I went through.
Plus a constant, both times.
OK.
Good.
So that's all there is for
part A. Now let's look
at part B. So OK.
So part B is a little more
complicated-looking.
Let me copy it over
here again.
So part B, we have the integral
from 1 to e of x
squared times the quantity
ln x squared dx.
So again, there are a couple of
possibilities for what we
could want to do here.
One thing is you could try just
a regular substitution.
So maybe a regular substitution
you might want to
try is u equals ln of x,
or x equals e to the u.
And now if you try that, you
can try it, and what you'll
see, is you'll get something.
So here we have a polynomial
times a function of the
logarithm, a power
of the logarithm.
If you try that substitution,
what you'll end up with is a
polynomial in u times
an exponential in u.
So OK.
So it's not clear that we've won
anything, if we make that
substitution.
The other thing we can try, is
we can try integration by
parts here.
Again, we have a product form.
And if you make that
substitution, you get
polynomial times exponential,
and that's also a promising
place for integration by parts,
after the substitution.
So OK.
So I'm not going to make
the substitution.
I'm just going to go, seeing
this product, I'm going to go
for integration by
parts directly.
So I need to decide what
pieces are which for
integration by parts.
And the thing to remember is
this that-- so I have here a
polynomial times a function
of the logarithm.
And the thing to remember is
that polynomials like to be
differentiated.
That's their preference.
But logarithms really, really
like to be differentiated.
You'd much rather differentiate
a logarithm than
integrate it.
You can integrate
a polynomial--
I mean you can integrate
either of them.
You can integrate
a polynomial.
When you integrate a polynomial,
you get something
that's still a fairly
nice polynomial.
Integrating logarithms
is harder, whereas
differentiating logarithms
makes them into
just powers of x.
So setting this up as an
integration by parts, we're
going to want to take this,
the everything with the
logarithm in it, and that's
the piece we want to
differentiate, to try
and simplify it.
So that's going to
be our u part.
So we're going to try u equals
ln x squared, and that leaves
v prime to be x squared.
So to do integration by parts--
OK.
We need to differentiate and
we need to integrate.
So if I differentiate ln x
squared, I get u prime.
The prime is equal to--
OK.
Well, this is a little
chain rule.
So it's 2 ln x times the
derivative of ln x,
which is 1 over x.
And if I integrate v prime,
I get v is equal to
x cubed over 3.
OK.
So now I use the formula for
integration by parts.
So I have that this integral--
what I'm going to do is I'm
going to call this, let me
give it a name, i.
Now I'm going to come down here
and I'm going to say, i
is equal to--
well, by integration by parts,
it's equal to uv minus the
integral of u prime v dx.
So in our case, uv is x cubed
over 3 times ln x squared.
But the thing to remember is,
this was a definite integral
to start out with.
It's from 1 to e.
So when you take this part out
front, you have to take the
difference of its two values.
So we're going to evaluate this
between x equals 1 and x
equals e, minus the definite
integral--
so we still have a definite
integral from one to e of u
prime v. So that's 2/3--
OK.
So now we have an ln x
over x times x cubed.
So the x and the x cubed, that
cancels 1 power of x out of
the numerator.
So we're left with 2/3
x squared ln x dx.
So.
One thing we see-- this is
just be, this is going to
evaluate to a constant.
We're going to plug in e e, and
we're going to plug in 1,
and we're going to take
the difference.
So that's just some number.
This part is still
some integral.
Are we done yet?
Well, it's not obvious
immediately how
to integrate this.
I mean, I don't already know
off the top of my head what
the antiderivative here is.
On the other hand, it's
definitely simpler than what
we started with, right?
Before we had x squared
ln x squared.
Here we just have
x squared ln x.
So we've simplified
the integrand.
And it's still in a form in
which we can further integrate
by parts, if you wanted to.
Right?
So now in this case the natural
thing to do would be
very similar to what
we did before.
We're going to take the u to be
the ln x, to be the piece
we differentiate, and
we're going to take
the v to be x squared.
OK?
So we can do that.
So this is equal to--
let's see.
I'm going to bring it,
now, upstairs.
So this is equal
to-- all right.
So we plug in e here.
We get e cubed over 3 times
1, minus when we plug in
1, ln of 1 is 0.
So that just gives me
e cubed over 3 for
the first part minus--
all right, and I'm going to
pull the 2/3 out front.
So it's minus 2/3 times--
OK.
So now I'm going to do
an integration by
parts on this one.
So again, like I said,
I'm going to take u
is equal to ln x.
I'm going to take v prime
is equal to x squared.
So that means u prime is equal
to 1 over x and v is equal to
x cubed over 3.
And so again, I get uv, which
is x cubed over 3 ln x, and
again, because it was a definite
integral, I have to
evaluate this between x equals
1 and e, minus--
OK.
So minus the integral of u
prime v. So this is the
integral from 1 to e. u prime
v is 1 over x times x cubed
over 3, so that's x
squared over 3 dx.
OK, so having written all that
down, what you see is this is
a constant minus 2/3.
OK.
This is just some constant.
We'll plug in e, we'll
plug in 1.
That's easy.
And now we have an integral,
and we've
reduced this finally.
Here we have just an integral
of a polynomial.
So an integral of a polynomial,
that's easy to
compute, you can
do it yourself.
And I'm going to let you finish
off the last couple of
steps for yourself.
In the end, the answer should
work out to 5 e cubed over 27
minus 2 over 27.
This is what you should find
the final answer to be when
you work it all out.
So I'll end there.