Welcome back to recitation.
In this video, I want
us to practice
doing integration again.
And so what we're going to do
is two problems. One is a
definite integral, one
is indefinite.
So this integral, we're going to
have, find the value of the
integral minus pi over 4 to pi
over 4 of secant cubed u du,
and then this one, I just want
you to actually just find an
antiderivative, then, for 1
over 2 sine u cosine u.
So why don't you take a while
to work on this, pause the
video, and then when you're
ready, restart the video, and
I will come back and show
you how I did it.
OK.
Welcome back.
So again, we're going to work
on finding, in this one, a
specific number, and in this
one, an antiderivative.
So we'll start off with the
integral from minus pi over 4
to pi over 4 of secant
cubed u du.
And the first thing I'm going
to do, is I'm going to drop
the bounds and just find the
function I need, and then I'll
bring the bounds back in.
I don't want to write the bounds
down at every step.
I'm not doing any substitution,
I don't think.
So I don't need to worry
about if I'm changing
the bounds or not.
So I'll keep the bounds the
same, but I won't write them
down again until near the end.
All right.
So let's look at
this integral.
So the easiest way, I think,
to start an integral like
this, is to split it up
into secant u and then
secant squared u.
Maybe there are some other ways
you did it, but when I
was looking at this problem, the
way I saw was to start off
and write this as secant
u times 1--
oops, let me make sure, yes--
times 1 plus tan squared u du.
Because secant squared
u is equal to 1 plus
tangent squared u.
And what does it do for us?
Well, it partially answers
the question, but not
completely, we'll see.
So what it does first, is it
gives us something we can find
pretty easily.
The first one, we just get the
integral of secant u du.
We know that one.
The second one is a little
harder, because we get the
integral of secant u tangent
squared u du.
And this has promise, but
it's not going to work
for us right away.
Because, you know, the
derivative of tangent is
secant squared, and
the derivative of
secant is secant tangent.
So a substitution won't work in
this case, because neither
one of these functions is a
derivative of the other one.
If I even move off of tangent,
and I have secant tangent
times another tangent, it's
not the right derivative.
A tangent's derivative
is secant squared.
So my main point here is that a
u substitution doesn't work,
or the the substitution
strategy doesn't work.
So what we're going to do, is
we're actually going to take
this part, and make it into an
integration by parts problem.
So this is going to be, I'm
going to stop writing equals
signs, I'm going to figure out
the integral of this one.
So this is a little sidebar, and
I'm going to look at the
integral of secant u
tangent squared u.
And the way I'm going to write
that, is I'm going to write
that as secant u tangent u will
be one function I want.
We'll call that w,
I guess, v prime.
We can use v prime.
And then what the usual thing
we call u, we'll call w.
So tangent u we'll call w.
And I want to write down, I want
to explain to you why I'm
picking these, and sort of where
this is going to get us.
So this is an easy thing to
take an antiderivative of.
Right?
I can take this.
I know v is going
to be secant u.
Because the derivative
of secant u is
secant u tangent u.
And then w is tangent u, w prime
is secant squared u.
So if you think about,
what does an
integration by parts have?
It's going to have vw minus
the integral of v w prime.
That's a lot to take in.
But the point is that that
integral is going to have the
antiderivative of this, which is
secant, and the derivative
of this, which is
secant squared.
So it's going to have
a secant cubed.
Which might seem weird, because
now we're getting back
to what we started with.
But the sign on the secant cubed
is going to be opposite.
Again, this is a
lot of talking.
But let's figure out now.
I just want to show you where
we're headed with this, why I
picked the things I did.
So as I mentioned-- let me
just write these down--
secant u is equal to v,
and secant squared u
is equal to w prime.
Sorry if that looks a little
weird, but that's a u.
OK.
So now let's write this with
an integration by parts.
I get vw, which is secant u
tangent u minus the integral
of vdw, which is secant
cubed u du.
So this is what I was trying
to show you we were
anticipating.
So when I put this all together,
I replace this
integral by these two things.
And what's the point there?
Notice what I have. If I
actually look at the pieces, I
have, up here, I have
a secant cubed u.
It's going to equal secant
u plus this--
I have to evaluate that
as the bounds--
minus this.
So I have the same thing on this
side that I had on the
other side, but with
a minus sign.
So if I add it to the other
side, I'm going
to get two of them.
So this was sort of where
we're headed.
Now let's put it all together.
Let's take it back.
So this stuff here
is that, right?
That's what we did.
I'm going to write just the
important stuff right here.
I've got the integral of secant
cubed u du is equal to
secant u tangent u.
Plus that secant--
I forgot to put that one in, so
let me write in that one.
Plus the integral of secant u
du minus secant cubed u du.
The integral of secant
cubed u du.
OK?
And now I'm going to
work some magic.
I'm actually going to erase
something and move it to the
other side.
So let me sneak an eraser
off screen.
I'm going to add this
to the other side.
And what's going to happen?
I come over here and
I get two of them.
Right?
There was one on this side,
with a minus sign.
I added it, and now I
have two of them.
And now what's the magic?
Well, I just divide
everything by 2.
And so this is going to
be over 2, and this is
going to be over 2.
And now I know what an
antiderivative is.
Notice I haven't put in the plus
C, because I'm about to
put in some bounds.
All right?
And by the way, I know
antiderivative of secant u.
So we'll get to that
in one second.
But hopefully everyone
follows.
I had an integral of secant
cubed u on this side.
I had a minus integral of secant
cubed u over here.
I added it to the other side.
It gave me two of them, so
then I just divided by 2.
All right?
And now let me just explicitly
write down the
last thing we need.
We still need this one.
And this is going to be 1/2
natural log absolute value
secant u plus tangent u.
OK.
So now we just have to evaluate
everywhere and we're done.
So now we have to evaluate
all of this.
Remember, I said I left
out the bounds.
The bounds are pi over 4 minus
pi over 4, pi over 4
minus pi over 4.
All right.
So I'm going to give myself a
little cheat sheet up here,
and then I'm going to write down
the numbers I get here.
So my cheat sheet is to remind
myself that secant of plus or
minus pi over 4 is equal
to square root 2.
Let me just make sure
that's right.
Cosine pi over 4 is 1
over square root 2.
Cosine is even, so plus
or minus pi over
4 will be the same.
Secant is 1 over that,
so I'm good.
Tangent of pi over 4.
Well, tangent is odd, so I
should say plus or minus here,
tangent is odd, so it's going
to be, they're going to have
two different signs.
Tangent pi over 4 is sine pi
over 4 over cosine pi over 4.
It's the same value there.
So it's 1.
So tangent plus or minus pi
over 4 is plus or minus 1.
So that's what we're
working with.
So now let's start
plugging in.
Secant pi over 4 tangent pi
over 4 gives me root 2
times 1 over 2.
So I get root 2 over 2,
is the first thing.
So I have to write--
this equals is from here.
So I have root 2 over 2.
And then secant minus pi over
4 is again root 2, tangent
minus pi over 4 is minus 1.
So I have minus, I have a
negative here, and then I have
a 1 here, or a root 2 here,
negative 1 over 2.
So I get another negative,
so I have a plus.
So one negative came from, I was
using the lower bound, and
one negative came from
the tangent.
That gave me a plus.
And then I have plus 1/2.
Well, again.
Natural log of secant pi over
4 is going to be-- so I'm
going to have natural log of
root 2 plus 1, and I'm going
to have a natural log
of root 2 minus 1.
And I'm going to have a negative
in between them.
So I'm going to work a
little magic here.
It's going to be natural
log of 2 plus 1 over
root 2 minus 1.
Now, just to point out, where
did that come from?
That came from putting in root
2 for both of the pi over 4s
and minus pi over 4.
Tangent pi over 4
was the plus 1.
Tangent of negative pi over
4 was the minus 1.
How do I get this division?
I had natural log of something
minus natural log
of something else.
So in the end, I get root 2 plus
1/2 natural log absolute
root 2 plus 1 over
root 2 minus 1.
All right.
That is part A. So part
A, let me just remind
you, what did we do?
We had secant cubed u.
We did a substitution for one
of the, for secant squared.
We got something we could deal
with, and something that
didn't look so promising, but
once we did an integration by
parts, we were back to
what we started with,
with a different sign.
So we moved it to
the other side.
We were basically able to solve
for secant cubed u.
So we got all the way
through, and then
we just had to evaluate.
So the big step was, once you
were here, knowing an
integration by parts actually
would save you.
That's sort of the hard
thing to see.
Takes a little while to
see that one, maybe.
All right.
So now the next one.
If we come back here, we're
trying to find an
antiderivative of 1 over
2 sine u cosine u.
And there may be some other ways
to do this, but actually,
this problem, part of the reason
I wanted to do this
problem, was I wanted to remind
you that it's good to
know some of the basic
trigonometric identities,
because it'll make your
life a lot easier.
So this integral is actually the
same as is the integral of
du over sine 2u.
And the reason is, there's a
trigonometric identity that
says, 2 sine u cosine u
is equal to sine 2u.
So I wanted to give you a reason
for why we know those,
why we know some of those
identities, and you end up in
these situations.
There might be other ways to
handle this one, but the
easiest, most direct way
is if you do this.
You change it so that b is
actually the same thing as
integral of du over sine 2u.
So it's just a straight up
double angle formula, you can
call it if you need
a fancy name.
And now what is this?
Well, this is equal to the
integral of what's 1 over
sine, is going to be cosecant.
Cosecant 2u du.
And we know the antiderivative
to cosecant u.
We know that that's going to
be negative natural log of
cosecant u plus cotangent u.
But the problem is,
when there's a 2
there, what do we do?
Well, just think about it as, if
you had the antiderivative,
you know by the chain rule,
if you just put in two u's
everywhere there was a u when
you took the derivative, you
would end up with an
extra 2 in front.
So you have to, basically
you have to just
put in 1/2 in front.
You could do a substitution to
check this, but it's really
straightforward to say, this
antiderivative is equal to
negative 1/2 natural log
absolute cosecant 2u plus
cotangent 2u.
Now that I have that written
out, I'll just point out
again, if there was no 2 here,
the 1/2 wouldn't be here, and
we'd just have cosecant u
cotangent u inside here.
But once we have to have the 2
to get a cosecant 2u in the
end, we also need to divide by
2 to kill it off when we take
a derivative.
The chain rule would give
us a 2 in front, so the
1/2 kills it off.
So we don't end up with, you
know, with this not here, the
derivative of this
is 2 cosecant 2u.
So we divide by 2,
then we get it.
We get the right answer.
So this one--
you know, I'm not intentionally
trying to trick you.
I just want to point out that
it's good to know some of
these trigonometric
identities.
It makes solving these
problems a lot
easier to deal with.
So the main point of this one
was actually knowing the
identity, in my mind.
Maybe you found another
way to do it.
Probably it didn't take
two lines, though.
So if you found other way to
do it, actually, it's good.
It's creative.
And I like that.
But I was hoping to convince you
that sometimes it's simple
to know a few of these
identities.
And that is where I will stop.