Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've learned a
whole bunch of different
integration techniques.
So I have here a couple of
problems that will give you an
opportunity to apply those
techniques, and figure out
which ones to apply.
So in particular I have one
definite integral, the
integral 0 to 2 of the quantity
x times e to the 1
minus x squared with
respect to x.
And the second one is an
indefinite integral of 2 arc
tan x divided by x squared
with respect to x.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to work
these out, come back, and we
can work them out together.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you had some luck
working on these integrals.
Let's get started.
We can do the first one first,
and then we'll go on to the
second one.
So here we want to compute the
integral from 0 to 2 of x e to
the 1 minus x squared dx.
So in order to do this,
we have to, you know--
well, we could look at it and
say, do I know the answer
immediately, off the
top of my head?
And this is not one of the, you
know, ones that we have
immediately already memorized
a formula for.
So then you say, OK.
So now I need to do something
in order to try
to integrate it.
And so, you know, you have a
whole bunch of techniques.
And for this one, when you look
at it, the technique that
is going to work for you is just
the simplest technique
that you have, which is just a
straightforward substitution.
And one way to figure that out,
is that you can look at
this and you can see that here
we have a composition of
functions, this e to the 1
minus x squared, and so
whenever you have a composition
of functions,
there's the opportunity for
there to have been a chain
rule somewhere.
And in this case, we see that
this composition of functions
is multiplied by x, and x is
very closely related to the
derivative of 1 minus
x squared.
So that's what's suggesting for
us a nice substitution.
And so the substitution we're
going to try, then, is that
we're going to put this inside
function, this 1 minus x
squared, we're going to
set u equal to that.
So, all right.
So this is equal to-- so
I'm going to say, u
equal 1 minus x squared.
So now if I take a differential,
if u equals 1
minus x squared, that means
that du is minus 2x dx.
And since this is a definite
integral, I also need to
change the bounds
of integration.
So when x is equal to 0, that
means that u is equal to,
well, 1 minus 0 squared is 1,
so that's the lower bound.
And when x is equal to 2, that
means that u is equal to 1
minus 2 squared, which
is negative 3.
So we make these
substitutions.
OK.
So what does our integral
become?
So this becomes the integral--
so now the lower bound becomes
u equals 1, and the upper
bound is u equals negative 3.
OK.
So now e to the 1 minus
x squared, that's
just e to the u.
And x dx--
well, that's almost du.
It's du divided by negative 2.
So du divided by negative 2.
So we make the substitution.
We transform our integral
to this form.
Now, this is a very nice,
simple integral, right?
This is just the integral of e
to the u with a, you know, a
constant multiple.
So, OK.
So we can do this right away.
So this is--
I'll pull the minus
1/2 out in front.
And now fundamental theorem
of calculus.
Antiderivative of the e to
the u is just e to the u.
And I have to take that
between my bounds.
So between u equals 1 and
u equals minus 3.
So notice that because we
changed bounds, we don't have
to go back and convert
everything back to x.
We can just plug in directly.
So OK.
So we plug in directly.
What do I get?
So first I get minus
1/2 times--
all right, so I'll just pull
the constant out in front.
So the first term is e to the
minus third minus e to the 1.
OK.
And if I wanted to, I could
rewrite this as e minus e to
the minus 3 over 2, or in
a variety of other ways.
All right.
So this one was a pretty
straightforward integration by
substitution, definite integral,
change bounds, and
at the end you get
this answer.
So let's take a look
at the second one.
So the second one is a bit
trickier, I think, and it
requires a bit more work.
So here it is.
Let me rewrite it.
So it's the antiderivative of 2
arc tan x over x squared dx.
So we have here an
antiderivative
that we have to compute.
And this is a kind of
messy-looking expression that
we're working with.
All right?
So this is not very pleasant.
So there are a couple of
different things we could
think to do.
So one thing that you could
think to do is you could say,
I really don't like arc tan.
I'm going to try and
get rid of arc tan.
And the way I'm going to get rid
of arc tan is by doing a
substitution, u equals arc
tan x, or x equals tan u.
So if you do that, that'll
get rid of your inverse
trigonometric function, but
it'll introduce, in the
bottom, you have this x squared,
so that'll introduce
like a tan u squared,
and dx will give you
some more trig functions.
So what you'll be left
with, then-- so this
will be u on top.
So you'll have u times a product
of trig functions.
So I guess it's up to you
whether you think that a
polynomial, or a power of
u times a bunch of trig
functions, is simpler
than an inverse trig
function times a power.
It's not clear to me that it's
actually that much simpler.
And in any case, we wouldn't
sort of be
finished at that stage.
There would still be a fair
amount more work to do.
So we can think about, what
other things could we do?
That's kind of the only obvious
substitution here.
But another thing that suggests
itself, is that we
could try an integration
by parts.
And one reason is, this is
a product of things.
You know, here it's arc 10x
times 1 over x squared.
And arc 10x is something that
works nicely with integration
by parts if you can
differentiate it.
Right?
So inverse trigonometric
functions behave like
logarithms with respect to
integration by parts.
By which I mean, they really
like to be differentiated.
Because when you differentiate
an arc tan, you get something
much simpler.
Well, simpler, anyhow.
Maybe not much simpler.
You get 1 over 1
plus x squared.
So if you can apply integration
by parts and
differentiate the arc tan, that
makes your life nice.
And so, then, in order for that
to work, you need for
everything else to be
something you can
antidifferentiate, and here
everything else is just 2 over
x squared, and so that's
something that
we know how to integrate.
It's easy to do.
So, OK.
So let's give that
a try, then.
So we're going to do integration
by parts, so I'm
going to set you equal
to arc tan x.
So that means u prime is equal
to 1 over 1 plus x squared.
And I'm going to let v prime
equal, well, I guess I have to
pick up the 2 somewhere, so I
might as well pick it up here.
2 over x squared.
And so then v, so I integrate
2 over x squared, so that
gives me x to the minus
1, with a minus sign.
So it's minus 2 over x.
So these are u, u prime,
v and v prime.
So now OK, so now I apply
integration by parts, and that
tells me this is equal to--
well, let's see.
So it's uv, which is minus
2 arc tan x over x.
That's uv. Minus the integral
of, now what the second part
is, v u prime dx.
So here v u prime is--
well, OK.
So they're minus 2.
I'm going to pull
that out front.
So it's plus 2--
all right.
And then the rest of it
is 1 over x times 1
plus x squared dx.
So if you apply integration by
parts, you have the uv stuff
that gets kicked out out front,
and then what you're
left with is this
second integral.
Now this is, to me this is
simpler-looking than what we
started with.
It's still not simple,
but it's simpler.
So it seems to me that, you
know, having reached this
stage, we can say, OK.
We've made some progress, and
now we have to keep going.
Right?
So it's not obvious to me what
the antiderivative of this
expression should be.
So how can I figure that out?
Well, there are a couple of
different options here.
One thing you might look
at this and see,
is you might see--
again, I have a 1 plus x squared
in the denominator,
and so that might make you
tempted to do a trig
substitution again.
And in fact, you could do a
trig substitution here.
You could put x equal tan theta,
and you would be able
to solve the question
like this.
But I don't think it's the
simplest way to go.
Because in addition--
well, on the one hand, this has
this 1 plus x squared in
the denominator, but on the
other hand, this is just a
rational function.
Yeah?
It's a ratio of two
polynomials.
The polynomial on top is just
1, and the polynomial on the
bottom is this product, x
times 1 plus x squared.
And so whenever you have a
rational function that you're
trying to integrate, you
can also always use--
what's it called--
partial fraction
decomposition.
So we can try to use partial
fractions on the second
expression.
And so I think I'd like
to do it that way.
So let's do that.
Let's do it down here.
So partial fractions on
the quantity 1 over x
times 1 plus x squared.
So if you remember your partial
fractions here, this
is completely factored.
This quadratic doesn't factor.
It doesn't have any real
roots, doesn't factor.
So OK, so we have a single
linear term, and a single
non-factorable quadratic term.
So partial fractions tells us
that we can write this in the
form a over x plus-- and now
because the second term is
quadratic, it needs to be bx
plus c over 1 plus x squared.
Right?
So when you have a quadratic
in the bottom, you get two
constants up at the top,
a linear polynomial.
And then you can always check.
You have three constants here,
and the degree of the
denominator is 3, so that's
one way of checking that
you're not completely off base,
that the degree down
here should always agree with
the number of constants that
you're solving for.
OK.
Good.
So now we need to solve
this for a, b, and c.
And so OK, because we have
this nice single linear
factor, we can do the cover
up method there.
So we cover up x, and we cover
up over x, and we cover up
everything else.
So on the right hand side, we
just end up with a, and on the
left hand side, well, so x.
So that's what we need, we
get whatever when we
plug in x equals 0.
So on this side, we get 1
over 1 plus 0 squared,
so that's just 1.
So the cover up method gives
us that a is equal to 1.
And now we need to solve
for b and c.
And probably the most
straightforward way, in this
case, to solve for b and
c, is you can always
just multiply through.
And if you multiply through--
OK.
So we'll multiply through
on the left hand.
We'll clear denominator, we'll
multiply through by x times 1
plus x squared.
So on the left we'll
get just 1.
On the right--
OK.
So we multiply a over x times
x times 1 plus x squared, so
that gives us a times 1 plus x
squared, but we know that a is
1, so this is-- the first term
becomes 1 plus x squared, and
the second term we multiply
through by x times 1 plus x
squared, and the 1 plus x
squareds cancel, and we're
left with plus x times
bx plus c.
Now, if you, maybe you could
at this point, there are a
number of different
ways to finish.
But one, for example, is you
could see, all right, if you
subtract the 1 plus x squared
over to the other side, you
have minus x squared, and
over here, you have bx
squared plus cx.
So for those things to be
equal, you need b to be
negative 1, and you
need c to be 0.
Right?
So OK.
So good.
So we have b equals minus
1, c equals 0.
So the partial fraction
decomposition, then, if we
plug this in, is 1 over x minus
x over 1 plus x squared.
So this is the partial fraction
decomposition of this
rational function.
So you apply that partial
fraction decomposition.
What do you do?
All right, So now you carry
that back upstairs to the
integral we were working on.
So our integral that we started
with is equal to,
now-- well, so this constant
is still out in front.
So it's minus 2 arc tan
x over x plus--
so now we've got 2 times--
all right.
So first, this is just algebra
that we've done, so we can
just substitute it in.
So we replace this 1 over x
times 1 plus x squared by 1
over x minus x over 1
plus x squared dx.
OK.
And now using the properties
of integration, this is a
difference of two--
an integral of a difference
is the
difference of the two integrals.
So we just integrate them
separately, right?
So this is equal to--
so OK, the part
out front never changes.
2 arc tan x over x,
plus 2 times--
OK.
So you integrate 1 over x, and
that just gives you ln of
absolute value of x.
And OK, so you integrate, so
the second part is x over 1
plus x squared.
Now, in the worst case, we would
need to do some more
work on this term and
split things up.
And one of them, we might
have to complete
the square or something.
But in this case, it actually
has worked out kind of nicely.
This x over 1 plus x squared is
a simple thing to handle.
That's just ln of 1
plus x squared.
Well, actually, 1/2 ln
of 1 plus x squared.
So this is minus 1/2 ln
I could write absolute value,
but 1 plus x squared is always
positive, so it doesn't
matter if I do or not.
And if I wanted, I could
rewrite this a bit.
I could rewrite this as-- just
to finish it, I could write 2
arc tan x over x plus 2 ln
absolute value of x minus ln
of 1 plus x squared.
And I was doing an
antiderivative.
So at some point, whenever I
finished the last one, I
should have added a constant.
So this should have had a plus
c here, and it should have a
plus c there.
Right, good.
So OK, so there's my answer.
And let's just recap quickly
how we arrived at it.
So we started with
this integral.
And we saw, we recognized it
as a good candidate for
integration by parts, and so
we applied integration by
parts, seeing that the arc tan
part was the part that really
wanted to be differentiated, and
that the 1 over x squared
part, you know, it could have
been differentiated, it
could've been integrated, but
since the arc tan wanted to be
differentiated, this
got integrated.
Good.
So we did integration by parts,
and then we're left
with a rational function as the
piece of the integral we
had left to compute.
So when you have a rational
function, one method that
always works is that you can
do partial fractions.
Now, in this case, this was
a fairly simple partial
fractions to do.
First of all, the degree of the
numerator was smaller than
the degree of the denominator,
so we didn't have to divide by
anything, you know, we didn't
have to do long division.
And the denominator had a fairly
simple form, so we
could just do the cover up
method, and then multiply
through and be done
fairly quickly.
But in any case.
So we did, we applied partial
fractions, so we got this
expression.
So then we carried that back
up to our integral, and
integrated.
OK, so then we had this integral
with the partial
fraction expression in it, and
that was easy to integrate.
So in this case, quite
easy to integrate.
Sometimes it's a little messier,
but we came out
pretty luckily this time.
So OK.
And so there you go.
So that's going to be
our final answer.
Now, this was long
and complicated.
And so sometimes, when you
do a long and complicated
computation, you worry,
did I make any stupid
mistakes along the way?
One way to check, always, when
you've done an antiderivative,
is you could always check, you
could take the derivative of
this expression.
So that'll require you to use
some product rule and some
chain rule.
IBut, you know, arithmetically
a little difficult, but not
sort of intellectually, right?
You just are applying rules
sort of automatically.
So you can take the derivative
of this expression, and check
to make sure that it actually
agrees with the thing that we
started with.
So good.
I'll end there.