We have two coaxial solenoids,
and they each have N windings,
they each have length l, and one
has radius r1, which is a,
and the other a radius
r2, which is b.
They are in series.
That means if they're in series,
that the current that
goes through is exactly
the same.
However, they are wound in such
a way that the magnetic
field in one is exactly
opposing the magnetic
field in the other.
As we have just seen, the
magnetic field in one solenoid
is independent of r.
It is mu 0 times N times the
current through one winding
divided by l, independent
of r.
The magnetic field for both
solenoids is identical, except
that they are in opposite
directions.
This screams for a superposition
solution.
If I look from above--
so this is the solenoid with
radius b, and this is the
solenoid with radius a--
the magnetic field in this
solenoid, of the inside
solenoid, is pointing inwards,
and there is no magnetic field
through a good approximation
outside the solenoid.
The magnetic field of the
solenoid with radius b is
everywhere inside at the same
strength as a magnetic field
inside this inner solenoid.
The b here we assume to a good
approximation is zero, and the
b outside this one is also zero,
due to the current of
the inner solenoid and not
due to the current
of the outer solenoid.
The answer to what the magnetic
field is quite simple.
The magnetic field is only
non-zero when r is less than b
and larger than a.
That is the value that you see
here, and b is 0 here, because
the two fields cancel each
other, and b also 0 outside,
so the b is only non-zero
in this hashed area.
It's very interesting.
You have a doughnut type
of magnetic field.
The next question is what
is the self-inductance?
L times I equals magnetic flux,
and the magnetic flux is
always peculiarly defined
in a solenoid.
You have to make this open
surface, which I have
discussed with you before.
It is a spiral case surface,
which is very hard to see, but
think of a spiral case that you
may know somewhere, and
think of the surface of that
spiral case, the steps.
That is an open surface, and it
is attached to that closed
loop wire through the
self-inductance, which, of
course has to return somehow
to the other sides.
The magnetic flux, the magnetic
field, penetrates
that staircase surface N times
if you have N windings, and
that's the way you should
really think of this.
When r equals less than a, the
magnetic flux is obviously
zero, because there's
no magnetic field.
The only magnetic flux that is
non-zero is the one going
through the [UNINTELLIGIBLE], so
that is when r equals less
than b and larger than a.
There the magnetic flux equals
N, the number of winding,
times the magnetic field going
through each one of those
staircase surfaces times the
cross-sectional area where the
magnetic field exists, and
that is this hashed area.
I find LI, which is this phi.
I get an N squared now, because
b has an N in it.
I have an I, I have a mu
0, and I have an L--
that's the b field-- and then
the area equals pi times b
squared minus a squared.
Obviously, I lose my I, because
L is only purely a
matter of geometry.
If you look at this, you will
see that only geometry
plays a role here.
Keep in mind that the b is
0 right here at the core.