Problem number one is a huge
solenoid, one that is used for
nuclear magnetic resonance.
It has a cross-sectional
circular radius of 0.5 meters,
it has a huge length of 2.5
meters, so that the whole body
can go in there.
It is used for medical
purposes.
The magnetic field
is quite strong.
It is half a Tesla.
It's a huge machine.
The first question is
how much energy is
stored in that machine?
The magnetic energy per cubic
meter, joules per cubic meter,
is given by this relationship,
and you have seen
this several times.
If I multiply this by the volume
of the solenoid, then I
should get the total energy.
I've made the assumption,
then, which is an
approximation, that the magnetic
field is constant in
the solenoid, it's zero outside,
and it's also zero
outside near the ends of
the solenoid, which
we know is not true.
This is a reasonable
approximation.
The volume equals pi r
squared, which is the
cross-section through the
solenoid, and the
length equals l.
I put in the numbers, and I find
very roughly 2 times 10
to the sixth joules.
This you should consider as
a somewhat rough answer.
How much current goes around a
ring which has a width of 1
centimeter?
We'll have to revisit the
solenoids, and go back to some
earlier calculations that
we have made to
refresh your memory.
Let's suppose this solenoid
has length l, it has N
windings, and the current
through each winding is I, and
we don't know either
one of them.
We make the assumption, perhaps
a little bit naive,
that the magnetic field only
exists inside the solenoid,
and that it is constant and that
it is this 1/2 ampere--
not ampere, 1/2 tesla.
I now use Ampere's Law to
calculate this magnetic field
in a way that you have
seen many times.
I take a closed loop.
Let this length be y, and
this length be y.
This is very far away.
I assume the magnetic field is
always in this direction, and
so when I calculate the dot
product from Ampere's Law,
integral B dot dl, I only have
a contribution through this
part, because B is perpendicular
here to dl
inside the solenoid.
It's also perpendicular
to dl here.
Here the magnetic field is very
weak, and certainly when
we take this very far out,
the contribution is
approximately zero.
I would only get, then, if I
go around this closed-loop
circle in this direction, I
would get only v times y.
That equals I through
this open surface.
This is mu 0 times I through
plus mu 0 times the
displacement current.
Don't confuse this with DC,
which is the displacement
current, and there is no
displacement current.
Now comes the question, how
many times does this I go
through this surface?
It penetrates through this
surface many times, so we get
B times y equals mu 0, and y
divided by l times N is the
number of times that it
penetrates through this
surface at these locations times
I. I find that IN equals
B times l divided by mu 0.
You realize, of course,
that the y cancels.
If you wanted to the equation in
terms of B, then you would
have mu 0 time N times
I divided by l.
This, by the way, would mean,
just to give you some feeling
for it, that if--
I'm not saying that's the
case, but if I were 100
amperes, then it would mean that
N would be very roughly
10 to the 4 windings, because
when I calculate IN, I know B,
I know l, and I know mu
0, so I find very
roughly 10 to the 6 amperes.
That's the meaning of IN the
way I have derived it.
Now, I'm going to look at this
cylinder, not as individual
windings, but I'm going to
look at it literally as a
shell cylinder open here, with
length l, and there is this
combined current going through
all these end wires.
They're going around and around
and around, making this
magnetic field like so.
Suppose I took a knife, and
I cut through here.
I really don't want to cut, but
I want to have a surface
here that cuts here through
all these currents that go
through here N times.
What, then, is the total
current that goes
through that sheet?
Well, that, of course, is
10 to the sixth amperes.
I just calculated it.
Now, I don't take a length l,
but I take something more
modest: I take a ring of which
this is only 1 centimeter, and
now I want to calculate how much
current goes through that
1 centimeter, so it's
immediately obvious that it is
10 to the sixth amperes divided
by 250, and that is 4
times 10 to the 3 amperes, going
only through this ring,
which has a thickness
of 1 centimeter.
Professor Bertschinger is now
asking you what is the outside
force on this 1 centimeter
ring?
I would like to make a
picture from above.
This is this ring, and it has
a thickness of 1 centimeter
going into the paper.
It has a current going in this
direction, and the magnetic
field, which we have assumed
was pointing upwards, is
inside B. This is a half
Tesla B field.
We know that the dF equals I
times dl cross B. It is a
cross product.
If I take here a little element
dl, in that I'm always
in the direction of the current,
then you can check
for yourself that the dl
cross B is a force
that is pointing outwards--
it's a little force dF--
and that force will be radially
pointing outwards
everywhere.
This radius will be little r.
Even though the net force on
these ring is zero, because
all these forces average out
to be 0, I'm sure that
Professor Bertschinger had in
mind that he wanted you to
integrate over the a
circumference 2 pi r the force
sort of like this.
I don't quite know how
to express it.
I would have phrased just
slightly differently, but I
think his intentions
are quite clear.
What that would mean is that the
total force, if you add up
all those radial force outwards,
would be I, which is
in this ribbon of 1 centimeter
times 2 pi r, which is the
circumference times
B. That's this B,
because the cross product--
you can forget the cross,
because the I and B aren't at
90 degree angles with respect
to each other.
We know that this value is 4
times 10 to the third, we know
2 pi r and B, and you
find 6,280 newtons.
This value, however, is
definitely too high, because I
have assumed now that the
individual windings of the
solenoids are all completely
emerged in that field of half
tesla, and that's
not the case.
Outside the solenoids, through
reasonable approximation, the
magnetic field is zero.
Inside the solenoid,
it is half tesla.
It is more reasonable, as is
suggested by Professor
Bertschinger to choose for a
mean magnetic field half the
value of the field inside.
Instead of half tesla, we should
take one quarter tesla.
Therefore, the actual force
that you would experience,
then, is this value
divided by 2.
This is the sum, then, of all
these forces as they are
pointing outwards.
A more reasonable question
is what is the
pressure on this ring?
Pressure, equal the force,
divided by the area.
The force is now 3,140 newtons,
which is half of
6,280, and I must multiply
that by 2 pi r, the
circumference of the ring.
The ring has a height
of 1 centimeter.
I work in mks units, and I find
10 to the 5 newtons per
square meter, which
is 1 atmosphere.
This is an overpressure.
Clearly, the air pressure
outside and inside the
solenoid is 1 atmosphere.
As a result of this current and
this magnetic field which
produced by the current, there
is an overpressure over and
above the equilibrium, 1
atmosphere in, and 1
atmosphere out, which
is trying to
blow this magnet apart.
One atmosphere is quite
a pressure.
There's 1 atmosphere pressure
on your hands, which is 10
newtons for every square
centimeter.
Or I like to think in kilogram
forces, so 1 kilogram force
for every square centimeter.
Why don't you implode?
Because there is equilibrium
inside your body, and the
pressure is also 1 atmosphere,
so you do not implode.
If you take a metal can, you
close it properly, and you
suck out the air, then the metal
can will implode, as you
saw last year during
a wonderful
demonstration in 8.01.
The outside force, the
1 kilogram per square
centimeter, is not compensated
by a similar pressure from
inside, because you're sucking
the air out, so this
atmospheric pressure can
sometimes be very, very
noticeable.
In the case of the magnet, the
magnet will experience an
overpressure from inside
out of 1 atmosphere.
Now you're being asked, or
you're being told, that the
magnetic energy density, which
has the dimensions joules per
square meter--
a joule is a newton meter per
cubic meter, so a joule is
also newtons per
square meter--
that this has the same
dimensions as that.
If you do calculate 1/2 B
squared divided by mu 0,
which, in this case, is
easy because B is
constant in the solenoid.
If B is not constant, then
it's a little harder.
You put in the numbers for B
and for mu 0, what do find?
Lo and behold: you find
the same 2.5--
10 to the power of 5.
So again, you find the
same 1 atmosphere.
In this case, the magnetic
energy density is exactly the
same as the overpressure that
the solenoid will experience.