NIKOLA KAMBUROV: Hi, guys.
Today we're going to see how one
can use linear algebra to
describe graphs and networks.
In particular, we'll do
the following problem.
We're given this very simple
graph here with five
nodes and six edges.
We've already labeled
them, and we've put
directions on the edges.
And we are asked to write down
the incidence matrix, A, and
then to compute its kernel and
the kernel of A transpose.
And finally, we're asked to
compute the trace of A
transpose A.
I'll give you a few moments to
try the problem on your own.
And then you'll see
my take on it.
Hello again.
OK, so let's first recall what
an incidence matrix is.
So an incidence matrix is
supposed to encode how the
nodes connect to the edges.
In particular, it has as many
rows as there are edges and as
many columns as there
are nodes.
And we're going to
fill in the rows.
And we'll fill them
out as follows.
So we're going to use only
negative 1, 1, and 0.
And we're going to put a
negative 1 in entry i and 1 in
entry j if the corresponding
edge connects
node i to node j.
OK, let me just do
it concretely.
So let's look at
edge number 1.
So it corresponds to
the first row.
It connects 1 to 2.
So we have a negative
1 and a 1.
Then edge number 2, it connects
node 2 to 3, so
negative 1, 1.
Edge number 3 connects node
1 to 3, so negative 1, 1.
And I believe you get
the picture, right?
So I'm just going to fill out
the rest of the entries.
All right, 4 is--
negative 1, to 1.
5 is--
well, 4, well, negative
1, 1 here.
And 6 is negative 1 and 1.
OK.
So we've constructed the matrix
A. Now, we'll compute
its null space.
And we're going to do it without
performing any row
operations whatsoever.
So in order to do this, it's
helpful to look at the graph
as an electric circuit and to
assign to each of the nodes an
electric potential.
If we collect all the electric
potentials in a vector x, then
A times x is a vector with as
many entries as there are
edges and gives precisely the
potential differences across
the edges of the graph.
OK, so then if Ax is to be 0,
this means that across the
graph, across all the edges of
the graph, all potential
differences are 0.
Therefore, all the potentials
at all the nodes need to be
equal to a constant number.
So therefore, we conclude that
the null space of A is spanned
by constant 1.
OK?
There are five 1's here,
corresponding to the five nodes.
Now what about the null
space of A transpose?
Adopt this analogy with
electric circuits.
But this time, we're going to
look at currents flowing
across the edges of the graph.
Oh, and we are going to adopt
the following convention for
the currents.
So a current is going to be
positive if it flows in the
direction of the edge and
negative if it flows in the
opposite direction.
Right.
So then what is A transpose y,
where y is a vector, each of
whose entries is a current
on the edge?
Well, the entries of A transpose
y are precisely
equal to the total current
flowing through each of the
nodes of the graph.
So A transpose y being equal
to 0 means that there is a
balance in the circuit, that the
currents that flow through
into each node equal the
currents that flow out of it.
Right.
And it's fairly easy to find
such a configuration of
currents that satisfies
this balance equation.
We do it by flowing around
loops of the graph.
So you see this graph
has three loops.
The first one is this
triangle up there.
The second one is this square.
And I'm just, by this curled
direction, I'm signifying in
which way I'm going
to trace the loop.
And there, the third loop
is along the outer
contour of the graph.
But in fact, the third one
can be thought of as a
superposition of these
two, and I'll
explain why in a second.
So let's figure out the
configuration of currents that
balances these loops.
So if we flow a current 1 from 1
to 2 and then flow a current
of 1 along edge 2, from 2 to 3,
and then we flow a current
of negative 1, mind that the
direction is opposite to the
direction of the loop, then
we're going to have a balanced
configuration of currents.
So let me write this down.
The following configuration,
so 1 along edge 1, 1 along
edge 2, and negative 1 along
edge 3, and the rest 0, is a
solution to A transpose y.
Let's see what solution we get
by flowing around the loop in
the square.
Well, we flow a current of 1
along edge 4, current of 1
along edge 5, current of 1 along
edge 6, and current of
negative 1 along edge 2.
So let's be careful.
So it was 0, then along
edge 2 was negative 1.
Along 3 is 0, along 4, 1,
along 5, 1, along 6, 1.
Now we can do the same thing
with the big loop and produce
a vector corresponding to it.
And I prompt you to do it.
But what you'll see is that
the vector that you get is
precisely a sum of these
two vectors.
In a way, the big loop
is a superposition
of the small loops.
OK, so we figured out what the
null space of A transpose is.
And now, let's concentrate our
attention on finding the trace
of A transpose A. We're going
to do it right here.
So the trace of a matrix
is the sum of
its diagonal entries.
And we've seen this many times
already, that the diagonal
entries of A transpose A are
precisely the magnitudes
squared of the columns
of A. OK?
So the 1, 1 entry is the
magnitude squared
of the first column.
The 2, 2 entry is the magnitude
squared of the
second column, and so on.
Now what is the magnitude
squared of a column of an
incidence matrix?
Well, each entry in a column
of an incidence matrix is
either 1, negative 1, or 0.
So when we square these entries,
we get 1's or 0's.
And when we add them up, we get
precisely a number which
is the nontrivial entries
in that column.
OK?
So the magnitude squared of the
column is the number of
nontrivial entries in it.
But if we go back to the matrix
A, and we count the
number of non-zero entries, this
is precisely the number
of edges that connect
with a node.
OK, so the number of edges that
connects with each node
is called the degree
of the node.
In this way, trace of A
transpose A will be just the
sum of the degrees of the
graph in the picture.
So we have there are 2 edges
connecting to 1, so 2, plus 3
edges connecting to 2, 3
edges connecting to 3.
And we've got a 2 for the number
of edges connecting to
4, and 2 for the number of
edges connecting to 5.
So altogether, we get 12.
So you see, in this problem,
we computed certain linear
algebra objects without
performing the usual algebraic
operations, but just by looking
at the graph and
seeing how the linear algebra
is encoded in it.
I hope it was most
illuminating.
I'll see you next time.