DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
I'd like to work this problem
with you in which we're going
to use determinants to compute
the area of a parallelogram
sitting in a plane.
So why don't you take a moment
to, why don't you take some
time to work this out, and we'll
check back and you can
see how I did it.
OK, so let's get started
on this problem.
Now the first thing that we need
to be careful about with
this problem is, we know that we
want to take a determinant,
but we need to be careful.
Determinants of pairs of
vectors make sense.
Determinants of points
do not make sense.
So here we have these four
points, which are the
endpoints of the
parallelogram.
And what we need to do from
these four points is get some
vectors that we can
compute with.
So over here, I have taken the
vectors which connect the
endpoints of the
parallelogram.
So you'll see that this 6, 1
here, this vector 6, 1 is
coming from the point
1, 1 in the original
parallelogram and 7, 2.
So this vector 6, 1 is just the
difference of 7, 2 and the
point 1, 1.
And similarly 5, 2 here is the
difference of our original
point 6, 3 and our
base point 1, 1.
So now that we have these two
vectors, the area of our
parallelogram is just
going to be the
determinant of our two vectors.
Well, we'd better be careful.
It's going to be plus or minus
the determinant is
going to be the area.
So let's compute this
determinant.
So we find 6 times 2 minus 5--
so we get 12 minus 5--
is 7.
Now we got a positive number,
and so this plus or minus we
take to be positive.
Had we computed our determinant
by transposing the
rows here, then we might have
found a negative seven, and of
course we want our area to be
positive, so we would just
choose seven.
So, let me just go through the
one tricky part of this
problem is the original
endpoints of our parallelogram
are not what are important
for the area.
What's important is the vectors
which connect the two
of our endpoints together.
And so we computed those 6, 1
and 5, 2, and then taking
their determinant gives us the
area of the parallelogram.
OK, I'll leave it at that.