PROFESSOR: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, we're going to take
a look at first-order linear
differential equations with
constant coefficients.
And specifically, we're going to
use integrating factors to
solve them.
So the equation that we're going
to solve today is x dot
plus kx equals 1.
And then in part B we're going
to change the right-hand side
to e to the minus 5t.
And then in part C, we're asked
to use the superposition
principle to solve x dot plus
kx equals 4 plus 7e
to the minus 5t.
So I'll let you think about this
for a moment, and I'll
come back in a second.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So I should mention that every
first-order linear
differential equation, whether
it has constant coefficients
or not, can always be solved
using an integrating factor.
However, in this case, we have
a constant coefficient, which
is particularly nice.
And later on in the course,
we're going to learn some even
better ways, or quicker ways,
to solve linear differential
equations with constant
coefficients.
But for today, we're asked to
use an integrating factor.
So for part A, we have
the equation x dot
plus kx equals 1.
And the first step
is to compute
the integrating factor.
So the integrating factor, which
I'll call g of t, it's
always going to be an
exponential of the integral of
the function that appears
in front of x.
So in this case, the function
is just a constant.
It's k.
So we have kdt, which gives
us e to the kt.
So once we have the integrating
factor, we just
multiply our equation
through by g of t.
And by construction, what the
integrating factor does is it
lets us combine these two terms
on the left-hand side
into an exact derivative.
So these two terms are actually
the time derivative
of the product x times
the integrating
factor e to the kt.
And then on the right-hand side
we just have e to the kt.
So we can just go ahead
and integrate both
sides of the equation.
And when we do that, the
right-hand side becomes the
integral kt, which is 1 over k e
to the kt plus a constant of
integration.
And now, just to isolate
x, I could divide
through by e to the kt.
And I obtain 1 over k plus a
constant e to the minus kt.
So here's the solution
to the ODE.
OK, so this concludes part A.
For part B, we have the equation
x dot plus kx equals
e to the negative 5t.
So if we take a look at this
equation, the only thing that
we've changed is the
right-hand side.
We haven't changed the
left-hand side.
And again, if we compute the
integrating factor, well, we
know that it's the same
integrating factor as in part
A. And the reason is that the
integrating factor only
depends on the left-hand side.
It only depends on the linear
terms. So I can multiply the
equation through by the
integrating factor again.
And when I do this, I'll just
combine the terms on the
right-hand side.
So this is e to the kt times
e to the minus 5t.
And again, by construction, the
left-hand side is going to
be the same as in part A,
the time derivative of
x times e to kt.
And now we can go ahead and
integrate both sides.
OK, so if we integrate this,
we end up getting 1 over k
minus 5, e to the k minus
5t, plus a constant c.
And if we step back and take a
look at this for a second, we
see that when k equals
5, we have a problem.
Particularly, the denominator
vanishes, which would
give us 1 over 0.
So this equation, this
right-hand side, actually only
holds when k is not
equal to 5.
So this is only valid for
k not equal to five.
So the question is, what happens
when k equals to five?
And in this case, we would have
x, e to the kt, times the
integral of 1dt, which
would just give us t
plus a constant c.
So in this case, we would have
t, e to the minus kt, plus c,
e to the minus kt.
And this is when k
is equal to 5.
Meanwhile, for k not equal to 5,
well, we have the solution
worked out already.
So we can just isolate x, and
divide through by e to the kt.
And we have 1 over k minus 5,
e to the minus 5t, plus c, e
to the minus kt.
And this concludes part B.
So the solution for k equal to
5 is t, e to the minus kt,
which would be e to the minus
5t, plus a constant c times e
to the minus 5t.
And when k is not equal to 5, we
have 1 over k minus 5, e to
the minus 5t, plus c,
e to the minus kt.
So I'd just like to point out
a few things between the
solutions for part A and for
part B. First off, we note
that both part A and part B
share a common solution of the
form constant c times
e to the minus kt.
So this is a term that appears
in the solution for both part
A and for part B. The reason is
this can be thought of as
the homogeneous solution to
the differential equation.
This is the term that solves the
differential equation when
the right-hand side
is set to 0.
Secondly, in part B, if we take
a look, when k is not
equal to 5, we have the term,
which is a constant, times e
to the minus 5t.
However, when we have k equal to
5, what happens is we have
a term which essentially
occurs from forcing the
differential equation on
resonance, which gives us an
extra factor of t times
e to the minus 5t.
And we'll see more about
resonance in the future.
OK, so for part c, we're asked
to use superposition.
To solve the differential
equation x dot plus kx equals
4 plus 7e to the minus 5t.
Now if we take a look at this
differential equation, we
already know the solution when
the right-hand side is 1 and
when the right-hand side
is e to the minus 5t.
So we've changed the right-hand
side now so it's 4
times 1 plus 7 times
e to the minus 5t.
So what's the total solution
going to be?
Well, it's going to be four
times our solution when the
right-hand side was 1, plus
seven times the solution when
the right-hand side was
e to the minus 5t.
This is one of the beautiful
things about linear equations.
When we add two forcings to the
right-hand side, our total
solution is just going to be
the sum of the solutions to
the
individual terms. OK.
So what this means is our
solution, x, is going to be 4
times the solution when the
right-hand side was 1.
And in that case, it was 1 over
k plus c, e to the minus
kt, plus 7 times the solution
when the right-hand side was e
to the minus 5t.
And when k was not equal to 5,
this becomes 1 over k minus 5,
e to the minus 5t, plus
c, e to the minus kt.
So if we take a look at the sum
of these two terms, I'll
denote the two constants
as c1 and c2.
We actually have 4 times
c1 plus 7 times c2.
That's just going to give
us a new constant, c3.
So in general, this becomes 4
over k plus 1 over k minus 5,
e to the minus 5t, plus a
constant c, e to the minus kt.
So I can just recombine the 4,
c, e to the minus kt, and the
7, c, e to the minus kt.
That together just gives me a
new constant, c3, times e to
the minus kt.
And this is the solution when
k is not equal to 5.
When k equals to 5, what we do
is we just replace this term
with t, e to the minus kt.
So this is when k is
not equal to 5.
It should be a 7 here.
So I'll just conclude there.
And for summary, we've taken a
look at a first-order linear
differential equation
with a couple
different right-hand sides.
We've solved them using
an integrating factor.
And then what we've done is
we've used the superposition
principle to solve the same
ODE for a right-hand side,
which is the superposition of
multiples of the functions
that we've had in part A and
for part B. So I'd like to
conclude here, and I'll
see you next time.