This lecture is mostly about
the idea of similar matrixes.
I'm going to tell you what that
word similar means and in what
way two matrixes are called
similar.
But before I do that,
I have a little more to say
about positive definite
matrixes.
You can tell this is a subject
I
think is really important and I
told you what positive definite
meant -- it means that this --
this expression,
this quadratic form,
x transpose I x is always
positive.
But the direct way to test it
was with eigenvalues or pivots
or determinants.
So I --
we know what it means,
we know how to test it,
but I didn't really say where
positive definite matrixes come
from.
And so one thing I want to say
is that they come from least
squares in -- and all sorts of
physical problems start with a
rectangular
matrix -- well,
you remember in least squares
the crucial combination was A
transpose A.
So I want to show that that's a
positive definite matrix.
Can -- so I -- I'm going to
speak a little more about
positive definite matrixes,
just recapping -- so let me ask
a
question.
It may be on the homework.
Suppose a matrix A is positive
definite.
I mean by that it's all -- I'm
assuming it's symmetric.
That's always built into the
definition.
So we have a symmetric positive
definite matrix.
What about its inverse?
Is the inverse of a symmetric
positive definite matrix also
symmetric positive definite?
So you quickly think,
okay, what do I know about the
pivots of the inverse matrix?
Not much.
What do I know about the
eigenvalues of the inverse
matrix?
Everything, right?
The eigenvalues of the inverse
are one over the eigenvalues of
the matrix.
So if my matrix starts out
positive definite,
then right away I know that its
inverse is positive definite,
because those positive
eigenvalues -- then one over the
eigenvalue is
also positive.
What if I know that A -- a
matrix A and a matrix B are both
positive definite?
But let me ask you this.
Suppose if A and B are positive
definite, what about -- what
about A plus B?
In some way,
you hope that that would be
true.
It's -- positive definite for a
matrix is kind of like positive
for a real number.
But we don't know the
eigenvalues of A plus B.
We don't know the pivots of A
plus B.
So we just, like,
have to go down this list of,
all right, which approach to
positive definite can we get a
handle on?
And this is a good one.
This is a good one.
Can we -- how would we decide
that -- if A was like this and
if B was like this,
then we would look at x
transpose A plus B x.
I'm sure this is in the
homework.
Now -- so we have x transpose A
x
bigger than zero,
x transpose B x positive for
all -- for all x,
so now I ask you about this
guy.
And of course,
you just add that and that and
we get what we want.
If A and B are positive
definites, so is A plus B.
So that's what I've shown.
So is A plus B.
Just -- be sort of ready for
all the approaches through
eigenvalues and through this
expression.
And now, finally,
one more thought about positive
definite is this combination
that came up in least squares.
Can I do that?
So now -- now suppose A is
rectangular, m by n.
I -- so I'm sorry that I've
used
the same letter A for the
positive definite matrixes in
the eigenvalue chapter that I
used way back in earlier
chapters when the matrix was
rectangular.
Now, that matrix -- a
rectangular matrix,
no way its positive definite.
It's not symmetric.
It's not even square in
general.
But you remember that the key
for these rectangular ones was A
transpose A.
That's square.
That's symmetric.
Those are things we knew -- we
knew back when we met this thing
in the least square stuff,
in the projection stuff.
But now we know something more
-- we can ask a more important
question, a deeper question --
is it positive definite?
And we sort of hope so.
Like, we -- we might -- in
analogy with numbers,
this is like -- sort of like
the square of a number,
and that's positive.
So now I want to ask the matrix
question.
Is A transpose
A positive definite?
Okay, now it's -- so again,
it's a rectangular A that I'm
starting with,
but it's the combination A
transpose A that's the square,
symmetric and hopefully
positive definite matrix.
So how -- how do I see that it
is positive definite,
or at least positive
semi-definite?
You'll see that.
Well, I don't know the
eigenvalues of this product.
I don't want to work with the
pivots.
The right thing -- the right
quantity to look at is this,
x transpose Ax -- A -- x
transpose times my matrix
times x.
I'd like to see that this thing
-- that that expression is
always positive.
I'm not doing it with numbers,
I'm doing it with symbols.
Do you see -- how do I see that
that expression comes out
positive?
I'm taking a rectangular matrix
A
and an A transpose -- that
gives me something square
symmetric, but now I want to see
that if I multiply -- that if I
do this -- I form this quadratic
expression that I get this
positive thing that goes upwards
when I graph it.
How do I see that that's
positive,
or absolutely it isn't negative
anyway?
We'll have to,
like, spend a minute on the
question could it be zero,
but it can't be negative.
Why can this never be negative?
The argument is -- like the one
key idea in so many steps in
linear algebra -- put those
parentheses
in a good way.
Put the parentheses around Ax
and what's the first part?
What's this x transpose A
transpose?
That is Ax transpose.
So what do we have?
We have the length squared of
Ax.
We have -- that's the column
vector Ax that's the row
vector Ax, its length squared,
certainly greater than or
possibly equal to zero.
So we have to deal with this
little possibility.
Could it be equal?
Well, when could the length
squared be zero?
Only if the vector is zero,
right?
That's the only vector that has
length squared zero.
So we have -- we would like to
-- I would like to get that
possibility out of there.
So I want to have Ax never --
never be zero,
except of course for the zero
vector.
How do I assure that Ax is
never zero?
The -- in other words,
how do I show that there's no
null space of A?
The rank should be -- so now
remember -- what's the rank when
there's no null space?
By no null space,
you know what I mean.
Only the zero vector in the
null space.
So if I have a --
if I have an 11 by 5 matrix --
so it's got 11 rows,
5 columns, when is there no
null space?
So the columns should be
independent -- what's the rank?
n 5 -- rank n.
Independent columns,
when -- so if I -- then I
conclude yes,
positive definite.
And this was the assumption --
then A transpose A is
invertible -- the least squares
equations all work fine.
And more than that -- the
matrix is even positive
definite.
And I just to say one comment
about numerical things,
with a positive definite
matrix,
you never have to do row
exchanges.
You never run into unsuitably
small numbers or zeroes in the
pivot position.
They're the right -- they're
the great matrixes to compute
with, and they're the great
matrixes to study.
So that's -- I wanted to take
this first ten
minutes of grab the first ten
minutes away from similar
matrixes and continue a -- this
much more with positive
definite.
I'm really at this point,
now, coming close to the end of
the heart of linear algebra.
The positive definiteness
brought everything together.
Similar matrixes,
which is coming the rest of
this hour is a key topic,
and please come on Monday.
Monday is about what's called
the SVD, singular values.
It's the -- has become a
central fact in -- a central
part of linear algebra.
I mean, you can come after
Monday
also, but -- Monday is,
-- that singular value thing
has made it into this course.
Ten years ago,
five years ago it wasn't in the
course, now it has to be.
Okay.
So can I begin today's
lecture proper with this idea
of similar matrixes.
This is what similar matrixes
mean.
So here -- let's start again.
I'll write it again.
So A and B are similar.
A and B are -- now I'm -- these
matrixes -- I'm no longer
talking about symmetric
matrixes,
in -- at least no longer
expecting symmetric matrixes.
I'm talking about two square
matrixes n by n.
A and B, they're n by n
matrixes.
And I'm introducing this word
similar.
So I'm going to say what does
it mean?
It means that they're connected
in the way --
well, in the way I've written
here, so let me rewrite it.
That means that for some matrix
M, which has to be invertible,
because you'll see that -- this
one matrix is -- take the other
matrix, multiply on the right by
M and on the left by M inverse.
So the question is,
why that combination?
But part of the answer you know
already.
You remember -- we've done this
-- we've taken a matrix A -- so
let's do an example of similar.
Suppose A -- the matrix A --
suppose it has a
full set of eigenvectors.
They go in this eigenvector
matrix S.
Then what was the main point of
the whole -- the main
calculation of the whole chapter
was -- is -- use that
eigenvector matrix S and its
inverse comes over there to
produce the nicest possible
matrix lambda.
Nicest possible because it's
diagonal.
So in our new language,
this is saying A is similar to
lambda.
A is similar to lambda,
because there is a matrix,
and this particular -- there is
an M and this particular M is
this important guy,
this eigenvector
matrix.
But if I take a different
matrix M and I look at M inverse
A M, the result won't come out
diagonal, but it will come out a
matrix B that's similar to A.
Do you see that I'm -- what I'm
doing is, like -- I'm putting
these matrixes into families.
All the matrixes in one -- in
the family are similar to each
other.
They're all -- each one in this
family is connected to each
other one by some matrix M and
the -- like the outstanding
member of the family is the
diagonal guy.
I mean, that's the simplest,
neatest matrix in this family
of all the matrixes that are
similar to A,
the best one is lambda.
But there are lots of others,
because I can take different --
instead of S,
I can take any old matrix M,
any old invertible matrix and
-- and do it.
I'd better do an example.
Okay.
Suppose I take A as the
matrix two one one two.
Okay.
Do you know the eigenvalue
matrix for that?
The eigenvalues of that matrix
are -- well, three and one.
So that -- and the eigenvectors
would be easy to find.
So this matrix is similar to
this one.
But my point is -- but also,
I can also take my matrix,
two one one two,
I could multiply it by -- let's
see, what -- I'm just going to
cook up a matrix M here.
I'm -- I'll -- let me just
invent -- one four one zero.
And over here I'll put M
inverse, and because I happened
to make that triangular,
I know that its inverse is
that, right?
So there's M inverse A M,
that's going to produce some
matrix -- oh,
well, I've got to do the
multiplication,
so hang on a second,
let -- I'll just copy that one
minus four zero one and multiply
these guys so I'm getting two
nine one
and six, I think.
Can you check it as I go,
because you -- see I'm just --
so that's two minus four,
I'm getting a minus two nine
minus 24 is a minus 15,
my God, how did I get this?
And that's probably one and
six.
So there's my matrix B.
And there's my matrix lambda,
there's my matrix A and my
point is these are all similar
matrixes.
They all have something in
common, besides being just two
by two.
They have something in common.
And that's -- and what is it?
What's the point about two
matrixes that are built out of
-- the B is built out of M
inverse A M.
What is it that A and B have in
common?
That's the main -- now I'm
telling you the main fact about
similar matrixes.
They have the same eigenvalues.
This is -- this chapter is
about eigenvalues,
and that's why we're interested
in this family of matrixes that
have the same eigenvalues.
What are the eigenvalues in
this example?
Lambda.
The eigenvalues of that I could
compute.
The eigenvalues of that I can
compute really fast.
So the eigenvalues are three
and one -- for this for sure.
Now did we -- do you see why
the eigenvalues are
three and one for that one?
If I tell you the eigenvalues
are three and one,
you prick -- quickly process
the trace, which is -- and four
-- agrees with four and you
process the determinant,
three times one -- the
determinant is three and you say
yes, it's right.
Now I'm hoping that the
eigenvalues of this thing are
three and one.
May I process the trace and the
determinant for that one?
What's the trace here?
The trace of this matrix is
four minus two and six,
and that's what it should be.
What's the determinant minus
twelve
plus fifteen is three.
The determinant is three.
The eigenvalues of that matrix
are also three and one.
And you see I created this
matrix just like -- I just took
any M, like, one that popped
into my head and computed M
inverse A M, got that matrix,
it didn't look anything special
but it's -- like A itself,
it has those eigenvalues three
and one.
So that's the main fact and let
me write it down.
Similar matrixes have the same
eigenvalues.
So I'll just put that as an
important point.
And think
why.
Why is that?
So that's what that family of
matrixes is.
The matrixes that are similar
to this A here are all the
matrixes with eigenvalues three
and one.
Every matrix with eigenvalues
three and one,
there's some M that connects
this guy to the one you think
of.
And then of course,
the most special guy in the
whole family is the diagonal one
with eigenvalues three and one
sitting there on the diagonal.
But also, I could find -- I
mean, tell me just a couple more
members of the family.
Another -- tell me another
matrix that has
eigenvalues three and one.
Well, let's see,
I -- oh, I'll just make it
triangular.
That's in the family.
There is some M that -- that
connects to this one.
And -- and also this.
There's some matrix M -- so
that M inverse A M comes out to
be that.
There's a whole family here.
And they all share the same
eigenvalues.
So why is that?
Okay.
I'm going to start -- the only
possibility is to start with Ax
equal lambda x.
Okay, so suppose A has the
eigenvalue lambda.
Now I want to get B into the
picture here somehow.
You remember B is M inverse A
M.
Let's just remember that over
here.
B is M inverse A M.
And I want to see its
eigenvalues.
How I going to get M inverse A
M into this equation?
Let me just sort of do it.
I'll put an M times an M
inverse in there,
right?
That was -- I haven't changed
the
left-hand side,
so I better not change the
right-hand side.
So everybody's okay so far,
I just put in there -- see,
I want to get a -- so now I'll
multiply on the left by M
inverse -- I have to do the same
to this side and that number
lambda's just a number,
so it factors out in the front.
So what I have here is this was
safe.
I did the same thing to both
sides.
And now I've got B.
There's B.
That's B times this vector M
inverse x is equal to lambda
times this vector M inverse x.
So what have I learned?
I've learned that B times some
vector is lambda times that
vector.
I've learned that lambda is an
eigenvalue of B also.
So this is -- if -- so this is
-- if lambda's an eigenvalue of
A, then I can write it this way
and I discover that lambda's an
eigenvalue of B.
That's the end of the proof.
The eigenvector didn't stay the
same.
Of course I don't expect the
eigenvectors to stay the same.
If all the eigenvalues are the
same and all the eigenvectors
are the same,
then probably the matrix is the
same.
Here the eigenvector changes,
so the eigenvector -- so the
point is then the eigenvector of
B --
of B is M inverse times the
eigenvector of A.
Okay.
That's all that this says here.
The eigenvector of A was X,
and so the M inverse -- similar
matrixes, then have the same
eigenvalues and their
eigenvectors are just moved
around.
Of course,
that's what we -- that's what
happened way back -- and the
most important similar matrixes
are to diagonalize.
So what was the point when we
diagonalized?
The eigenvalues stayed the
same, of course.
Three and one.
What about the eigenvectors?
The eigenvectors were whatever
they were for the matrix A,
but then what were the
eigenvectors for the diagonal
matrix?
They're just -- what are the
eigenvectors of a diagonal
matrix?
They're just one zero and zero
one.
So this step made the
eigenvectors nice,
didn't change the eigenvalues,
and every time we don't change
the
eigenvalues.
Same eigenvalues.
Okay.
Now -- so I've got all these
matrixes in -- I've got this
family of matrixes with
eigenvalues three and one.
Fine.
That's a nice family.
It's nice because those two
eigenvalues are different.
I now have to --
to get into that -- the -- into
the less happy possibility that
the two eigenvalues could be the
same.
And then it's a little
trickier, because you remember
when two eigenvalues are the
same, what's the bad
possibility?
That there might not be enough
-- a full set of eigenvectors
and we
might not be able to
diagonalize.
So I need to discuss the bad
case.
So the bad -- can I just say
bad?
If lambda one equals lambda
two, then the matrix might not
be diagonalizable.
Suppose lambda one equals
lambda two equals four,
say.
Now if I look at the family of
matrixes with eigenvalues four
and four, well,
one possibility occurs to me.
One family with eigenvalues
four and four has this matrix in
it, four times the identity.
Then another -- but now I want
to ask also about the matrix
four four one zero.
And my point --
here's the whole point of this
-- of this bad stuff,
is that this guy is not in the
same family with that one.
The family of a -- of matrixes
that have eigenvalues four and
four is two families.
There's this total loner here
who's in a family off -- right?
Just by himself.
And all the others are in with
this guy.
So the big family includes this
one.
And it includes a whole lot of
other matrixes,
all -- in fact,
in this two by two case,
it -- you see where -- what do
I mean -- so what I using,
this word family -- in a
family, I mean
they're similar.
So my point is that the only
matrix that's similar to this is
itself.
The only matrix that's similar
to four times the identity is
four times the identity.
It's off by itself.
Why is that?
The -- if this is my matrix,
four times the identity,
and I take
it, I multiply on the right by
any matrix M,
I multiply on the left by M
inverse, what do I get?
This is any M,
but what's the result?
Well, factoring out a four,
that's just the identity matrix
in there.
So then the M inverse cancels
the M, so I've just got this
matrix back
again.
So whatever the M is,
I'm not getting any more
members of the family.
So this is one small family,
because it only has one person.
One matrix, excuse me.
I think of these matrixes as
people by this point,
in eighteen oh six.
Okay, the other family includes
all the rest --
all other matrixes that have
eigenvalues four and four.
This is somehow the best one in
that family.
See, I can't make it diagonal.
If I -- if it's diagonal,
it's this one.
It's in its own,
by itself.
So I have to think,
okay, what's the nearest I can
get
to diagonal?
But it will not be
diagonalizable.
That -- do you know that that
matrix is not diagonalizable?
Of course, because if it was
diagonalizable,
it would be similar to that,
which it isn't.
The eigenvalues of this are
four
and four, but what's the catch
with that matrix?
It's only got one eigenvector.
That's a non-diagonalizable
matrix.
Only one eigenvector.
And somehow,
if I made that one into a ten
or to a million,
I could find an M,
it's in the family,
it's similar.
But the best --
so the best guy in this family
is this one.
And this is called the Jordan
-- so this guy Jordan picked out
-- so he, like,
studied, these families of
matrixes, and each family,
he picked out the nicest,
most diagonal one.
But not completely diagonal,
because there's nobody -- there
isn't a diagonal matrix in this
family, so there's a one up
there in the Jordan form.
Okay.
I think we've got to see some
more matrixes in that family.
So, all right,
let me -- let's just think of
some other matrixes whose
eigenvalues are four and four
but they're not
four times the identity.
So -- and I believe that --
that this -- that all the
examples we pick up will be
similar to each other and -- do
you see why -- in this topic of
similar matrixes,
the climax is the Jordan form.
So it says that every
matrix -- I'll write down what
the Jordan form -- what Jordan
discovered.
He found the best looking
matrix in each family.
And that's -- then we've got --
then we've covered all matrixes
including the non-diagonalizable
one.
That -- that's the point,
that in some way,
Jordan completed the
diagonalization by coming as
near as he could,
which is his Jordan form.
And therefore,
if you want to cover all
matrixes, you've got to get him
in the picture.
It used to be -- when I took
eighteen oh six,
that was the climax of the
course, this Jordan form stuff.
I think it's not the climax of
linear algebra anymore,
because -- it's not easy to
find this Jordan form for a
general matrix,
because it depends on these
eigenvalues being exactly the
same.
You'd have to know exactly the
eigenvalues and it -- and you'd
have to know exactly the rank
and the slightest change in
numbers will change those
eigenvalues, change the rank and
therefore the whole thing is
numerically not an -- a good
thing.
But for algebra,
it's the right thing to
understand this family.
So just tell me another matrix
-- a few more matrixes -- so
more members of the family.
Let me put down again what the
best one is.
Okay.
All right.
Some more matrixes.
Let's see, what I looking for?
I'm looking for matrixes whose
trace is what?
So if I'm looking for more
matrixes in the family,
they'll all have the same
eigenvalues, four and four.
So their trace will be eight.
So why don't I just take,
like, five and three -- I've
got the trace right,
now the determinant
should be what?
Sixteen.
So I just fix this up -- shall
I put maybe a one and a minus
one there?
Okay.
There's a matrix with
eigenvalues four and four,
because the trace is eight and
the determinant is sixteen.
And I don't think it's
diagonalizable.
Do you know why it's not
diagonalizable?
Because if it was
diagonalizable,
the diagonal form would have to
be this.
But I can't get to that form,
because whatever I do with any
M inverse and M I stay with that
form.
I could never get -- connect
those.
So I can put down more members
--
here -- here's another easy
one.
I could put the four and the
four and a seventeen down there.
All these matrixes are similar.
If I'm -- I could find an M
that would show that that one is
similar to that one.
And in -- you can see the
general picture is I can take
any a and any 8-a
here and any -- oh,
I don't know,
whatever you put it'd be --
anyway, you can see.
I can fill this in,
fill this in to make the trace
equal eight, the determinant
equal 16, I get all that family
of matrixes and they're all
similar.
So we see what eigenvalues do.
They're all similar and they
all have only one eigenvector.
So I -- if I'm -- if you were
going to -- allow me to add to
this picture,
they have the same lambdas and
they also have the same number
of independent eigenvectors.
Because if I get an eigenvector
for x I get one for --
for A, I get one for B also.
So -- and same number of
eigenvectors.
But even more than that -- even
more than that -- I mean,
it's not enough just to count
eigenvectors.
Yes, let me give you an example
why it's not even enough to
count eigenvectors.
So another example.
So here are some matrixes --
oh, let me make them four by
four -- okay,
here -- here's a matrix.
I mean, like if you want
nightmares, think about matrixes
like these.
Uh, so a one off the diagonal
-- say a one there,
how many -- what are the
eigenvalues of that matrix?
Oh, I mean --
okay.
What are the eigenvalues of
that matrix?
Please.
Four 0s, right?
So we're really getting bad
matrixes now.
So I mean, this is,
like -- Jordan was a good guy,
but he had to think about
matrixes that all --
that had, like -- an eigenvalue
repeated four times.
How many eigenvectors does that
matrix have?
Well, I'm -- eigenvectors will
be -- since the eigenvalue is
zero, eigenvectors will be in
the null space,
right?
I'm -- eigenvectors have got to
be
A x equal zero x.
So what's the dimension of the
null space?
Two.
Somebody said two.
And that's right.
How -- why?
Because you ask what's the rank
of that matrix,
the rank is obviously two.
The number of independent rows
is
two, the number of independent
columns is two,
the rank is two so the null --
the dimension of the null space
is four minus two,
so it's got two eigenvectors.
Two eigenvectors.
Two independent eigenvectors.
All right.
The dimension of the null space
is two.
Now, suppose I change this zero
to a seven.
The eigenvalues are all still
zero, how -- what about -- how
many eigenvectors?
What's the dimension of the --
what's the rank of this matrix
now?
Still two, right?
So it's okay.
And actually,
this would be similar to the
one
that had a zero in there.
But it's not as beautiful,
Jordan picked this one.
He picked -- he put ones -- we
have a one on the -- above the
diagonal for every missing
eigenvector, and here we're
missing two because we've got
two,
so we've got two eigenvectors
and two are missing,
because it's a four by four
matrix.
Okay, now -- but I was going to
give you this second example.
0 1 0 0, let me just move the
one.
Oop, not there.
Off the diagonal and zero zero
zero
zero zero.
Okay.
So now tell me about this
matrix.
Its eigenvalues are four zeroes
again.
Its rank is two again.
So it has two eigenvectors and
two missing.
But the darn thing is not
similar to that one.
A -- a count of eigenvectors
looks like these could be
similar,
but they're not.
Jordan -- see,
this is like -- a little three
by three block and a little one
by one block.
And this one is like a two by
two block and a two by two
block, and those blocks are
called Jordan blocks.
So let me say what is a Jordan
block?
J block number I has -- so a
Jordan block has a repeated
eigenvalue, lambda I,
lambda I on the diagonal.
Zeroes below and ones above.
So there's a block with this
guy repeated,
but it only has one
eigenvector.
So a Jordan block has one
eigenvector only.
This one has one eigenvector,
this block has one eigenvector
and we get two.
This block has one eigenvector
and that block has one
eigenvector and we get two.
So -- but the blocks are
different sizes.
And that -- it turns out Jordan
worked out -- then this is not
similar, not
similar to this one.
So the -- so I'm,
like, giving you the whole
story -- well,
not the whole story,
but the main themes of the
story -- is here's Jordan's
theorem.
Every square matrix A is
similar to A Jordan matrix J.
And what's a Jordan matrix J?
It's a matrix with these
blocks,
block -- Jordan block number
one, Jordan block number two and
so on.
And let's say Jordan block
number d.
And those Jordan blocks look
like that, so the eigenvalues
are sitting on the diagonal,
but we've got some of these
ones above the diagonal.
We've got the number of -- so
the number of blocks -- the
number of blocks is the number
of eigenvectors,
because we get one eigenvector
per block.
So what I'm -- so if I
summarize Jordan's idea -- start
with any A.
If its eigenvalues are
distinct, then what's it similar
to?
This is the good case.
if I start with a matrix A and
it has different eigenvalues --
it's n eigenvalues,
none of them are repeated,
then that's a diagonal --
diagonalizable matrix -- the
Jordan blocks is -- has -- the
Jordan matrix is diagonal.
It's lambda.
So the good case --
the good case,
J is lambda.
All -- there are -- d=n.
There are n eigenvectors,
n blocks, diagonal,
everything great.
But Jordan covered all cases by
including these cases of
repeated eigenvalues and missing
eigenvectors.
Okay.
That's a description of Jordan.
That --
that's -- I haven't told you
how to compute this thing,
and it isn't easy.
Whereas the good case is the --
the good case is what 18.06 is
about.
The -- this case is what 18.06
was about 20 years ago.
So you can see you probably
won't have on the final exam the
computation of a Jordan matrix
for some horrible thing with
four repeated eigenvalues.
I'm not that crazy about the
Jordan form.
But I'm very positive about
positive definite matrixes and
about the idea that's coming
Monday, the singular value
decomposition.
So I'll see you on Monday,
and have a great weekend.
Bye.