BEN HARRIS: Hi.
Today we're going
to do a problem
about similar matrices.
The problem is right here.
So the question asks, which of
the following statements are
true, and it asks you
to explain why.
The first statement is if A and
B are similar matrices,
then 2A cubed plus A minus 3
times the identity is similar
to 2 times B cubed plus B minus
3 times the identity.
The second question asks if A
and B are 3 by 3 matrices with
eigenvalues 1, 0, and -1,
then they're similar.
And the third part asks you
whether these two j matrices
are similar.
OK.
I'll give you a moment to hit
pause and try it on your own.
I'll be back in just a moment,
and we can do it together.
And we're back.
Let's start with part a.
Part a is true.
Why?
Well, what does it mean for
A and B to be similar?
Right, we know there's some
matrix M, such that-- that's
what st means--
when I multiply A on the left
by M and the right by M
inverse,
I get B. OK.
So let's take that same matrix
M and multiply it on the left
and the right of 2A cubed plus
A minus 3 times the identity.
OK.
What do we get here?
Well, the point is when A times
A cubed times m inverse,
we can just write that
as 3 MAM inverses.
Similarly, we have an MAM
inverse and an M times the
identity times m inverse.
Good.
Remember that M times A times M
inverse is B. So we just get
2B cubed, 3B plus B minus--
well, M times the identity is
just M. So we just get the
identity back, and we have
3 times the identity.
Good.
And this is a general remark,
that if you have matrices A
and B that are similar, then
any polynomials in these
matrices A and B will
be similar.
It's the exact same
justification.
OK.
Now let's go on to part B. So
now A and B are 3 by 3 similar
matrices with the same
eigenvalues.
And their eigenvalues
are distinct.
So it turns out that
b is true, as well.
And why is that?
A matrix with distinct
eigenvalues is diagonalizable.
So we can write A as S, lambda,
S inverse, where
lambda is just this
eigenvalue matrix.
We can also write B as T,
lambda, T inverse, where
lambda is the same in both cases
because they have the
same eigenvalues.
Good.
Now I'll let you--
so before we check it, let's
just say the point.
The point is if two matrices
are similar to the same
matrix, then they're similar
to each other.
Similarity is a transitive
relation.
And I'll just let you check that
you can take TS inverse A
times TS inverse inverse, and
you'll get B. This falls
directly from these
two relations.
Good.
Now let's take on part
C. Part C is false.
Let's come back over here
and look at these two
matrices, J1 and J2.
The first thing you should
see is that these
two are Jordan blocks--
they're not Jordan blocks,
they're matrices in Jordan
normal form.
They're different matrices in
Jordan normal form, so they
will not be similar.
But let's actually see why.
Let's look at--
remember one of the things that
similarity preserves are
eigenvectors and eigenvalues.
So let's look at the eigenspace
with eigenvalue
minus one with these
two matrices.
So J1 plus the identity--
let's look at the nullspace
of this matrix.
So this is just 0's on the
diagonal and 1's right above
the diagonal, and J2
plus the identity.
This is just 0, 1, 0, 0.
So the point is that the
nullspace of this matrix is
just one dimensional.
So there's only one independent
eigenvector of J1
with eigenvalue minus 1 whereas
the nullspace of this
matrix is two dimensional.
There are two independent
eigenvectors with
eigenvalue minus 1.
So the dimension--
the nullspace--
of J1 plus the identity, this
is 1, and this is 2.
So they cannot possibly
be similar.
Good.
So that completes the problem.
It's a nice exercise to do
this more generally.
And you can use these techniques
not just looking at
the number of independent
eigenvectors and the nullspace
of your J minus lambda I matrix,
but also powers of J
minus lambda I and
their nullspaces.
You can use this to show that
any two matrices in Jordan
normal form that are different
are not similar.
This same method works.
And that's a nice exercise if
you want to go a little
further with similar matrices.
Let's just recap the properties
we saw here.
We saw that if we had two
similar matrices, then any
polynomials in those matrices
were similar.
And we saw that if we have two
matrices that have the same
distinct eigenvalues, then
they're similar.
And we saw that, in a special
case, we saw that two matrices
in Jordan normal form that are
different are not similar.
Thanks.