JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture you've started
learning about quadratic
approximation.
So today we're just going to
do a quick example of it.
So I have a question written
here on the board.
What is the quadratic
approximation of the function
f of x equals e to the x plus x
squared-- so here x and plus
x squared is the exponent, so
it's e to the quantity x plus
x squared--
near x equals 0.
So why don't you take a minute
or two, pause the video, work
this out on your own and
then come back and
we can do it together.
All right.
Welcome back.
So there are two different ways
we can do this problem.
Let's first just do it the
totally straightforward way,
which is that you have this
formula for quadratic
approximations in terms of the
derivatives of your function.
And so, so we can just
apply that formula.
So here, so the formula
is that the quadratic
approximation of the
function f--
so here, near the point 0--
is equal to f of 0 plus f prime
of 0 x plus f double
prime of 0 over 2
times x squared.
All right.
So in order to use this formula
we just need to know
what the derivatives of
our function are and
their values at 0.
So first we can do the first
derivative of f.
So for that it's just a
straightforward application of
the chain rule.
Our outer function is e to the
x and our inner function is x
plus x squared.
So the derivative, then applying
the chain rule is e
to the x plus x squared times
1 plus 2x, which I can also
write as e--
well, yeah, let me
just reorder it--
2x plus 1 times e to the
x plus x squared.
OK.
So that's the first
derivative.
And for the second derivative
I can apply just the
product rule here.
Right?
So I've got this, you know--
the second derivative is the
derivative of the first
derivative--
so here I have a product.
So f double prime of x is equal
to-- well, so we take
the derivative of the first
one, which is just--
2 times the second plus the
derivative of the second one.
Well, the second one is e
to the x plus x squared.
It's actually f of x, so we
already computed it once.
So the derivative of the second
is 2x plus 1 e to the x
plus x squared times
the first. So times
another 2x plus 1.
OK, and if I multiply these two
together and combine all
my terms, this is 4x squared
plus 4x plus 3 times e to the
x plus x squared.
So these are the first and
second derivatives, and what I
need to plug them into
my formula is I need
their values at 0.
So I need the function
value at 0.
So f of 0, well that's e to
the 0 plus 0 squared.
So it's e to the 0,
so that's just 1.
f prime at 0, let's see, I go
over to my formula for f prime
and I plug in x equals 0, so
I have 2 times 0 plus 1, so
that's 1 times e to the 0.
So that's 1 times 1,
that's also 1.
And for f double time at 0, I go
to my formula for f double
prime and I put in 0.
And so this is 0 and that's 0.
So I have a 3 times
1 so that's 3.
And now I just take these three
values and I plug them
right into my formula.
So the quadratic approximation
is Q of f equals 1 plus x plus
3x squared over 2.
All right.
Great.
So that was one way to
do this problem.
Another way to do this problem
is the following.
And in this case, I'm not sure
which way is simpler, but in
some cases one way is clearly
easier than the other.
So if we illustrate both then
you'll have twice as many
tools to work with.
So the other way
is to notice--
so the exponential function is
nice when you have, you know,
one of your exponential
rules--
is that the exponential of a
sum is the product of the
exponentials.
So we can rewrite f of x equals
e to the x times e to
the x squared.
Now this may seem a little bit
silly to you, but if you
watched Christine's recitation
video you saw that to find the
quadratic approximation to a
product, it's enough to find
the quadratic approximations
to each piece separately,
multiply together, and then
take that quadratic
approximation.
So in this case the quadratic
approximations are things you
might already know.
So in particular, we saw in--
sorry-- in lecture that the
quadratic approximation of e
to the x is 1 plus x plus x
squared over 2.
And I'm going to tell you--
if you haven't seen it in
recitation, there are a bunch
of different ways you could
work it out for yourself--
but the quadratic approximation
for e to the x
squared is equal to
1 plus x squared.
All right, so if you don't
believe me, by all means work
that out for yourself
to check it.
So in this case, so that means
that the quadratic
approximation of
f is equal to--
by the rule Christine
showed you--
it's the, so it's equal to the
quadratic approximation of the
product of the quadratic
approximations.
So that's 1 plus x plus
x squared over 2
times 1 plus x squared.
Now if you multiply these two
out, that's not hard.
There are six terms. So this is
the quadratic approximation
of 1 plus x plus x
squared over 2.
So multiply 1 through here
and now x squared.
So that's plus x squared
plus x cubed plus--
OK, some fourth degree term--
x to the fourth over 2.
And now the quadratic
approximation to this we get
just by dropping the cubic and
quartic terms. So, and OK, and
we can add these two square
terms together So this is
equal to 1 plus x plus
3x squared over 2.
All right.
And luckily, doing the same
problem two different ways we
get the same answer, which
is what should happen.
So that's that.