PROFESSOR: Hi, welcome
back to recitation.
I have a nice exercise here
for you that tests your
knowledge of triple
integration.
So in particular I've got
for you a cylinder.
And my cylinder has height
h and it has radius b.
And this is the kind
of cylinder I like.
It's a constant density
cylinder.
So its density is just
1 everywhere.
So what I'd like you to do is
for the cylinder I'd like you
to compute its moment
of inertia
around its central axis.
So why don't you pause the
video, have a go at that, come
back, and you can check your
work against mine.
Hopefully you had some luck
working on this problem.
Let's talk about it.
So the first thing to notice
is that there aren't any
coordinates in this problem.
I've given you a cylinder but
it's up to you to choose
coordinates, a way to arrange
your cylinder in space or a
way to arrange your coordinates
with respect to
your cylinder.
So a convenient thing to do in
this case is going to be-- you
know, we're working with respect
to the central axis of
the cylinder.
So let's make that
one of our axes.
So in particular why don't
we make it our z-axis.
That seems like a natural
sort of thing to do.
So let me try and draw a
little picture here.
So we've got our cylinder.
And there it is with our
3 coordinate axes.
I guess it's got radius b
and it's got height h.
Now we've arranged it, now we
have coordinates, so now we
want to see what it is we're
trying to do with it.
So we're trying to compute
a moment of inertia.
So we have to remember what
a moment of inertia means.
So let me think.
So a moment of inertia, when
you have a solid-- so your
moment of inertia I with respect
to an axis is what you
get when you take the
triple integral.
So let's say your solid is D.
Your solid D. So you take D.
So you take a triple integral
over D and you're integrating
r squared with respect to
the element of mass.
OK.
So r squared here, this is the
distance from the axis around
which you're computing the
moment of inertia.
And in our case, so in
any case, this little
moment of mass is--
sorry, little element
of mass--
is density times a little
element of volume.
So we can also write this as the
triple integral over our
region of r squared times
delta times dV.
OK, so this is what this
is in general.
So now let's think about
it in our case.
Well, in our case, we've
cleverly chosen our central
axis to be the z-axis.
So this r is just the distance
from the z-axis.
This I was kind enough to give
you a constant density
cylinder, so this
delta is just 1.
That's going to be easy.
And then we have this
triple integral
over the whole cylinder.
So we want a triple integral
over the whole cylinder of
some integrand that
involves r.
So a natural thing to do
in this situation--
the natural sort of thing to do
when you have a cylinder or
anything that's rotationally
symmetric, and you have an
integrand that behaves nicely
with respect to rotation, that
can be written easily in terms
of r, or r and theta--
is to do cylindrical
coordinates.
Is to think of cylindrical
So in our case that means we
just need to figure out-- at
this point-- we need to figure
out how do we integrate over
the cylinder in cylindrical
coordinates?
So let's do it.
So in our case, so it doesn't
matter too much what order we
do things in.
So we need dV. We need to write
that in terms of the
cylindrical coordinates.
So that's dz, dr, and d theta.
And so we know that dV
is r dz dr d theta.
You might want some other order
there, but that's a
good, nice order.
It usually is the simplest
order to consider.
So this moment of inertia in our
case is going to be this
triple integral.
OK, so we said r squared
delta, r squared times
density, density is 1.
So that's just r squared.
And r, the distance to
the axis is r, the
distance to the z-axis.
So that's just r squared
times r dz dr d theta.
So this is the integral we're
trying to compute, but we need
bounds, right?
It's a triple integral, it's a
definite integral, we need to
figure out what the bounds
are to evaluate it
as an iterated integral.
So let's go look at this
little picture we drew.
So I guess I didn't discuss
this, but I made a choice just
to put the bottom of the
cylinder in the xy plane and
the top at height h.
It's not going to matter.
If you had made some
other choice, it
would work out fine.
So that means the z is
going from 0 to h,
regardless of r and theta.
So z is going from 0 to h.
That's nice, let's put
that over here.
z is the inside one.
It's going from 0 to h.
Then r is next.
Well, this is also--
you know, cylinders are great
for cylindrical coordinates.
Shocker, right, given the name.
I know.
So r is going from 0 to
what's the radius?
Our radius was b.
So r goes from 0 to
b, and that's true
regardless of theta.
So back over here, if we have r
going from 0 to b and theta
is just going from 0 to 2 pi,
we're doing a full rotation
all the way around
the cylinder.
So this is what our moment of
inertia is, and now we just
have to compute it.
So we've got our inner
integral here is
with respect to z.
So the inner integral is
the integral from 0 to
h of r cubed dz.
And r cubed doesn't have
any z's in it.
Fabulous.
So that's just going to
be r cubed z, where z
goes from 0 to h.
So that's h r cubed minus 0.
So hr cubed.
All right.
So that's the inner.
Now let's look at the
middle integral.
So this is going to be
the integral as--
that's our r integral.
So that's going from 0 to b.
And what are we integrating?
We're integrating the
inner integral.
So the inner integral
was h r cubed.
So we're integrating h r
cubed dr from 0 to b.
All right, this is not
quite as easy.
But h as a constant, we're
integrating r cubed r.
I've done worse.
You've done worse.
So that's going to be h
r to the fourth over 4
between 0 and b.
So OK.
So that's h b to the fourth over
4 minus h times 0 to the
fourth over 4.
So the second term's 0.
So this is just equal to h times
b to the fourth over 4.
And finally, we have our
outer most integral.
So what was that integral?
Well, that was the integral from
0 to 2 pi d theta of the
second integral.
So this is of the
middle integral.
So it's the integral from 0 to
2 pi d theta of the middle
integral which was h b
to the fourth over 4.
And this is just a
constant again.
Great.
So this is hb to the fourth
over 4 times 2 pi.
So what does that work out to?
That's h b to the fourth
pi over 2.
All right.
So there you go.
Now if you wanted to, you could
also rewrite this a
little bit, because you
could note that
this is pi h b squared.
That's your volume
of your cylinder.
And in fact, it's not just your
volume, it's your mass of
your cylinder, because it
had constant density 1.
So you also could've written
this as mass times a
squared over 2.
Sorry. b squared over 2.
I don't know where
a came from.
Mass times b squared.
So you have some other options
for how you could write this
answer by involving the volume
and mass and so on.
So let's just recap
very quickly.
Why we did what we did.
We had a cylinder.
And so really, given a cylinder,
it was a natural
choice to look at cylindrical
coordinates.
And once we had cylindrical
coordinates,
everything was easy.
So we just took our general form
of the moment of inertia,
took the region in question, in
cylindrical coordinates it
was very, very easy to describe
this entire region.
And then our integrals were
pretty easy to compute after
we made that choice.
After we made that choice they
were nice and easy to compute.
So I'll stop there.