JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been
learning about triple
integration, and I have a nice
average value problem for you
using triple integration here.
So what I'd like you to do is
to consider the tetrahedron
that has vertices at the origin,
and at the points 1,
0, 0, and 0, 1, 0,
and 0, 0, 1.
So that's one point on each of
the positive axes at distance
1 from the origin.
So I've taken the liberty of
drawing it here for you.
So consider that solid
tetrahedron.
And what I'd like you to do is
find the average distance of
the points in that tetrahedron
from the xy plane.
All right.
So I'd like you to compute the
average value of the distance
as the point ranges over the
whole tetrahedron of its
distance from the xy plane.
So why don't you pause the
video, spend some time working
that out, come back, and we
can work it out together.
Hopefully, you had some luck
with this problem.
Let's get started.
So the average value of a
function F over a region R is
going to be 1 over the volume of
the region times the triple
integral over your whole region
R of the function value
f of x, y, z with respect to
volume, in any order you want.
So I guess I'll write dv here,
and then to evaluate this, you
set it up as an iterated
integral.
So in our case, the function
we're trying to find the
average value of is the distance
between a point and
the xy plane.
But that's an easy
function, right?
That's just z.
For any point in space, its
distance from the xy plane is
just its height.
It's z-value.
So the function that we're
seeking to find the average
value of is z, and so most of
the work of this problem then
is going to be in figuring out
what the bounds are and then
doing the actual integral
after that.
So OK.
So let's think about
the bounds.
This tetrahedron is
a nice, reasonably
simple, geometric object.
So in fact, it doesn't matter
too much which order you take
your bounds.
So I think I'm going to do
it in the order dz dy dx.
You know, I'll do z first,
and then y, and then x.
But it doesn't matter.
If you do it a different way,
it'll probably work out very
similarly overall, and you'll
still be able to compare the
overall process.
So let's think about z.
Yeah?
So in this tetrahedron, we want
to integrate with respect
to z first. So we look at this
tetrahedron and we say, OK, at
a point when we choose the x-
and y-values, what's the
lowest surface-- what's the
smallest value z can take--
and what's the upper surface--
what's the
largest value z can take?
So the lowest surface here
is the xy plane.
That's the bottom face
of this tetrahedron.
And for any choice of x and y,
the lowest value z can take is
when it's in the xy plane.
So when it's equal to 0.
So this is going to be equal,
so in our case, so
let's set this up.
So it's going to be an
iterated integral.
The function we're integrating
is z, and I said
we'll do dz dy dx.
And we just said that the lowest
value that z takes--
the dz--
is 0.
So the up-highest value that
z takes is when it
hits this top surface.
This plane that passes through
the point (1, 0, 0), (0, 1,
0), and (0, 0, 1).
All right.
So we need to know the equation
of that plane.
Luckily, that's a pretty easy
plane to write down the
equation for.
So this slanted plane passing
through the three vertices
other than the origin is
the plane x plus y
plus z equals 1.
All right.
So it's a nice, easy
plane to work with.
And so what we want to know
is what's the value
of z on that plane.
So we isolate z on one
side and we bring
everything else over.
So we have that top value of z,
the largest value of z that
z can take when x and y are
fixed, is 1 minus x minus 1.
So that's what goes up here.
So that's the biggest
value z can take.
OK, good.
So now we need to figure out
what the bounds on y are in
terms of x.
So what I like to do in this
case is I like to draw a
projection of your surface.
So then you're in a
two-dimensional world, and
then you can look at that
image more easily.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to look at this
tetrahedron and we're going to
imagine projecting it down
into the xy plane.
So for every point in the
tetrahedron, we're going to
draw a dot below it
in the xy plane.
And then we're going to look
at that set of dots.
So what that's going to give us
is this bottom face of the
tetrahedron.
Every point of the tetrahedron
is above its bottom face.
That's not true for every
tetrahedron, but it's
true for this one.
So the region that we're
interested in
is that bottom face.
So I'm going to draw another
picture of it
over on my left here.
So that region is the region
that has vertices (0, 0), and
(1, 0), and (0, 1).
So it's this triangle.
And this bottom edge of
the triangle is the
line y equals 0.
This left edge is the
line x equals 0.
And this slanted line is the
line x plus y equals 1.
OK, so this is that same bottom
face that we just drew.
But now I've changed my axes to
our usual two-dimensional
direction with x to the
right and y up.
OK.
So we're doing dy next.
So we need to figure out for a
fixed value of x, what are the
bounds on y?
So we see from this picture that
for any fixed value of x,
y goes from 0--
the x-axis--
up to this line.
OK?
So on the x-axis, y takes the
value 0, and on this line, y
takes the value 1 minus x.
Finally, our outermost variable
of integration is x,
and so we need to know what are
the absolute largest and
smallest values that x takes.
So we can do that looking either
at this picture or
looking at our original
picture.
Either way, it's not hard
to see that x just goes
between 0 and 1.
The smallest value that
x takes in this
tetrahedron is 0.
The largest value
it takes is 1.
So that's our integral that
we have to compute.
So that's not that bad at all.
So now you have to go through
and you have to actually
integrate this.
Yeah?
And so I'm going to look at my
notes just to make sure I
don't make any big arithmetic
mistakes.
So let's see.
Now we do these one at a time.
So this innermost integral
is an integral of z dz.
OK, well that's easy.
That's z squared over 2.
And then we're taking z squared
over 2 between 0 and 1
minus x minus y.
So this innermost integral is z
squared over 2 between 0 and
1 minus x minus y.
So that's equal to what the
innermost integral gives us,
which is 1 minus x minus
y squared over 2.
So that's what we get for
the innermost integral.
So our integral that we're
looking at then is equal to
the integral as x goes from 0
to 1, of the integral as y
goes from 0 to 1 minus
x of this integrand.
So this is the inner one.
Let me write that.
That's what I've got here.
Just integrating z with respect
to z gives me z
squared over 2.
And then I evaluated at the
bounds of the integral.
OK, so now I need to
do the middle one.
So let's do that up here.
So I need to compute
the integral.
So now I take the bounds for the
middle one is y, and the
bounds are from 0 to 1 minus
x of the inner integral.
This thing that I
just computed.
So that's of 1 minus x minus
y squared over 2, dy.
OK.
So All right.
So this isn't that bad.
This is a quadratic
polynomial in y.
And so it's not terribly
hard to see.
I'm running a little bit
out of board space.
So I'm not going to give you a
full, detailed explanation.
But it's not hard to see, I
think, that this integral of 1
minus x minus y squared over 2
with respect to y is 1 minus x
minus y cubed over 3, but it's
negative, because the sign
here is negative.
And you could check by
differentiating this and
seeing that you get that.
And so we have to evaluate
that as y goes from
0 to 1 minus x.
So what do we get?
Well, when y is equal to
one minus x, this is 0.
So we get 0 minus--
and when y is equal to 0, this
is minus 1 minus x quantity
cubed over 6--
so it's minus minus, so that's
just 1 minus x cubed over 6.
And so finally the outermost
integral is we take the inner
two integrals and we integrate
them with respect to x as x
goes from 0 to 1.
So it's the integral from
0 to 1 of 1 minus x
cubed over 6, dx.
And that's going to equal--
I've run out of space--
1 over 24.
All right.
Except I've done something wrong
right at the beginning.
I hope you all caught me.
Right?
I had this 1 over v factor
here, and it disappeared.
Right?
I forgot about this 1 over v,
so over here, I should have
written 1 over v right in
front of that integral.
I've correctly computed 1 over
24 as the value of my triple
integral, but the average height
here isn't 1 over 24.
It's 1 over 24v. All right.
So the average height is 1 over
24v, and so we need to go
and we need to look at our
tetrahedron and figure out
what its volume is.
So if we come over here and
see our tetrahedron.
Now this is nice, simple
tetrahedron.
The volume of a tetrahedron is
1/3 the area of the base times
the height, right?
So this is a nice,
easy tetrahedron.
Its height is 1.
Its base is a right triangle
whose legs are both 1.
So the base area is 1/2,
so the volume is 1/6.
So if the volume is 1/6, and we
said the average value is 1
over 24v, so that works
out to 1 over 4.
So let me write that
just in this space.
So the average height
then is 1 over 4.
So that's going to be
our final answer.
OK, so let's just recap
briefly what we did.
We had an average value problem
that we started with.
So we use this general formula
for average value problems.
When you have a function f
that you want to take its
average value of over a region
R, what do you do?
Well, you take 1 over the volume
of the region times the
triple integral of your function
f with respect to
volume over that region.
OK.
So this is the average
value in general.
In our particular case, the
function was the height.
It was z.
And then you have to set it out
choosing the proper bounds
for your integrals.
So in this case, you choose
some order of integration
based on the region.
In this particular case, it's
a nice, simple region.
It doesn't matter too much
what order you choose.
So I chose dz dy dx.
And then what does that mean?
So for the innermost one, you
look at your original solid.
So I'm going to go back and look
at this picture again.
So for your innermost variable
you say-- so if it's z-- you
say, so when I fix x and y,
what's the bottom surface and
what's the top surface when
I solve that for z in
terms of x and y?
So here, that was the plane z
equals 0, and the plane z
equals 1 minus x minus y.
So that explains my
bounds over here.
Why they were 0 and
1 minus x minus y.
Then, when you go to your
next variable-- in this
case, it was y--
what do you do?
Well, first you project to
eliminate this first variable.
So you project your
region down.
Down in this case,
because it's z.
So you project in
the z-direction.
And you draw this shadow
of your region.
So this is what I drew here.
This is the shadow of my region
in the xy plane after I
projected it.
And then you do the
same thing.
So now this just like what you
did when you had to find
bounds for double integrals,
when you wrote them as
iterated integrals a
few lectures ago.
And so then you do
the same thing.
So then in this case, I
was next integrating
with respect to y.
So I needed to find the bounds
on y with respect to x.
So I needed to look in this
picture at the bottom edge and
the top edge of this region.
And then your outermost
variable, you look at its
absolute bounds.
So the largest and smallest
value it takes on the region.
OK, then you have an iterated
integral and you evaluate it
by successive integrations.
OK.
So that was what we did.
We just did the three integrals,
starting from the
inside and working our way out.