MARTINA BALAGOVIC: Welcome.
Today's problem actually
appeared in a quiz.
It appeared in quiz one in fall
of 1999 as question four.
The problem puts the usual solve
the following system
upside down by saying we have
some matrix and we know that
all the solutions to ax equals
this vector here, 1, 4, 1, 1,
all the solutions to this
problem are given by x equals
0, 1, 1 plus any number
c times 1, 2, 1.
And we're asked to say
everything that we can about
the columns of the matrix A.
So I'm going to let you pretend
that you are on an
exam, try to solve it yourself,
and then come back
and compare your solution
with mine.
OK, welcome back.
So the first thing that you
should think about in this
sort of situation is what
is the size of a?
Well if we want to multiply a
with an x, that has three
entries, so a should
have three columns.
Let me call those columns
c1, c2, and c3.
And when I take some linear
combinations of c1, c2 and c3,
I'm going to get this vector
here, 1, 4, 1, 1.
So all the ci's, c1, c2, and
c3 are vectors in R4.
Now, if you know about, if you
learned about particular
solutions and special solutions,
then my notation
here shouldn't surprise you.
I'm going to call this
vector here xp, and
this vector here xs.
And I'm going to use the fact
that xp plus c times xs
satisfies A times
this equals b.
I will call this vector
b, for any number c.
In particular, what I'm going
to conclude is that when c
equals 0 we get a times
xp equals b.
But also that when c equals 1,
we get a times xp plus a times
xs equals b.
Replacing this by b, we get that
this implies that a times
Axs equals 0.
So in trying to find what are
the columns, c1, c2, and c3 of
the matrix A, let's look
at these two equations.
xp satisfies a times xp equals
b, and xs satisfies A
times xs equals 0.
Again, if you know what a
particular and special
solutions are this shouldn't
surprise you.
But we also know what xp and xs
are, so let's use them to
try to calculate
c1, c2, and c3.
A times xp equals b means that
the linear combination of c1,
c2, and c3 encoded in the vector
xp, which is 0, 1, 1,
gives the vector b.
So c1, c2, c3 times 0, 1,
1 gives us 1, 4, 1, 1.
In other words, c2
plus c3 equal b.
Let's turn our attention
to A times xs equals 0.
This says that c1, c2, c3 times
xs was defined to be 0,
2, 1 equals 0.
In other words, 2 times
c2 plus c3 equals 0.
Now solving this system where
the unknowns are vectors but
it's still just a linear
system, we can see, for
example, from the second
equation that c3
equals minus 2c2.
And plugging it back into the
original equation getting c2
minus 2c2 equals b from which it
follows that c2 is equal to
minus b, and that c3 is
equal to 2 times b.
So from this tiny amount of
information, we just knew the
solutions to this one particular
equation involving
A, we got the second column of
A and the third column of A
completely explicitly
calculated.
Now, what can we say about
the first column?
I said before that all the
solutions of ax equals b are
of the form a particular
solution plus some number
times a special solution.
And the information that we have
is that there's just one
number here.
So we said everything, once we
remove this vector here,
everything that we get
here will satisfy A
times x equals 0.
And the fact that everything
that satisfies A times x
equals 0 is a multiple of this
one vector that was given to
us means that the null space
of A has dimension one.
There is just one special
solution.
So dimension of the null
space of A is 1.
So rank of A is the number of
columns minus this dimension
of null space, and
it's equal to 2.
As rank of A is equal to 2,
the number of linearly
independent columns needs
to be 2 as well.
So the only thing that we can
say at this point is if the
first column was also a multiple
of b, as the second
and the third are, then the rank
would be smaller than 2.
So that is the only thing
that cannot happen.
So c1 is not a multiple of b.
Not any multiple, including
not a 0 multiple.
And that's pretty much
everything we can say.
Yes, if it was some other
multiple of it, then we would
be able to find some other
vector here and we would have
two parameters.
But it's not, and this
is everything that we
can say about it.