The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons License.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or to view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: All right, so
let's begin Lecture Six.
We're talking today about
exponentials and logarithms.
And these are the last
functions that I need to
introduce, the last standard
functions that we need to
connect with Calculus, that
you've learned about.
And they're certainly as
fundamental, if not more so,
than trigonometric functions.
So first of all, we'll start
out with a number, a, which
is positive, which is
usually called a base.
And then we have these
properties that a to the
power 0 is always 1.
That's how we get started.
And a^1 is a.
And of course a^2 ,
not surprisingly,
is a times a, etc.
And the general rule is that
a^(X1 X2) is a^X1 times a^X2 .
So this is the basic rule of
exponents, and with these two
initial properties,
that defines the
exponential function.
And then there's an additional
property, which is deduced from
these, which is the composition
of exponential functions, which
is that you take a to the
X1 power, to the X2 power.
Then that turns out to be
a to the X1 times X2.
So that's an additional
property that we'll take
for granted, which you
learned in high school.
Now, in order to understand
what all the values of a^x are,
we need to first remember that
if you're taking a rational
power that it's the ratio of
two integers power of a.
That's going to be a ^ m, and
then we're want to have to
take the nth root of that.
So that's the definition.
And then, when you're defining
a ^ x, so a^x is defined
for all x by filling in.
So I'm gonna use that
expression in quotation
marks, "filling
in" by continuity.
This is really what your
calculator does when it gives
you a to the power x, because
you can't even punch in
the square root of x.
It doesn't really exist
on your calculator.
There's some decimal expansion.
So it takes the decimal
expansion to a certain length
and spits out a number
which is pretty close
to the correct answer.
But indeed, in theory, there is
an a to the power, square root
of 2, even though the square
root of 2 is irrational.
And there's a to the
pi and so forth.
All right, so that's the
exponential function, and
let's draw a picture of one.
So we'll try, say y = 2^X here.
And I'm not going to draw such
a careful graph, but let's just
plot the most important point,
which is the point (0,1).
That's 2^0, which is 1.
And then maybe we'll go
back up here to - 1 here.
And 2 to the - 1 is
this point here.
This is (-1, 0.5) .
The reciprocal.
And over here, we have
1, and so that goes
all the way up to 2.
And then exponentials
are remarkably fast.
So it's off the board what
happens next out at 2.
It's already above my range
here, but the graph looks
something like this.
All right.
Now I've just visually, at
least, graphically filled in
all the rest of the points.
You have to imagine all these
rational numbers, and so forth.
So this point here would
have been (1, 2).
And so forth.
All right?
So that's not too far along.
So now what's our goal?
Well, obviously we want
to do calculus here.
So our goal, here, for now -
and it's gonna take a while.
We have to think about
it pretty hard.
We have to calculate what
this derivative is.
All right, so we'll
get started.
And the way we get started is
simply by plugging in the
definition of the derivative.
The derivative is the limit as
delta x goes to 0 of a to the
x plus delta x, minus a to
the x, divided by delta x.
So that's what it is.
And now, the only step that we
can really perform here to make
this is into something a little
bit simpler is to use this very
first rule that we have here.
That the exponential of
the sum is the product
of the exponentials.
So we have here, a^x .
So what I want to use is
just the property that a^x
delta x = (a^x) (a^delta x).
And if I do that, I see that I
can factor out a common factor
in the numerator, which is a^x.
So we'll write this as the
limit as delta x goes to 0, of
a to the x times this ratio,
now a to the delta x, minus
1, divided by delta x.
So far, so good?
We're actually almost to
some serious progress here.
So there's one other important
conceptual step which
we need to understand.
And this is a
relatively simple one.
We actually did this
before, by the way.
We did this with
sines and cosines.
The next thing I want to point
out to you is that you're used
to thinking of x as
being the variable.
And indeed, already we were
discussing x as being the
variable and a as being fixed.
But for the purposes of this
limit, there's a different
variable that's moving. x is
fixed and delta x is the
thing that's moving.
So that means that this factor
here, which is a common
factor, is constant.
And we can just factor
it out of the limit.
It doesn't affect
the limit at all.
A constant times a limit is the
same as whether we multiply
before or after we
take the limit.
So I'm just going to
factor that out.
So that's my next step here.
a^x, and then I have the limit.
Delta x goes to 0 of a
to the delta x minus
1, divided by delta x.
All right?
And so what I have here,
so this is by definition
the derivative.
So here is d/ dx of
a^x, and it's equal to
this expression here.
Now, I want to stare at this
expression, and see what it's
telling us, because it's
telling us as much as we can
get so far, without some...
So first let's just look
at what this says.
So what it's saying is that the
derivative of a^x is a^x times
something that we
don't yet know.
And I'm going to call
this something, this
mystery number, M(a) .
So I'm gonna make the label,
M(a) is equal to the limit as
delta x goes to 0 of a to
the delta x minus 1
divided by delta x.
All right?
So this is a definition.
So this mystery number
M(a) has a geometric
interpretation, as well.
So let me describe that.
It has a geometric
interpretation, and it's a
very, very significant number.
So let's work out what that is.
So first of all, let's rewrite
the expression in the box,
using the shorthand
for this number.
So if I just rewrite it, it
says d/dx of a^x is equal
to this factor, which
is M(a), times a^x .
So the derivative of the
exponential is this
mystery number times a^x.
So we've almost solved the
problem of finding the
derivative of a^x.
We just have to figure out
this one number, M(a),
and we get the rest.
So let me point out two more
things about this number, M(a).
So first of all, if I plug in
x = 0, that's going to be
d / dx of a^x , at x = 0.
According to this formula,
that's M(a) times a^0 ,
which of course M(a).
So what is M(a) ?
M(a) is the derivative
of this function at 0.
So M(a) is the slope of a^x
at x = 0, of the graph.
The graph of a^x at 0.
So again over here, if you
looked at the picture.
I'll draw the one tangent
line in here, which
is this one here.
And this thing has slope,
what we're calling M(2).
So, if I graph the function
y = 2 ^x, I'll get a
certain slope here.
If I graph it with a
different base, I might
get another slope.
And what we got so far is the
following phenomenon: if we
know this one number, if we
know the slope at this one
place, we will be able to
figure out the formula for
the slope everywhere else.
Now, that's actually exactly
the same thing that we did
for sines and cosines.
We knew the slope of the
sine and the cosine
function at x = 0.
The sine function had slope 1.
The cosine function
had slope 0.
And then from the sum formulas,
well that's exactly this kind
of thing here, from
the sum formulas.
This sum formula, in fact
is easier than the ones
for sines and cosines.
From the sum formulas,
we worked out what the
slope was everywhere.
So we're following the same
procedure that we did before.
But at this point we're stuck.
We're stuck, because that time
using radians, this very clever
idea of radians in geometry, we
were able to actually figure
out what the slope is.
Whereas here, we're not
so sure, what M(2)
is, for instance.
We just don't know yet.
So, the basic question that
we have to deal with right
now is what is M(a)?
That's what we're left with.
And, the curious fact is
that the clever thing to
do is to beg the question.
So we're going to go through
a very circular route here.
That is circuitous,
not circular.
Circular is a bad word in math.
That means that one thing
depends on another, and
that depends on it, and
maybe both are wrong.
Circuitous means, we're
going to be taking
a roundabout route.
And we're going to discover
that even though we refuse to
answer this question right
now, we'll succeed in
answering it eventually.
All right?
So how are we going
to beg the question?
What we're going to say instead
is we're going to define a
mystery base, or number e, as
the unique number,
so that M(e) = 1.
That's the trick that
we're going to use.
We don't yet know what e is,
but we're just going to
suppose that we have it.
Now, I'm going to show you a
bunch of consequences of this,
and also I have to persuade you
that it actually does exist.
So first, let me explain what
the first consequence is.
First of all, if M(e) is 1,
then if you look at this
formula over here and you write
it down for e, you have
something which is a very
usable formula. d / dx
of e^x is just e^x.
All right, so that's an
incredibly important formula
which is the fundamental one.
It's the only one you have to
remember from what we've done.
So maybe I should have
highlighted it in
several colors here.
That's a big deal.
Very happy.
And again, let me just
emphasize, also that this
is the one which at
x = 0 has slope 1.
That's the way we
defined it, alright?
So if you plug in x = 0 here on
the right hand side, you got 1.
Slope 1 at x = 0.
So that's great.
Except of course, since we
don't know what e is, this
is a little bit dicey.
So, next even before
explaining what e is...
In fact, we won't get to
what e really is until the
very end of this lecture.
But I have to persuade
you why e exists.
We have to have some
explanation for why we know
there is such a number.
Ok, so first of all, let me
start with the one that we
supposedly know, which
is the function 2^x .
We'll call it f(x) is 2^x.
All right?
So that's the first thing.
And remember, that the property
that it had, was that
f '(0) was M(2) .
That was the derivative of
this function, the slope
of x = 0. of the graph.
Of the tangent line, that is.
So now, what we're going
to consider is any
kind of stretching.
We're going to stretch this
function by a factor k.
Any number k.
So what we're going to
consider is f(kx).
If you do that, that's
the same as 2^kx.
Right?
But now if I use the second law
of exponents that I have over
there, that's the same thing as
2 to the k to the power x,
which is the same thing as some
base b ^ x, where
b is equal to...
Let's write that down
over here. b is 2^k .
Right.
So whatever it is, if I have
a different base which is
expressed in terms of 2, by
being of the form 2^k , then
that new function is
described by this function f
(kx) , the stretch.
So what happens when you
stretch a function?
That's the same thing as
shrinking the x axis.
So when k gets larger, this
corresponding point over here
would be over here, and so
this corresponding point
would be over here.
So you shrink this picture,
and the slope here tilts up.
So, as we increase k, the slope
gets steeper and steeper.
Let's see that explicitly,
numerically here.
Explicitly, numerically, if I
take the derivative here...
So the derivative with
respect to x of b^ x, that's
the chain rule, right?
That's the derivative
with respect to x of
f(kx), which is what?
It's k times f '(kx) .
And so if we do it at 0, we're
just getting k times f '(0) ,
which is k times this M(2).
So how is it exactly that we
cook up the right base b?
So b = e when k = 1
over this number.
In other words, we can pick all
possible slopes that we want.
This just has the effect
of multiplying the
slope by a factor.
And we can shift the slope at
0 however we want, and we're
going to do it so that the
slope exactly matches 1,
the one that we want.
We still don't know what k is.
We still don't know what e is.
But at least we know that
it's there somewhere.
Yes?
Student: How do you
know it's f(kx)?
PROFESSOR: How do I know?
Well, f(x) is 2 ^ x.
If f(x) is 2^x, then the
formula for f(kx) is this.
I've decided what f(x)
is, so therefore there's
a formula for f(kx).
And furthermore, by the chain
rule, there's a formula
for the derivative.
And it's k times the
derivative of f.
So again, scaling does this.
By the way, we did exactly
the same thing with the
sine and cosine function.
If you think of the sine
function here, let me just
remind you here, what happens
with the chain rule, you get
k times cosine k t here.
So the fact that we set things
up beautifully with radians
that this thing is, but we
could change the scale to
anything, such as degrees, by
the appropriate factor k.
And then there would be
this scale factor shift of
the derivative formulas.
Of course, the one with radians
is the easy one, because
the factor is 1.
The one with degrees is
horrible, because the factor is
some crazy number like 180 over
pi, or something like that.
Okay, so there's something
going on here which is
exactly the same as that
kind of re-scaling.
So, so far we've got only one
formula which is a keeper here.
This one.
We have a preliminary formula
that we still haven't
completely explained which has
a little wavy line there.
And we have to fit all
these things together.
Okay, so now to fit them
together, I need to
introduce the natural log.
So the natural log is
denoted this way, ln(x).
So maybe I'll call it a
new letter name, we'll
call it w = ln x here.
But if we were reversing
things, if we started out with
a function y = e^x , the
property that it would have is
that it's the inverse
function of e^x .
So it has the property
that the lny = x.
Right?
So this defines the log.
Now the logarithm has a bunch
of properties and they
come from the exponential
properties in principle.
You remember these.
And I'm just going to
remind you of them.
So the main one that I just
want to remind you of is that
the ln (X1*X2) = ln X1
ln X2.
And maybe a few more are
worth reminding you of.
One is that the
logarithm of 1 is 0.
A second is that the
logarithm of e is 1.
Alright?
So these correspond to the
inverse relationships here.
If I plug in here,
x = 0 and x = 1.
If I plug in x = 0 and x = 1, I
get the corresponding numbers
here: y = 1 and y = e.
And maybe it would be worth
it to plot the picture
once to reinforce this.
So here I'll put them
on the same chart.
If you have here e
to the x over here.
It looks like this.
Then the logarithm which I'll
maybe put in a different color.
So this crosses at this all
important point here, (0,1).
And now in order to figure out
what the inverse function
is, I have to take the flip
across the diagonal, x = y.
So that's this shape here,
going down like this.
And here's the point (1, 0).
So (1, 0) corresponds
to this identity here.
But the log of 1 is 0.
And notice, so this is ln
x, the graph of ln x.
And notice it's only defined
for x positive, which
corresponds to the fact that e
to the x is always positive.
So in other words, this white
curve is only above this axis,
and the orange one is
to the right here.
It's only defined
for x positive.
Oh, one other thing I should
mention is the slope here is 1.
And so the slope there
is also going to be 1.
Now, what we're allowed to do
relatively easily, because we
have the tools to do it, is to
compute the derivative
of the logarithm.
So to find the derivative of
a log, we're going to use
implicit differentiation.
This is how we find
the derivative of any
inverse function.
So remember the way that works
is if you know the derivative
of the function, you can find
the derivative of the
inverse function.
And the mechanism is the
following: you write
down here w = ln x.
Here's the function.
We're trying to find
the derivative of w.
But now we don't know how to
differentiate this equation,
but if we exponentiate it,
so that's the same
thing as e^w = x.
Because let's just
stick this in here.
e^ln x = x.
Now we can differentiate this.
So let's do the
differentiation here.
We have d/dx e ^ w = d
/ dx of x, which is 1.
And then this, by the
chain rule, is d / dw
of e^w times dw /dx.
The product of
these two factors.
That's equal to 1.
And now this guy, the one
little guy that we actually
know and can use,
that's this guy here.
So this is e^w times
dw/ dx, which is 1.
And so finally, dw/
dx = 1 / e^w .
But what is that?
It's x.
So this is 1 / x.
So what we discovered is, and
now I get to put another green
guy around here, is that
this is equal to 1/x.
So alright, now we have two
companion formulas here.
The rate of change
of ln x is 1 / x.
And the rate of change of
e^x is itself, is e^x.
And it's time to return to the
problem that we were having a
little bit of trouble with,
which is somewhat not explicit,
which is this M(a) times x.
We want to now differentiate
a to the x in general;
not just e^x .
So let's work that out, and I
want to explain it in a couple
of ways, so you're want to have
to remember this, because
I'm going to erase it.
But what I'd like you to do is,
so now I want to teach you how
to differentiate basically
any exponential.
So now to differentiate
There are two methods.
They're practically
the same method.
They have the same
amount of arithmetic.
You'll see both of them, and
they're equally valuable.
So we're going to
just describes them.
Method one I'm going
to illustrate on
the function a^x .
So we're interested in
differentiating this thing,
exactly this problem that I
still didn't solve yet.
Ok?
So here it is.
And here's the procedure.
The procedure is to write, so
the method is to use base
e, or convert to base e.
So how do you
convert to base e?
Well, you write a^x
as e to some power.
So what power is it?
It's e to the power ln
a, to the power x.
And that is just e ^ x ln a.
So we've made our
conversion now to base e.
The exponential of something.
So now I'm going to carry
out the differentiation.
So d / dx of a ^x = d
/ dx of e ^ x ln a.
And now, this is a step which
causes great confusion
when you first see it.
And you must get used to it,
because it's easy, not hard.
Okay?
The rate of change of this
with respect to x is, let
me do it by analogy here.
Because say I had e ^ 3X and
I were differentiating it.
The chain rule would say that
this is just 3, the rate of
change of 3X with respect
to x times e ^ 3X.
The rate of change of e to
the u with respect to u.
So this is the
ordinary chain rule.
And what we're doing up here is
exactly the same thing, because
ln a, as frightening as it
looks, with all three letters
there, is just a fixed number.
It's not moving.
It's a constant.
So the constant just
accelerates the rate of change
by that factor, which is what
the chain rule is doing.
So this is equal to ln
a times e ^ x ln a.
Same business here with
ln a replacing 3.
So this is something you've got
to get used to in time for the
exam, for instance, because
you're going to be doing
a million of these.
So do get used to it.
So here's the formula.
On the other hand, this
expression here was
the same as a ^ x.
So another way of writing this,
and I'll put this into a
box, but actually I never
remember this particularly.
I just re-derive it every
time, is that the derivative
of a^x = (ln a) a^x .
Now I'm going to get rid
of what's underneath it.
So this is another formula.
So there's the formula I've
essentially finished here.
And notice, what is
the magic number?
The magic number is
the natural log of a.
That's what it was.
We didn't know what
it was in advance.
This is what it is.
It's the natural log of a.
Let me emphasize to you again,
something about what's going on
here, which has to do
with scale change.
So, for example, the derivative
with respect to x of
2^x is (ln 2) 2 ^ x.
The derivative with respect to
x, these are the two most
obvious bases that you might
want to use, is log
10 times 10^x .
So one of the things that's
natural about the natural
logarithm is that even if we
insisted that we must use base
2, or that we must use base 10,
we'd still be stuck with
natural logarithms.
They come up naturally.
They're the ones which are
independent of our human
construct of base
2 and base 10.
The natural logarithm is
the one that comes up
without reference.
And we'll be mentioning a
few other ways in which
it's natural later.
So I told you about this first
method, now I want to tell you
about a second method here.
So the second is called
logarithmic differentiation.
So how does this work?
Well, sometimes you're having
trouble differentiating a
function, and it's easier to
differentiate its logarithm.
That may seem peculiar, but
actually we'll give several
examples where this is clearly
the case, that the logarithm is
easier to differentiate
than the function.
So it could be that this is an
easier quantity to understand.
So we want to relate it
back to the function u.
So I'm going to write it a
slightly different way.
Let's write it in
terms of primes here.
So the basic identity is the
chain rule again, and the
derivative of the logarithm,
well maybe I'll write
it out this way first.
So this would be d of ln
u/ du, times du / dx .
These are the two factors.
And that's the same thing, so
remember what the derivative
of the logarithm is.
This is 1 / u.
So here I have a 1 / u, and
here I have a du / dx.
So I'm going to encode this on
the next board here, which is
sort of the main formula you
always need to remember, which
is that (ln u)' = u' / u.
That's the one to
remember here.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: The question is how
did I get this step here?
So this is the chain rule.
The rate of change of ln u with
respect to x is the rate of
change of ln u with respect u,
times the rate of change
of u with respect to x.
That's the chain rule.
So now I've worked out this
identity here, and now let's
show how it handles this
case, d / dx of a^x.
Let's do this one.
So in order to get that one,
I would take u = a^x .
And now let's just take
a look at what ln u is.
Ln u = x ln a.
Now I claimed that this is
pretty easy to differentiate.
Again, it may seem hard, but
it's actually quite easy.
So maybe somebody
can hazard a guess.
What's the derivative
of x ln a?
It's just log a.
So this is the same thing that
I was talking about before,
which is if you've got 3X, and
you're taking its derivative
with respect to x
here, that's just 3.
That's the kind of
thing you have.
Again, don't be put off by this
massive piece of junk here.
It's a constant.
So again, keep that in mind.
It comes up regularly in
this kind of question.
So there's is our formula,
that the logarithmic
derivative is this.
But let's just rewrite that.
That's the same thing as u'
/ u, which is log u prime
is equal to ln a, right?
So this is our
differentiation formula.
So here we have u'.
u' is equal to u times ln a, if
I just multiply through by u.
And that's what we wanted.
That's d / dx of a^x = ln
a (I'll reverse the order
of the two, which is
customary) times a^x.
So this is the way
that logarithmic
differentiation works.
It's the same arithmetic as the
previous method, but we don't
have to convert to base e.
We're just keeping track of
the exponents and doing
differentiation on the
exponents, and multiplying
through at the end.
Okay, so I'm going to do two
trickier examples, which
illustrate logarithmic
differentiation.
Again, these could be done
equally well by using base
e, but I won't do it.
Method one and method
two always both work.
So here's a second example:
again this is a problem when
you have moving exponents.
But this time, we're going to
complicate matters by having
both a moving exponent
and a moving base.
So we have a function u, which
is, well maybe I'll call it
v, since we already had a
function u, which is x ^ x.
A really complicated
looking function here.
So again you can handle
this by converting to
base e, method one.
But we'll do the logarithmic
differentiation
version, alright?
So I take the logs
of both sides.
And now I differentiate it.
And now when I differentiate
this here, I have to
use the product rule.
This time, instead of
having ln a, a constant,
I have a variable here.
So I have two factors.
I have ln x when I
differentiate with
respect to x.
When I differentiate with
respect to this factor here, I
get that x times the derivative
of that, which is 1/x.
So, here's my formula.
Almost finished.
So I have here v' / v.
I'm going to multiply these
two things together.
I'll put it on the other side,
because I don't want to get it
mixed up with ln x plus
one, the quantity.
And now I'm almost done.
I have v' = v (1
ln x), and that's just d /
dx( x ^x) = x^x (1 + lnx).
That's it.
So these two methods always
work for moving exponents.
So the next thing that I'd
like to do is another
fairly tricky example.
And this one is not strictly
speaking within Calculus.
Although we're going to use the
tools that we just described to
carry it out, in fact it will
use some Calculus
in the very end.
And what I'm going to do is I'm
going to evaluate the limit as
n goes to infinity of one plus
one over n to the power n.
So now, the reason why I want
to discuss this is, is it
turns out to have a very
interesting answer.
And it's a problem
that you can approach
exactly by this method.
And the reason is that it
has a moving exponent.
The exponent n
here is changing.
And so if you want to keep
track of that, a good way to
do that is to use logarithms.
So in order to figure out this
limit, we're going to take the
log of it and figure out what
the limit of the log is,
instead of the log
of the limit.
Those will be the same thing.
So we're going to take the
natural log of this quantity
here, and that's n ln (1
(1 / n)).
And now I'm going to rewrite
this in a form which will make
it more recognizable, so what
I'd like to do is I'm going to
write n or maybe I should say
it this way: delta x = 1 / n.
So if n is going to infinity,
then this delta x is
going to be going to 0.
So this is more familiar
territory for us in
this class, anyway.
So let's rewrite it.
So here, we have
one over delta x.
And then that is
multiplied by ln 1
delta x.
So n is the reciprocal
of delta x.
Now I want to change this
in a very, very minor way.
I'm going to
subtract 0 from it.
So that's the same thing.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to subtract ln 1 from it.
That's just equal to 0.
So this is not a problem,
and I'll put some
parentheses around it.
Now you're supposed to
recognize, all of a sudden,
what pattern this fits into.
This is the thing which we need
to calculate in order to
calculate the derivative
of the log function.
So this is in the limit as
delta x goes to 0 equal to
the derivative of ln x.
Where?
Well the base point is x=1.
That's where we're
evaluating it.
That's the X0.
That's the base value.
So this is the
difference quotient.
That's exactly what it is.
And so this by definition
tends to the limit here.
But we know what the derivative
of the log function is.
The derivative of the
log function is 1 / x.
So this limit is 1.
So we got it.
We got the limit.
And now we just have to work
backwards to figure out what
this limit that we've
got over here is.
So let's do that.
So let's see here the
log approached 1.
So the limit as n goes
to infinity of 1 plus
(1 over n) to the n.
So sorry, the log of this.
Yeah, let's write it this way.
It's the same thing, as well,
the thing that we know
is the log of this.
1 plus 1 over n to the n.
And goes to infinity.
That's the one that
we just figured out.
But now this thing is the
exponential of that.
So it's really e to
this power here.
So this guy is the same as the
limit of the log of the limit
of the thing, which is the
same as log of the limit.
The limit of the log and the
log of the limit are the same.
Ok, so I take the logarithm,
then I'm going to
take the exponential.
That just undoes
what I did before.
And so this limit is
just 1, is e ^ 1.
And so the limit that we
want here is equal to e.
So I claim that with this
step, we've actually
closed the loop, finally.
Because we have an honest
numerical way to calculate e.
The first.
There are many such.
But this one is a perfectly
honest numerical
way to calculate e.
We had this thing.
We didn't know
exactly what it was.
It was this M(e), there was
M(a), the logarithm, and so on.
We have all that stuff.
But we really didn't
need to nail down what
this number e is.
And this is telling us, if you
take for example 1 plus 1 over
100 to the 100th power, that's
going to be a very good,
perfectly decent anyway,
approximation to e.
So this is a numerical
approximation, which is all we
can ever do with just this
kind of irrational number.
And so that closes the loop,
and we now have a coherent
family of functions, which are
actually well defined and for
which we have practical
methods to calculate.
Okay see you next time.