Well, we knew how to find them
by that determinant of A minus
lambda I equals zero.
But, of course,
there could be shortcuts.
There could be,
like, useful information about
the eigenvalues that we can
speed things up with.
OK.
Then, the new stuff starts out
with a differential equation,
so I'll do a problem.
I'll do a differential equation
problem first.
What's special about symmetric
matrices?
Can we just say that in words?
I'd better write it down,
though.
What's special about symmetric
matrices?
Their eigenvalues are real.
The eigenvalues of a symmetric
matrix always come out real,
and there always are enough
eigenvectors.
Even if there are repeated
eigenvalues, there are enough
eigenvectors,
and we can choose those
eigenvectors to be orthogonal.
So if A equals A transposed,
the big fact will be that we
can diagonalize it,
and those eigenvector matrix,
with the eigenvectors in the
column, can be an orthogonal
matrix.
So we get a Q lambda Q
transpose.
That, in three symbols,
expresses a wonderful fact,
a fundamental fact for
symmetric matrices.
OK.
Then, we went beyond that fact
to ask about positive definite
matrices, when the eigenvalues
were positive.
I'll do an example of that.
Now we've left symmetry.
Similar matrices are any square
matrices, but two matrices are
similar if they're related that
way.
And what's the key point about
similar matrices?
Somehow, those matrices are
representing the same thing in
different basis,
in chapter seven language.
In chapter six language,
what's up with these similar
matrices?
What's the key fact,
the key positive fact about
similar matrices?
They have the same eigenvalues.
Same eigenvalues.
So if one of them grows,
the other one grows.
If one of them decays to zero,
the other one decays to zero.
Powers of A will look like
powers of B, because powers of A
and powers of B only differ by
an M inverse and an M way on the
outside.
So if these are similar,
then B to the k-th power is M
inverse A to the k-th power M.
And that's why I say,
eh, this M, it does change the
eigenvectors,
but it doesn't change the
eigenvalues.
So same lambdas.
And then, finally,
I've got to review the point
about the SVD,
the Singular Value
Decomposition.
OK.
So that's what this quiz has
got to cover,
and now I'll just take problems
from earlier exams,
starting with a differential
equation.
OK.
And always ready for questions.
So here is an exam from about
the year zero,
and it has a three by three.
So that was -- but it's a
pretty special-looking matrix,
it's got zeroes on the
diagonal, it's got minus ones
above, and it's got plus ones
like that.
So that's the matrix A.
OK.
Step one is,
well, I want to solve that
equation.
I want to find the general
solution.
I haven't given you a u(0)
here, so I'm looking for the
general solution,
so now what's the form of the
general solution?
With three arbitrary constants
going to be inside it,
because those will be used to
match the initial condition.
So the general form is u at
time t is some multiple of the
first special solution.
The first special solution will
be growing like the eigenvalue,
and it's the eigenvector.
So that's a pure exponential
solution, just staying with that
eigenvector.
Of course, I haven't found,
yet, the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors.
That's, normally,
the first job.
Now, there will be second one,
growing like e to the lambda
two, and a third one growing
like e to the lambda three.
So we're all done -- well,
we haven't done anything yet,
actually.
I've got to find the
eigenvalues and eigenvectors,
and then I would match u(0) by
choosing the right three
constants.
OK.
So now I ask -- ask you about
the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors,
and you look at this matrix and
what do you see in that matrix?
Um, well, I guess we might ask
ourselves right away,
is it singular?
Is it singular?
Because, if so,
then we really have a head
start, we know one of the
eigenvalues is zero.
Is that matrix singular?
Eh, I don't know,
do you take the determinant to
find out?
Or maybe you look at the first
row and third row and say,
hey, the first row and third
row are just opposite signs,
they're linear-dependent?
The first column and third
column are dependent -- it's
singular.
So one eigenvalue is zero.
Let's make that lambda one.
Lambda one, then,
will be zero.
OK.
Now we've got a couple of other
eigenvalues to find,
and, I suppose the simplest way
is to look at A minus lambda I
So let me just put minus lambda
in here, minus ones above,
ones below.
But, actually,
before I do it,
that matrix is not symmetric,
for sure, right?
In fact, it's the very opposite
of symmetric.
That matrix A transpose,
how is A transpose connected to
A?
It's negative A.
It's an anti-symmetric matrix,
skew-symmetric matrix.
And we've met,
maybe, a two-by-two example of
skew-symmetric matrices,
and let me just say,
what's the deal with their
eigenvalues?
They're pure imaginary.
They'll be on the imaginary
axis, there be some multiple of
I if it's an anti-symmetric,
skew-symmetric matrix.
So I'm looking for multiples of
I, and of course,
that's zero times I,
that's on the imaginary axis,
but maybe I just do it out,
here.
Lambda cubed.
well, maybe that's minus lambda
cubed, and then a zero and a
zero.
Zero, and then maybe I have a
plus a lambda,
and another plus lambda,
but those go with a minus sign.
Am I getting minus two lambda
equals zero?
So.
So I'm solving lambda cube plus
two lambda equals zero.
So one root factors out lambda,
and the the rest is lambda
squared plus two.
OK.
This is going the way we
expect, right?
Because this gives the root
lambda equals zero,
and gives the other two roots,
which are lambda equal what?
The solutions of when is lambda
squared plus two equals zero
then the eigenvalues those guys,
what are they?
They're a multiple of i,
they're just square root of two
i.
When I set this equals to zero,
I have lambda squared equal to
minus two, right?
To make that zero?
And the roots are square root
of two i and minus the square
root of two i.
So now I know what those are.
I'll put those in,
now.
Either the zero t is just a
one.
That's just a one.
This is square root of two I
and this is minus square root of
two I.
So, is the solution decaying to
zero?
Is this a completely stable
problem where the solution is
going to zero?
No.
In fact, all these things are
staying the same size.
This thing is getting
multiplied by this number.
e to the I something t,
that's a number that has
magnitude one,
and sort of wanders around the
unit circle.
Same for this.
So that the solution doesn't
blow up, and it doesn't go to
zero.
OK.
And to find out what it
actually is, we would have to
plug in initial conditions.
But actually,
the next question I ask is,
when does the solution return
to its initial value?
I won't even say what's the
initial value.
This is a case in which I think
this solution is periodic after.
At t equals zero,
it starts with c1,
c2, and c3, and then at some
value of t, it comes back to
that.
So that's a very special
question, Well,
let's just take three seconds,
because that special question
isn't likely to be on the quiz.
But it comes back to the start,
when?
Well, whenever we have e to the
two pi i, that's one,
and we've come back again.
So it comes back to the start.
It's periodic,
when this square root of two i
-- shall I call it capital T,
for the period?
For that particular T,
if that equals two pi i,
then e to this thing is one,
and we've come around again.
So the period is T is
determined here,
cancel the i-s,
and T is pi times the square
root of two.
So that's pretty neat.
We get all the information
about all solutions,
we haven't fixed on only one
particular solution,
but it comes around again.
So this was probably my first
chance to say something about
the whole family of
anti-symmetric,
skew-symmetric matrices.
OK.
And then, finally,
I asked, take two eigenvectors
(again, I haven't computed the
eigenvectors) and it turns out
they're orthogonal.
They're orthogonal.
The eigenvectors of a symmetric
matrix, or a skew-symmetric
matrix, are always orthogonal.
I guess may conscience makes me
tell you, what are all the
matrices that have orthogonal
eigenvectors?
And symmetric is the most
important class,
so that's the one we've spoken
about.
But let me just put that little
fact down, here.
Orthogonal x-s.
eigenvectors.
A matrix has orthogonal
eigenvectors,
the exact condition -- it's
quite beautiful that I can tell
you exactly when that happens.
It happens when A times A
transpose equals A transpose
times A.
Any time that's the condition
for orthogonal eigenvectors.
And because we're interested in
special families of vectors,
tell me some special families
that fit.
This is the whole requirement.
That's a pretty special
requirement most matrices have.
So the average three-by-three
matrix has three eigenvectors,
but not orthogonal.
But if it happens to commute
with its transpose,
then, wonderfully,
the eigenvectors are
orthogonal.
Now, do you see how symmetric
matrices pass this test?
Of course.
If A transpose equals A,
then both sides are A squared,
we've got it.
How do anti-symmetric matrices
pass this test?
If A transpose equals minus A,
then we've got it again,
because we've got minus A
squared on both sides.
So that's another group.
And finally,
let me ask you about our other
favorite family,
orthogonal matrices.
Do orthogonal matrices pass
this test, if A is a Q,
do they pass the test for
orthogonal eigenvectors.
Well, if A is Q,
an orthogonal matrix,
what is Q transpose Q?
It's I.
And what is Q Q transpose?
It's I, we're talking square
matrices here.
So yes, it passes the test.
So the special cases are
symmetric, anti-symmetric (I'll
say skew-symmetric,) and
orthogonal.
Those are the three important
special classes that are in this
family.
OK.
That's like a comment that,
could have been made back in,
section six point four.
OK, I can pursue the
differential equations,
also this question,
didn't ask you to tell me,
how would I find this matrix
exponential, e to the At?
So can I erase this?
I'll just stay with this
same...
how would I find e to the At?
Because, how does that come in?
That's the key matrix for a
differential equation,
because the solution is -- the
solution is u(t) is e^(At) u(0).
So this is like the fundamental
matrix that multiplies the given
function and gives the answer.
And how would we compute it if
we wanted that?
We don't always have to find e
to the At, because I can go
directly to the answer without
any e to the At-s,
but hiding here is an e to the
At, and how would I compute it?
Well, if A is diagonalizable.
So I'm now going to put in my
usual if A can be diagonalized
(and everybody remember that
there is an if there,
because it might not have
enough eigenvectors) this
example does have enough,
random matrices have enough.
So if we can diagonalize,
then we get a nice formula for
this, because an S comes way out
at the beginning,
and S inverse comes way out at
the end, and we only have to
take the exponential of lambda.
And that's just a diagonal
matrix, so that's just e the
lambda one t,
these guys are showing up,
now, in e to the lambda nt.
OK?
That's a really quick review of
that formula.
It's something we can compute
it quickly if we have done the S
and lambda part.
If we know S and lambda,
then it's not hard to take that
step.
OK, that's some comments on
differential equations.
I would like to go on to a next
question that I started here.
And it's, got several parts,
and I can just read it out.
What we're given is a
three-by-three matrix,
and we're told its eigenvalues,
except one of these is,
like, we don't know,
and we're told the
eigenvectors.
And I want to ask you about the
matrix.
OK.
So, first question.
Is the matrix diagonalizable?
And I really mean for which c,
because I don't know c,
so my questions will all be,
for which is there a condition
on c, does one c work.
But your answer should tell me
all the c-s that work.
I'm not asking for you to tell
me, well, c equal four,
yes, that checks out.
I want to know all the c-s that
make it diagonalizable.
OK?
What's the real on
diagonalizable?
We need enough eigenvectors,
right?
We don't care what those
eigenvalues are,
it's eigenvectors that count
for
diagonalizable,
and we need three independent
ones, and are those three guys
independent?
Yes.
Actually, let's look at them
for a moment.
What do you see about those
three vectors right away?
They're more than independent.
Can you see why those three got
chosen?
Because it will come up in the
next part, they're orthogonal.
Those eigenvectors are
orthogonal.
They're certainly independent.
So the answer to diagonalizable
is, yes, all c,
all c.
Doesn't matter.
c could be a repeated guy,
but we've got enough
eigenvectors,
so that's what we care about.
OK, second question.
For which values of c is it
symmetric?
OK, what's the answer to that
one?
If we know the same setup if we
know that much about it,
we know those eigenvectors,
and we've noticed they're
orthogonal, then which c-s will
work?
So the eigenvalues of that
symmetric matrix have to be
real.
So all real c.
If c was i, the matrix wouldn't
have been symmetric.
But if c is a real number,
then we've got real
eigenvalues, we've got
orthogonal eigenvectors,
that matrix is symmetric.
OK, positive definite.
OK, now this is a sub-case of
symmetric, so we need c to be
real, so we've got a symmetric
matrix, but we also want the
thing to be positive definite.
Now, we're looking at
eigenvalues, we've got a lot of
tests for positive definite,
but eigenvalues,
if we know them,
is certainly a good,
quick, clean test.
Could this matrix be positive
definite?
No.
No, because it's got an
eigenvalue zero.
It could be positive
semi-definite,
you know, like consolation
prize, if c was greater or equal
to zero, it would be positive
semi-definite.
But it's not,
no.
Semi-definite,
if I put that comment in,
semi-definite,
that the condition would be c
greater or equal to zero.
That would be all right.
OK.
Next part.
Is it a Markov matrix?
Hm.
Could this matrix be,
if I choose the number c
correctly, a Markov matrix?
Well, what do we know about
Markov matrices?
Mainly, we know something about
their eigenvalues.
One eigenvalue is always one,
and the other eigenvalues are
smaller.
Not larger.
So an eigenvalue two can't
happen.
So the answer is,
no, not a ma- that's never a
Markov matrix.
OK?
And finally,
could one half of A be a
projection matrix?
So could it- could this --
eh-eh could this be twice a
projection matrix?
So let me write it this way.
Could A over two be a
projection matrix?
OK, what are projection
matrices?
They're real.
I mean, th- they're symmetric,
so their eigenvalues are real.
But more than that,
we know what those eigenvalues
have to be.
What do the eigenvalues of a
projection matrix have to be?
See, that any nice matrix we've
got an idea about its
eigenvalues.
So the eigenvalues of
projection matrices are zero and
one.
Zero and one,
only.
Because P squared equals P,
let me call this matrix P,
so P squared equals P,
so lambda squared equals
lambda, because eigenvalues of P
squared are lambda squared,
and we must have that,
so lambda equals zero or one.
OK.
Now what value of c will work
there?
So, then, there are some value
that will work,
and what will work?
c equals zero will work,
or what else will work?
c equal to two.
Because if c is two,
then when we divide by two,
this Eigenvalue of two will
drop to one, and so will the
other one, so,
or c equal to two.
OK, those are the guys that
will work, and it was the fact
that those eigenvectors were
orthogonal, the fact that those
eigenvectors were orthogonal
carried us a lot of the way,
here.
If they weren't orthogonal,
then symmetric would have been
dead, positive definite would
have been dead,
projection would have been
dead.
But those eigenvectors were
orthogonal, so it came down to
the eigenvalues.
OK, that was like a chance to
review a lot of this chapter.
Shall I jump to the singular
value decomposition,
then, as the third,
topic for, for the review?
OK, so I'm going to.
jump to this.
OK.
So this is the singular value
decomposition,
known to everybody as the SVD.
And that's a factorization of A
into orthogonal times diagonal
times orthogonal.
And we always call those U and
sigma and V transpose.
OK.
And the key to that -- this is
for every matrix,
every A, every A.
Rectangular,
doesn't matter,
whatever, has this
decomposition.
So it's really important.
And the key to it is to look at
things like A transpose A.
Can we remember what happens
with A transpose A?
If I just transpose that I get
V sigma transpose U transpose,
that's multiplying A,
which is U, sigma V transpose,
and the result is V on the
outside, s- U transpose U is the
identity, because it's an
orthogonal matrix.
So I'm just left with sigma
transpose sigma in the middle,
that's a diagonal,
possibly rectangular diagonal
by its transpose,
so the result,
this is orthogonal,
diagonal, orthogonal.
So, I guess,
actually, this is the SVD for A
transpose A.
Here I see orthogonal,
diagonal, and orthogonal.
Great.
But a little more is happening.
For A transpose A,
the difference is,
the orthogonal guys are the
same.
It's V and V transpose.
What I seeing here?
I'm seeing the factorization
for a symmetric matrix.
This thing is symmetric.
So in a symmetric case,
U is the same as V.
U is the same as V for this
symmetric matrix,
and, of course,
we see it happening.
OK.
So that tells us,
right away, what V is.
V is the eigenvector matrix for
A transpose A.
OK.
Now, if you were here when I
lectured about this topic,
when I gave the topic on
singular value decompositions,
you'll remember that I got into
trouble.
I'm sorry to remember that
myself, but it happened.
OK.
How did it happen?
I was in great shape for a
while, cruising along.
So I found the eigenvectors for
A transpose A.
Good.
I found the singular values,
what were they?
What were the singular values?
The singular value number i,
or -- these are the guys in
sigma -- this is diagonal with
the number sigma in it.
This diagonal is sigma one,
sigma two, up to the rank,
sigma r, those are the non-zero
ones.
So I found those,
and what are they?
Remind me about that?
Well, here, I'm seeing them
squared, so their squares are
the eigenvalues of A transpose
A.
Good.
So I just take the square root,
if I want the eigenvalues of A
transpose --
If I want the sigmas and I know
these, I take the square root,
the positive square root.
OK.
Where did I run into trouble?
Well, then, my final step was
to find U.
And I didn't read the book.
So, I did something that was
practically right,
but --
well, I guess practically right
is not quite the same.
OK, so I thought,
OK, I'll look at A A transpose.
What happened when I looked at
A A transpose?
Let me just put it here,
and then I can feel it.
OK, so here's A A transpose.
So that's U sigma V transpose,
that's A, and then the
transpose is V sigma transpose,
U sigma transpose.
Fine.
And then, in the middle is the
identity again,
so it looks great.
U sigma sigma transpose,
U transpose.
Fine.
All good, and now these columns
of U are the eigenvectors,
that's U is the eigenvector
matrix for this guy.
That was correct,
so I did that fine.
Where did something go wrong?
A sign went wrong.
A sign went wrong because --
and now -- now I see,
actually, somebody told me
right after class,
we can't tell from this
description which sign to give
the eigenvectors.
If these are the eigenvectors
of this matrix,
well, if you give me an
eigenvector and I change all its
signs, we've still got another
eigenvector.
So what I wasn't able to
determine (and I had a
fifty-fifty change and life let
me down,) the signs I just
happened to pick for the
eigenvectors,
one of them I should have
reversed the sign.
So, from this,
I can't tell whether the
eigenvector or its negative is
the right one to use in there.
So the right way to do it is
to, having settled on the signs,
the Vs also,
I don't know which sign to
choose, but I choose one.
I choose one.
And then, instead,
I should have used the one that
tells me what sign to choose,
the rule that A times a V is
sigma times the U.
So, having decided on the V,
I multiply by A,
I'll notice the factor sigma
coming out, and there will be a
unit vector there,
and I now know exactly what it
is, and not only up to a change
of sign.
So that's the good and,
of course, this is the main
point about the SVD.
That's the point that we've
diagonalized,
that's A times the matrix of Vs
equals U times the diagonal
matrix of sigmas.
That's the same as that.
OK.
So that's, like,
correcting the wrong sign from
that earlier lecture.
And that would complete that,
so that's how you would compute
the SVD.
Now, on the quiz,
I going to ask -- well,
maybe on the final.
So we've got quiz and final
ahead.
Sometimes, you might be asked
to find the SVD if I give you
the matrix -- let me come back,
now, to the main board -- or,
I might give you the pieces.
And I might ask you something
about the matrix.
For example,
suppose I ask you,
oh, let's say,
if I tell you what sigma is --
OK.
Let's take one example.
Suppose sigma is -- so all
that's how we would compute
them.
But now, suppose I give you
these.
Suppose I give you sigma is,
say, three two.
And I tell you that U has a
couple of columns,
and V has a couple of columns.
OK.
Those are orthogonal columns,
of course, because U and V are
orthogonal.
I'm just sort of,
like, getting you to think
about the SVD,
because we only had that one
lecture about it,
and one homework,
and, what kind of a matrix have
I got here?
What do I know about this
matrix?
All I really know right now is
that its singular values,
those sigmas are three and two,
and the only thing interesting
that I can see in that is that
they're not zero.
I know that this matrix is
non-singular,
right?
That's invertible,
I don't have any zero
eigenvalues, and zero singular
values, that's invertible,
there's a typical SVD for a
nice two-by-two non-singular
invertible good matrix.
If I actually gave you a
matrix, then you'd have to find
the Us and the Vs as we just
spoke.
But, there.
Now, what if the two wasn't a
two but it was -- well,
let me make an extreme case,
here -- suppose it was minus
five.
That's wrong,
right away.
That's not a singular value
decomposition,
right?
The singular values are not
negative.
So that's not a singular value
decomposition,
and forget it.
OK.
So let me ask you about that
one.
What can you tell me about that
matrix?
It's singular,
right?
It's got a singular matrix
there in the middle,
and, let's see,
so, OK, it's singular,
maybe you can tell me,
its rank?
What's the rank of A?
It's clearly -- somebody just
say it -- one,
thanks.
The rank is one,
so the null space,
what's the dimension of the
null space?
One.
Right?
We've got a two-by-two matrix
of rank one, so of all that
stuff from the beginning of the
course is still with us.
The dimensions of those
fundamental spaces is still
central, and a basis for them.
Now, can you tell me a vector
that's in the null space?
And then that will be my last
point to make about the SVD.
Can you tell me a vector that's
in the null space?
So what would I multiply by and
get zero, here?
I think the answer is probably
v2.
I think probably v2 is in the
null space, because I think that
must be the eigenvector going
with this zero eigenvalue.
Yes.
Have a look at that.
And I could ask you the null
space of A transpose.
And I could ask you the column
space.
All that stuff.
Everything is sitting there in
the SVD.
The SVD takes a little more
time to compute,
but it displays all the good
stuff about a matrix.
OK.
Any question about the SVD?
Let me keep going with further
topics.
Now, let's see.
Similar matrices we've talked
about, let me see if I've got
another, -- OK.
Here's a true false,
so we can do that,
easily.
So.
Question, A given.
A is symmetric and orthogonal.
OK.
So beautiful matrices like that
don't come along every day.
But what can we say first about
its eigenvalues?
Actually, of course.
Here are our two most important
classes of matrices,
and we're looking at the
intersection.
So those really are neat
matrices, and what can you tell
me about what could the possible
eigenvalues be?
Eigenvalues can be what?
What do I know about the
eigenvalues of a symmetric
matrix?
Lambda is real.
What do I know about the
eigenvalues of an orthogonal
matrix?
Ha.
Maybe nothing.
But, no, that can't be.
What do I know about the
eigenvalues of an orthogonal
matrix?
Well, what feels right?
Basing mathematics on just a
little gut instinct here,
the eigenvalues of an
orthogonal matrix ought to have
magnitude one.
Orthogonal matrices are like
rotations, they're not changing
the length, so orthogonal,
the eigenvalues are one.
Let me just show you why.
Why?
So the matrix,
can I call it Q for orthogonal
for the moment?
If I look at Q x equal lambda
x, how do I see that this thing
has magnitude one?
I take the length of both
sides.
This is taking lengths,
taking lengths,
this is whatever the magnitude
is times the length of x.
And what's the length of Q x if
Q is an orthogonal matrix?
This is something you should
know.
It's the same as the length of
x.
Orthogonal matrices don't
change lengths.
So lambda has to be one.
Right.
OK.
That's worth committing to
memory, that could show up
again.
OK.
So what's the answer now to
this question,
what can the eigenvalues be?
There's only two possibilities,
and they are one and the other
one, the other possibility is
negative one,
right, because these have the
right magnitude,
and they're real.
OK.
TK.
true -- OK.
True or false?
A is sure to be positive
definite.
Well, this is a great matrix,
but
is it sure to be positive
definite?
No.
If it could have an eigenvalue
minus one, it wouldn't be
positive definite.
True or false,
it has no repeated eigenvalues.
That's false,
too.
In fact, it's going to have
repeated eigenvalues if it's as
big
as three by three,
one of these c- one of these,
at least, will have to get
repeated.
Sure.
So it's got repeated
eigenvalues, but,
is it diagonalizable?
It's got these many,
many, repeated eigenvalues.
If it's fifty by fifty,
it's certainly got a lot of
repetitions.
Is it diagonalizable?
Yes.
All symmetric matrices,
all orthogonal matrices can be
diagonalized.
And, in fact,
the eigenvectors can even be
chosen orthogonal.
So it could be,
sort of, like,
diagonalized the best way with
a Q, and not just any old S.
OK.
Is it non-singular?
Is a symmetric orthogonal
matrix non-singular?
Sure.
Orthogonal matrices are always
non-singular.
And, obviously,
we don't have any zero
Eigenvalues.
Is it sure to be
diagonalizable?
Yes.
Now, here's a final step --
show that one-half of A plus I
is A -- that is,
prove one-half of A plus I is a
projection matrix.
OK?
Let's see.
What do I do?
I could see two ways to do
this.
I could check the properties of
a projection matrix,
which are what?
A projection matrix is
symmetric.
Well, that's certainly
symmetric, because A is.
And what's the other property?
I should square it,
and hopefully get the same
thing back.
So can I do that,
square and see if I get the
same thing back?
So if I square it,
I'll get one-quarter of A
squared plus two A plus I,
right?
And the question is,
does that agree with p- the
thing itself?
One-half A plus I.
Hm.
I guess I'd like to know
something about A squared.
What is A squared?
That's our problem.
If A is symmetric and
orthogonal, A is symmetric and
orthogonal.
This is what we're given,
right?
It's symmetric,
and it's orthogonal.
So what's A squared?
I.
A squared is I,
because A times A -- if A
equals its own inverse,
so A times A is the same as A
times A inverse,
which is I.
So this A squared here is I.
And now we've got it.
We've got two identities over
four, that's good,
and we've got two As over four,
that's good.
OK.
So it turned out to be a
projection matrix safely.
And we could also have said,
well, what are the eigenvalues
of this thing?
What are the eigenvalues of a
half A plus I?
If the eigenvalues of A are one
and minus one,
what are the eigenvalues of A
plus I?
Just stay with it these last
thirty seconds here.
What if I know these
eigenvalues of A,
and I add the identity,
the eigenvalues of A plus I are
zero and two.
And then when I divide by two,
the eigenvalues are zero and
one.
So it's symmetric,
it's got the right eigenvalues,
it's a projection matrix.
OK, you're seeing a lot of
stuff about eigenvalues,
and special matrices,
and that's what the quiz is
about.
OK, so good luck on the quiz.