PROFESSOR: Hi there.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about when vectors
are linearly independent, when
they span the space, what a
basis is, what a dimension
of a vector space is.
And the problem for today
is exactly about that.
We have a vector space
that is given.
It's spanned by these
four vectors.
And we're asked to find the
dimension of that vector space
and the basis for it.
Well why don't you hit pause on
the video, and work on it
for a while.
And I'll come back in a little
bit to help you out with it.
We're back.
Let's work on it.
So we need to find the dimension
and the basis.
Remember what the
dimension is?
It's simply the number of
vectors in a basis for the
vector space.
So actually, the problem
is backwards.
We want to find the basis for
the space first, and then find
the dimension.
I'll write first here
and second here.
So we want to find a basis for
the vector space spanned by
these four vectors.
So you might be tempted to just
say that a basis for this
vector space is those four
vectors, because they span the
vector space.
But there's another thing that
a basis has to satisfy.
And it is the elements of the
basis have to be linearly
independent.
We don't know that these are.
So we have to check.
How do we check that four
vectors are linearly
independent?
Well, there's a couple
of different ways.
But here's what we're
going to do.
We're going to put these vectors
as rows of a matrix.
And then we'll do elimination.
And when we get to the end, the
rows that have pivots are
the independent ones.
So let's do that.
1, 1, -2, 0, -1, 1, 2, 0,
-4, 1, 0, 1, 3, -3, 2,
2, 3, 0, -2, 0.
By now you must have done
elimination a million times,
so I'll go a little
bit faster.
1, 1, -2, 0, -1, 0, 1,
0, plus 2, -4, 2--
this one's already done--
1, 3, -3, 2, 2, -2, 3, -2,
0, plus 4, -2, and 2.
One more step.
1, 1, -2, 0, -1--
all these are done--
0, 1, 2, -4, 2, 0, 1 minus 1 is
0, 3 minus 2 is 1, -3 plus
4 is 1, 2 minus 2 is 0,
1 minus 1 is 0, 2,
2 again, and 0.
Well, you can see where
this is going.
In the next step, this row
is going to disappear.
1, 1, -2, 2, 0, -1, 0, 1,
2, -4, 2, 0, 0, 1, 1,
0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0.
All right.
We're done with elimination.
So let's circle our pivots.
All right, here are
our pivots.
We have three pivots.
And so these three rows are
linearly independent.
And in fact, these rows still
span the same space that the
initial four rows did.
Because when you do elimination,
all that you're
doing is recombining your
rows by doing linear
combinations of them.
So, for example, your first
row stayed the same
throughout.
Your second row was replaced
by row 2 minus row 1.
But it's really still spanning
the same space.
And it goes on.
And then the fourth row, it
turns out, was useless.
You only needed the
first three.
So the elements for a basis--
well, it will be these three.
So let me write that.
Basis (1, 1, -2, 0, -1),
2, 2 and 0, 0, 1, 1, 0.
Could you have used the
first three rows?
Yes, you could.
You can't always do that.
Sometimes in elimination, you
have to switch rows, because
there's a 0 where a
pivot should be.
When that happens, you have to
use these three, or you have
to keep track of which row you
switched to go back and use
the initial ones.
But it's really safe
to use these ones.
And also they're simpler than
the ones that you started
with, so why not?
The other question that we had
was what is the dimension of
the vector space?
Well, this is the easy part.
The dimension of the vector
space is 1, 2, 3.
And that solves the problem.
But there's one more thing
that I want to tell you.
I told you that there's a couple
of ways to find out
which of those four vectors
are linearly independent.
And the one that I used was
I put them into rows and
performed elimination and picked
out the rows that have
pivots on them.
Another way to do it is to write
the initial vectors as
columns of the matrix and then
perform elimination.
That also works and, as you
know, because you're only
working with the transpose of
this matrix, you get the same
number of pivots.
Let's go over here where
I have the same--
well, the transpose
of that matrix--
I have the same vectors, but
now written as columns.
My four initial vectors
written as columns.
And here I have performed
elimination.
And this is the final result.
Let me circle the
pivots again.
Here they are, three, which
is going to give me three
linearly independent vectors and
hence, three elements of
the basis, and hence,
dimension 3
for the vector space.
But I could no longer use
these three columns as
elements of the basis, because
when I did elimination, I
changed the column space.
So the column space of this
vector-- of this matrix is not
the same as the column space
of the eliminated version.
So I cannot use these.
In fact, if you look at them,
you can probably understand
that they're not going to span
the same space as these.
Because all that I have down
here are 0s, and I get a lot
more than just 0s in the last
two entries of the vectors.
So what I need to do is--
the pivots are in the first,
second, and third columns.
I need to use these three
columns as my basis.
I'll just write basis
down here.
And that will work too.
So see, I have produced two
different bases for the same
vector space, which
is totally fine.
You can pick the basis
that you prefer.
All right.
We're done.
Thank you.