The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
Some content in this audio is
not covered under a Creative
Commons license.
For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT
OpenCourseWare website.
TA: A bunch of puzzles.
AUDIENCE: The first one's easy,
and then everything
after that is such a scam.
TA: Is it like a series,
or is it just one book?
AUDIENCE: I don't know.
I found it.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
Everyone's looking at him and
they're like, you can do a
practice leg in a one-person
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
We'll just give you any puzzle
that gets progressively more
impossible.
TA: Actually, I want to throw
out one suggestion.
If anybody's having trouble
thinking about what to put up
for a program post, and you
haven't been able to keep up
with your program posts, one
thing that you might want to
attempt is just a quick
postmortem on
the previous project.
What went right, what you would
rather have gone right,
what went wrong, and just a
couple of other points.
Just sort of a reflection, just
thinking about what you
might want to try to change or
what you want to make sure
that you keep doing for
the next project.
That's just a good idea.
So if you could do
that next week.
It will be done today, so after
this week's program
post, you might want to try
to do the exercise.
PROFESSOR: So today, well first
of all I want to say if
you can't see the screen, you
might want to position
yourself so that you can,
because most of everything is
going to be up here for today.
So I don't know if, for those
of you who have taken or are
taking video game studies, how
much you're going into this.
But some of today's talk is
definitely going to be more on
the video games studies
theoretical side.
And we're not actually requiring
you to implement
this stuff, so a lot what we are
going to be talking about
today is rhetoric and meaning
and how that relates to
simulation.
If you're not conscious of this,
or you don't put this in
your game, that's fine.
This is just something that I
think is really interesting,
and I hope you guys
will as well.
So, first of all, I want to
talk about what simulation
means, and it would help if
I did this correctly.
There we go.
OK.
So, Gonzalo Frasca says, to
simulate is to model a source
system or different system which
maintains for someone
some of the behaviors of
the original system.
And so to me, this definition
is really important for a
couple of reasons.
First of all, he puts source
in parentheses.
For him and in his writing, he
doesn't necessarily think you
need one, which is a whole other
argument all together.
I want to point out that all of
this will assume that there
is a star system and that the
design is consciousness.
That's part of the board game
assignment, to make a game
based on a real world system.
But this technician has
a lot of space in it.
It maintains for somebody
some of the behaviors.
It's intentionally very loose.
And this'll come into to play
shortly, because a big part we
are going to talk about today
is the relationship with
subjectivity and simulation,
which I hope you guys saw a
little bit of in the
reading for today.
So to give a more rigorous
definition, this is a model
taken from an extremely dry
textbook called Theory of
Modeling and Simulation.
Zeigler and all have
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] of what it
offers, and basically
they present a
simulation that's like this.
So the idea is, you have a star
system that exists within
the experimental frame.
This frame refers to, these are
the conditions under which
we are interested in
the star system.
Right?
So if you want to make a game,
say about life at MIT, there's
some things you are going to
include, some things you're
going to exclude, right?
You probably don't care about
the effect of the moon's
gravity on the campus,
for example.
And so then there's the
modelling relation.
So we observed the star system
under certain conditions, and
then we focused on the elements
that are important to
us, and from that we construct
the model.
And you notice, here they
distinguish between a
simulator and a model, which is
not something that I think
we do necessarily.
Because we tend to think that
simulations are complex
technological software
entities.
So separating this indicates
that multiple
things can be a simulator.
For example, in terms
of games, you can
have a board game.
You can have a video game.
And these could be based on the
same model, or they could
be derived from the same system,
but the simulator
exactly can be a couple
of different things.
And so this is a sort
of technical way
of looking at it.
What I want to talk about
specifically is what I refer
to in my writing as
a simulation gap.
And this is another way of
looking at the elements in a
simulation.
So, major components such as
star system, the simulation,
the user, and I have all of
these super intuitive arrows.
So we'll go through
them quickly.
So the arrow at A,
this is kind of
the abstraction process.
We are looking at a star system
we're considering,
presumably within some sort of
experimental frame that we
care about.
And then from that we derive
behaviors and rules for what
we want to implement into
the simulation.
So the arrow with B represents
the user.
So this might be me.
And this is me interacting
with the game.
This is me playing with it,
seeing how the simulation
works, watching it run.
But then, importantly, there's
also arrow C my recognition
that it's based on something.
If you can't tell that
simulation has a star system,
you're going to think of it very
differently than if you
know where that star
system is.
And so D, then, is the
proverbial simulation gap.
And this is the space in
between all of them.
And this is a model of how
users, in working with a
simulation, can create
a subjective
interpretation of it.
They assign values to it.
They look at are there value
judgments in the game.
They may consider various parts
of the game to have
certain meaning or express
certain ideas.
And this arises from
understanding the difference
between the star system
and the simulation.
I wasn't able to compress the
quote down into a slide, but
Ian Bogost said that the
simulation gap is kind of--
a user's interpretation of a
simulation converges-- all
right, let's see if I
can get this right.
It's horribly wordy
in the book.
But he's basically saying your
interpretation is based on
what the simulation includes as
much as what it excludes.
We look at these design
decisions as having meaning.
And so we saw this in
the star article.
I'm sorry, this picture
is lo-res,
but the game is lo-res.
I don't know if you
remember this.
There's this key point in the
article for today when
[? Star ?] is talking about
discussing SimCity 2000 with
his daughter.
And if you remember, he and his
daughter react differently
to the game's exclusion
of mixed-use field.
Actually, I probably
want to check.
Has anyone not played SimCity?
Any of the versions?
No experience?
OK.
So SimCity basically is a--
he's called it a software toy.
It's a simulation of a city.
That's the name.
And the idea is you start with
an empty space, and are trying
to build it up into
a burgeoning
metropolis, or whatever.
One of the defining features
of the games
is it's very open.
There's no real set goals.
And this is primarily
done through zoning.
And zoning is designating
land for specific uses.
So the main zones in the game,
and in actual urban planning
are residential, commercial,
and industrial.
So to mark a segment of land
as residential means, this
land is approved for building
housing, basically apartments,
houses, etc.
Commercial zones are things
like commerce, offices,
retailers, those kind of things,
whereas industry is
manufacturing, mostly.
And so in the game, you can
basically say this chunk of
land is for this use.
But in reality, it's usually
not that cut and dry.
And so mixed-use development is
a particular kind of zoning
where you're saying this land
can be used for multiple
things at the same time.
And you see this a lot,
actually, in Boston,
especially down Newbury Street,
Back Bay, where the
ground levels of these apartment
buildings are
restaurants or stores.
And then there's space
to let apartments
built right above them.
And that's not possible
in any SimCity.
And so to get back to the
article then, the author is
saying that he thinks the
simulation is prejudiced
against this kind.
It's against having this kind
of zoning because the game
just leaves it out.
Whereas his daughter
says, well this
is just how it works.
So for the two of them, they
both interpret this exclusion
differently.
The daughter thinks, well, OK,
this is just how the game is.
It's not important.
And again the author
says well this is
actually a political decision.
So if any of you are familiar
with the game, can you think
of other games that
are examples
of politics in SimCity?
It's written about a fair
amount, actually.
AUDIENCE: There's the energy
scope, where you can choose
between coal or nuclear
and whatnot.
I think when you do get to the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
They had their own agendas,
certainly.
AUDIENCE: Well, it's
not only that.
I think it's cheaper to build a
hydroelectric plant than it
is to build a nuclear plant.
Because the material
cost of building it
in SimCity is cheaper.
PROFESSOR: That's certainly
part of it.
Although it's interesting to
know that in the game, I think
part of that is that the hydro
plants don't generate as much,
so you need a lot of them.
AUDIENCE: Maybe.
I haven't played
in a long time.
PROFESSOR: Yes.
I think they took the hydro
plants out in 2000.
AUDIENCE: Oftentimes it's
a lot of rules, anyways.
It was often to your interest to
build industrial zones near
a border of your city, so
that your city wouldn't
be polluted as much.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
And it's a result of the
pollution model.
The industrial zones pollute in
a circle, so if you pollute
on the edge of the map, half
that circle is non-existent.
But there's a question.
Is the simulation arguing that
you should send your pollution
to other cities, or is it just
a result of how it works?
Jason?
AUDIENCE: The decision on how
to follow things like how
taxes affect group
rates, and how
different sections interact.
All those types of things
definitely have models from
what they come from, which have
certain slightly bigger
political slants to them.
AUDIENCE: I was just
wondering.
I think the difference in how
the father and the daughter
viewed the system is that
the father already had a
preconception of what the
city should be like.
But the kid wouldn't necessarily
know because they
haven't been exposed
to all of this.
So to them, it's like oh, OK,
this is how it works.
But the father knows that there
are other things in the
model system as opposed
to the simulation.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
And that's, again, emphasizing
the fact that the user has
their own subjectivity.
Different people are going to
assign different values to
these things.
AUDIENCE: Mass transit in
SimCity is universally
considered to be a part of the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: In some games they'll
complain about the
lack of roads, but they don't
do anything about it.
They keep moving in.
AUDIENCE: How are
they moving in?
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
And actually, in the
first one, you
could just have trains.
You could just have rail lines,
and there weren't even
train stations.
Everything was built up
against the tracks.
Which in reality, I've
lived next to the
commuter rail lines.
It's not pleasant.
AUDIENCE: In come cities, a
significant portion of the
population does make do with
only public transport, and you
can get a taxi.
PROFESSOR: Just one
final point.
It's a very small detail, but
a lot of the games will let
you declare your city a
nuclear-free zone, which just
basically means you can't build
a nuclear power plant.
But that stimulates growth.
People want to move there more
because there's no nuclear
power plants.
So I want to go through a few
more really short examples.
Civilization Revolution is
more like a stripped down
Civilization.
Is anyone familiar with
this version?
Now, specifically are you
familiar with the DS version?
That's the only one I've played
that's actually based
in [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: It's on iPhone, too.
PROFESSOR: Oh yeah, it's
probably the same
thing on the iPhone.
So I've noticed, having played
this game a lot, in the game,
they have all these different
civilizations, and all
represented by a
famous leader.
So the Indians are lead by
Gandhi for however many
thousands of years
the game goes on.
And I've noticed that Gandhi
is incredibly aggressive.
Almost to the point where he
declares war on someone.
He will stay at war
the whole time.
I usually end up back
again, honestly.
And you can try to make peace,
and they'll never do it.
They'll say, oh yeah,
we'll be friends.
And then three turns later,
they're declaring war.
But on the other hand, Alexander
the Great, who
conquered much of Greece and
Macedonia, and was very
expansionist, is a
total pacifist.
He'll never fight you.
He never wants to declare war.
And not only that, but
he never expands.
They almost always just have
their one city, and they never
try to grow and spread,
which is totally not
what the Greeks did.
So there's this question here.
Is this the result, then, of
bias in the simulation?
Do the designers just think,
is it bad history?
AUDIENCE: I think that's
backwards.
Wrong pointer.
AUDIENCE: That might be it,
because in, for example,
Civilization 4, and I think 5,
they have the same characters,
where if you're being India,
your player can be Gandhian.
He's pacifistic in that.
And I'm pretty sure Alexander
the Great is probably also
expansionist.
I'm not sure why they did
that in this version.
PROFESSOR: Maybe
they messed up.
AUDIENCE: Gandhi, in number 5,
is still really aggressive.
AUDIENCE: Maybe they just
thought it was funny.
AUDIENCE: Maybe they
like irony.
PROFESSOR: I actually have
my own theory on this.
Part of the game is your
civilization has a certain
government, and governments
get different benefits.
Actually, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
benefit in this game.
Indians start with
fundamentalism, which gives
you a bonus to attack.
Whereas the Greeks start with
a democracy, and then a
democracy that people won't
declare war in.
So there's this kind of weird,
and my theory is that Indians
always attack you because they
always have an attack bonus.
And the Greeks never attack you
because they're a democracy.
As we know, democracies aren't
necessarily pacifistic.
And again this is my
thinking on it.
This understanding the rules of
the system, and then I kind
of infer this AI behavior
based on that.
But again, this is
my position.
It's easy to find people
complaining about historical
inaccuracies in Civilization.
There's always this question.
Is it part of the system?
Is the system just behaving in
a certain way because of
certain properties?
Is there another intent there?
We can infer all these different
meanings from what
the simulation includes
and what it excludes.
So I want to ask, has anyone
not played September 12?
Can I get a volunteer to play?
AUDIENCE: Go for it, Jeremy.
PROFESSOR: Do you
want to play?
So you can control
with the mouse.
Can everyone read this OK?
Should I read it.
It's not a game.
You can't win or lose.
It's a simulation.
It has no ending.
It's already begun.
And here it goes.
So, all you can do is--
[INTERPOSING  VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So do you see what's
happening to the people
that you just hit with this?
[VIDEO GAME SOUNDS]
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] --turn
into errors.
PROFESSOR: You can read in the
intro screen that this is
meant to be a simulation
of the United
States' response to 9/11.
AUDIENCE: There's a puppy!
PROFESSOR: Do you think you're
making things better?
[PLAYING VIDEO GAME]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: -- just to
kill the puppy?
AUDIENCE: That is
one crazy dog.
AUDIENCE: What the heck?
PROFESSOR: Do you notice
anything about when you
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
Anything unusual?
So apparently as soon as you
click, there is a delay.
You can never specifically
target.
Even if you say, I want to get
these terrorists, the delay
means the odds are you're
not going to.
Because they're going
to move away.
AUDIENCE: Did you bomb
the other terrorists?
AUDIENCE: No.
If you kill a terrorist, you
don't bomb more terrorists.
AUDIENCE: Oh really?
AUDIENCE: Leopard terrorists.
AUDIENCE: Ooh, it's a kid.
AUDIENCE: It's a
kid terrorist?
AUDIENCE: You shouldn't have
brought adult terrorists.
AUDIENCE: Great strategy.
If you turn all of the regular
civilians into terrorists,
then you can just
kill everyone.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: I think they also come
in from the side there.
AUDIENCE: Well you've got
to kill them faster.
AUDIENCE: Last night, someone
figured out that if you camped
out in the corner, eventually
one would wander into the
corner without any
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] on it and you
completely could probably
kill only terrorists
in the entire game.
AUDIENCE: That's boring.
AUDIENCE: How about just kill
everyone, become terrorists
and then chase them.
PROFESSOR: So I want to say that
this game has received a
lot of criticism.
So this is actually Gonzalo
Frasca's game, if you still
remember the quote from
the beginning.
Notable designer Greg
Costikyan has really
criticized this, saying
this is really harsh.
How can you call this
a simulation.
This is so insensitive.
And you notice that this game
leaves out a lot of the
aspects of terrorism and how
peaceful interactions work.
You don't see 9/11
happening here.
It really simplifies the
act of what makes
someone become a terrorist.
You don't have all of the other
pressures in the region,
all of the other countries'
influences.
It's very stripped down.
And I think Frasca talked about
part of the point here
is that it's ignoring so much.
Because that seems to be
the way that the US
government has responded.
It's like this happened, and now
we're just going to start
bombing them.
And so this is a really great
example of how what has been
stripped out and what's been
left in really creates a
strong statement.
And you can interpret it in
a lot of different ways.
I personally think that what
he's going for is this idea
that the rhetoric surrounding
the War on Terror and the
political actions are ignoring
a lot of factors, including
our own role in the
region of attack.
But anyways, I don't mean to
turn this into a subplot.
Does anyone else have any other
observations or anything
to say about it?
AUDIENCE: I know that, as a
result of this, or inspired by
this, there is a great
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] article.
That tells us we can expect
a new mother of all bombs
developed generates 10,000
terrorists with every blast.
PROFESSOR: So another example,
has anyone not played Every
Day the Same Dream?
Does anyone want to play?
AUDIENCE: I'll try.
PROFESSOR: OK.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
Gandhi is not part
of the system.
Gandhi is just not like
a player, he's
not part the system.
PROFESSOR: In Civilization?
Well, the AI controls him.
AUDIENCE: There was
some music.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
AUDIENCE: Did you hit a car?
AUDIENCE: Aw, you can't jump?
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
a cubicle!
AUDIENCE: What is the biggest
cubicle in this room?
AUDIENCE: Computer science.
Software.
AUDIENCE: I get it.
Anything more to it?
AUDIENCE: You probably won't
have enough time to do
everything.
AUDIENCE: Keep going forward.
You can just keep
going forward.
AUDIENCE: Oh, you [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Oh my god!
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
Go left, go left.
AUDIENCE: Left, left?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
spent a day.
AUDIENCE: You guys don't usually
spend a day with a
homeless guy in the graveyard?
AUDIENCE: Why wouldn't you?
It's cool.
AUDIENCE: Don't get dressed.
AUDIENCE: Next time don't
put your clothes on.
AUDIENCE: I'm going to get
dressed like a homeless guy.
AUDIENCE: Wow!
AUDIENCE: OK, do I crash
the car, or do I--
AUDIENCE: Dude, get
out of the car.
AUDIENCE: Let's power
through it.
Just get out of the car.
Just get out.
Go left.
AUDIENCE: See that guy.
He abandoned his car.
AUDIENCE: Oh, a cow.
Sweet.
AUDIENCE: I can't?
Aww.
AUDIENCE: Hold up traffic,
[? Kev. ?]
Aw.
Leaf is gone.
AUDIENCE: I want to see what
my boss is going to say.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
What?
AUDIENCE: You can't go left.
AUDIENCE: You can't go left?
AUDIENCE: I think you can.
I think there's a car there.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Car's are inside--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: You are late?
He didn't notice I missed
day of work?
AUDIENCE: This is
why you're late.
AUDIENCE: The [? graphic's ?]
going down.
AUDIENCE: It's all your fault.
AUDIENCE: Oh.
I'm going to get fired because
the company is going to go
down the drain.
In three days.
AUDIENCE: Walk past
your office.
AUDIENCE: Hmm?
PROFESSOR: Walk past
your office.
Or your cubicle, around it.
The experience of the game is a
little bit stronger when you
don't have people talking.
We don't have enough
time [INAUDIBLE].
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Push it.
AUDIENCE: Should I?
AUDIENCE: Do it.
AUDIENCE: All I see
is [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I told you I
was going forward.
AUDIENCE: What?
AUDIENCE: It's Groundhog's
Day.
AUDIENCE: It is the Matrix.
All right.
We're going naked this time.
AUDIENCE: You're still
wearing underwear.
There, I watched TV.
Now we've got feeling this
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
I guess not.
AUDIENCE: Did this skip, too?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, because we--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Everything different
you do is another step.
AUDIENCE: So this is
the last step then.
AUDIENCE: Naked.
Naked.
AUDIENCE: HIt a car.
AUDIENCE: I can't.
AUDIENCE: You can't hit it?
AUDIENCE: I'm jamming it.
AUDIENCE: Are the cars
the same everyday?
PROFESSOR: And the leap
was something, too.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Now what?
AUDIENCE: I assume you have to
go past your office again.
But you're going to want to get
dressed, or you're going
to get fired again.
AUDIENCE: No, he won't.
AUDIENCE: No, I won't.
AUDIENCE: Oh, right.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
left me.
AUDIENCE: You keep
on reminding me,
because I had a job.
AUDIENCE: Where are you going?
You're fired.
AUDIENCE: I'm going to
go postal at work.
Don't worry about it.
AUDIENCE: He's going
to kill himself.
AUDIENCE: Am I doing the
right thing here?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: We're the
homeless guys.
AUDIENCE: It's Saturday!
AUDIENCE: Good call.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
He got fired, too.
Ha ha.
I can't crash cars now.
Really not one's going out
because day 6 is Saturday.
So no one's going to work.
AUDIENCE: Are we not supposed
to get up yet?
AUDIENCE: Oh, look.
You have no cubicle anymore.
AUDIENCE: You're retired.
AUDIENCE: That would be funny.
AUDIENCE: You finished
the program.
AUDIENCE: That's you.
AUDIENCE: I don't know.
Everyone else looks the same.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, they
all look the same.
AUDIENCE: Deep.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: It reminds me of that
one game where you walk
into a bar that's right
across, and you
can pick up a wife.
AUDIENCE: Oh, Passage.
That's a weird game.
AUDIENCE: It reminds me
of that game a lot.
PROFESSOR: So there's a couple
things that I want to say
about this game.
First of all, if you remember
[? Prospect's ?]
definition of a simulation,
it's talking about
the space in it.
And I would consider
this a simulation.
This is based on a
source system.
But it's not the kind of number
crunching CS thing that
we associate with the word.
For me, personally, I worked
a pretty horrible dead-end
cubicle job for about 18 months,
before I came in here.
For me, this game really
resonates, because it really
closely matches the
experience.
You're just doing the same thing
every day, and any sort
of deviation from the
norm stands out.
But in terms of exclusion
inclusion, one of the
interesting things about this
game, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
makes its point.
There is nothing else.
It's all a workday.
There is no weekend.
There's no I got home and
there's something different.
And that's the limited
agency in the game.
By that I mean it can be easy to
forget about, especially in
a place like MIT, but a lot of
people I know end up in these
very dead-end jobs.
This is a huge part of
any major economy.
There are people who
just go to their
cubicle day after day.
When I was at that crap job, I
knew people who had been there
for 40 years.
AUDIENCE: What kind
of job was it?
PROFESSOR: It was for
a mutual fund
subsidiary at Bank of America.
Back in the financial
district.
I'm not sure if it would have
been better for me to stay,
given the whole, you know, we
tanked the economy but we
awarded ourselves billions
of dollars.
Maybe I should have
stuck around.
PROFESSOR: So it was a well-paid
type of job.
I mean, in this climate, it
might have become well-paid.
But it wasn't at the time.
It was actually, a lot of what
I did was trade corrections.
This is kind of a tangent,
but it drives me bonkers.
Financial representatives and
advisers make an obscene
amount of money, yet most of
them don't know the difference
between dollars and
shares in stock.
And most of my job is correcting
that for them.
It's unbelievable.
And it's no surprise to
me that the thing
is all fucked up.
Anyway, so any other reactions
to this game or
thoughts about this game?
AUDIENCE: The color
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: What do
you mean color?
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: There's also nothing
meaningful on the
screen, right?
AUDIENCE: There was some kind
of static noise, right?
But you turned it off?
PROFESSOR: I think so.
I forgot to close the September
12 window, so there
was some noise from that.
AUDIENCE: The use of color, just
in general, was really
interesting.
In particular, the only thing at
your work that is colorful
is the plumbing stock sign, the
exit sign which tells you
where to go kill yourself.
The leap is colorful.
AUDIENCE: I think the cows.
And the hobos.
I think it's interesting.
It's kind of from the heritage
of the game Another World.
Because sort of an early
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] look at what
it would be like to be
a human transplant
onto another planet.
You know [UNINTELLIGIBLE] that,
in the beginning your
character is extremely
vulnerable
and slow and clumsy.
And it uses the same control
schemes on the same
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] channel
endings.
And by the same token, you're
playing an ordinary person.
It's not the boss.
Not this person coming in.
And you don't go into a
postal-style power trip, either.
PROFESSOR: And so, I just wanted
to say, I actually
haven't seen the talk, but
apparently, someone has argued
that this game is just
a critique of
the art game movement.
Right, that it's making
fun of the whole
pretentiousness of that.
I don't really see that, but
again, it's subjectivity.
Like where does this
actually go.
AUDIENCE: Well, what do the
creators say to that?
AUDIENCE: You'll find that
really creative people like
that never want to
talk about it.
AUDIENCE: I thought there
was an artist
statement on the website.
PROFESSOR: I'm sorry?
PROFESSOR: I thought
there was an artist
statement for this somewhere.
PROFESSOR: There could be.
I honestly haven't
looked it up.
OK, so moving on.
So anyway, good theory.
If you have a theory about how
things work, the best way to
test it is to figure out what's
a horrible example.
So we've been talking about
simulations and subjectivity,
and saying, OK, how does this
model explain the way meaning
gets invented in a game and
Mario is a really good example
to throw with that.
So what are some things that
are abstracted into the
simulation?
Like what's here?
What's not?
AUDIENCE: It's physics.
You can jump to the moon.
AUDIENCE: You can
move in mid-air.
You can slam against extremely
hard things and break them.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
things and kill them.
Technically [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: You can punch hard
things and breaking them.
PROFESSOR: You can get bigger.
You can shoot fire
out of your hand.
AUDIENCE: Still, the plumbers
don't seem to
really do any work.
They do get out of fights and
clean up coins here and there,
so that technically
counts as points.
AUDIENCE: Why is it
significant that he's a plumber?
Is it so he can clean pipes?
AUDIENCE:He was the one
who [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: And this
is the point.
He's an Italian, and
he's the plumber.
So if you focus on him,
what can we say
this game is arguing?
That Italian plumbers
have hard heads?
He doesn't even eat.
Do they not need to eat?
How do you--?
AUDIENCE: He eats mushrooms.
PROFESSOR: So to me, Mario is
a really interesting example
because we think of
it as a simulation
because it has physics.
When it came out, it had the
most advanced jumping physics
ever designed.
It's interesting.
So there's a couple
of things here.
There's so many of the
fantastical elements.
Like walking mushrooms-
AUDIENCE: He can jump
like five times.
PROFESSOR: -and flying
turtles and stuff.
Yeah.
Just the way that he jumps.
You also notice that unlike the
other games, it's hard to
find anything political
in Mario.
You could say he's
hoarding money.
Maybe he's a capitalist.
AUDIENCE: There's this
whole long essay
about how he's a communist.
PROFESSOR: Interesting.
Could you post that
on the forum?
AUDIENCE: I will.
PROFESSOR: One thing again,
just [UNINTELLIGIBLE] to
notice is it's gender
politics.
So the only female
is the princess.
And what does she do?
She sits and waits.
She has no agency, and it's
all about the masculine.
So you can have a feminist
reading.
AUDIENCE: Is Bowser masculine?
PROFESSOR: That's an interesting
question.
Because it's also how much do
you bring in other elements?
Do you think about the cartoon
when you think about this?
Do you think about
the other games?
Do you just look at Mario
as an isolated event?
AUDIENCE: Peach kicks
ass, man.
AUDIENCE: That's true.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Well there's
the Super
Princess Peach, actually.
But her [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: She gets very upset.
She cries.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
competitive development.
I think there's something you
said about the idea that
snappers-- is that
a Braunembaun?
AUDIENCE: It's Powell.
AUDIENCE: Powell and
Braunembaun are working together.
Then [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
but has Nintendo ever made
a proper Peach game?
I don't think so.
PROFESSOR: Especially in the
American Super Mario II, when
you can control Peach.
And she is popular because
she floats.
So I mean again, this is
to say that this theory
emphasizes subjectivity.
There's just no lacking here
that we would find meaningful
or that we would actually
pick apart.
With that said, I certainly
think it works, especially
with more political
games, games that
have more of a message.
And again, this is all
stuff to think about.
It's not something we're
necessarily looking for.
So anything else with
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] in there?
AUDIENCE: There's one probable
reason why Mario's club--
actually the original pre-Super
Mario Brothers where
basically there is one screen,
and all this bad stuff is
coming out of pipes.
And the idea is that you are
trying to clear all the pipes
of all the bad stuff.
AUDIENCE: I never got
that from it.
AUDIENCE: The pipes are there.
AUDIENCE: I guess in that case
what you are asking what do I
bring from outside.
And I recall the typing from
that being a big point of what
[INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So it's like a
Donkey Kong, Mario was
actually originally
a carpenter.
And they retroactively changed
him into a plumber because
Mario Brothers, the original,
was about plumbing.
But they wanted to keep the
character the same.
AUDIENCE: Mario's
in Donkey Kong?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR: They retroactively
changed his name and his
profession.
AUDIENCE: --Donkey Kong
on Super Nintendo.
PROFESSOR: So that's
the example.
Anyone not played this one?
You want to give it a shot?
AUDIENCE: Surprise.
You have to play this
game again.
PROFESSOR: Do you want
to shoot, Jeremy?
AUDIENCE: I was actually just
thinking of their Cooking Mama
simulation that started this.
PROFESSOR: Oh, gosh.
Princess Pamela Andersen has
been captured by evil Ronald
McDonald, who plans on making
her a part of his Unhappy
Meals, along with the chickens
who are tortured for
McDonald's Restaurants.
Help save the princess,
blah blah blah.
Arrow key is move, space
bar to jump.
To beat enemies, jumping
on their heads.
You can also hit the down arrow
to do the proverbial
heads thing.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Ah.
Pamela Andersen.
AUDIENCE: I thought they
weren't nuggets.
[MUSIC]
[LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: I want to thank all
of you for being here for the
opening of my new vegetarian
restaurant, [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Ronald McDonald--
Finally I've found the perfect
toy for my next Unhappy Meal.
[INAUDIBLE]
Looks like we have to take
the princess once again
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Let's go.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Wow.
PROFESSOR: Did you know
McDonald's is one of the
biggest sellers of
chicken flesh?
And they use an outdated method
of slaughter that leads
to extreme suffering
for birds.
AUDIENCE: So.
Wow.
It's not obvious at all
that it's from PETA.
PROFESSOR: You think
it's from PETA?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Ooh, a kitten.
They're cooking hamburgers.
AUDIENCE: Are you getting any
carnivorous responses?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I think Super Meat
Boy is a response.
AUDIENCE: You worried about
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: What was
that, spinach?
AUDIENCE: I like growth
hormones as
the reason for that.
AUDIENCE: There it is.
I don't know if this
goes against one of
PETA's earlier ads.
It was a sticker that had a
chick that looked like that
and it said I'm not a nugget.
This character's
name is Nugget.
PROFESSOR: There's also
a KFC version of this.
But I think this one has more.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Not really.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: You are the best
Super Chicken Sisters player.
OK.
didn't
AUDIENCE: Even the
mustache odds.
Wait, why is Wario a bad guy?
AUDIENCE: What do they have
against mustaches?
PROFESSOR: OK, anyways.
That goes on.
So this game is really different
than the other games
we've looked at.
Does anyone have a sense
of that as well?
AUDIENCE: Slightly political.
AUDIENCE: Not subtle.
AUDIENCE: For the most part
it's just a re-skinning.
And so we were discussing this
in our other class, about Ian
Bogost's perspective games.
We looked at, what was it
called, it was Space Invaders.
PROFESSOR: Tax Invaders?
AUDIENCE: No.
It was a McCain ad.
And it was about corporal
spending.
PROFESSOR: Oh yeah.
I know of that one.
AUDIENCE: [? CorpWars, ?]
I think it was called.
It's just a re-skinning, and
so they are using the same
metaphors to just get people
to play it, and it's not
really improving their point or
it's not doing anything for
their cause.
AUDIENCE: The simulation of this
game seems to not really
apply to their point at all.
You're really just playing
Mario, and it
happens to look different.
As opposed to September 12,
evolve where the actual
simulation itself had meaning
with what they
were trying to say.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
The mechanics are having to do
with the political point, or
the narrative.
AUDIENCE: This is a secondary
critique of Mario.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
What was up with that?
AUDIENCE: I don't even know,
what were they trying to say
about Mario?
AUDIENCE: They're kind of
enunciating the fact that it's
basically a Mario ripoff.
Nintendo [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Yes, we know it's a Mario
ripoff, so we're going to tell
you that we're aware of it.
PROFESSOR: PETA also has an
established problem with
Nintendo, with their Cooking
Mama re-skin.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
technically --although Nintendo
has licenses.
PROFESSOR: Well I guess Nintendo
received the brunt of
PETA's wrath, in that
case anyways.
AUDIENCE: What is
Cooking Mama?
AUDIENCE: It's a DS game
that's about cooking.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] because
they're working
out vegetarian options.
AUDIENCE: Wow.
AUDIENCE: So they made another
flash game similar to this one
where Cooking Mama kills animals
and the features are
really bloody and slitting
their throats and stuff.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Remember we played
the video game yesterday in
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Video Game Studies?
PROFESSOR: Was that a McDonald's
video game?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
It was at videogame.com.
And that one is a simulation
of running McDonald's.
And it presents itself as
serious, and at first, most of
us in the class, as I was,
thought it was produced at
McDonald's.
And as it goes on, you can
manage the beef farms and the
soy farms, and then your
slaughterhouse, and then your
stores, and then your
corporate area.
And at first it seems like, hey
we're going to show you
how the business at
McDonald's works.
And then you get this farm
portion, and there's the
option to use [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
crops.
And you think, oh
I can do that.
It's a trade off.
Then you have to bribe the mayor
so you can destroy his
crops to put yours.
And you're like, wait.
Then you can choose to
feed your cows sludge
to make them fatter.
There's all these little things
that you can add on.
You can bribe a climate expert
to say that you're
environmentally friendly.
AUDIENCE: Are these bribes
based on any fact?
AUDIENCE: I don't know.
It was a good game, too.
We played it, and it was
really challenging.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: You know it's
the same company.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: CNS 590, and
apparently it's almost
impossible.
They do their own act as they
corrupt everything.
AUDIENCE: And that's advanced
rhetoric, right?
To be successful,
you have to--
AUDIENCE: The guy next to me
was playing all-natural
organic without corrupting
anyone.
And he was--
he went to [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
But at least learn the actions
you're taking in the game.
You're supposed to hear when
you're walking past someone
who just talked to you about
how McDonald's sucks.
AUDIENCE: That wasn't
very effective.
This was just like, oh,
I'm hungry now.
AUDIENCE: If it's the
difference between a
simulation and a game, this is
really more of a game than a
real simulation.
In a real simulation, the
mechanics have to relate to
whatever it is.
PROFESSOR: But again,
who's to say?
This isn't any more or less a
simulation than Mario was.
AUDIENCE: I don't think Mario
is a simulation either.
PROFESSOR: So that's
exactly what it is.
This game has a point to make,
but it's doing so in a very
narrative fictional way.
It's not leveraging
the simulation.
And generally speaking,
these games
are just not as effective.
And that's one of the cool
things about simulations.
You get to see how it
works and experience
things first hand.
Whereas, is this any more or
less effective than a pamphlet
or a brochure?
Maybe in terms of exposure.
A lot of people can play this
game, but it's not doing
anything that any other type
of media could do.
And that's what I got.
So we're going to do some of the
brainstorm exercise again
and talk about projects for
the next assignment.
Does anyone else have anything
they want to add
before we move on.
AUDIENCE: There's a lot
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the issue of [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
simulation.
I mean we'll be playing games
that are ostensibly
simulations, or at
least satires.
AUDIENCE: Which are a
different crunch.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
And I want to point out --
back to one of the
earlier points--
[INAUDIBLE]
system.
It doesn't necessarily--
it does make a game.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] system doesn't
have to be a real
world focus.
It could be any system.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
They're all very much based
on fictional systems.
But Michael's game is
particularly good, but they're
trying to figure out what the
system is in those storybooks.
And make them, relevent
for those players.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: So we can do
fictional systems?
PROFESSOR: Not for this
particular one.
Not for the assignment.
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Does anyone know
why they came out
with Lego Star Wars?
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] of
the Lego games?
AUDIENCE: Because
they're awesome.
AUDIENCE: It's a funny idea
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: But I think Lego was
not doing very well until
they got the Star Wars license
to make actual Lego sets.
And that was a big revenue
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
That was last year.
If you have a toy store in
Europe, it will be half Lego.
I've had that experience of,
wow, I remember when I wanted
this when I was six.
And you can't get it.
Just everything that's sold in
the US, legal basis kind of--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It just seems so funny
that they have Lego Star
Wars video game.
AUDIENCE: Well, there's also
Lego Harry Potter.
AUDIENCE: Well, they make
Lego everything.
They have Lego [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Indiana Jones.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: --Lego Star Wars.
It's probably more on topic
for stuff like video game
studies, but it probably
works well with a
number of classes offered.
that the video game--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
It will talk about different
licensing.
We'll talk about different
franchises and how we
[INAUDIBLE].
So if you are interested there
was another similar point that
I wanted to make.
Oh, all right, simulations.
There's actually a games
simulations class that's being
offered in DUSP here.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] largely
using simulations
for educational games.
You saw [INAUDIBLE].
It's a really, really
good class.
And he approaches it in
a very similar way.
For instance, let's
look at a model.
Let's look at those assumptions
and what you're
choosing to simulate, what
you're choosing to leave out.
And he'll get to things like
game play, [INAUDIBLE].
He's pretty well equipped after
taking this class to
start thinking about
those issues.
But he looks a lot
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
How does someone constructing
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the basic first step of how
to release simulation.
[INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: That's for CNS 590
Education Exploration for
Games and Simulations.
AUDIENCE: It's multiple
courses.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
It's definitely crossed
with 11.
I think it's crossed with at
least one other thing.
AUDIENCE: CNS [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
TA: Actually we can
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So this time I'm going to
do it is a brainstorming
similarly as last time.
But instead of brainstorming the
whole game ideas, which is
what we did last time, I want
people to pull out systems.
Pull out the real world systems
that you might want to
write a game about.
Because what if [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
near the end
up reciting two models, and
one of the game play, it's
probably going to be
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] determined by
who your teammates are.
And who already has a team?
AUDIENCE: We do.
AUDIENCE: We had a
different idea.
AUDIENCE: I think I have
an idea for us to do.
AUDIENCE: It's possible.
So I will recommend
being friends with
it and sharing it.
You don't have to.
But if you are going to hold
back, try to contribute a
couple of ideas [INAUDIBLE].
So, as you know [INAUDIBLE].
Anyone or any ideas?
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I'll start with Jeremy
and then I'll
work my way back again.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
trying to build a pyramid.
AUDIENCE: OK, pyramid
building.
AUDIENCE: I told you the
green one was good.
AUDIENCE: That was a lot
more than [INAUDIBLE]
at MIT.
AUDIENCE: Rennaisance Italian
political machinations.
AUDIENCE: OK.
Renaissance Italian politics.
OK.
AUDIENCE: Your four
years here at MIT.
MIT undergrad.
AUDIENCE: A real-time tower of
defense, but let's say you're
in a tower.
Think of who saw Inglorious
Basterds.
I said think Inglorious
Remember the guy in the tower?
Something like that.
Sparking a siege or something.
AUDIENCE: So American sniper
or German plot base.
AUDIENCE: Like tower
of defense.
Very similar, except you're
not military.
AUDIENCE: Running a marathon?
AUDIENCE: National politics.
AUDIENCE: From Las Vegas.
AUDIENCE: What?
AUDIENCE: Surviving the
Department of Motor Vehicles.
AUDIENCE: Middle School
popularity contest.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I'm not supposed
to make any jokes
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Being a cook in a
really busy restaurant.
AUDIENCE: Making nuclear
fusion work.
Finding lab scale scientific
endeavors.
I'm thinking NASA.
NASA planning.
TA: NASA scale types.
AUDIENCE: The immigration
process to America.
AUDIENCE: High school student
body election or student
government.
AUDIENCE: Evolution.
And also I give--
I know I love this idea-- ants
trying to find their way home.
AUDIENCE: Developing
a music career.
AUDIENCE: A career
in academia.
Also immune system.
TA: Academia and
immune system.
I like that.
AUDIENCE: Give myself
a fever, ah!
AUDIENCE: Auction house.
AUDIENCE: Lost in Japan.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
TA: Patrick.
AUDIENCE: Making photos
in a darkroom.
AUDIENCE: Culturing bacteria.
AUDIENCE: Transfat.
AUDIENCE: Similar to the
immigration to the US,
crossing the Caribbean Sea
in a boat or a raft.
AUDIENCE: Or one,
then the other.
TA: How many r's in Caribbean?
AUDIENCE: Two.
AUDIENCE: I'm pretty
sure it's one.
AUDIENCE: I'm pretty sure it's
two r's and two- let's see.
Oh yeah.
It's one r and two b's.
Damn.
AUDIENCE: Learning
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Westward expansion
of America.
AUDIENCE: Westward expansion.
AUDIENCE: Travelers to Oregon.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: The Oregon Trail.
AUDIENCE: Tech support.
AUDIENCE: Ooh.
You have committed suicide.
AUDIENCE: Advertising
executives at Apple.
PROFESSOR: I read was this
article about how Steve Jobs
was [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I'd think about
a person's journey of
understanding self.
TA: Self discovery.
AUDIENCE: Also a presidential
election.
TA: A presidential election.
AUDIENCE: Shepherding.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Mechanics are
kind of interesting
when you look at them.
AUDIENCE: Viking colony in the
new world before they left.
AUDIENCE: I don't know if you
guys still have it, but I made
a game [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It's probably indoors
somewhere.
You stole my idea.
TA: If two people have the same
idea, maybe you could
work on a team together.
AUDIENCE: Making a movie.
Like pre-production.
AUDIENCE: Being a castaway.
AUDIENCE: Running a religious
industry.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Raising a kid?
AUDIENCE: Right in the middle
of that right now.
AUDIENCE: Piracy without
getting caught.
AUDIENCE: As in high
seas piracy?
AUDIENCE: No. software piracy.
AUDIENCE: Designing
a board game.
AUDIENCE: Brainstorming.
AUDIENCE: Building a computer.
AUDIENCE: Waking up.
TA: Waking up.
AUDIENCE: Acknowledging
a [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: A couple.
Imperialism.
Well it's another
religious one.
Organizing a mass suicide.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Filing a divorce
TA: I called finding
a divorce.
AUDIENCE: I said finding
a horse.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Running away
from the police.
AUDIENCE: Crime scene
investigation.
AUDIENCE: Firefighting.
AUDIENCE: Falling asleep.
AUDIENCE: Waking up.
Falling asleep.
AUDIENCE: Organizing a heist.
AUDIENCE: Running the
Catholic Church.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: Money laundering.
Tax evasion.
AUDIENCE: Mafia.
TA: Is that the same idea?
AUDIENCE: They could be
two separate ideas.
TA: They could be
separate ideas.
Tax evasion happens small
scale and large scale.
AUDIENCE: Picking up kids flying
into a summer camp at
the airport and not trying
to lose them.
TA: What?
Not losing-
AUDIENCE: Not losing
arriving children.
TA: I could see that would
be at an airport
meeting kids game.
AUDIENCE: A gang or mafia
organization.
TA: Mafia organization.
AUDIENCE: The spread of fire
through different materials.
TA: Fire spread.
TA: Would probably work
very well with the
firefighting game.
AUDIENCE: Carrying
out a hit with a
small team of assassins.
Like you go into a hotel
in Dubai or something.
TA: This is the point
of the game.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Or dot-com boom and bust.
TA: Dot-com boom and bust.
AUDIENCE: Rescuing
Chilean miners.
AUDIENCE: Running a city.
AUDIENCE: We talked about
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Putting on and
taking off clothes.
Or putting on clothes.
AUDIENCE: I'm pretty sure there
are games where you are
taking off your clothes.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Hot sauce
eating contest.
AUDIENCE: Which is
already a game.
AUDIENCE: Well, sure.
AUDIENCE: Start a company, or
a Silicon Valley bubble.
TA: So Silicon, dot-com
boom and bust as well.
AUDIENCE: Surviving
a family reunion.
AUDIENCE: Containing
an oil spill.
AUDIENCE: Making a
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] lab.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Cooking's a game.
There's flavors and such.
AUDIENCE: Getting drunk,
or trying not to.
AUDIENCE: Make a
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Nuclear
proliferation.
AUDIENCE: I mean, bomb making
plus international diplomacy.
AUDIENCE: Living alone
on an island.
TA: That's kind of like
castaway as well.
Yeah, so island.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: So bomb disarming.
Also Congress and
Supreme Court as
two separate entities.
TA: Sorry, you have
to repeat that.
What now?
AUDIENCE: Bomb disarming.
Congress and the Supreme Court
as very separate ideas.
TA: Oh.
Congress.
We've had very many presidents
in the Congress
Supreme Court area.
Let's see.
I lost track.
Calvin.
AUDIENCE: Surgery.
AUDIENCE: Operation.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I
love that game.
AUDIENCE: Running
and orphanage.
AUDIENCE: If I might,
running a charity.
AUDIENCE: Creating and spreading
[? means. ?]
AUDIENCE: It'd be great if
you could actually spread
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Being a tourist
in Amsterdam.
TA: Very specific.
OK.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Basic programs
at MIT.
AUDIENCE: That's worse.
AUDIENCE: Playing games.
AUDIENCE: Wait, how do
you imagine that
you're playing a game.
And you play too many games.
And you [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
Being an IPS.
AUDIENCE: Twitter.
AUDIENCE: Being a pro gamer.
TA: The pro gamer game.
AUDIENCE: Managing traffic
intersections.
TA: Traffic intersections.
AUDIENCE: Being a programmer.
A software designer.
TA: We have programmer
and pro gamer.
Two different things.
AUDIENCE: Fishing.
And losing weight.
AUDIENCE: The historical
whaling industry.
AUDIENCE: It's not a current
system, right?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Chastity and
candle making.
AUDIENCE: Unicorns.
AUDIENCE: Wait, unicorns?
AUDIENCE: Maybe we should
combine that into medieval
guild operations.
AUDIENCE: Running railroads.
TA: Railroads.
AUDIENCE: Lumberjacking.
AUDIENCE: Spelunking.
AUDIENCE: Stock market
speculation.
TA: Stock market?
Or speculation in particular.
AUDIENCE: Salem witch trials.
Or witch hunts in general.
TA: Witch hunts.
AUDIENCE: Unions.
TA: I'm starting to think
that [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Building a house.
AUDIENCE: FedEx.
TA: FedEx.
AUDIENCE: Spreading
a mass hysteria.
Like McCarthy style.
TA: Also known as [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Cold War spying
and the internet.
TA: Cold War espionage.
And the internet.
AUDIENCE: Communism.
AUDIENCE: Computer virus.
AUDIENCE: Hurricanes
and oceans.
AUDIENCE: Could you do something
like astrology,
which is not a real-world
system, but is--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
TA: Yes.
You can do astrology.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
virus.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
But that would be more
like a real virus.
TA: I would suggest limiting
yourselves to
just the real world.
I mean, coming up with things
like zombie outbreaks, sure
there is a system
you can model.
But if you're just trying to
push on the edges of the
constraints, then you're just
trying to give yourself an
easier time.
And more often I see the results
actually turn out to
be less interesting because
people are just
going for the ideas.
They just [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
them really, really quickly.
People aren't actually
trying to work it.
But that being said, even with
a lot of the ideas up here, a
lot of them have connections.
Even there will be
the obvious ones.
Like oil spill containing and
oil spill starting could
practically be the same thing.
Everything with the presidential
election.
Spreading mass hysteria
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And these ideas are now
up on the board.
You have until the end
of Friday, I guess.
We don't really need
to know until the
beginning of next week.
So actually by the end of
Friday, you should know who is
on your team and what project
you're working on.
Over the weekend, you know
who's on your team.
You know to email people
on your team.
And what idea you're
starting with.
Again, the idea can diverge a
little bit, but I like the
previous project.
We do want you to keep with
whatever you started with and
use it as core system.
You may choose presidential
election.
It may be something about
winning votes.
And then you decide no, you
want to make a game of
gerrymandering.
That's fine.
Because it's still keeping
in with the
same core of the system.
But say oh, we want to do
something about winning votes
and then instead it became
about religion or
something like that.
I could see how you got there,
but that's not really keeping
with the spirit at this
particular time.
So stick with the original
core system that you're
working with.
And try to find the fun in it.
Don't try to like, oh, this
is a really dull simulator
mechanic, but if we add a bunch
of [UNINTELLIGIBLE] then
it becomes funny.
No.
Try to find it fun in
the original system.
And if you can't try to pick
apart the system and find the
one component that is fun.
So all of bomb making might
not be so much fun as as
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the blood--
Yeah, that might be
the fun part.
The one part, I'll be, oops my
hand slipped, and therefore I
am now dead.
That part might be actually kind
of fun, as opposed to OK,
now I need to figure out how
to get [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Cool.
All these ideas are going
to stay up on
the board for a while.