The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK, so I'm
actually to keep the
discussion today pretty short
because the games that we've
got lined up are pretty long.
Two of them I know
are really good.
One of them was good last year
so we'll see again this year.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So we'll see.
Are there 4 games at least.
AUDIENCE: I'm [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Mexico and Puerto Rico
which will be five.
I just haven't pulled
it out yet.
AUDIENCE: I call Thebes.
GUEST SPEAKER: Cool.
For people--
have you played Thebes before.
AUDIENCE: No.
GUEST SPEAKER: Good.
OK.
So for people who played San
Juan last time, I think Puerto
Rico's an interesting
comparison.
Because, San Juan actually, it's
a sequel to Puerto Rico.
So you kind of--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Which one
was San Juan?
GUEST SPEAKER: That was
the one where, how
would describe it?
AUDIENCE: Is it related to Race
for the Galaxy as well?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You choose
the action.
GUEST SPEAKER: Ah, Race?
So that takes us right
into today's game.
So Puerto Rico is kind of
what was [INAUDIBLE].
Puerto Rico is the, I guess
it was actually the first
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
we needed previous
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
inspirations.
And San Juan's kind of the card
game of this, which is
why we introduced it earlier.
Because you guys were working
on card games.
Race to the Galaxy is more of
a spiritual succession as
described in the reading.
But you could also
think of it as a
clone with a few upgrades.
Because it wasn't
the same people.
It wasn't the same
people who made--
AUDIENCE: It was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: To clarify, the guy
who did San Juan and the guy
who did Race to the Galaxy were
kind of collaborating.
So the games are really
similar because they
influenced each other.
But they were not strictly
the same project.
GUEST SPEAKER: So you can think
of it as multiple people
from the same artist community
turning out similar games at
the same time.
AUDIENCE: Nice.
GUEST SPEAKER: But, yeah,
informed by each other, and
when Race came out it was very
much seen as this is Puerto
Rico with problems fixed, or the
game has expanded my bad--
AUDIENCE: And problems
added, too.
GUEST SPEAKER: --and problems
added, too, and, of course,
completely different scenes.
But at least in terms of game
mechanics, that's a nice
connection that you can actually
see among the games
that you played before
and you're going
to be playing today.
Not every single game that we've
got here has got that
kind of heritage factor.
These games aren't specifically
picked, to me, to
match up with previous
games or sequels.
The only reason why I'm talking
about sequels because
we had to talk about them
sooner or later.
Of course, Battlestar Galactica
is really a
[? rotation ?]
of the TV series.
And I wouldn't quite call this
a sequel, in a sense, because
simply, this is not based
on a previous
Battlestar Galactica game.
I'm sure there were previous
Battlestar Galactica games
that were based on the old
'70s TV series that have
nothing to do with this one.
This is more of the
adaptation.
And the reason why I'm using
that upgrade is so that we can
be very clear in
our vocabulary.
This is taking elements of
something that's in a
different medium, like the film
or the TV series, and
trying to figure out what in
that TV series, in that world,
that has been created, that
fictional world, might yield
interesting game playing.
And this game is pretty much
about figuring out who is the
Cylon in and among
all the players.
Among all the players, there's
going to be traitors.
And you try to hide your
activities, and you try to
help people, help the human race
survive, if you happen
not to be a traitor.
But some of the things that you
end up doing in order to
help the human race, not just
surviving and not looking
suspicious.
If you played Mafia it kind of
has a little bit of that feel.
Only this is way more
heavy [? weighing ?]
of a game mechanics because they
really, really wanted to
make you think like the
characters, that you have the
same dilemmas that
the characters
in the TV show have.
AUDIENCE: Does the Cylon know
that he or she is a Cylon?
GUEST SPEAKER: I believe
that, I believe you
can find out halfway.
AUDIENCE: OK.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, if I recall
the rules correctly.
And then there are players
who will know
right from the beginning.
So there may be more than one.
In fact, there is really
more than one.
AUDIENCE: I'm psyched.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK, so there
were a bunch of different
things that were listed in--
they were given as reasons why
people want to do sequels.
But for the most part the big
one is just you're building
off an established base.
You're not having to rebuild
everything from scratch.
In many cases, a sequel doesn't
actually cost less or
take less time than making
your original game.
You just end up spending,
hopefully, spending that
development time a little
bit more wisely.
You avoid a lot of pitfalls
because you're pretty much
making a very similar game.
The game industry's been one of
those fields where, oddly
enough, part two, the follow
up, tends to be better then
the original.
As opposed to how many movie
sequels are generally better
than the original?
Godfather, that's one of them.
AUDIENCE: Back to the Future.
AUDIENCE: It's rare.
GUEST SPEAKER: It's
really rare.
I'm thinking the Clint Eastwood
man with no name
series, Godfather.
Any other?
AUDIENCE: Back to the Future.
GUEST SPEAKER: Back
to the Future?
AUDIENCE: I don't know.
I could go either way.
AUDIENCE: I don't agree.
GUEST SPEAKER: It could
go either way.
AUDIENCE: It's arguable.
It's arguable.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: You mean like
Empire Strikes Back.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK, The
AUDIENCE: Spider-Man, perhaps?
AUDIENCE: Spider-Man 2.
AUDIENCE: I don't know.
I felt like they were all bad.
AUDIENCE: They were all bad.
AUDIENCE: That's true.
AUDIENCE: It was better.
GUEST SPEAKER: But,
yeah, as we--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Dark Knight?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, I will,
yeah, I'll give you that.
But it's still kind of tough.
Whereas how many good
games sequels--
How many games can you think of
where you played both the
first, the original, and
then the sequel to it?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Just the sequel.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK, well, some
of them are spaced apart so
far that you actually only
ended up playing--
AUDIENCE: Well, I mean
like Half-Life.
GUEST SPEAKER: Half-Life,
Half-Life 2, for instance.
AUDIENCE: Star Trek.
GUEST SPEAKER: Star
Trek, Star Trek 2.
AUDIENCE: Age of Empires.
GUEST SPEAKER: Age of Empires
I, II, and then III.
AUDIENCE: Shogun - Total War.
GUEST SPEAKER: Shogun.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: The Total
War series.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, Total War
is kind of an interesting
thing because they don't
pitch them as sequels.
But they very much pitch
them as a series.
And the whole idea is that if
you liked one game, you
actually know a lot about what
any of the other games
in that series do.
Sure, graphically they're
upgrading.
Game mechanics wise
they're trying to
portal a lot of things.
Some of them are medieval.
Some of them are Japanese.
AUDIENCE: In the readings,
they mentioned that Final
Fantastic VII was the
sequel to VI.
Is that correct?
Is that correct nomenclature?
GUEST SPEAKER: And I will
disagree with that, actually.
Final Fantasy VII actually has
a sequel, for instance.
AUDIENCE: Right.
GUEST SPEAKER: What was
it, Crisis Core?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: There's a
couple, actually.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: More than one--
GUEST SPEAKER: First of all,
there's the movie.
That sequel was the movie.
And then they did a
bunch of things.
AUDIENCE: Oh God, there were--
GUEST SPEAKER: Final Fantasy
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Final Fantasy--
GUEST SPEAKER: --an entry
in a series but--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: But I think when
it comes to, this is what
we're going to be pitching
to a publisher--
I'm not sure that Square Enix
needs to pitch Final Fantasy
themselves--
Think of another game that has
an [? all ?] series, if anyone
can come up with one.
AUDIENCE: Baldur's Gate.
GUEST SPEAKER: Baldur's Gate
might be actually a good one
because different companies end
up working on different
types of revisions.
Actually, most of these--
well, actually, Fallout and
Baldur's Gate both come from
Interplay, I believe,
originally.
AUDIENCE: They went out of
business after Bloodlands.
We were talking about
this yesterday.
GUEST SPEAKER: I suspect
that was before that--
AUDIENCE: That was Vampires
Bloodlines.
AUDIENCE: Yes, this
came up yesterday.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: But basically--
leaving aside what makes a
company go out of business--
the issue of when you have a
series and then you have
different companies making
different versions, Guitar
Hero III, for instance--
AUDIENCE: Knights of Republic.
GUEST SPEAKER: Knights
of the Old--
AUDIENCE: The second one was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
GUEST SPEAKER: So BioWare was
the first one and Obsidian did
the second one.
Fallout was Bethesda,
Obsidian, I believe.
Obsidian's really built a whole
business model around
making part two of something.
AUDIENCE: Or expansion
packs and stuff.
GUEST SPEAKER: Expansion
packs, no.
You have closely related
to that.
And in those cases, sometimes,
like in the case of BioWare,
Obsidian connections, they
have a good relationship,
they've all written a lot of
technology, and they are
getting an advantage of we've
kind of ironed out the kinks,
we're just sort of continuing
the story, especially the
story based game.
Knights of the Old Republic,
clearly you've got to fit it
within the Star Wars story.
And they had the interest to
basically keep the tale of
these characters going,
even more so for--
well, Mass Effect was
by Bioware, but
that sort of thing.
But then you have the other
angle where you just want to
get the same success but you
want to tell a different
story, or in the case of
Guitar Hero III have a
completely different
set of music.
And in Final Fantasy VII, you
had certain game mechanics and
certain things that carry
on from game to game.
And definitely you want
to carry the fans
from game to game.
But part of the appeal of the
Final Fantasy series is that
every single one is going to
be a different story, not
dramatically different but it's
going to be a different
story with different characters
and a different world.
So but this is pitched very
similarly when you go to a
game company and your whole idea
is how do we get the fans
to buy even more, or even more
fans, to buy version two.
There are two edges to that
sword, though, because what
typically happens in a lot of
sequel development is, they
are trying so hard to please
the original fans often by
adding complexity, by adding
things that build on things
that players of the first game
already know, that you
actually start alienating
new players.
The game becomes just so complex
or just complex enough
that people start getting
turned off.
A couple of weeks ago over here
we played Guitar Freaks
on Friday Games for Gambit.
And the first version is
actually extremely accessible.
Once again, from the second
version all the way up to, I
think, the version 4 that we
were playing, it is almost
impossible for a new player to
jump in because they've got
one beginning friendly song and
everything else is based
for fans of the game.
So you imagine a Guitar Hero
game that's built entirely for
people who've already mastered
expert on the previous game.
That's kind of what happened
with Guitar Freaks.
And in many cases, that might
be enough if the game was
particularly successful the
first time around, and you
only get 80% of the fan base
to buy the second version,
that's still a lot of money.
And it's a way lower risk
compared to coming up with new
IP from scratch.
And a lot of companies, when
they're creating IP, they're
very much specifically thinking,
right off the bat,
what are the sequel
opportunities.
Even now, because you've got
downloadable content, so it's
even narrower than that, is what
are downloadable content
opportunities?
How do we release extension
packs really, really quickly?
And how do we create stories,
worlds, technology that's just
going to be able to anticipate
all that.
There's a game up there now on
Xbox Live Arcade called Monday
Night Combat.
And they did some of the old
clever hacks to basically
allow them to update the game
on a week to week basis.
Whereas typically that kind
of a certification that's
required from Microsoft
is really expensive.
Every time you want to release a
new version, you have to put
it through an entire rigorous
QA testing schedule, again.
But they came up with some
technology that let them make
at least game tuning changes on
the fly without having to
go through the Microsoft
testing series.
So it's not technically
releasing the sequel but they
were very much thinking
about how do we keep
updating this game.
I wouldn't be surprised if Steam
started off as that.
There's a battle net kind of
started off as just an easy
way for them to get up patches
and to keep tuning this game,
and eventually someone involved
decides, hey, we can
sell games this way.
And launch was kind of bumpy.
But it's fine now.
There is one thing which the
book didn't mention which is
the reboot, the sort of
franchise reboot.
This can sometimes happen when
you have a publisher who's got
control of an RP that kind
of floundered halfway.
Maybe there was a bad execution
on creation and
possible circumstance.
Or they just play out the
formula to death.
And then they want to try to get
a new batch of fans, a few
people who liked the
original one.
And I was talking with the Tomb
Raider game where they're
just trying to--
they've rebooted the Tomb
Raider franchise several
times, at this point, each time
trying to say, OK, you've
probably heard from Tomb Raider
from the huge amount of
advertising that we've done when
you may not have actually
liked the previous versions
of the games.
And we're doing to reboot this
franchise by making a
different game in
that same world.
In Tomb Raider we'll use
characters and we'll use the
fiction, but we'll change the
game play significantly.
Because we're not going after
the old fans anymore.
We're going after a new batch.
It's probably about the same
technical challenge as
updating, as trying to
make a sequel for a
completely new platform.
Because they're basically having
to write everything
from scratch.
But the good news, of course,
is that all that previous
advertising that you did a
decade ago still works.
Let me think of--
Can anyone think of a good
example of a good reboot?
AUDIENCE: Is Mario
64 a reboot?
AUDIENCE: No.
GUEST SPEAKER: I think it was
seen to a lot of people that
it was because it wasn't clearly
a sequel to any of the
previous Mario games.
And it was kind of
Nintendo kind of
saying, hey, it's not--
AUDIENCE: It's not really
a clone of anything.
GUEST SPEAKER: It's
not really--
It invented a lot of things for
the first time, in fact.
I would say that Mario 64 and,
of course, the way how they
branded it, they didn't brand
it Super Mario World, what 5
or Super Mario 4 or anything,
they called it Mario 64 to
sort of distinguish it
from some of the--
AUDIENCE: I would almost call
IT an upgrade more than a
reboot, though.
Because it was mostly just
a move from 2D to 3D.
AUDIENCE: It was more
than that, I think.
GUEST SPEAKER: It's a good
challenge because to the
player it may seem like it's not
that but for a technical
point of view they had to
continue to reinvent how Mario
moves, the way how Mario jumps
frankly, the way how the
camera moves, it never used to
be a huge problem in the 2D
games, but was the primary thing
that they've managed to
figure out how to get working
in 3D was the camera.
I wouldn't be surprised if their
marketing pitched it a
little bit like a sequel.
But it was also very, very clear
of this is going to be a
whole new generation, you've
never played Mario on anything
like this, so don't expect your
previous Mario experience
to carry over necessarily.
AUDIENCE: I was going to
say Metroid, as well.
GUEST SPEAKER: Metroid Prime?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, that's
a really good example.
In fact, Metroid Prime was an
instance where they gave the
franchise to a completely
different developer.
Previously, it's all
internal Nintendo.
And then Nintendo went to a
western developer, Retro
Studios over in Texas and
basically had them make the
first western version
of Metroid.
But they had a very heavy hand
in controlling that.
Whereas--
I'm not sure we're going to
be playing this later--
Castlevania: Lords of Shadow
which just came out, kind of
went the other way around.
Western developers, a Spanish
developer, decided to make a
Castlevania clone.
They loved Castlevania.
And they were going to make
a game that was just like
Castlevania but they don't call
it Castlevania because
they didn't have the
rights for it.
And they showed it off at E3
or something, and Konami
basically said, why don't
we just turn this into a
Castlevania game, Hideo
Kojima to [INAUDIBLE]
making it work.
AUDIENCE: It must have been
their dream come true.
GUEST SPEAKER: That
was probably
their dream come true.
That was probably what
they wanted.
And you had the advantage of the
all the Castlevania fans
now saying OK, this is going
to be in canon, if we liked
Castlevania, we'll probably
like this one, which is
exactly what they were
trying to get across.
It's like imagine the people
who made Torchlight being
approached from Blizzard saying
why don't we just turn
this into Diablo 3.
AUDIENCE:A bunch of people who
made Torchlight were from
Blizzard, right?
GUEST SPEAKER: I wouldn't
be surprised.
AUDIENCE: Were they from
the Diablo team?
GUEST SPEAKER: I wouldn't
be surprised.
In the same sense that a lot of
people who built GuildWars
were from the World
of Warcraft team.
So that's less an issue of
sequels and more an issue of
that's just how the game
industry works.
People move from project
to project and carry
knowledge with them.
AUDIENCE: Like Call of Duty was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes, Call
of Duty, yes and--
AUDIENCE: They got tired
of it and were
like we can do better.
GUEST SPEAKER: That's an
interesting discussion of
instead of sequels you have
companies making effectively
clones competing against
the original franchise.
And in this product case
they're trying--
there's people who left EA on
2015, I believe, and then they
started Infinity Ward.
And they made a game
that basically
competed with the original.
AUDIENCE: The first Call of Duty
was so ridiculously good,
at least, it marked me when I
played it the first time.
GUEST SPEAKER: But it's very
clearly trying to be Medal of
Honor the next version.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, clearly, yeah,
no, of course, of course.
GUEST SPEAKER: So that's an
interesting situation where
it's hard to be a spiritual
successor when you're
competing against the
original product.
But you can think of them--
AUDIENCE: BioWare did
that with Dragon--
I mean not competing against
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
Dragon Age because they don't
have the rights to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] game anymore.
GUEST SPEAKER: Well, Dragon Age
is more of a DND clone, I
would say, which--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Empire Earth
reinvented itself with--
GUEST SPEAKER: Which one?
AUDIENCE: --with
Empire Earth--
GUEST SPEAKER: Empire Earth.
AUDIENCE: --with zero success.
It didn't do [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: I kind of lost
track of that series.
AUDIENCE: In the whole game, the
first game was like, you
can go through 15 ages.
You can literally play a game
against someone and go from
prehistoric units to nukes in
the same game with everything
in between.
And then they released the
sequel which, I think,
overseas and then it's like
they [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
themselves and go, we're going
to simplify everything,
there's just going to be four
ages, kind of like in Ancient
Empires, and we're not going
to have this massive
progression.
And they tried to simplify
everything.
And it totally bombed.
GUEST SPEAKER: I think
that's a rebooting.
But I think that's a
reboot gone wrong.
That's a, our original game is
not selling well enough among
new players, maybe, and it's
not entirely satisfying our
old fans, so we're going to take
this franchise that we
advertised really, really well,
and we're going to make
it completely, effectively a new
game, maybe with the same
theme but a new game
that targeted at
a new set of players.
Sometimes it works.
Sometimes it bombs.
Might and Magic released a game
called Clash of Heroes,
Might and Magic Clash of Heroes
for the Nintendo DS.
Who's played any
of the original
Might and Magic games?
AUDIENCE: Different from Heroes
of Might and Magic?
GUEST SPEAKER: Either
of them, actually.
So who's played Heroes
of Might and Magic?
Can you describe the game?
What's it like?
AUDIENCE: Want to
go, [? Fred? ?]
AUDIENCE: Well, it's like
essentially just a turn based
strategy game where you have
cities and you have heroes.
And these heroes lead armies.
And you encounter other smaller
armies and try to
defeat them and stuff.
And you have--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
city, you start with--
you have an economy.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you have an
economy and you build things
in your city that can then
produce better units for your
armies and stuff.
You can take over other
cities and--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: Like
Civilization, I would say.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, it's like
Civilization but if you took
Civilization and removed
everything that wasn't military.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: And that was what
played out and gave it its
distinctive arena--
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: --turn based--
AUDIENCE: You're trying to do
stuff like battlefields where
the turn based, you have your
units on one side and the
opponent's units on
the other side.
And you move units together.
So if you have pikemen and
bowmen, you have the clump of
all bowmen who then move
together as a unit.
GUEST SPEAKER: So Clash of
Heroes, a Nintendo DS game in
the Might and Magic series, and
what they did was, they
made a match three game.
They made a game where you--
it's like Bejeweled.
You take three bowmen, put them
in a row, and then they
become a bunch of bowmen who
are going to attack.
So they get the same idea
of let's take--
and because the Nintendo DS
has two screens, so the
enemy's armies are on one and
yours are on the other.
It's kind of like sending
troops up and down.
But the game play's dramatically
different.
It's effectively a
franchise reboot.
They want to get the same idea
of leading massive armies
against each other.
I think they take some of the
characters, at least some of
the technologies that came with
the original Heroes of
Might and Magic.
But that's as far as it got.
Everything else they changed.
Because they were going for a
completely different audience,
the assumption being Nintendo
DS players liked match three
games like Bejeweled, actually
really good.
I'd encourage it if you like
match three games.
I was going to put Sarah on the
spot for having worked on
Thief II, and Thief Gold,
and Thief 2 Gold,
and a number of releases.
But maybe we can start telling
us a little bit about your
original involvement on Thief.
SARAH: Sure.
Do you want me to stand up
to actually hear me?
GUEST SPEAKER: I can bring
the mike closer.
SARAH: So Thief: The Dark
Project, I came on as actually
as team tester.
Part way through it I became
community manager,
essentially.
And then I actually stepped into
a design role for about
the second half of
the project.
And I continued to work as a
designer and project manager
on Thief II and Thief Gold.
GUEST SPEAKER: What were
you designing in Thief?
SARAH: In Thief I, I was pretty
specifically designing
game play for a level
that someone
else had already built.
Building levels took a lot
longer than putting in game
play, at least from
my point of view.
I believe the person who built
it thought that building
levels was a lot faster
than laying game play.
So it was a good combination.
But it was built by an artist
who didn't have the scripting
experience or the testing
visions to go through and make
sure that all the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] for the game
play experience is working.
So I was basically handed
a level and
said, OK, make it fun.
GUEST SPEAKER: Now Thief is a
first person stealth game.
Basically you're looking through
the eyes of a thief
who is not physically
all that robust.
But he can sneak.
And he can shoot arrows,
usually at
your back, and hide.
SARAH: And the AI is, unlike in
most games where the AI is
tuned sort of aha, we noticed
you, we charge you, the AI is
carefully tuned to both tell the
player if the AI sort of
notices you, if the AI thinks
he's looking for you and is
looking for, and if he's
actually coming after you.
So that a player who makes a
noise while sneaking up on
them will realize that, oh, he
noticed that, I should go be
more quiet.
So the AI feedback and
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] was actually
really pretty important
to playing experience.
If you didn't give the player an
avenue to approach a guard
from behind or to sneak up on
them in some way, you'll
pretty much guarantee the
player will get killed.
Because the player could not, in
fact, take one guard on one
to one many times.
You could probably kill one
guard face to face, but then
he'd be sufficiently wounded
that the second fight would
finish him off.
So you had to be giving the
player channels and ways to
sneak up and places to hide and
things like that if you
wanted to have an interesting
game and a challenging game.
GUEST SPEAKER: And that's the
game play we say you're
talking about.
SARAH: Those are the game
plays we've been talking
about, yeah, placing AIs
determining their path,
putting-- this actually
particularly had a lot of
traps in it--
so creating the traps and giving
clues to the player in
games so that they could, A,
either notice the trap was
there before getting hit by it
and finding some other way to
trigger it, or notice that it
was there or notice it was
there and then discover
how to get out of it.
GUEST SPEAKER: Thief
is a 199--
SARAH: Oh God, 19-- ancient
at this point.
GUEST SPEAKER: 199--
SARAH: 199--, 1996, it was
released around the
same time Doom was.
GUEST SPEAKER: And it's pretty
impressive because in Doom you
can't look up, I believe.
You can shoot up
but you can't--
SARAH: Yeah.
I think you can crouch.
You can lean around corners.
You can, in fact, shoot
your bow while
leaning around corners.
And, yeah, you can look up
and down and all around.
GUEST SPEAKER: So that's Thief
I. What happens when Thief II
gets approved?
SARAH: Well, the first thing I
had to do was convince people
they wanted to do Thief II.
Because while Thief was a great
game and it's actually
sold fairly well over time,
its initial sales were not
what publishers want to see.
Because the initial sales a
publisher wants to see is, oh
my God, it sold 10 million
copies, awesome.
Instead what we did was we
sold a fairly good first
initial sell through and then
it just kind of kept going.
So the first thing we had to
do was convince them that,
yes, Thief II would be a good
idea, enough people are
continuing to buy Thief I. Those
same people will all run
out and buy Thief II on
the very first day.
And the way we did that was,
first of all, taking a look at
forums and saying, hey look,
people are pretty excited
about this.
They're enjoying it.
It's got good lasting power.
Our fans are going to stick
around to play with it a
second time.
And that was sort of a marketing
end analysis that
led into a publisher.
And the other part was saying,
OK, what are the improvements
we're going to make
to this game?
How are we going to change this
game to make it better
than Thief I while still
taking advantage of
everything we did?
So we created basically a big
design doc with, here are the
areas that we thought we could
have done better in Thief I.
Here's what we're going
to improve.
And here are the changes
we're going to make.
So we're not going to
make Thief I, again.
We're going to take what Thief
I was, add some improvements
to it, make a deeper story,
and hopefully get a more
variety of game play was what
we actually ended up aiming
for in our initial docs.
We wanted to give Garrett
additional abilities,
vary the game play.
The game play in Thief
I was all speed.
We tried to have some additional
types of missions
in Thief II.
But there was a little more
face to face fighting.
There was a little
more subterfuge.
Instead of just sneaking around,
we also had, OK, so
now you need to disguise
yourself as someone and sneak
in, sneak out again.
You need to pass for them while
getting a goal done and
things like that.
So we tried to find, what are
additional stealth and
subterfuge issues and game
play we can have?
GUEST SPEAKER: How many of those
features in Thief II
were inherited from dropped
features from Thief I?
SARAH: A lot of them inherited
from dropped ideas from Thief
I. But when they first started
designing Thief-- and I was
not on the initial Thief design
team so now I'm making
up what they were
talking about.
It wasn't clear that it
was going to be--
It was sort of like, it's going
to be a stealthy game,
but we hadn't actually
defined what stealthy
game play was yet.
So it was Thief I that kind of
told us what, this is what
stealth game play that works.
And once we found the one or
two things that worked, we
kind of went with that
and put in that.
It was in Thief II, we got to
play around what are some
other ideas of stealthy
game play?
What are some other ways to
trick people into [INAUDIBLE]?
GUEST SPEAKER: And people that
played Metal Gear Solid or any
of the games in Metal Gear Solid
series, it owes a lot to
Thief, especially the really,
really noisy end you see.
It wasn't, I heard something,
I wonder what's over there.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
SARAH: DS-X also.
GUEST SPEAKER: But DS-X is also
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
SARAH: But that's what I'm
saying is that DS-X also
actually took a lot of Thief's
lessons and went on with them
from there.
GUEST SPEAKER: Again, a lot
of people working on
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
SARAH: DS-X2, more
DS-X2, but yeah.
Looking Glass folded and
went out of business.
And a lot of people moved to
Austin to then work on Thief
III and DS-X2 and those
projects there.
GUEST SPEAKER: I
have a question
about the Gold version.
SARAH: The Gold version?
The Gold versions of the games
are really a way to try to
convince, from the marketing
point of view, is a way to
convince players to buy the
same material again.
I'm being a little cynical
here, and I admit that.
But we added new, we did, in
fact, add, what we did was, we
added several new missions.
So it was expanded play.
And then we went back and
problems that we knew were in
the missions, we fixed them.
And we actually added some
richer game play to several of
the missions that, oh God, we
have to get this out the door,
we have to get this out the
door, this would be so cool if
we could set this up but
we don't have time
to, and out it goes.
And so we went back
and we touched up
over half of the missions.
We added some additional
game play.
We added extra goals.
We took areas where we thought
the game play was particularly
weak because we'd gotten rushed
on finishing it and we
made the levels a bit longer and
a little more interesting
in our opinion.
And then we also added
three new levels.
And it was kind of a chance,
it was a do over.
We had very limited programming
resources so we
didn't really get to add much
in the way of new features.
But we were able to go back
and tune it and make
significant changes to the
levels, to the way that the
guards worked, to the scripting
behind the levels.
Vin was working on a 3D mod.
There's usually a fair bit the
designer can do behind the
walls of telling the AIs what to
do and how to think and how
the game play flows.
And Thief, especially, had an
extremely rich editor that--
more powerful, I think, than any
other editor I ever worked
with, even though it is
now 15 years old, 15
years old, I think.
It's still the most powerful
editor for a
designer I have ever seen.
GUEST SPEAKER: So
did you feel--
You mentioned you looked
at forums and
you look at fan input.
And how much of that, of what
went into making the sequel,
actually came from fan input?
Or was it just like verifying
what you already wanted to do.
SARAH: Part of it was to verify
what we wanted to do.
Part of it was to verify there
was enough interest that
people would want to do it.
Part of it was to see, what
did people like most?
Which of the missions did
people like most?
Are there any good ideas out
there for how to play a game
that we think, yes,
they're right, we
never thought of that.
I think that one of the things
people talked about a lot was
actually disguise missions.
And I think we had two disguise
missions in Thief II
where you're kind of disguising
yourself as, no,
no, no, no one looked at me, I'm
just another guard walking
around, don't worry about me.
And that was something that we
said, oh, yeah, that would be
really cool.
And that's something we had no
time to implement for Thief
but, if we're choosing new
features to implement in Thief
II, that was actually not an
amazingly difficult one.
Because you just, if you've got
a way to put a tag on the
play that says, oh, guards
don't get upset
when they see you.
GUEST SPEAKER: Did you have a
situations where players came
out with exploits that
you tried to
address in the Gold version?
SARAH: There were not,
no, actually.
There were a couple of places
where people found bugs that
were level enders that
got people stuck that
we went in and fixed.
There were not a whole lot of
exploits that I recall us
trying to go in and fix.
AUDIENCE: So if somebody
deliberately found something
that put them on the roof of the
castle or something like
that, then you didn't want them
trying to [INAUDIBLE]?
SARAH: If it allowed the player
to get to a place when
he broke the game, we
did try to fix it.
Because we tried to fix anything
that was game breaker
where you could get up on
the wall and then leap
off into the void.
But sometimes what we'd do is,
rather than stop you from
getting up on the castle and
proving how cool you were,
we'd let you get up on the
castle but we'd put in
invisible barriers so you
couldn't hurl yourself into
the darkness and then
crash the game.
If players enjoyed finding those
things so taking them
out doesn't enhance
the game play.
And the point of the Gold
project was to try to make
something the game play was
sufficiently enhanced that it
was worthwhile to go
out and buy again.
GUEST SPEAKER: So now we're in
an environment where patches
pretty much is downloaded,
right?
SARAH: Yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: We don't
necessarily have that
situation in the year 1996.
Is there still a role of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASES]
new releases?
SARAH: I think now again that
would be an expansion pack.
I don't think that you would
do a Gold version.
You'd do an expansion pack.
And with an expansion pack
patch you could fix old
problems and you might introduce
new games and of
levels, but I don't think
you do it with the
hassle of doing a Gold.
I think you just do
an expansion pack.
[APPLAUSE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Questions
for Sarah and her
experience on it?
AUDIENCE: Pretty much all of
your data points just came
from forums where you--
SARAH: Oh yeah, oh yeah, that
was just one of the places
where we looked.
We also looked at sales
and continuing sales
and things like that.
Like I said, that was actually
more of a marketing sales to
sort of do, here's why we think
players will like it.
Here's some experiences
we got.
Here's the hard data on our
sales, how our sales are
continuing, and the fact that
while it did not come out and
sell 100,000 copies the first
month, it's continuing to sell
20,000 or 30,000 copies a month,
which means that word
of mouth is pretty strong, and
people are continuing to go
out and buy it and go
out and play it.
And here's the forum where a
whole bunch of people are
using the editor released.
And the activity in that forum
is going up over time not down
over time which indicates you've
got more people coming
into it, people are coming in,
they're staying at and using
it, and you've got more people
continuing to come in, the
community's growing, which means
that there's interest
there and there's people who
are paying attention to
project and are going to
continue to pay attention to
your product.
AUDIENCE: But also it
gave for finding
dead ends, for finding--
You said you fixed some of the
dead games [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
SARAH: Yeah, oh yeah, yeah.
Well, the difference
between a--
let me think--
At our height, we had a 12
person QA department.
And 50,000 users
is pretty big.
And we did our best
on testing it.
And we had another 10 or 15
helpers through our publisher.
But we had comparatively
speaking a ridiculously small
QA department for the game.
GUEST SPEAKER: But then you
have the situation where
someone notes something on the
forum and then you can verify
it with your QA team.
SARAH: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: And you can
actually figure out whether
what they were seeing was
exactly the problem they were
describing.
SARAH: And it being a solely
single player game--
I know a lot of games do large
beta tests where they ask 500,
or 200, or 1,000 people
to play the game.
We did not do any external
testing like that at all.
Yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: And this was
also back in the '90s that
wasn't being done.
SARAH: Oh, yeah, it was not
the sort of thing that was
really done in the
'90s as well.
It's very much a developmental
shift.
AUDIENCE: Did you ever
explicitly ask on the forums
if there were another sequel,
would you buy it?
SARAH: I don't know.
I did not do that.
I was not on the forums.
I helped with some of the forum
data in [? reforms ?]
but I didn't really post
on the forums a lot.
AUDIENCE: Do you think that
would be viable tactic, or
would you just say, people would
probably just say yes.
SARAH: I think that your data
wouldn't be very good.
AUDIENCE: OK.
SARAH: The most you're probably
going to get is the
1,000 people who read
the forum say, yes.
And that's 1,000 people.
And that's not enough sales
to justify doing anything.
AUDIENCE: Gotcha.
SARAH: It's more interesting,
I think it's more useful to
look at trends, if you've
got a survey out
maybe, I don't know.
GUEST SPEAKER: I've seen
companies bring in focus
groups, people who played the
first game to come in and
bouncing off either prototypes
or features that they're
planning for the second version
to see how they will
respond to them.
I would say that the information
you back from that
is also not very good.
But it might be something that
is done to gain traction in
internal studio politics, and it
was like, well, we did this
exercise where we brought these
people in and they said
these features are OK, so
we can take the risk of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
As opposed to driving the entire
process [INAUDIBLE].
SARAH: Games don't respond
really well to focus test
based development.
GUEST SPEAKER: Or
focus group--
SARAH: Or focus group
based development.
Getting feedback on your
games is great.
Finding out how many people are
likely to like your game
is a lot harder.
GUEST SPEAKER: Especially if
they can't actually see it
when you're asking them the
question then they have no
idea what they're
commenting on.
They'll make something up that
they think you want to hear,
is, yes, of course, we'll
buy a copy of the game.
We loved the first one.
Sure.
But if they haven't actually
seen the second version of the
game [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE], so
you don't actually know if
that is the case.
For those of you who do missed
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
talk last week, he was talking
about how Inamplitude which
was a sequel--
Was Amplitude--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Oh yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: I think it was
in the very first one.
So that was Frequency.
He was talking about how the
folks from Sony were helping
them run their focus groups.
And they did two tests and one
of the tests was, after they
played the game, they did a
survey of how many people were
planning on buying this
when it came out.
And they had a particularly
high score, like 80% or
something like that, like the
highest survey I've ever seen.
But they also did a survey of
how many people were planning
on buying the game just by
looking at the box before they
had played the game.
And that was a particularly
low number.
And the Sony people called
it, said this is
not going to sell.
Because, sure, the people who
played their game are going to
enjoy the game.
But no one's going to play the
game in the first place
because people can't figure out
what your game's about.
And they tried to address those
problems with the sequel.
That's one thing which
[? Brenda ?] talks about, your
chance to do a do over, a chance
for you to go back and
fix the problems that you
found in the first one,
especially when you find
those problems really
close to ship date.
There's nothing you can do about
the first time around.
But if you're lucky, you get
a second chance to do it.
SARAH: I also noticed that
Frequency was not called in,
or rather, it wasn't
Frequency II.
GUEST SPEAKER: There
was a Frequency II.
They called it Amplitude.
So it was actually kind of a
reboot as well because they
kind of just wanted people, OK,
let's pretend Frequency
didn't happen and
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And we'll make sure that our
Frequency people who loved the
game know what it is.
SARAH: Ahead of time.
It's much easier to tell the
small base who liked you, oh
yeah, and buy this game, than it
is to tell a large group of
people who weren't interested
the first time, no, no, you
didn't like it the first time,
but trust us, you'll
like it this time.
GUEST SPEAKER: I've seen a
couple of companies do
effectively Gold versions every
time they move to a new
platform, like the latest
platform which they release it
on tends to become the
definitive version that, if
you're a big fan of the
franchise and you're willing
to buy this game multiple times,
you want to get that
because of the few extra
features that they've put in.
Maybe it's different endings.
Maybe it's upgraded cutscenes.
If it's a role playing game
I see that a lot.
Maybe they redid the cutscenes
from scratch or redid the
audio from scratch.
So it's the same assets but
they're higher resolution.
And, of course, you have games
that started out there like
this online flash games and
stuff like that and then
you've got to move
them to other
platforms like DS or PSP.
And those games tend to have not
only completely reworked
controls because the controls
are different but also a lot
more features because you have
to now justify to people who
may have loved the game but
didn't pay any money for the
first version to actually put
down money for it now.
So [? N ?] is a good
example of that.
There's a game that came
out by [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and the DS and PSP what
started life as
a free flash game.
And lots of people loved it.
But lots of people didn't have
to pay any money for their
first version.
So how much do you love it is
kind of a weird factor.
I guess we should start
with the games.