The following content is
provided by MIT OpenCourseWare
under a Creative
Commons license.
Additional information
about our license and MIT
OpenCourseWare in general is
available at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Handout
for today's lecture.
And you'll get a sheet that
asks you about your preferences
for recitation time.
For the moment, that's the
critical piece of paper.
What you want to do is, if you
are -- well whoever you are,
get your name on their, your ID
number, I don't remember,
it probably asks for
your email address.
It does not ask for your year.
Please put that, and also
put down if you're a
BCS Course Nine major.
We will attempt to lottery
into the class as many
of you as we can.
And we will do that,
basically, today.
And you'll get an email from
us telling you whether you
are in the class or not.
I will take care of all those
add-drop cards then next
Tuesday when we meet again.
How many people here are here
without being lotteried in,
just to give me a feeling for?
Well, all right how many
people are lotteried in?
How many people don't think
they know what that means?
OK, good.
Well, we'll see what we can do.
We will try to squeeze as
many of you in as we can.
Those of you who are not
lotteried in, do not check
the little box that says,
I was lotteried in.
Because we can check and if you
a nasty lying person, we don't
want you in this class and we
will do bad things to
you or something.
Let me see.
What, yes --
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: OK.
Let's do it that way.
Who still needs a syllabus?
OK.
Oh, I see we have a new
improvement this year.
Last year they didn't have a
cool digital clock there.
OK.
Who still needs a
writing assignment?
I'm just trying to see
which, who still needs
a writing assignment?
It's the one that says
writing assignments on it.
All right.
So they're scattered
around randomly, too.
I don't understand
how this is working.
But I'm sure it's
working somehow.
I need a Handout 1 by the way,
when somebody has a Handout 1.
No, I've read the syllabus.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Well, here, you just
got deputized.
Who still needs the cool
TA signup, recitation
signup sheet?
This lovely person
will help you.
Up there somewhere.
If you're just coming in, come
down here and collect handouts.
Somebody please deliver me
enough handouts so we can
give people handouts.
There's the handout
for today's lecture.
There are four things
altogether, sit around until
the other two show up.
All right, these
are the other two.
All right let's try
this game again.
Who's still looking
for a syllabus.
A couple of syllabi, out in
the cheap seats back there.
And a few over there.
OK, who still needs the
writing assignments?
We need some writing
assignments down front.
And who still needs the
recitation signup sheet?
That's the critical one.
Recitation signup sheet,
who's got those?
OK.
Once you've got
stuff, you can go.
Leave me all the extras.
At this point, if you don't
have one of the handouts,
pick it up later.
Unless you're still missing
the recitation signup sheet.
None of the other stuff
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
OK.
Is there anybody who still
needs the recitation sheet?
No, OK, good.
So, name, ID, email, year.
Whether or not
you're a BCS major.
Pick your top four choices.
Number them one, two, three,
and four, because we'll try to
put you in your first choice.
And tell us whether you're a
winner in the Haas lottery.
There will be handouts,
typically, in each lecture.
Typically they will be there
and there when you come in.
And, remember the there part.
Because when 300 people
all try to get it there,
it's kind of a pain.
So either side in the front.
How many people need more
time with this exciting
recitation sheet?
We want it now.
We want it instantly, because
we're going to solve the
problem of recitations.
Actually, I suppose we don't
have to solve it before the
end of class this way, do we?
But we might as well, while
we've got everybody here.
So do that now.
And while people are playing
with that, I will entertain any
other entertaining questions
about the course that
are on people's minds.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Is the fifth
edition book OK?
You can use the fifth edition.
We're on to the sixth edition.
You can use the fifth edition
as long as you don't come and
complain if you get the
question wrong on the final
because the info happens to
have been in the sixth edition.
Basically, you're not
going to flunk the course
using the fifth edition.
It's not going to
be a big issue.
But it's a dealer's choice.
You do it at your own risk.
The risk is smallish.
You can decide if it trades
off sufficiently with
the money involved.
I like the first
edition best, myself.
I think it's all been
downhill since then.
But I wouldn't use the first
edition at this point.
Anything else that I should
be answering about the
course while people are
playing with forms?
Yes.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: It's an hour.
Once a week.
At a time that you are
currently determining
for yourself with luck.
OK.
Time for another round
of polling here.
How many people still would
like more time to play
with this exciting form?
I will take the opportunity, at
least I will try to take the
opportunity, depends if I can
find the opportunity This
is a Hass-D course.
Your writing papers.
Some of you know that
that's hard work for you.
Some of you will discover that
you and your TA disagree about
your talents in writing.
In either case, you may want to
avail yourself of the fact that
we have three writing tutors
attached to this course.
They're good, they
do great stuff.
At least your predecessors
have told me so.
And it is my belief that
two of them were going
to be here today.
Oh yes, look at that.
There they are.
I couldn't tell, they looked
so young like undergraduates.
Why don't you
introduce yourselves?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: When you read the
syllabus, you will discover
useful things like their
names, again, and
their email contacts.
And also useful thoughts like,
3 am the day before it's due is
not the time you want to send a
panicked note saying, I can't
get started on my paper.
Think about it ahead of time
and they will be useful.
Also useful to you will be, we
will have a series of workshops
in the library for how to do
research for these
sorts of papers.
And details about that will
emerge later on in the term.
But I would strongly encourage
people to go to one
of those sessions.
Because doing research for
college-level papers in a
course like this is different
than what you did in high
school, probably, and it's
certainly different than
feeding the keywords for
whatever topic you're writing
about into Google and
calling it a day.
You laugh, but some people
did that last year.
It was not a pleasant sight.
OK.
I think that people are
done with this exciting
form, don't you?
She wants them passed
to the center aisle.
It's very bad form to
rip up the paper of
the guy next to you.
OK, are there any of those
forms still out there?
All right.
Now that we've done the really
exciting part, let's try
saying something about
what this course is about.
And why you bothered to try to
get yourself lotteried in.
Many, many, many many
-- any other forms?
Last chance.
Many many, many many MIT
courses are of the form, so
when you go to the first
class you get the syllabus.
You look at the list of topics.
You say, I don't know anything
about these topics but I sure
hope that by the end of the
course I know something
about these topics.
And Intro Psych class is
different from that.
Because if you take a look at
the list of topics in the
course, which you can find by
the way on the back page of the
syllabus but you don't need to
go looking for it right now,
you will discover memory,
learning, cognition, emotion,
personality, intelligence, a
whole set of topics that you
already have some notion about.
They're terms that you
use in everyday speech.
That you can converse
about perfectly happily.
The job of this course is to
dig behind the, what you
would know in what's
known as folk psychology.
Folk psychology is a term
coined in the 19th century
to refer to the psychology
that folk know.
As opposed to the psychology
that one would learn in the
academy, like you are here.
What we used to say, actually,
when the term was defined for
me in graduate school, I think
somebody said, folk psychology,
that's the psychology that
your grandmother knows.
That doesn't work so well.
Because your grandmother
may well have a Ph.D in
psychology these days.
Folk psychology is what the
psychology that you would
know without bothering to
take a course like this.
The psychology you just
pick up on the street.
This course is designed
to go beyond that.
Well, let me dig up an example.
Let me close the door.
And so, as an example, I
could assert oh, let's
see, I need a person.
Well, this is why one
sits in the front.
You're a person.
That's very good.
What's your name?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: You're Mark.
OK.
Who is that woman
sitting next to you?
This is Laura.
OK.
I could say that
Mark loves Laura.
It may or may not be true.
For all I know,
Mark, it is true.
Well, this is going to
be a more interesting
example then sometimes.
But, all right.
If I assert that Mark loves
Laura without much knowledge of
either Mark or Laura here, you
had -- that's not a sentence
that's hard for you
to understand.
But what is it that we're
actually talking about?
So, all right, what's love?
I think, I didn't check, I was
going to check this morning
but I didn't check.
I think that probably the line
you would get in a dictionary
would assert that love is an
emotion, and then it would go
on to describe what kind
of an emotion it is.
But it's an odd emotion
if it is an emotion.
If you think about other
emotions that are pretty
straightforward.
Let's say, sadness or
happiness to give two
straightforward examples.
You know what sadness and
happiness feel like.
They have a distinctive
feeling to them
There is a distinctive
feeling to being in love.
There's no doubt that
there's a feeling.
It's actually an interesting
question why we use the same
word feeling to talk about
feeling in love, and
feeling the table.
What's the commonality there?
But the feeling of being in
love is not simple in the same
way that the feeling of sadness
of the feeling of happiness is.
For instance, you can be
sad or happy in love.
You can be in love and the
experience of that could
be either sad or happy.
The experience of being
sad cannot be either
sad or -- sad is sad.
It's, in some sense, an atomic
sensation in a way that
love does not appear to be.
You can wake up in the
morning feeling sad.
Disembodied sort of sadness.
Or disembodied sort
of happiness.
You can't really, it's hard to
imagine what it would be to
wake up and say I feel love.
It's not clear that that makes
sort of a quasi-religious sense
that you could get to it.
I feel love for the
whole universe, or
something like that.
It's lovely, but, you
see the distinction.
So maybe it's not an emotion
in the simple sense that
sadness or happiness is.
Maybe it's a way of thinking
about your current state.
You know, I feel happy and my
heart is pounding and I'm
sitting next to, oh God I've
forgotten her name already.
Laura.
Lara.
No U.
L-A-R-A Lara.
And Mark.
They both have two
letters in common.
That's the basis for
this relationship.
Anyway, where was I?
You're not going to wake
up feeling a disembodied
sense of love.
Maybe maybe what it is is
a thought the state that
you are currently in.
So maybe it's a cognition
rather than an emotion.
But if it's a cognition it's a
different kind of combination
from what you might think
of as, sort of, an
atomic cognition.
Because it has this
aspect of feeling to it.
That that cognitions don't,
what's the, capital
of Equatorial Guinea.
I have no idea.
But it's a thought that, I
can think about that fact.
It doesn't carry with it any
deep feeling unless it turns
out to be a question
on the final exam.
But you can have thoughts
that aren't colored in this
emotional kind of a way.
So it's not a simple cognition.
It might be more useful to
call it a motivation than
to call it an emotion.
Motivations are like emotions
in the sense that having this
affective, affect is the sort
of jargony term for feeling,
this affective component to it.
But the sorts of things that
get talked about as motivations
are things like thirst.
So, it being warm, I'm thirsty.
That's a faintly unpleasant
state and a motivation is
something that motivates me
to do something to
change my state.
And hunger is another
good example.
So what kind of motivation
would love be?
Love might be a motivation
that it's directed to
an object of some sort.
And, I probably shouldn't have
caught that cold from the
third-grader in my house.
That's better.
It's a motivation that, if love
is a motivation, what it's
motivating you to do is to
perhaps get closer, to possess
the object of desire.
Now Mark and Lara are busy
sitting there saying, oh boy,
that doesn't sound so good.
But love, of course, can
be used not just in the
Mark and Lara sense.
But you can love your laptop
or something like that.
And have, we won't go
there, Mark, it's OK.
But those are two clearly
different senses of love.
Or, at least your chortling
suggests that you think of
them in different senses.
You might ask what love is for.
And the motive, if thirst is
a motivation, it's because
you need liquid in
order to be alive.
If you don't drink stuff
you're going to be dead.
What's love for?
Well, the usual answers to
that, these days in psychology,
would come out of the chunk of
psychology that's called
evolutionary psychology.
That sees these core
motivations, if you like, as
things that evolved over the
history of the species and of
life in general, to
serve useful purposes
for the organism.
In this case, love is
presumably in service of that
great evolutionary good which
is to get your genes into
the next generation.
That your goal, if you're a
thoroughgoing evolutionary
psychologist, your goal in life
basically is to get genes into
the next generation to
perpetuate your genes.
And the sex and reproduction
thing is a good way to do that.
It's not the only way to do
that, it's important to note.
How many of you are
only children?
Well, actually, let's go
at it the other way.
How many of you have siblings?
OK.
One way for you to gain this
sort of evolutionary
immortality of getting your
genes into the next
generation is to be a really
good aunt or uncle.
You protect and preserve that
little niece or nephew of
yours, and they're carrying a
bundle of your genes, too.
So it's not that having and
raising children is the only
evolutionary route
to the future.
But it is a good one.
And the love of business would
seem to be related to that.
But it's not necessary.
If you think about it,
well, all right spider.
Let's think of spiders.
Spiders, the reproduction thing
works fine with spiders.
It's not clear how much
love and romance there
is involved here.
It's not clear for a
couple of reasons.
One of them is, it's very
unclear what's going on in the
mind of an animal in general.
You just don't have any access.
In fact, or at least, you
have only the barest
of influential access.
In fact, I don't have any
access to what's going
on inside your mind.
It is an assumption on my
part that you guys have
mental lives like mine.
You could be what the
philosophers, what is, in
philosopher jargon, you
could all be zombies.
Which, if you're doing
philosophy means, you're things
that look human, behave like
they're human, but aren't human
because there's nothing
happening in there.
There's no, you could be
cunningly designed machines.
I don't know that, but it's
a useful assumption that
your mental life and my
mental are the similar.
It is not a terribly useful
assumption that my mental
life and a spider's
mental life are similar.
And in any case, if you look at
spider behavior, it doesn't
look much like romantic love.
I mean, the guy spends most of
his time trying to avoid being
killed by the female spider,
who is typically much bigger.
He does a variety of
courtships, we'll talk about
this later in the term, but I
cannot resist, there are
variety of spider species where
the spider does engage in a lot
of courtship behavior.
The male spider, he
brings her presents.
Like, he brings her a dead fly.
The reason he brings her a dead
fly is that she's busy chowing
down on the dead fly, she
doesn't bite his
little head off.
And it's not
desperately romantic.
But, in any case, it does
work perfectly well
for reproduction.
It suggests that there might
be, even when you're talking
about love between potential
mates, that there might be a
distinction to be made between
love and, well, lust or some
sort of sex drive or
something like that.
There is evidence at a
neurochemical level that
these are distinct.
The chemical pathways in the
brain that are involved in
romantic love seem to be those
that are also involved in
parent-child bonds
of attachment.
They involve chemicals like,
well, your brain generates
opioid chemicals, which are
like opium, which is why opium
is a powerful drug when taken
externally, taken from
the from the outside.
But in any case, the bonds of
love involve those chemicals.
The bonds of lust involve
things like testosterone and
other androgens and estrogens
that they may have talked
about in endless length
in high school biology or
something of that sort.
But there's evidence that
these are separate.
How did they come together?
Well, evolutionary
psychologists suggested the
link might be that if you bring
love to bear, this romantic
bonding, this attachment to
bear, then you've got pairs of
people who stick around.
Stick to each other in ways
that are good for the begetting
and raising of children.
And that maybe this bonding
between parent and child got
co-opted into being
romantic love.
Between potential mates.
Another way of putting it would
be to say, well, maybe romantic
love exists because
straight-out, just regular old
lust, is not compatible
with civilization.
If people are just simply
acting on their evolutionarily
based desire to mate, it's
hard to run a civilization.
It's hard to run a university,
for instance, because
people are busy.
So what you've got to do, what
you've got to do, is, if you're
going to run a civilization you
have to find some way to
channel that sex drive into
other activities so that the
rest of civilization
can keep going.
Now, if you start talking in
those terms, you're talking in
terms that you will see are
very much like what Freud said.
Freud argued that things like
romantic love are necessary in
order to have a civilization.
In the absence of, if
you're a spider you don't
need romantic love.
But you're also not going to
have, spider civilization
is somewhat more limited.
Now, how does Lara know
that Mark loves her?
Well, he said so.
Right?
Well, that's cool.
I can say so, too.
Right?
I love you.
I might even sort of, kind
of, mean it in this sort
of generic, I love all of
humanity kind of sense.
But it's obviously different.
Now, there are various other
ways that he can be indicating
the fact that he is
in love with her.
But she's got to
figure this out.
Is he really in love with me,
or is he just kind of, actually
he's got to figure it out too.
Am I really in love with her?
Her active perception is, it
would be perfectly possible
for her to be wrong.
She looks at him, she thinks,
he's in love with me.
And he's thinking, I'm not in
love with her, I'm just faking.
Could be.
Now, could it go the other way?
Could he be thinking,
I'm in love with her,
and it not be true?
Is that logically possible?
Now, and who can tell you
that it wasn't true?
Your mother?
You don't really love her.
Well, you probably wouldn't
buy that any more.
But you would have once.
If you plot, let's see, how
are we going to do this?
All right.
Well, this is age.
I know this axis is age.
So if you plot the percentage
of people who say, you
ask kids, who knows your
inner emotions the best?
You or, give an open-ended
question but the real
categories are you
or Mom and Dad.
It turns out, so, if this is
you and this is Mom and Dad,
that function crosses the 50%
point at the surprisingly late
age of early adolescence.
Before that, the majority of
kids will assert that Mom and
Dad know their emotions better
than they themselves know it.
How could that be the case?
Well, it's hard to get yourself
back into that mental
state at this point.
It gets easier again once you
have kids of your own, because
you're looking at your kid.
And you're, like, your
four year old kid.
And your kids doing, and you
say, gotta go to the bathroom.
No, I don't gotta go
to the bathroom.
You gotta go to the bathroom.
Nuh-uh, I don't have to
go to the bathroom.
You sure you don't have
to go to the bathroom?
No, no, OK, I guess you don't
have to go to the bathroom,
let's all get in the car.
I've got to go to the bathroom.
And so, if the kid is a little
self-reflective he thinks, hey,
wait a minute, first of all not
only do I have to go to the
bathroom, but you know Mom and
Dad, they, like, knew
that before I did.
That's cool.
That's also a little scary
because I thought a whole
bunch of other things.
I wonder if they know
those things too.
Eventually, you figure out, no,
they didn't know that stuff.
Which is just as well
for all concerned.
But returning to the love
example the point is
that you need to know.
You need to perform an
active perception to decide
somebody else loves you.
And you need to do an active
sort of self-perception to
decide that you love
somebody else.
You might also ask yourself
at that point, well, what
is it that you love?
Physical attributes?
That's considered
sort of crass.
And even worse would be to
say, I love her for her
money and possessions.
That sounds terrible.
But if you ask yourself, what
are you watching on TV, there's
a continuous pairing of love,
sex, and cars, soda,
anything, right?
Well, I can't think of any
particular ads at the
moment because I don't
watch enough TV.
I'll ask my kids if there
are any good sex and soda
ads on at the moment.
But there certainly have been.
In any case, typically,
we say things like, I
love her for her mind.
Or something like that.
Now, you could love your
laptop for its mind, too.
It doesn't seem to be
quite the same thing.
Now, all right.
So, the question of what it
is that you might love.
Where is that love, if in you?
Does that question make
any sort of sense?
Well, there's a traditional
answer to that.
If you asked where love lives,
the sort of conventional,
out-there in several hundred
years ago, probably
would be simpler.
Kind of answer would be, heart?
Well, yeah.
Liver is good too but that's
only if you're, the cool white
virgin snows upon my heart have
abated the ardor of my liver,
says the prince guy in
Shakespeare's Tempest.
There's this notion, very
much a folk psychological
notion, that emotions are
resident in the viscera.
And that makes a
degree of sense.
Because, when you see the
object of your heart's desire,
you know it's your heart's
desire because your heart
goes thump, thump, thump.
Right?
Now, you think that if love is
localized, if there is some
chunk of you that is your love
for whoever this significant
other might be, where's
that likely to be?
Brain, somebody
muttered up there.
Yeah, it's probably
in your brain.
You can imagine why that was
a hard notion to come by.
Because you look at the object
of your desire and you don't
suddenly say, aah, my head.
And you probably won't
be sending brain-shaped
chocolates to anybody at
Valentine's Day either.
But it is an interesting
question to ask, whether or
not, all right brain maybe.
Is it localized enough that
there's some little piece of
brain that we could go to
and say, Mark's love
for Lara is there.
And if we went in and pulled
that board out of his computer,
that he'd know who Lara was, he
knew everything else, they just
wouldn't be in love any more.
Is that level of
localization plausible?
Is the love normal?
Is his love, Mark loves
Lara for her mind.
Is that normal?
Suppose he loved
her for her foot?
Would that be normal?
What's the difference?
Why would one be -- and if it
wasn't normal, who gets to
decide that it's normal?
Do we, as a community,
get to decide?
Does the family get to decide?
Is there some objective way
to decide whether something
is or is not normal?
And if it's not normal, what
do we get to do about it?
Do we get to, if it's not
normal, would drugs fix it?
Would surgery fix it?
Would some sort of
therapy fix it?
You can see what's
going on here.
From a simple sort of statement
like, you know, Mark loves
Lara, we can get to,
essentially, any of the topics
that will show up in
a course like this.
And you could have done, we
wouldn't have had to use love
as the particular example.
Behind any of these things that
we use perfectly comfortably in
everyday life is a large set of
very interesting questions,
only a very few of which, of
course, I can manage to address
in an introductory-level
course.
But the goal here would be to
give you some sort of overview
of the sorts of topics and the
sorts of answers that modern
academic psychology
has come up with.
The way that we do that
is through lectures.
Through recitations,
which should not be
treated as optional.
We expect you to be there.
They're not just like reviews
for the exam, or there are no
problems in an introductory
psych class the way there would
be in chemistry or something.
you're expected to be there.
They're an integral
part of the course.
And there's the textbook.
It's a good idea to look at it.
I won't go into a lot
more detail about the
mechanics of the course.
The syllabus will tell you most
of what you want to know.
And it's a really good idea to
actually take a look at the
syllabus and to take a look
at the writing assignments.
Because they have due dates
attached to them, and
things like that.
I will answer any blazingly
mechanical questions about the
course, if they have occurred
to anybody at the moment.
Otherwise I will plunge into
the brain in a moment.
After satisfying my first
motivation yet more.
OK, let me say that the sort of
ideological grounding of this
course is that the course, like
academic psychology generally,
is materialist in its ideology.
What does that mean?
What that means is that the
mind is what the brain does.
And that if you have thoughts,
if you have feelings.
If you have memories,
that these things arise
out of the brain.
This is not to say they're
necessarily, if we wanted to
teach a straight neuroscience
course we'd just teach
you about the brain.
But it is to say that it is in
distinction to another old
philosophical position.
Which is dualism.
Which says that the mind
is somehow an immaterial
something that is
separate from the brain.
It interacts with you, it
interacts with your body,
but it is separate.
The reason for talking about
the brain for this lecture and
a chunk of the next lecture is
this notion that the mind
is what the brain does.
And, well, if we want
to find out what the
brain does, let's see.
We could make a little
bit of a list here.
You go up.
Gotta get rid of a little
more of whatever that was.
So, do I have a copy of the
handout here somewhere?
Yes.
OK.
So I can ask because it just
has for broad classes of
methods on the handout,
without describing them.
How might we go about finding
out what the brain does?
Oh, this reminds me to say,
anytime during the course of
the term, if you've got a
question, comment, or whatever,
feel free to raise your hand.
And I will attempt
to answer it.
If I think we're being
hopelessly you diverted from
where I think we need to get
in the lecture, I may have
to cut off discussion.
But I'm more than happy
to have the opportunity.
So don't, just because it's a
great big lecture, don't feel
that you've just got to sit
there and not do anything
interactive like
raise your hand.
Of course, if you raise your
hand you might end up exposing
the details of your romantic
engagements with the person
sitting next to you, but that's
a risk you have to take.
Anyway.
If you wanted to find out how
the brain worked, what the
brain did, how could we
go about doing that?
Anybody got -- Yes?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: You could cut the
brain open and look at it.
OK, that's Option 0
on my list of 1-4.
Not because it's trivial in any
sense, but I'm looking for
techniques that get more at the
function than at the structure.
But there is a certain amount
that you do learn from just
looking at the structure.
In, fact, Descartes, one of the
founders of the dualist view,
looked at the anatomy of the
brain, thought, if the
immaterial mind and soul are
interacting with the brain,
well, the brain is a
double structure, right?
It's got these two, sort of,
symmetrical hemispheres.
That interaction between the
immaterial soul and the
body must be at one point.
He looked at the anatomy, saw
the pineal gland, which is a
piece of brain lying on the
mid-line and thought, because
there's only one of those,
that must be the point.
So, you can make inferences
from structure alone.
That particular inference is
wrong, but you could do it.
Yes, the person in front there.
Yes, you.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: OK, MRI.
We will make that into
the larger category of
imaging techniques.
For psych purposes, the most
dramatic version of this is
so-called FMRI, for Functional
Magnetic Resonance Imaging.
This is the new entry
on the list, really.
Remarkable breakthrough in the
time that I've been teaching
this course is the ability to
now look at the structure and
some aspects of the function of
the brain in intact, you know,
a wide awake human beings.
You simply couldn't
do that any more.
And that's a remarkable --
well, it's a remarkable boom
for psychology and a huge
advance for medicine.
So, for instance, if
you had a brain tumor.
There are symptoms of
having a brain tumor.
But the only way to find out
if you actually had a tumor,
because you want to take this
tumor out if you could, the
only way to find out, a
generation ago was to do
exploratory surgery.
And open up the brain and
see where the thing was.
Now you'd be in an MR scanner
by the end of the day.
And we'd know.
So, yes, very useful technique.
You're going to offer
me another one?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: OK.
So we'll put this under
the category of lesions.
Brain damage.
If this is the newest, this
is probably the oldest
of the basic techniques.
If you damage brains in
the same way, you end up
getting symptoms that are
similar across people.
And even across species,
in many cases.
And that is a tipoff that,
first of all, the brain
has something to do
with mental life.
And that specific bits of brain
have specific things to do with
specific aspects
of mental life.
The real advances in this sort
of research, and this sort of
understanding of the brain,
came, I guess, mid- to late
nineteenth century, with
advances both in medicine and
in, I suppose, what you could
call military technology.
In earlier times, if you got a
penetrating wound to the brain,
odds were that you were
simply going to be dead.
But by the mid- to late
nineteenth century, people were
surviving with penetrating
brain injuries.
And it became clear -- and
bullets could be leaving
comparatively small lesions.
And so it became increasingly
clear that different bits
of brain damage did
different things.
Let me find myself a place to
draw another picture here.
I need a brain.
So, here we go.
One quick, this is your brain.
Just to orient things here.
OK, so.
Front, back, bottom, top.
If I'm facing that way, this
would be looking at the outside
surface of the left hemisphere.
You've got two cerebral
hemispheres, about this size,
stuck inside your head.
The brain's got
lots of wrinkles.
There are a couple of large
ones that I'm drawing
here for my purposes.
Because the cerebral
hemispheres are conventionally
divided up into four lobes.
The terms for which are written
on the handouts, so I will just
give you the initials rather
than writing out
the whole thing.
Conveniently, the frontal
lobe is at the front.
After that, you just simply
have to learn them.
Temporal lobe down
at the bottom.
Occipital lobe at the back.
And the parietal lobe on the
other side of this big central
sulcus that divides the frontal
from the parietal lobe.
What was found, I think
originally in the
Franco-Prussian War,
if memory serves.
1870s, was that if you got
lesions to the back of the
brain here, to the cortex,
the wrinkled outside
surface is known as cortex.
That's from the Latin
word for cork.
Which is what anatomists
thought it looked like.
If you get lesions back
here, you get problems
with your vision.
Very specifically.
And, if you got a great big
lesion that took out the entire
occipital cortex on both sides,
you'd be functionally blind.
But if you got a small lesion,
let's say in the left
hemisphere, you would have a
small region of blindness.
And it would always be on the
right side of the visual world.
And that's relative to where
you're actually looking.
Fixating at the moment.
So, if I fixate on this guy
there, who I'm now staring at,
then if I had a lesion in my
left hemisphere some region
out here, I would be blind.
If the lesion was in my right
hemisphere the blind region
would be on the opposite
side, on the left.
That's the sort of thing
that you could discover
from lesion studies.
And so, lesions happen when you
get brain injury from a bullet.
Lesions happen from strokes.
One of the great advantages to
imaging technologies is that in
the 1870s, or even until quite
recently, the only way you knew
about where the lesion exactly
was, was if the patient
died and came to autopsy.
You could look at the brain,
and look at what was damaged.
Now you can look at that brain
in an intact individual and see
where the damage might be.
So, damage to the brain can
tell you something about.
It's got the drawback that
you're trying to infer normal
function from an abnormal
brain at that point.
And that's not perfectly
straightforward.
But it does provide, and is
perhaps the oldest technique
for providing lots
of information.
Yes, you were about to
give me another method?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: OK, behavior
is item, that's 0, than
behavior is going to be 5.
And we'll spend an awful
lot of the course talking
about behavioral measures.
But in behavior, without going
in and doing something with the
tissue of the brain, you're
essentially treating the
brain as a black box.
At that point.
It may tell you something
about the brain in connection
with the rest of this.
But we're looking for
techniques that are
specifically about
studying brain itself.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: [? Wake ?]
surgery?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: This
just sounds cool.
Keep going on.
What did you have in --
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: What's
the surgery part?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: I'm just trying to
see if there's a 6 here that
I'm just not thinking of.
That would be cool.
Otherwise I can sort of --
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Oh yeah, actually.
That's one I didn't
put in, typically.
Which is that you can go and
start infusing stuff into,
chemicals into, the brain.
And changing behavior.
Do I want to say anything more
about that at the moment?
Good, I'll use that one.
Thank you.
We'll call this
stimulation in general.
Stimulation.
You can go in and
stimulate brain.
So, I was going to do that
and segue from the chemical
stimulation to electrical
stimulation, but you
got there for me.
You can go in and stimulate the
brain electrically in rats.
But you can also do
this in humans.
In fact, so back in the 1950s,
Wilder Penfield, psychologist
who's working with some
neurosurgeons up in Montreal.
And what they were doing was,
they were doing neurosurgery
on patients with
intractable epilepsy.
Epilepsy is an electrical storm
in the brain, basically.
And often is started by a piece
of abnormal or damaged tissue
that acts as a generator.
And then what happens is a sort
of an abnormal electrical
activity spreads from that
point of generation across the
brain or across some
chunk of the brain.
And causes a seizure or
lapse of awareness.
The sort of symptoms that
you get in epilepsy.
Often, this is
controllable by drugs.
But in some cases it's not.
And one of the treatments that
can be tried is to go in
and try to lesion this
little chunk of brain.
If you take out the generator
you can often reduce the
severity or eliminate
the seizures.
But if you're going to take
brain tissue out, you
gotta be really careful.
Because, well, actually
where I put this is a
pretty good example.
We knew from lesion studies
going back, again, into the
nineteenth century, that areas
around here that go by names
like Broca and Wernicke's area,
which are the names of 19th
century neurologists, actually.
Vitally important in
the production and
understanding of language.
If you are right-handed, those
areas exist in the left
hemisphere of the brain.
So this is a left
hemisphere the brain.
That'll work fine.
And if they're damaged by
stroke, you will have trouble
with understanding language or
producing language, or both.
Depends on the exact
nature of the.
Stroke But very bad
lesions to have.
So, if you were to discover
that the epileptogenic focus,
the piece of bad tissue, was
sitting in there, you would
say, look, I'm sorry.
We don't want to
do this surgery.
Because while I could perhaps
reduce the frequency of your
seizures, it's going to
mean that you've got real
problems with language.
And that tradeoff
is not worth it.
On the other hand, if the
generator was here, I can
reduce the frequency
of your seizures.
And you'll have a relatively
small area of blindness out
in the right visual
field somewhere.
Say, look, I'm not thrilled
about being blind in some
part of my visual field.
But that tradeoff is worth it.
So you need to know where you
are in the brain in order
to do this sort of surgery.
And what Penfield did was
to stimulate the brain
of awake individuals.
In effect, to ask, what's
this bit of brain doing.
Now, how can you do that?
Doesn't that kind
of hurt a lot?
The answer is that they're
under local anesthetic to get
through the skull and the outer
surface, the membranes across
the surface of the brain.
Because, in case you hadn't
noticed, digging holes with
a sharp stick in your
skull really hurts.
But once you get to brain,
there are no pain receptors
in the brain itself.
There's nothing.
Once you've got the brain
exposed, you can do anything
you want to the brain.
And the brain won't
particularly complain.
I don't suggest you try this.
But you could.
Now, let's step back.
Why have pain receptors at all?
What's pain good for?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Pain's there to keep
you from hurting yourself.
If you don't have pain, and
your hand's on the hot stove,
you say, oh, I'm cooking my
hand that's no big deal.
In fact, there rare cases of
people who are congenitally
insensitive to pain.
And it's bad news.
They end up injuring
themselves.
That being the case, why
not have pain receptors
in your Brain Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Yeah by the time
-- if you're thinking in
evolutionary terms, by the time
the bear is chewing on your
brain, you might as well just
kind of go with the experience.
Because it's not going
to matter much.
So, the advantage here is
that you can go in and
stimulate brain tissue.
And it's a somewhat, from
the sound of it, somewhat
uncanny experience.
But it's not an
unpleasant experience.
And so, all right, so what
Penfield did, stick a little
electrode, say, here.
And put a little
electrical current there.
And what the patient would
report, if it was here, this
is to the parietal side of
this big central sulcus.
What the patient would
report is is, it feels like
you're touching my foot.
OK.
Move the electrode
a little bit.
OK, now it feels like you're
sort of touching me in
the middle of my back.
Now it feels like you're
touching my hand.
It's the end of my nose.
And what Penfield found was
that the surface of the body
was laid out across the
surface of the brain.
And the left hemisphere would
actually be the surface of
the right side of the body.
I don't know what that is
And it is feet up, head
down, as I recall.
But that chunk of brain which
is called somatosensory cortex,
the term's on the handout
somewhere, represents the
sensations coming
from the skin.
Now, I haven't drawn a terribly
realistic picture here.
But the actual map is
hugely distorted.
yes?
Is something -- OK.
I'll do that.
Pay no attention to the
man behind the curtain.
Anyway.
So this map, known as
the homunculus, for the
little man in the head.
The sensory homunculus,
specifically.
It's massively distorted.
Some chunks of your skin are
heavily over-represented
in the brain.
Some are heavily
underrepresented.
So what's over-represented?
Hands.
And?
Face.
And on the face.
Lips.
Lips and tongue and
things like that.
So, somewhere in Gleitman, a
chapter you'll read tonight
with luck, there's a picture.
People love making little
models of the homunculus.
So you project it back out into
the world, and what would
it look like if this
was a 1:1 mapping.
And you get this guy with you
huge lips and huge hands,
and a little tiny back.
And the way to get a feeling
for this is to ask yourself, if
you were trying to figure out
what something felt like, how
would you go about doing that?
Well, you would go and
explore it with your hands.
A little kid, less restrained
than you, would also probably
put it in its mouth
and feel it that way.
What would you wouldn't do is
rub it against your back,
or something like that.
Because it's the hands and the
lips and stuff that have the
very dense sensory
skin receptors.
And it's sparser on your back.
Now, you will also, you can
test the prudery already of
your introductory psych text
by checking out whether the
homunculus is anatomically lee.
Correct The genitalia are
well represented in the
sensory homunculus also.
My recollection is that they
are well represented in
Gleitman there are texts where
it's kind of -- Actually,
there's one great version where
the homunculus is wearing,
like, a little towel.
I've seen that once.
That was cute.
So stimulate here and the
person feels like you're
touching them on their skin.
If you go around to the right
hemisphere, they'd feel
the stimulation down the
left side of the body.
Go to the other side of this,
into the frontal lobe, and
instead of saying, oh, I feel
like you're touching my
leg, the leg would twitch.
Left hemisphere, right leg.
You move a little further
the arm would twitch.
Or just one muscle in the
arm, or something like that.
Here you've got a motor
homunculus, laid out
across the motor cortex.
And this chunk of the brain is
important in the generation
of voluntary movements.
Again, it's a distorted map.
Hands, very over-represented.
If you're a monkey, feet
are very over-represented.
But you, who cannot hang upside
down from a tree by your feet
or your tail or whatever, your
feet are comparatively
impoverished in their
representation.
Tongue and vocal apparatus,
heavily over-represented.
So, same sort of story.
Sensory and motor.
Now, these days, you don't even
need to go and cut open the
skull to do this sort of thing.
Transcranial magnetic
stimulation, or TMS, for short,
involves generating a large
magnetic field close
to the skull.
As your physics background
will tell you, that generates
an electrical field.
If you shape the magnetic field
right, you can generate an
electrical field in
the brain tissue.
And, basically, produce the
same sort of brain stimulation
that Penfield was producing
in an open skull.
With the same results.
Nancy Kanwisher, who's a
professor in the department
here, used to be up at Harvard.
Got on the front of the Harvard
Gazette for teaching her intro
class with a TMS simulator in
hand and say, want to see
where my motor cortex is?
Pow.
No, I'm not going
to do that, sorry.
The reason I'm not going
to do that, by the
way, is I'm a chicken.
TMS is almost undoubtedly safe.
Lots of people do it.
But it sounds too much like
things that I learned about
when I was taking intro psych,
that were used to generate
epileptic foci in rats.
Let's stimulate, pow, pow,
pow, pow, and now the
rat's got epilepsy.
It doesn't seem to happen
in TMS, but I'm a chicken.
When it comes to my brain.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Well, we'll find out
if I can spell homunculus.
Paul, is it a U or an O?
U?
Ho-munc-u-lus.
One of the reasons for
handouts, by the way, is so
that when people ask me can
I please spell it, it's on
the handout somewhere.
Because the answer's
no I can't.
So the homunculus, probably
derived from the Latin for a
little man in the head, and
I apologize to the women.
I was trying to figure out
today what the little woman
in the head would be.
But my Latin has waned since
I took it in college.
Maybe it's the femunculus,
I'm not sure.
But, in any case,
that's the homunculus.
So, that's stimulation
techniques.
I'm shopping for one more
useful technique here.
Anybody care to offer me
another technique for
figuring out what's
going on in the brain?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Case studies are
typically these lesion studies.
Somebody has something
wrong with them.
And we try to figure out
what's wrong with them.
That goes way back, by the way.
The early efforts to figure out
what bits of brain did come
from the phrenologists,
early 19th century.
Phrenology.
If you know anything about
phrenology, you learned it
from the Cartoon Network.
Because you watched Bugs Bunny
beat Elmer Fudd over the head.
And then the bumps showed
up and you felt the bumps.
Looking at me like,
what's he talking about.
Or you know it because there's
a wide, any of these umpteen
cartoons or sculptures where
you have a head that's got
little functions all over it.
Good, somebody remembers it.
I'm not just making
up weird stuff.
The phrenologists believed that
the shape of the skull
reflected the underlying shape
of the brain, that bigger
meant more of that
particular function.
Which is rather like this.
I mean, it's not a completely
wacko assumption.
And they then used a case study
system to try to figure out
what different parts
of the brain did.
So if you wanted to know where
criminality was in the brain,
you go and find yourself
some criminals.
And check where they got
big chunks of their brain.
And that's where those
sort of maps came from.
It's a rather ad hoc sounding
kind of process, now.
So, amativeness, lust, is
typically located back here.
The reason it's located back
here is because Spurzheim, one
of the founders of phrenology,
had in his care a, how did he
describe it, I think
she's described as
a passionate widow.
And every time Spurzheim put
her his hand on the back of
her neck, it became
red and inflamed.
And he therefore concluded
that that's where lust lived.
Erm.
It turns out, though, that if
you read old phrenology texts,
the original phrenology texts,
they read not unlike
introductory psych texts, or
introductory brain science
texts, with a few
unfortunate assumptions.
Like the notion that they skull
shape reflects underlying brain
shape, which it does
not very well.
There was -- yes, pink person.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: OK well that's --
so, we'll put the, looking
at the cells part in
under the anatomy.
My wife would hate this.
My wife is a neuroanatomist.
That's what she
does for a living.
She would want many
categories for that.
All by itself.
But, yeah, so you can go
look at, certainly as,
well you can use this in
a number of contexts.
If you're going to go
stimulate, these days, if
you're going to go stimulate
brain cells, you might be
doing it on a slice
of brain in a dish.
To see how it's connected
to the next one.
And you would be looking
at the individual cells
under a microscope while
you were doing that.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Oh yeah, that's
a, genetics is another
candidate for 5.
But I will, actually if you
take a look at, that allows
me to make a somewhat
different point.
On the handouts, the writing
assignments that you get in
this course this year will
have as their starting point
readings that live on the
stellar website for the course.
Or they particularly will if
I ever give Mara the disk
to put them up there.
I'll have to remember that.
The one that's on for this
lecture, if one wanted to write
based starting from this
lecture, is actually
a genetic study.
Turns out that there are two
flavors of vole out there.
A little rodent-like animal.
Some voles are promiscuous.
Some voles are not promiscuous.
They just hang out with one,
I guess lady voles, that's a
basketball team, isn't it?
Anyway, the, I guess
they're [? valls, ?]
not voles.
Anyway, the claim of a new
paper this year is that
manipulation of a single gene
is able to turn promiscuous
voles into faithful voles.
So in that sense, yes,
absolutely genetics are a new
tool for getting to this.
It's not what I'm pushing for.
I'll take one more bit of
fishing expedition and then
I'll just -- all right,
that'll be, that's fine, too.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: In vole land yes?
It's, the male voles
who are promiscuous.
And they're manipulating
the sexual behavior
of the male voles.
The female voles don't have the
big asymmetry, the two species
of voles don't have the big
asymmetry in their behavior
to start with, apparently.
So yeah, I think
it's a guy thing.
More on that later in the term.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Reading
brain signals.
We'll call that recording.
In some fashion or other.
If you can stick an electrode
into the brain and stimulate,
you can also stick an electrode
into the brain and record
from brain tissue.
And ask what a particular cell
or bunch of cells are doing.
You can do this at a large
scale level in walking around
human beings or animals, by
putting electrodes
on the skull.
You can read massed activities
of large numbers of neurons
off the surface of the skull.
And that's so-called electoral
encephalogram, EEG.
But that's very useful, for
instance, in telling the
difference between different
wake and sleep states.
If you are deeply asleep,
the sort of sleep that when
the alarm clock goes off
you're uh, where am I.
If you look at the EEG,
you find big, slow waves.
All the cells are active.
And then all the
cells are quiet.
And they're all
firing together.
When you're looking at an awake
individual, the waveform is
much smaller amplitude
and higher frequency.
Because the calculus
piece of your brain
is currently napping.
And the psychology
piece is wide awake.
And various bits are
doing things out of
sync with each other.
So you can see that from
massed recordings.
But if you now go
stick an electrode.
Let's suppose we go and stick
an electrode into, well,
let's take the same cell
that I stimulate here.
And if the patient said, I feel
that in my toe, if instead of
stimulating, you record, you
find out that that cell doesn't
change its behavior at all over
a huge range of possible things
that the organism
could be doing.
But if you poke the toe, that
cell says, here I am, I'm
interested in that
and exactly that.
You go poke the armpit
or something, the
cell doesn't care.
You poke the other, the next to
over, the cell doesn't care.
You poke one particular
toe, let us say,
that cell will care.
Take a cell out here somewhere,
and that cell will care only if
you put visual stimuli in a
particular little spot in the
right side of the visual
space, in a very particular
part of visual space.
Move over a little bit, and
it'll want stimulation in
a different piece
of visual space.
Move elsewhere in the brain,
and now rather than liking,
say, just something simple like
a line moving around, a cell
down here, this is typically
done in things like monkeys and
so, that cell might be very
interested if you show it
the hand of a monkey.
The cell's thrilled.
Show it a hunk of
chalk, I don't care.
A nearby one might like
the face of a monkey.
And so on.
So you can find out what
individual cells are
interested in, by
recording their activity.
There are some significant
drawbacks to this.
One of them is that you can
only sample from a tiny
fraction of the cells, even
in an area that you
are interested in.
How many cells do you think
there are, how many neurons
do you think there
are, in the brain?
So, the answer's -- yes,
a lot is a good answer.
But the answer's going to
be expressed in terms
of 10 to the X.
What's X, would you guess?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: The 24's are
a little high and the
9's are a little low.
When I asked this question when
I was in graduate school, I got
the answer that there are
approximately, nobody knows
the answer for sure, because
who's going to go and count.
That there are 10 to the
12 neurons in the brain.
And of these, I didn't even
tell you on this picture,
but we can draw a
tail on this thing.
Hanging off the back of the
brain, sort of underneath the
back, is the cerebellum.
It means little brain.
It's important in learning and
motor control sorts of things.
We're not going to say much
about it here, sadly.
But what my professor said
was, there are, 10 to the
12 neurons in the brain.
Of these, 10 to the 13th
are in the cerebellum.
The quick on the uptake crowd
picked up that there's
a problem here.
What he was trying to
tell me was not that he
didn't understand math.
But that, look, we don't even
really know to an order of
magnitude how many cells
there are in the brain.
But, lots.
On this order.
How many cells can you record
from in a study of some
function in the brain?
Heroic single-unit, single-cell
recording studies might have on
the order of 10 to the 2nd,
100 cells recorded from.
Moreover, if you're going to
stick an electrode in the
brain, the cells that it
encounters are going to be
biased by things like size.
You're more likely to get big
cells than little cells.
And big cells do things that
are different than little
cells do in the brain.
So, you can imagine that it
would be difficult to figure
out what your laptop did
by recording from single
components on the motherboard.
That wouldn't be
particularly easy.
It gets significantly worse
when you try to do that
in the brain as a whole.
The things we know best about
in the brain are things where
we can bring all of these
techniques to bear, and get
what would be called converging
evidence, converging
data, on it.
Evidence from multiple
different sources, and then
corroborate that by looking
at behavioral measures.
Oh, let me say, all right.
This is the moments in the
lecture where I really feel my
wife looking over my shoulder.
In two minutes I will polish
off the rest of the brain.
So that's just the
surface of the brain.
The brain is a 3-D structure.
One way to very grossly think
about the overall structure of
the brain is that if this
cortex, lying underneath cortex
is what, are a bunch of
structures that often get
called limbic structures.
This is really an
outdated term.
It comes from the word for
ring, and it was the notion
that there was a circuit
of structures lying
under the cortex.
But there's a collection of
structures who will show up
later in the term, with names
like the amygdala, from
the Latin for almond.
Hippocampus, Latin for almond
or Greek for almond, I'm
not sure at the moment.
Hippocampus, from the
word for seahorse.
Not because you have almonds or
seahorses in your brain, but
because the shapes of these
things are faintly reminiscent
of such things out
in the real world.
And other structures that turn
out to be vitally important in
your emotional life
and in memory.
Hippocampus will show up
later as critical in memory.
Lying underneath there, and
heading on down into the spinal
cord, oh I don't know, let's
call it the core today, or
something, are a set of
structures that, well, we tend
to spend a lot of time in
psychology talking about the
cool stuff happening up in the
cortex and stuff like that.
But the stuff you really don't
want to lose, the stuff we
don't know about from lesion
studies, is down here.
Because something in your brain
has to say to your heart, beat.
Beat.
That piece of brain goes,
you've got really big trouble.
There's another piece
down there that says,
time to breathe.
Time to breathe again.
I mean, it's not
glamorous work.
But, yeah, somebody, so there's
a whole set of stuff here
running vegetative processes.
And also important, not just
for pacemaker kinds of things.
But also for general issues
of arousal, and sleep and
wakefulness, those
sort of things.
So that is an embarrassingly
brief tour of, you can spend
your life on neuroanatomy.
Trust me, my wife does.
We'll come back and talk about
single cells on Tuesday.