JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about the divergence
theorem, also known as Gauss'
theorem, and flux, and all
that good stuff.
So I have a nice exercise
on it for you here.
So what I want is I want you to
take F, and I want it to be
the field whose components are
x over rho cubed, y over rho
cubed, and z over rho cubed.
So here, rho is your usual rho
from spherical coordinates.
Rho is equal to the square
root of x squared plus y
squared plus z squared.
And I want S to be the surface
of the box whose vertices are
plus or minus 2, plus or minus
2, plus or minus 2.
So it's a cubicle box.
So what I'd like you to do, is
first in part a, I'd like you
to show that the divergence of
F is 0, wherever the field F
is defined.
In part b, what I'd like you to
think about is whether we
can conclude from that, that the
flux through the surface
of S is equal to 0.
All right.
And in part c, what I'd like
you to do is to use the
extended version of Gauss'
theorem-- or the extended
version of the divergence
theorem--
in order to actually compute
the flux through S by
computing an integral.
So why don't you pause the video
for a couple of minutes,
work out this problem,
come back, and we
can work it out together.
Hopefully you had some luck
with this problem.
Let's get started.
Part a asks you to compute the
divergence of F. So in order
to compute that, we're going
to need to take the partial
derivatives of the components of
F. And in order to do that,
at some point I'm going to
need to take a partial
derivative of rho.
So let me first compute the
partial derivatives of rho,
and that will save me a tiny
bit of work later.
So rho is equal to the square
root of x squared plus y
squared plus z squared.
So partial rho partial x--
well, you just apply your usual
chain rule here-- and I
guess we get a half, but then we
get a 2 that cancels it, so
I think this works out to x
divided by the square root of
x squared plus y squared plus
z squared, so that's
x divided by rho.
All right.
And I'm just going to keep rho
around here, because otherwise
I have to write out the square
root of x squared plus y
squared plus z squared over and
over again, and this is
going to save me some effort
and would save you
some effort as well.
So OK.
So this is rho.
So this is d rho dx.
So we want to take the x partial
of the first component
of F. So that's the x partial
of x over rho cubed.
OK.
And you just apply your
usual quotient rule,
so what do we get?
We get the derivative
of the top.
So that's rho cubed minus--
OK, so the top is x times the
derivative of the bottom,
which is going to be 3 rho
squared times x over rho--
so that's 3--
so we have an x-- so it's 3x
squared rho, divided by the
bottom squared, which
is rho to the sixth.
And I guess there's a common
factor of rho everywhere that
we can cancel out.
So this is equal to rho squared
minus 3x squared
divided by rho to the fifth.
OK.
So that's the x-partial
derivative of the first
component of F.
Now we need the y-partial
derivative of the second
component of F, and the
z-partial derivative of the
third component of F. But if you
go and look back at what
the formula for F was, you see
that this is a very, very
symmetric formula.
So in order to get from the
first component to the second
component, we just change x to
y, and to get from the second
component to the third, we just
change y to z, because of
course rho treats x,
y, and z the same.
So what does that mean?
Well, that means that the
partial derivatives are easy
to compute.
Having computed this x-partial
derivative, we also get that
partial over partial y of the
second component-- which is y
over rho cubed--
is equal to rho squared
minus 3y squared,
over rho to the fifth.
And the last one we get, partial
over partial z of z
over rho cubed is equal
to rho squared minus--
I'm getting a little
cramped here--
3z squared, over rho
to the fifth.
And so adding these up, we get
that div F is equal to the sum
of those three things.
So let's see what we've got.
We've got a 3--
so the denominators are
all rho to the fifth.
And we've got 3 rho squared
minus 3x squared minus 3y
squared minus 3z squared.
So this is equal to 3 rho
squared minus 3x squared minus
3y squared minus 3z squared,
all over rho to the fifth.
But of course, rho squared is x
squared plus y squared plus
z squared, so this numerator
is just 0.
So this is equal to 0.
OK.
Which is what we thought
it should be.
All right.
Good.
So that's part a.
We just computed the partial
derivatives of F, and then
added them together to
get the divergence.
And we found that, in fact,
yes, the divergence
was equal to 0.
Great.
So that's part a.
So let's go look at
what part b was.
Part b asks, can we conclude
that the flux through the
surface S is 0?
All right.
Now remember what the divergence
theorem says.
The divergence theorem says
that the flux through a
surface of a field is equal to
the triple integral of the
divergence of that field over
the interior, provided the
field is defined and
differentiable
and nice, or whatever.
Everywhere inside.
OK?
But this field has a problem.
Almost everywhere, this field
is nicely behaved, but at 0,
we have a real problem.
We're dividing by 0.
Right?
So this field is not
defined at 0.
So there's a single point in the
middle of this cube where
this field behaves badly.
And that means we can't
apply the divergence
theorem inside this cube.
So since we can't apply the
divergence theorem, we aren't
allowed to conclude immediately
that the flux
through this surface is 0.
OK.
So the answer is no.
We can't conclude that the flux
through S is 0, because
one of the hypotheses
of the divergence
theorem isn't satisfied.
Namely, the field isn't defined
everywhere inside the surface.
OK.
So the answer to b is no.
OK, I'm just going
to write that.
But it's no because the
hypotheses aren't satisfied.
OK, so now let's
look at part c.
So part c suggests, we can't
conclude that the flux is 0.
So we still want to know
what the flux is.
That's still an interesting
question, so part c suggests
that maybe you can still use the
extended Gauss' theorem to
compute what this flux is.
So let's think about how
we could do that.
So remember what extended
Gauss' theorem says?
Or extended divergence
theorem.
I'm going to try and just say
Gauss' theorem from now on so
I stop having to say both.
But I mean both.
I mean, they're the same
theorem, right?
OK.
So Gauss' theorem says, when you
have a surface bounding a
region, the flux through the
surface is equal to the triple
integral of divergence over
the region, provided
everything is well-defined
and nice.
Extended Gauss' theorem says,
this is still true if your
region has more than
one boundary.
So for example, if your region
is a hollow something--
so if it's a spherical shell
that has an outside sphere and
an inside sphere--
then extended Gauss' theorem
says, OK, so
you do the same thing.
You take the triple integral
of the divergence over the
solid region.
And then you take the flux, but
you add up the flux over
all of the boundary pieces.
So you add up the flux over the
outside boundary surface,
and also, if there is
one, through any
other boundary surface.
OK?
And those two things
are equal.
So the total flux through all
of the boundary surface is
equal to the integral of
divergence over the whole
region bounded by
those surfaces.
So how are we going
to use this?
We're trying to compute the
flux through a surface.
OK, but we don't want to compute
a double integral if
we can avoid it.
We don't want to compute
the surface integral.
So what we'd like to do is we'd
like to find a convenient
region over which to compute
this integral to put us in a
situation where we can apply
extended Gauss' theorem.
We can't use just the inside of
the cube, so we want some
other region.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to walk over here.
There are many possible things
you could do, but
this is a nice one.
All right.
One thing you could do is you
could take a big sphere.
Take a big sphere.
So we've got our cube here.
This is the point 2, 2, 2, and
this is the point 2, 2, minus
2, and so on.
So we've taken a big sphere of
radius R-- for some big R that
contains our surface S that
we're interested in-- that
completely contains the cube.
OK?
So why have we done that?
Extended Gauss' theorem.
OK, so what does extended Gauss'
theorem say for the
region between the sphere
and this cube.
All right.
So our cube is named S.
Let's call our sphere
S2, because why not?
OK.
And let's call the solid
region between
the cube and sphere--
just for convenience, let's
give it a name--
so--
we often call solid regions
D-- so let's call it D.
So it's this spherical region,
but it has a cubical hole in
the middle of it.
OK.
So what does extended
Gauss' theorem say?
So extended Gauss' theorem says
that the triple integral
over D of the divergence of F dV
is equal to the sum of the
fluxes through each
of the surfaces.
But for this, we want the flux
out of the solid region.
So for the sphere, the flux
out of the inside of the
sphere is the flux out
of the sphere.
So that's integral over S2 of
F dot n, d surface area.
But for the cube, the flux out
of this region is the flux
into the cube.
Right?
Out here, you're living in a
region outside the cube, so
when you leave that region,
you're going into the cube.
So this is the negative of the
flux that we really want.
So this is minus the flux
through the cube of F dot n,
with respect to surface area.
So remember, the signs here
are different, because I'm
taking this normal to be the
outward pointing normal to
both surfaces.
The normal that points
away from the origin.
But the normal pointing away
from the origin on the cube is
the normal that points into the
solid region instead of
the normal that points out
of the solid region.
So that's why this
minus is here.
OK.
Whew.
All right, so what
does this mean?
So first of all, F is
well-defined everywhere in
this region D. The only
place F was badly
behaved was the origin.
And this region doesn't contain
it, which is why this
trick works.
So we've already computed that
the divergence of F is 0
everywhere.
It's defined.
So it's 0 on all of D,
and so this triple
integral is just 0.
So if this triple integral is 0,
that means we can just add
the thing that we're interested
in to both sides,
and we get that the surface
integral over the cube of F
dot n, with respect to surface
area, is equal to the surface
integral over the sphere
of F dot n, with
respect to surface area.
OK.
So we've converted this original
integral-- our flux
integral that we're interested
in-- and we found that it's
equal to this separate
flux integral
over a different surface.
This time over a big sphere.
OK, so that's nice.
Why do we want to do that?
Well, we want to do that because
F is a really nicely
behaved field with respect
to a sphere.
F is a radial field.
So F dot n is really
easy to understand.
F dot n: n is a unit normal
and F is a radial field.
So on a sphere, the normal
is radial, right?
It's parallel to the
position vector.
And F is radial.
So they're both pointing in
exactly the same direction.
So when you take that dot
product, n is the unit vector
in the same direction as F, so
when you dot that with F, you
just get the length of F. OK,
so what does that mean?
That means over here, this
integrand is really easy to
understand.
OK?
This integrand F dot n on the
sphere is just equal to the
length of the vector F.
Now what is the length
of the vector F?
Well, we know what F is.
It's x over rho cubed, i hat
plus y over rho cubed, j hat
plus z over rho cubed, k hat.
So OK, so you compute the length
of that vector, and
what do you get?
Well, it's exactly 1
over rho squared.
OK.
But we said that this
is a sphere.
I guess I didn't
write it down.
Let me write it down
right here.
This is a sphere whose radius
is big R. It doesn't really
matter very much what R we
choose, we just want it to be
big enough so that it contains
the whole cube.
If you said this a sphere
of radius 10, that would
completely do the trick.
That would be totally fine.
OK, so the radius of the sphere
is big R, so the length
of the field-- we said
back over here--
is 1 over R squared.
The length of the vector F. So
this flux integral then, is
the integral over the sphere--
S2--
of a constant.
So it's the integral over
the sphere of 1
over R squared, dS.
But when you integrate a
constant over a surface, what
you get is just that constant
times the surface area.
Well, what's the surface area?
This is a sphere.
It's easy to understand
its surface area.
Its surface area is
4 pi R squared.
Right?
So this is equal to the surface
area, so that's 4 pi R
squared, times whatever
that constant was.
So the constant was
1 over R squared.
And so the R squared's cancel.
Right?
This is why it didn't matter
what R we chose, because
they're just going to cancel
at the end, anyhow.
OK, so those cancel, and
we're left with 4 pi.
So let's just quickly recap what
we did in this part c.
We're looking to compute
the flux over the cube.
But it's a kind of unpleasant
integral we'd have to compute
to total up the fluxes over
these various, different
faces and so on.
So instead, we had this clever
idea that we'll apply the
divergence theorem to replace
the cube with a
more congenial surface.
Because this is a nice
radial vector field,
that's our main hint.
Because there was a rho
involved in the
problem, if you will.
So the surface that we choose
is some big sphere.
And then we apply the extended
Gauss' theorem to the solid
region between the cube
and the sphere.
Outside the cube, but
inside the sphere.
So because the divergence of the
field is 0, the extended
Gauss' theorem tells us
that the two fluxes--
the flux out of the cube and the
flux out of the sphere--
are actually equal
to each other.
But since the fluxes are
actually equal to each other,
in order to compute the flux out
of the cube, it's enough
to compute the flux
out of the sphere.
OK.
But computing the flux out of
the sphere is relatively easy,
because on the sphere,
the integrand F
dot n is just a constant.
And so then we're integrating a
constant over the surface of
a sphere, and that just gives
us the surface area of the
sphere times that constant,
which is 4 pi R squared, times
1 over R squared,
which is 4 pi.
So the flux out of the cube then
is also equal to 4 pi.
I'll stop there.