JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture you've been learning
about surface
integrals, flux, and the
divergence theorem.
And I have a nice problem here
that'll put your knowledge of
those things to the test. So
in this situation, I have a
hemisphere.
So this is a hemisphere.
It's the right half of a sphere,
so the part where y is
positive, or non-negative,
I guess.
So just the surface of that
hemisphere, and it has radius
R and it's centered
at the origin.
So I have this hemisphere and
I have the field F, which is
given by y times j hat.
So it's just always in
the y-direction.
So I have this field and I have
this hemisphere, and what
I'd like to do is I'd like you
to compute the flux of the
field through this hemisphere.
But as a hint, rather than
doing it by computing the
surface integral by
parameterizing, what I'd like
you to do is to use the
divergence theorem to make
your life a little bit easier.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to work
that out, come back and we
can work on it together.
Hopefully, you had some luck
working on this problem.
Let's see how we can
go about it.
So the thing that we're
asked to compute--
let's give this a name, just
so we can refer to it.
So let's call this surface of
the sphere S. All right.
So we want the flux through S.
And so the flux through S is
the double integral over S of
our field F dotted with the
normal with respect to surface
area, so with respect to
surface area.
So I guess this was a kind of
bad choice, this S. We've got
S that means--
this S means the sphere, this
S just means surface area.
OK.
Hopefully, you can keep
those two sorted.
This is the thing
that we want.
And we'd like to compute it.
Rather than by parameterizing
this hemisphere, we'd like to
compute it by using the
divergence theorem.
So the divergence theorem
relates the integral over a
surface to a triple integral
over a region.
So what we'd like to find is a
solid region for which this is
all or part of the boundary.
Now this half hemisphere--
rather, half-sphere,
this hemisphere--
doesn't actually enclose a
region, but there's an obvious
region that's closely related
to it, which would be the
solid sphere.
If you just filled in that
half-sphere there.
So then, for that
solid sphere--
so the right half of the solid
sphere, with radius R,
centered at the origin,
that hemisphere--
that solid hemisphere, has a
surface that consists of S,
and it also consists of a disc
centered at the origin.
So it consists of--
I'm going to draw it in right
here-- it's this disc.
This one.
That disc right there, together
with our hemisphere
that interests us, make up the
boundary of this solid
hemisphere.
So I'm going to call
that disc--
I'm going to give it a name--
I'm going to call it S2.
So we want this integral and
we're going to use the
divergence theorem.
So the way we're going to use
the divergence theorem is
we're going to use the
divergence theorem to relate
this double integral
over a surface
to that triple integral.
But I'm going to have to get S2
involved because I need--
for the divergence theorem
to apply--
I need surfaces which
completely
bound a solid region.
So what we know by the
divergence theorem is that the
double integral over both S
and S2 of F dot n hat with
respect to surface area is equal
to the triple integral--
OK, so I guess I need
another letter here.
So I'm going to call this
D for that whole
half-hemisphere, the
solid hemisphere.
So D, this is the solid
hemisphere.
So this D is the solid
hemisphere
that they bound of--
OK, so it's the triple integral
over D of the
divergence of F with
respect to volume.
So this is what the divergence
theorem tells us and now we--
so OK.
So good.
So now what's going to be nice
is that in this case this
triple integral is going to
be very easy to compute.
And the surface integral
over S2 is going
to be easy to compute.
And so what we're going to be
left with after we compute
those two things, we'll be able
to subtract and get just
the surface integral over S.
So lets think about doing
those things.
So first let's do the surface
integral over S2.
The surface integral over S2
of F dot n with respect to
surface area.
Well, what is F on
that disc S2?
So let's go look at
our picture again.
So this disc is the disc of
radius R centered at the
origin in the x, z plane.
So it's in the x, z plane.
So that means it's in the
plane y equals 0.
So F on that disc is just 0.
It's the 0 field.
It's 0 everywhere
on that disc.
And if you take a surface
integral of a 0 field dot the
normal vector, well, 0 dot
the normal is just 0.
So if we come back over
here, this integrand
is 0 dot the normal.
So it's always 0.
So we're integrating 0.
So we just get 0.
Definite integral of 0 is 0.
Double integral of 0 is 0.
Great.
So this S2, the surface integral
of F is really easy
to compute.
That's the first
one we needed.
Now we need the triple
integral.
So let's compute the triple
integral over the solid
hemisphere of div F dV.
Well, what is div F?
Well, you know, so div F is just
the sum of the partial
derivatives of the
three components.
So in our case if we go back and
look, well, F is 0 i hat
plus y j hat plus 0 k hat.
So when you take the partial
derivatives you get 0 plus the
partial derivative of y with
respect to y is just 1, plus
from the third component
we also get 0.
So the divergence--
let's go back over here-- the
divergence is just 1.
It's just a constant 1.
That's great.
So this triple integral
is equal to--
I'm going to bring
it down here--
so it's equal to the triple
integral over D of 1 dV. But,
of course, when you integrate 1
over a solid region what you
get is just the volume
of that region.
So whatever this number is
it's the volume of that
hemisphere.
Well, OK, so what's the
volume of a sphere?
It's 4/3 pi r cubed.
So the volume of a hemisphere
is half of that.
So that's 2 pi R cubed
divided by 3.
So that's the triple integral
of the divergence over the
solid region.
So what does that mean?
So our integral, the integral
over S of F dot n with respect
to surface area is equal to this
triple integral over D of
div F dV minus the double
integral over S2 of F dot n d
surface area.
And so we just saw that this
is equal to 2 pi R cubed
over 3 minus 0.
But 0 is 0.
So it's just 2 pi
R cubed over 3.
So let's quickly recap.
To start off with, we just
had this hemisphere.
And we're asked to compute a
surface integral over this
hemisphere of a flux of this
field F. So rather than going
ahead and calculating it
directly, what we realized is
that by the divergence theorem
we could consider this to be a
difference of a triple integral
minus another surface
integral such that those two
surfaces together bounded the
region that you were triple
integrating over.
So in principle there were many
possible regions that we
could have chosen.
Many possible solid regions that
we could have chosen to
do that triple integral over and
to use the other half of
its boundary.
But there's one particularly
nice one, which is just the
solid hemisphere of which this
hemisphere s was the boundary,
or part of the boundary.
And so then that gave us
this other part of its
boundary was this disc.
So we introduced this new solid
region, D, and the rest
of its boundary, which was this
other surface, this disc.
S2.
And so then, by the divergence
theorem, rather than computing
the integral over our original
region S we could just compute
the triple integral over the
solid region and the surface
integral over the other
half of the boundary.
So sometimes that won't
be helpful.
Sometimes you'll have an ugly
field, you'll have an ugly
region, things won't work out.
But in this case, it worked
out really nicely.
The triple integral was easy
to compute, as we saw over
here, because the divergence
was constant.
Because the divergence was just
equal to 1, the triple
integral just gave the volume.
And the other surface integral
was also easy to compute
because F dot n on that surface
was equal to 0.
So integrating it
was very easy.
We just were integrating
0 and we got 0.
So in this case, these choices
worked out very, very nicely.
They made our life
nice and simple.
And so in the end, all we had
to do were these two almost
trivial integrals.
They didn't really require
any computation
at all on our part.
And then a little bit of
subtraction, except we were
subtracting 0 so even the
subtraction was easy.
So that was what we did, worked
out very nicely, 2 pi R
cubed over 3 was our answer.
And I'll end there.