JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about flux and
surface integrals in the
divergence theorem, and I have
a nice problem about
that for you here.
So I've got this field F, and
it's a little bit ugly right?
All right.
So its coordinates are x to the
fourth y, minus 2x cubed y
squared, and z squared.
And it's passing through the
surface of a solid that's
bounded by the plane z equals
0, by the plane z equals h,
and by the surface
x squared plus y
squared equals R squared.
So often we call this
solid a cylinder.
So it's got its bottom surface
in the plane z equals 0, and
its top surface in the plane
z equals h, and it's got a
circular base with
radius R there.
So what I'd like you to do is
to compute the flux of this
field F through this cylinder.
So I'll point out before I let
you at it, that to compute
this as a surface integral,
you could do it.
You could do it.
If you really want an exercise
in nasty arithmetic, I invite
you to do it.
But you might be able to think
of a way to do this that
requires less effort than
parametrizing the three
surfaces and integrating
and so on.
So I'll leave you with that.
Why don't you pause the video,
work this one out, come back,
and we can work on
it together.
Hopefully, you had some luck
working on this problem.
Right before I left, I mentioned
that you were
computing a flux through a
surface here, but that doing
it as a surface integral is
maybe not the best way to go.
And so, even without that hint,
probably many of you
realized that really the way
that we want to go about this
problem is with the divergence
theorem.
OK.
So in our case, the divergence
theorem--
I'm just abbreviating
it div T-H-M here--
says start with the double
integral over the surface of F
dot n d surface area.
So S here is the surface
of this solid.
So the divergence theorem says
that this surface integral,
which is the flux that we're
interested in, is equal to the
triple integral over the solid
region D-- so that's bounded
by the surface, and so that's
the solid cylinder here--
of div F dV. OK.
So in our case, this is nice,
because in fact, this solid
region D is an easier to
understand, or easier to
grapple with region than
the surface that we
started with, right?
It's just one solid piece.
It's easy to parametrize,
in fact.
It's easy to describe especially
in cylindrical
coordinates, but also in
rectangular coordinates.
Whereas this surface S, if we
wanted to talk about it, we'd
need to split it up into three
pieces, and we'd need to
parametrize it.
And it's kind of a hassle,
relatively speaking.
Also, the divergence of this
field F is a lot simpler than
the field itself.
If we go and look at this field,
all of its components
are polynomials.
To compute its divergence,
we take
derivatives of all of them.
And so that makes their degrees
lower, and then we
just add them.
Life is a little bit simpler.
So OK.
So this process of using the
divergence theorem is going to
make our lives easier.
It's going to make this nasty
surface integral into an easy
to compute triple integral.
So let's see actually
how it does.
So let's compute div F first.
So we know what
the integrand is.
All right.
So we need to look at the
components of F, and so we
need to take the partial
of the first one
with respect to x.
So that's x to the fourth
y with respect to x.
So put that down over here.
That's 4x cubed y.
We just treat y as a constant.
OK, so now we come back
and we need to look
at the second one.
So it's minus 2x cubed
y squared.
And it's the second one.
We take its partial
with respect to y.
So OK.
So that's going to be minus
2x cubed times 2y.
So that's going to be
minus 4x cubed y.
And then we come back and we
look at the last component.
And that's z squared.
And so we need to take its
partial with respect to z.
So in this case, that's
just 2z, and so we
add that on as well.
Plus 2z.
And in this case, not only are
these polynomials simpler than
the coordinates of F that we
had, but in fact, we've got
some simplification here.
Life gets really,
really simple.
So in fact, this is just going
to work out to 2z.
So the divergence here is very
simple compared with the
function F. More simple than we
have a right to expect, but
in any case, good.
It's nice to work with.
OK.
So that's the divergence.
So I'm going to write,
this is the flux.
These integrals that we're
interested in.
This surface integral, and
then by the divergence
theorem, it's the same as
this triple integral.
So the divergence is this 2z.
So the flux is what I get when
I just put that in here.
So flux is equal to the triple
integral over our solid of 2z
dV. OK, so I've left some
stuff out of this.
Because I'm going to start
writing down the bounds and
writing this down as an
iterated integral now.
OK.
So we have to choose some
coordinate system in which to
integrate over this solid.
And so we have three kinds of
natural choices that we always
look back to.
There are rectangular
coordinates and cylindrical
coordinates and spherical
coordinates.
So spherical coordinates seem
pretty clearly inappropriate.
Rectangular and cylindrical?
You know, you could try and
do it in rectangular.
It's not horrible.
But this is a cylinder, right?
I mean, it's crying out for
us to use cylindrical
coordinates.
So let's use cylindrical
So we're going to use
cylindrical coordinates.
So to get dV we need a z, an r,
and a theta, but remember
there's this extra
factor of r.
So it's going to be 2z times
r dz dr d theta.
Right?
This is dV. This r dz
dr d theta part.
So that's what dV is when we use
cylindrical coordinates.
OK, so now let's figure out
what the bounds are.
So let's go look
at the cylinder
that we had over here.
So it's bounded between z equals
0 at the bottom surface
and z equals h at
the top surface.
OK.
So that's easy enough.
That's what the bounds
on z are.
So let's put those in.
So z is the innermost one, so
that's going from 0 to h.
OK.
How about the next one?
So the next one is r.
So let's go back over here.
So r is the radius here after
we project it down.
And we just get the circle
of radius big R
centered at the origin.
So little r is going
from 0 to big R.
And theta is the circle.
It's the whole circle.
So theta is going
from 0 to 2 pi.
So cylinders are really easy
to describe what they look
like in cylindrical
coordinates.
So let's put those in.
So little r is going from
0 to big R, and theta is
going from 0 to 2 pi.
OK.
Wonderful.
Now we just have to compute
this, right?
We've got our flux is this
triple integral.
So let's compute it.
Let's walk over to this little
bit of empty board space.
OK, so we have an iterated
integral.
So let's do it.
So the inner integral
is the integral from
0 to h of 2zr dz.
Well, that's not that bad.
That's equal to r
as a constant.
So it's equal to rz squared
as z goes between 0 and h.
It's dz, so z is going
from 0 to h.
So plug in, and we just get
h squared r minus 0.
So just h squared r.
OK.
So now let's do the
middle integral.
So the middle integral is the
integral from 0 to big R d
little r of the inner
integral.
So this is the integral from 0
to big R of the inner integral
which was h squared little
r d little r.
OK.
And that's not that
bad either.
So h is just a constant.
So this is equal to 1/2 h
squared r squared from r
equals 0 to big R. And
so that's 1/2 h
squared big R squared.
That's the middle integral.
So the outer one now.
OK.
So let's go back and look.
So we're doing d theta as theta
goes from 0 to 2 pi of
whatever the middle
integral was.
So it's the integral from 0 to
2 pi of whatever the value of
the middle integral was.
So this is 1/2 h squared
big R squared d theta.
And this is all just constant
with respect to theta.
So that's going to be just
pi h squared r squared.
You're just multiplying
it by 2 pi.
All right.
So pi h squared r squared.
So this is our final answer.
Let's just quickly recap
what we did.
We had to compute the flux of
this field F through the
surface of a solid cylinder.
And so we had options.
We could do it directly by
trying to compute the surface
integrals, but in this case,
life was a lot easier if we
applied the divergence
theorem.
So the divergence theorem
says that the flux--
which is equal to this
surface integral--
can also be written as the
triple integral over the solid
region bounded by the
surface of the
divergence of the field.
All right.
And so in our case, the
divergence was very nice and
simple, and the solid region
D was relatively simpler to
describe than-- its surface
that bounds it--
S. So this is why we think of
the divergence theorem.
Because the divergence of the
field is easy to understand,
and the solid is easier to
describe than its surface.
So those are both things that
make us think to use the
divergence theorem for
a problem like this.
So then by the divergence
theorem, the flux is just that
triple integral, and so we wrote
it out here that we were
integrating over a cylinder.
So a natural thing to do is use
cylindrical coordinates.
And then we computed the
triple integral just
like we always do.
I did it in three steps: inner,
middle, and outer.
You don't have to do it
exactly this way if
you don't want to.
But it works for me.
OK.
And we got our final answer:
pi h squared r squared.
I'll stop there.