matrix.
And maybe I could just recap
for a minute what is that magic
formula doing?
For example,
it's supposed to be --
it's supposed to produce a
projection, if I multiply by a
b, so I take P times b,
I'm supposed to project that
vector b to the nearest point in
the column space.
OK.
Can I just -- one way to recap
is to take the two extreme
cases.
Suppose a vector b is in the
column space?
Then what do I get when I apply
the projection P?
So I'm projecting into the
column space but I'm starting
with a vector in this case
that's already in the column
space, so of course when I
project it I get B again,
right.
And I want to show you how that
comes out of this formula.
Let me do the other extreme.
Suppose that vector is
perpendicular to the column
space.
So imagine this column space as
a plane and imagine b as
sticking straight up
perpendicular to it.
What's the nearest point in the
column space to b in that case?
So what's the projection onto
the plane, the nearest point in
the plane, if the vector b that
I'm looking at is --
got no component in the column
space, it's sticking completely
-- ninety degrees with it,
then Pb should be zero,
right.
So those are the two extreme
cases.
The average vector has a
component P in the column space
and a component perpendicular to
it, and what the projection does
is it kills this part and it
preserves this part.
OK.
Can we just see why that's
true?
Just -- that formula ought to
work.
So let me start with this one.
What vectors are in the -- are
perpendicular to the column
space?
How do I see that I really get
zero?
I have to think,
what does it mean for a vector
b to be perpendicular to the
column space?
So if it's perpendicular to all
the columns, then it's in some
other space.
We've got our four spaces so
the reason I do this is it's
perfectly using what we know
about our four spaces.
What vectors are perpendicular
to the column space?
Those are the guys in the null
space of A transpose,
right?
That's the first section of
this chapter,
that's the key geometry of
these spaces.
If I'm perpendicular to the
column space,
I'm in the null space of A
transpose.
OK.
So if I'm in the null space of
A transpose, and I multiply this
big formula times b,
so now I'm getting Pb,
this is now the projection,
Pb, do you see that I get zero?
Of course I get zero.
Right at the end there,
A transpose b will give me zero
right away.
So that's why that zero's here.
Because if I'm perpendicular to
the column space,
then I'm in the null space of A
transpose and A transpose b is
zilch.
OK, what about the other
possibility.
How do I see that this formula
gives me the right answer if b
is in the column space?
So what's a typical vector in
the column space?
It's a combination of the
columns.
How do I write a combination of
the columns?
So tell me, how would I write,
you know, your everyday vector
that's in the column space?
It would have the form A times
some x, right?
That's what's in the column
space, A times something.
That makes it a combination of
the columns.
So these b's were in the null
space of A transpose.
These guys in the column space,
those b's are Ax-s.
Right?
If b is in the column space
then it has the form Ax.
I'm going to stick that on the
quiz or the final for sure.
That you have to realize --
because we've said it like a
thousand times that the things
in the column space are vectors
A times x.
OK.
And do you see what happens now
if we use our formula?
There's an A transpose A.
Gets canceled by its inverse.
We're left with an A times x.
So the result was Ax.
Which was b.
Do you see that it works?
This is that whole business.
Cancel, cancel,
leaving Ax.
And Ax was b.
So that turned out to be b,
in this case.
OK, so geometrically what we're
seeing is we're taking a vector
--
we've got the column space and
perpendicular to that is the
null space of A transpose.
And our typical vector b is out
here.
There's zero,
so there's our typical vector
b, and what we're doing is we're
projecting it to P.
And the --
and of course at the same time
we're finding the other part of
it which is e.
So the two pieces,
the projection piece and the
error piece, add up to the
original b.
OK.
That's like what our matrix
does.
So this is P -- P is --
this P is Ab,
is sorry -- is Pb,
it's the projection,
applied to b,
and this one is -- OK,
that's a projection too.
That's a projection down onto
that space.
What's a good formula for it?
Suppose I ask you for the
projection of the projection
matrix onto the --
this space, this perpendicular
space?
So if this projection was P,
what's the projection that
gives me e?
It's the -- what I want is to
get the rest of the vector,
so it'll be just I minus P
times b, that's a projection
too.
That's the projection onto the
perpendicular space.
OK.
So if P's a projection,
I minus P is a projection.
If P is symmetric,
I minus P is symmetric.
If P squared equals P,
then I minus P squared equals I
minus P.
It's just -- the algebra -- is
only doing what your --
picture is completely telling
you.
But the algebra leads to this
expression.
That expression for P given --
given a basis for the subspace,
given the matrix A whose
columns are a basis for our
column space.
OK, that's recap because you --
you need to see that formula
more than once.
And now can I pick up on using
it?
So now -- and the -- it's like,
let me do that again,
I'll go right through a problem
that I started at the end,
which is find a best straight
line.
You remember that problem,
I --
I picked a particular set of
points, they weren't specially
brilliant, t equal one,
two, three, the heights were
one, two, and then two again.
So they were -- heights were
that point, that point,
which makes it look like I've
got a nice forty-five-degree
line --
but then the third point didn't
lie on the line.
And I wanted to find the best
straight line.
So I'm looking for the -- this
line, y=C+Dt.
And it's not going to go
through all three points,
because no line goes through
all three points.
So I'm going to pick the best
line, the --
the best being the one that
makes the overall error as small
as I can make it.
Now I have to tell you,
what is that overall error?
And -- because that determines
what's the winning line.
If we don't know -- I mean we
have to decide what we mean by
the error --
and then we minimize and we
find the right -- the best C and
D.
OK.
So if I went through this -- if
I went through that point,
I would solve the equation
C+D=1.
Because at t equal to one --
I'd have C plus D,
and it would come out right.
If it went through this point,
I'd have C plus two D equal to
two.
Because at t equal to two,
I would like to get the answer
two.
At the third point,
I have C plus three D because t
is three, but the --
the answer I'm shooting for is
two again.
So those are my three
equations.
And they don't have a solution.
But they've got a best
solution.
What do I mean by best
solution?
So let me take time out to
remember what I'm talking about
for best solution.
So this is my equation Ax=b.
A is this matrix,
one, one, one,
one, two, three.
x is my -- only have two
unknowns, C and D,
and b is my right-hand side,
one, two, three.
OK.
No solution.
Three eq- I have a three by two
matrix, I do have two
independent columns --
so I do have a basis for the
column space,
those two columns are
independent, they're a basis for
the column space,
but the column space doesn't
include that vector.
So best possible in this --
what would best possible mean?
The way that comes out to
linear equations is I --
I want to minimize the sum of
these -- I'm going to make an
error here.
I'm going to make an error
here.
there.
And I'm going to sum and square
and add up those errors.
So it's a sum of squares.
It's a least squares solution
I'm looking for.
So if I --
those errors are the difference
between Ax and b.
That's what I want to make
small.
And the way I'm measuring this
-- this is a vector,
right?
This is e1,e2 ,e3.
The Ax-b, this is the e.
The error vector.
And small means its length.
The length of that vector.
That's what I'm going to try to
minimize.
And it's convenient to square.
If I make something small,
I make -- this is a never
negative quantity,
right?
The length of that vector.
The length will be zero exactly
when the --
when I have the zero vector
here.
That's exactly the case when I
can solve exactly,
b is in the column space,
all great.
But I'm not in that case now.
I'm going to have an error
vector, e.
What's this error vector in my
picture?
I guess what I'm trying to say
is there's --
there's two pictures of what's
going on.
There's two pictures of what's
One picture is -- in this is
the three points and the line.
And in that picture,
what are the three errors?
The three errors are what I
miss by in this equation.
So it's this -- this little bit
here.
That vertical distance up to
the line.
There's one -- sorry there's
one, and there's C plus D.
And it's that difference.
Here's two and here's C+2D.
So vertically it's that
distance -- that little error
there is e1.
This little error here is e2.
This little error coming up is
e3.
And what's my overall error?
Is e1 square plus e2 squared
plus e3 squared.
That's what I'm trying to make
small.
I -- some statisticians -- this
is a big part of statistics,
fitting straight lines is a big
part of science --
and specifically statistics,
where the right word to use
would be regression.
I'm doing regression here.
Linear regression.
And I'm using this sum of
squares as the measure of error.
Again, some statisticians would
be --
they would say,
OK, I'll solve that problem
because it's the clean problem.
It leads to a beautiful linear
system.
But they would be a little
careful about these squares,
for -- in this case.
If one of these points was way
off.
Suppose I had a measurement at
t equal zero that was way off.
Well, would the straight line,
would the best line be the same
if I had this fourth point?
Suppose I have this fourth data
point.
No, certainly the line would --
it wouldn't be the -- that
wouldn't be the best line.
Because that line would have a
giant error --
and when I squared it it would
be like way out of sight
compared to the others.
So this would be called by
statisticians an outlier,
and they would not be happy to
see the whole problem turned
topsy-turvy by this one outlier,
which could be a mistake,
after all.
So they wouldn't -- so they
wouldn't like maybe squaring,
if there were outliers,
they would want to identify
them.
OK.
I'm not going to -- I don't
want to suggest that least
squares isn't used,
it's the most used,
but it's not exclusively used
because it's a little --
overcompensates for outliers.
Because of that squaring.
OK.
So suppose we don't have this
guy, we just have these three
equations.
And I want to make -- minimize
this error.
OK.
Now, what I said is there's two
pictures to look at.
One picture is this one.
The three points,
the best line.
And the errors.
Now, on this picture,
what are these points on the
line, the points that are really
on the line?
So they're -- points,
let me call them P1,
P2, and P3, those are three
numbers, so this --
this height is P1,
this height is P2,
this height is P3,
and what are those guys?
Suppose those were the three
values instead of -- there's b1,
ev- everybody's seen all these
-- sorry, my art is as usual not
the greatest,
but there's the given b1,
the given b2,
and the given b3.
I promise not to put a single
letter more on that picture.
OK.
There's b1, P1 is the one on
the line, and e1 is the distance
between.
And same at points two and same
at points three.
OK, so what's up?
What's up with those Ps?
P1, P2, P3, what are they?
They're the components,
they lie on the line,
right?
They're the points which if
instead of one,
two, two, which were the b's,
suppose I put P1,
P2, P3 in here.
I'll figure out in a minute
what those numbers are.
But I just want to get the
picture of what I'm doing.
If I put P1,
P2, P3 in those three
equations, what would be good
about the three equations?
I could solve them.
A line goes through the Ps.
So the P1, P2,
P3 vector, that's in the column
space.
That is a combination of these
columns.
It's the closest combination.
It's this picture.
See, I've got the two pictures
like here's the picture that
shows the points,
this is a picture in a
blackboard plane,
here's a picture that's showing
the vectors.
The vector b,
which is in this case,
in this example is the vector
one, two, two.
The column space is in this
case spanned by the -- well,
you see A there.
The column space of the matrix
one, one, one,
one, two, three.
And this picture shows the
nearest point.
There's the -- that point P1,
P2, P3, which I'm going to
compute before the end of this
hour, is the closest point in
the column space.
OK.
Let me -- t
I don't dare leave it any
longer -- can I just compute it
now.
So I want to compute -- find P.
All right.
Find P.
Find x, which is CD,
find P and P.
OK.
And I really should put these
little hats on to remind myself
that they're the estimated the
best line, not the perfect line.
OK.
How do I proceed?
Let's just run through the
mechanics.
What's the equation for x?
The -- or x hat.
The equation for that is A
transpose A x hat equals A
transpose x -- A transpose b.
The most -- I'm -- will venture
to call that the most important
equation in statistics.
And in estimation.
And whatever you're -- wherever
you've got error and noise this
is the estimate that you use
first.
OK.
Whenever you're fitting things
by a few parameters,
that's the equation to use.
OK, let's solve it.
What is A transpose A?
So I have to figure out what
these matrices are.
One, one, one,
one, two, three and one,
one, one, one,
two, three, that gives me some
matrix, that gives me a matrix,
what do I get out of that,
three, six, six,
and one and four and nine,
fourteen.
OK.
And what do I expect to see in
that matrix and I do see it,
just before I keep going with
the calculation?
I expect that matrix to be
symmetric.
I expect it to be invertible.
And near the end of the course
I'm going to say I expect it to
be positive definite,
but that's a future fact about
this crucial matrix,
A transpose A.
OK.
And now let me figure A
transpose b.
So let me -- can I tack on b as
an extra column here,
one, two, two?
And tack on the extra A
transpose b is -- looks like
five and one and four and six,
eleven.
I think my equations are three
C plus six D equals five,
and six D plus fourt-six C plus
fourteen D is eleven.
Can I just for safety see if I
did that right?
One, one, one times one,
two, two is five.
One, two, three,
that's one, four and six,
eleven.
Looks good.
These are my equations.
That's my -- they're called the
normal equations.
I'll just write that word down
because it -- so I solve them.
I solve that for C and D.
I would like to -- before I
solve them could I do one thing
that's on the -- that's just
above here?
I would like to -- I'd like to
find these equations from
calculus.
I'd like to find them from this
minimizing thing.
So what's the first error?
The first error is what I
missed by in the first equation.
C plus D minus one squared.
And the second error is what I
miss in the second equation.
C plus two D minus two squared.
And the third error squared is
C plus three D minus two
squared.
That's my -- overall squared
error that I'm trying to
minimize.
OK.
So how would you minimize that?
OK, linear algebra has given us
the equations for the minimum.
But we could use calculus too.
That's a function of two
variables, C and D,
and we're looking for the
minimum.
So how do we find it?
Directly from calculus,
we take partial derivatives,
right, we've got two variables,
C and D, so take the partial
derivative with respect to C and
set it to zero,
and you'll get that equation.
Take the partial derivative
with respect -- I'm not going to
write it all out,
just -- you will.
The partial derivative with
respect to D,
it -- you know,
it's going to be linear,
that's the beauty of these
squares,that if I have the
square of something and I take
its derivative I get something
linear.
And this is what I get.
So this is the derivative of
the error with respect to C
being zero,
and this is the derivative of
the error with respect to D
being zero.
Wherever you look,
these equations keep coming.
So now I guess I'm going to
solve it, what will I do,
I'll subtract,
I'll do elimination of course,
because that's the only thing I
know how to do.
Two of these away from this
would give me -- let's see,
six, so would that be two Ds
equals one?
Ha.
So it wasn't -- I was afraid
these numbers were going to come
out awful.
But if I take two of those away
from that, the equation I get
left is two D equals one,
so I think D is a half and C is
whatever back substitution
gives, six D is three,
so three C plus three is five,
I'm doing back substitution
now, right, three,
can I do it in light letters,
three C plus that six D is
three equals five,
so three C is two,
so I think C is two-thirds.
One-half and two-thirds.
So the best line,
the best line is the constant
two-thirds plus one-half t.
And I -- is my picture more or
less right?
Let me write,
let me copy that best line down
again, two-thirds and a half.
Let me -- I'll put in the
two-thirds and the half.
OK.
So what's this P1,
that's the value at t equal to
one.
At t equal to one,
I have two-thirds plus a half,
which is -- what's that,
four-sixths and three-sixths,
so P1, oh, I promised not to
write another thing on this --
I'll erase P1 and I'll put
seven-sixths.
OK.
And yeah, it's above one,
and e1 is one-sixth,
right.
You see it all.
Right?
What's P2?
OK.
At point t equal to two,
where's my line here?
At t equal to two,
it's two-thirds plus one,
right?
That's five-thirds.
Two-thirds and t is two,
so that's two-thirds and one
make five-thirds.
And that's -- sure enough,
that's smaller than the exact
two.
And then final P3,
when t is three,
oh, what's two-thirds plus
three-halves?
It's the same as three-halves
plus two-thirds.
It's -- so maybe four-sixths
and nine-sixths,
maybe thirteen-sixths.
OK, and again,
look, oh, look at this,
OK.
You have to admire the beauty
of this answer.
What's this first error?
So here are the errors.
e1, e2 and e3.
OK, what was that first error,
e1?
Well, if we decide the errors
counting up, then it's
one-sixth.
And the last error,
thirteen-sixths minus the
correct two is one-sixth again.
And what's this error in the
middle?
Let's see, the correct answer
was two, two.
And we got five-thirds and it's
the other direction,
minus one-third,
minus two-sixths.
That's our error vector.
In our picture,
in our other picture,
here it is.
We just found P and e.
e is this vector,
one-sixth, minus two-sixths,
one-sixth, and P is this guy.
Well, maybe I have the signs of
e wrong, I think I have,
let me fix it.
Because I would like this
one-sixth -- I would like this
plus the P to give the original
b.
I want P plus e to match b.
So I want minus a sixth,
plus seven-sixths to give the
correct b equal one.
OK.
Now -- I'm going to take a deep
breath here, and ask what do we
know about this error vector e?
You've seen now this whole
problem worked completely
through, and I even think the
numbers are right.
So there's P,
so let me -- I'll write --
if I can put it down here,
B is P plus e.
b I believe was one,
two, two.
The nearest point had
seven-sixths,
what were the others?
Five-thirds and
thirteen-sixths.
And the e vector was minus a
sixth, two-sixths,
one-third in other words,
and minus a sixth.
OK.
Tell me some stuff about these
two vectors.
Tell me something about those
two vectors, well,
they add to b,
right, great.
OK.
What else?
What else about those two
vectors, the P,
the projection vector P,
and the error vector e.
What else do you know about
them?
They're perpendicular,
right.
Do we dare verify that?
Can you take the dot product of
those vectors?
I'm like getting like minus
seven over thirty-six,
can I change that to
ten-sixths?
Oh, God, come out right here.
Minus seven over thirty-six,
plus twenty over thirty-six,
minus thirteen over thirty-six.
Thank you, God.
OK.
And what else should we know
about that vector?
Actually we know -- I've got to
say we know even a little more.
This vector,
e, is perpendicular to P,
but it's perpendicular to other
stuff too.
It's perpendicular not just to
this guy in the column space,
this is in the column space for
sure.
This is perpendicular to the
column space.
So like give me another vector
it's perpendicular to.
Another because it's
perpendicular to the whole
column space,
not just to this -- this
particular projection that's --
that is in the column space,
but it's perpendicular to other
stuff, whatever's in the column
space, so tell me another vector
in the -- oh,
well, I've written down the
matrix, so tell me another
vector in the column space.
Pick a nice one.
One, one, one.
That's what everybody's
thinking.
OK, one, one,
one is in the column space.
And this guy is supposed to be
perpendicular to one,
one, one.
Is it?
Sure.
If I take the dot product with
one, one, one I get minus a
sixth, plus two-sixths,
minus a sixth,
zero.
And it's perpendicular to one,
two, three.
Because if I take the dot
product with one,
two, three I get minus one,
plus four, minus three,
zero again.
OK, do you see the -- I hope
you see the two pictures.
The picture here for vectors
and,
the picture here for the best
line, and it's the same picture,
just -- this one's in the plane
and it's showing the line,
this one never did show the
line, this -- in this picture,
C and D never showed up.
In this picture,
C and D were --
you know, they determined that
line.
But the two are exactly the
same.
C and D is the combination of
the two columns that gives P.
OK.
So that's these squares.
And the special but most
important example of fitting by
straight line,
so the homework that's coming
then Wednesday asks you to fit
by straight lines.
So you're just going to end up
solving the key equation.
You're going to end up solving
that key equation and then P
will be Ax hat.
That's it.
OK.
Now, can I put in a little
piece of linear algebra that I
mentioned earlier,
mentioned again,
but I never did write?
And I've --
I should do it right.
It's about this matrix A
transpose A.
There.
I was sure that that matrix
would be invertible.
And of course I wanted to be
sure it was invertible,
because I planned to solve this
system with with that matrix.
So and I announced like before
-- as the chapter was just
starting, I announced that it
would be invertible.
But now I -- can I come back to
that?
OK.
So what I said was -- that if A
has independent columns,
then A transpose A is
invertible.
And I would like to -- first to
repeat that important fact,
that that's the requirement
that makes everything go here.
It's this independent columns
of A that guarantees everything
goes through.
And think why.
Why does this matrix A
transpose A,
why is it invertible if the
columns of A are independent?
OK, there's -- so if it wasn't
invertible, I'm -- so I want to
prove that.
If it isn't invertible,
then what?
I want to reach -- I want to
follow that -- follow that line
--
of thinking and see what I come
to.
Suppose, so proof.
Suppose A transpose Ax is zero.
I'm trying to prove this.
This is now to prove.
I don't like hammer away at too
many proofs in this course.
But this is like the central
fact and it brings in all the
stuff we know.
OK.
So I'll start the proof.
Suppose A transpose Ax is zero.
What -- and I'm aiming to prove
A transpose A is invertible.
So what do I want to prove now?
So I'm aiming to prove this
fact.
I'll use this,
and I'm aiming to prove that
this matrix is invertible,
OK, so if I suppose A transpose
Ax is zero, then what conclusion
do I want to reach?
I'd like to know that x must be
zero.
I want to show x must be zero.
To show now -- to prove x must
be the zero vector.
Is that right,
that's what we worked in the
previous chapter to understand,
that a matrix was invertible
when its null space is only the
zero vector.
So that's what I want to show.
How come if A transpose Ax is
zero, how come x must be zero?
What's going to be the reason?
Actually I have two ways to do
it.
Let me show you one way.
This is -- here,
trick.
Take the dot product of both
sides with x.
So I'll multiply both sides by
x transpose.
x transpose A transpose Ax
equals zero.
I shouldn't have written trick.
That makes it sound like just a
dumb idea.
Brilliant idea,
I should have put.
OK.
I'll just put idea.
Now, I got to that equation,
x transpose A transpose Ax=0,
and I'm hoping you can see the
right way to -- to look at that
equation.
What can I conclude from that
equation, that if I have x
transpose A -- well,
what is x transpose A transpose
Ax?
Does that -- what it's giving
you?
It's again going to be putting
in parentheses,
I'm looking at Ax and what I
seeing here?
Its transpose.
So I'm seeing here this is Ax
transpose Ax.
Equaling zero.
Now if Ax transpose Ax,
so like let's call it y or
something, if y transpose y is
zero, what does that tell me?
That the vector has to be zero,
right?
This is the length squared,
that's the length of the vector
Ax squared,
that's Ax times Ax.
So I conclude that Ax has to be
zero.
Well, I'm getting somewhere.
Now that I know Ax is zero,
now I'm going to use my little
hypothesis.
Somewhere every mathematician
has to use the hypothesis.
Right?
Now, if A has independent
columns and we've -- we're at
the point where Ax is zero,
what does that tell us?
I could -- I mean that could be
like a fill-in question on the
final exam.
If A has independent columns
and if Ax equals zero then what?
Please say it.
x is zero, right.
Which was just what we wanted
to prove.
That -- do you see why that is?
If Ax eq- equals zero,
now we're using -- here we used
this was the square of
something, so I'll put in little
parentheses the observation we
made, that was a square which is
zero, so the thing has to be
zero.
Now we're using the hypothesis
of independent columns at the A
has independent columns.
If A has independent columns,
this is telling me x is in its
null space, and the only thing
in the null space of such a
matrix is the zero vector.
OK.
So that's the argument and you
see how it really used our
understanding of the --
of the null space.
OK.
That's great.
All right.
So where are we then?
That board is like the backup
theory that tells me that this
matrix had to be invertible
because these columns were
independent.
OK.
there's one case of independent
--
there's one case where the
geometry gets even better.
When the -- there's one case
when columns are sure to be
independent.
And let me put that -- let me
write that down and that'll be
the subject for next time.
Columns are sure --
are certainly independent,
definitely independent,
if they're perpendicular.
Oh, I've got to rule out the
zero column, let me give them
all length one,
so they can't be zero if they
are perpendicular unit vectors.
Like the vectors one,
zero, zero, zero,
one, zero and zero,
zero, one.
Those vectors are unit vectors,
they're perpendicular,
and they certainly are
independent.
And what's more,
suppose they're -- oh,
that's so nice,
I mean what is A transpose A
for that matrix?
For the matrix with these three
columns?
It's the identity.
So here's the key to the
lecture that's coming.
If we're dealing with
perpendicular unit vectors and
the word for that will be -- see
I could have said orthogonal,
but I said perpendicular -- and
this unit vectors gets put in as
the word normal.
Orthonormal vectors.
Those are the best columns you
could ask for.
Matrices with -- whose columns
are orthonormal,
they're perpendicular to each
other, and they're unit vectors,
well, they don't have to be
those three, let me do a final
example over here,
how about one at an angle like
that and one at ninety degrees,
that vector would be cos theta,
sine theta, a unit vector,
and this vector would be minus
sine theta cos theta.
That is our absolute favorite
pair of orthonormal vectors.
They're both unit vectors and
they're perpendicular.
That angle is ninety degrees.
So like our job next time is
first to see why orthonormal
vectors are great,
and then to make vectors
orthonormal by picking the right
basis.
OK, see you.
Thanks.