PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, we're going to take
a look at homogeneous
equations with constant
coefficients, and
specifically, the case where
we have real roots.
And we'll start the problem off
by looking at the equation
x dot dot plus 8x dot
plus 7x equals 0.
And we're asked to find the
general solution to this
differential equation.
And then we also have the
question, do all the solutions
go to 0 as t goes to infinity?
And then for part B, we're going
to take a look at just
the differential equation y
dot equals negative ky.
So this is the same equation
that we've seen in past
recitations.
And we're just going to show
that we can use this method to
solve this differential
equation and
obtain the same result.
And then lastly, we're asked,
or we're told that we have
eight routes to an eighth order
differential equation,
negative 4, negative 3, negative
2, negative 1,
0, 1, 2, and 3.
And we're asked, what is
the general solution.
So why don't you take a moment
and try and work these
problems out, and I'll
be back in a minute.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
OK, so we're asked to find the
general solution to x double
dot plus 8x dot plus
7x equals 0.
And we see that this is a
differential equation, it's
linear, and it has constant
coefficients.
And whenever we have a
differential equation that's
linear with constant
coefficients, one of the
standard ways to generate the
solution is to seek what
sometimes mathematicians call
an ansatz, but it's to try a
solution of the form x is equal
to a constant times e to
the st.
And if we substitute a solution
n of this form, we
see that taking the second
derivative of this function
pulls down two s's.
One derivative pulls
down one s.
We have no derivatives here.
And we also have, on each term,
a factor of c times e to
the st. And we want
this to be 0.
So specifically, ce to the st
can't be 0 for all time.
So the only way that this can
hold is if s squared plus 8s
plus 7 equals 0.
So what this means is if we
choose s to solve this
polynomial, then x
equals ce to the
st will be the solution.
And this will be the solution
for any constant, c.
OK, so what are the roots to
this algebraic equation.
Well, we can factorize it.
The roots are going to be
negative 7 and negative 1.
And notice how this whole
process has turned a
differential equation into a
simpler algebraic equation.
So if we can solve the algebraic
equation, then we
can solve the differential
equation.
OK, so the general solution.
Well, we've just shown that we
can take any constant times e
to the st, provided s is equal
to negative 1 or negative 7.
So the general solution is going
to be some constant, c1,
times e to the minus t, plus
c2 can be a different
constant, e to the minus 7t.
So notice how there's
two constants
in the final solution.
And the reason there's two
constants is because we
started out with a second-order
differential equation.
So, in some sense, for each
order of the differential
equation, we always
have one constant.
It's almost as if for each time
we integrate, we have a
constant of integration.
So at the end of the day, we
have two constants in our
general solution.
As part of part A, we're also
asked for any solution to this
differential equation, does the
solution go to 0 as t goes
to infinity?
Well, the general solution
has this form.
So for any constant c1 and c2,
the solution is c1 e to the
minus t plus c2, e
to the minus 7t.
And we see that no matter what
c1 and c2 are, this term, as t
goes to infinity, is multiplied
by e to the minus
t, which goes to 0.
And the second term
also goes to 0.
So as t goes to infinity, both
e to the minus t and e to the
minus 7t both go to 0.
So that means that any constant
times e to the minus
t plus any constant times
e to the minus 7t
must also go to 0.
So hence, x of t goes to 0
as t goes to infinity.
OK.
For part B, we have the
differential equation y dot
equals negative ky.
And this is the first-order
linear differential equation
with constant coefficients.
And we're going to use
the same trick.
We let y is equal to c times e
to the st. And we see that the
characteristic equation in
this case, it's not a
polynomial.
It's just s, s is equal
to negative k.
So we get y is equal to
c e to the negative kt
is the general solution.
And this is exactly what we had
in previous recitations,
when we used, for example,
integrating factors to solve
this very same differential
equation.
So this just shows that we can
use the same method to solve
first-order linear differential
equations.
OK.
Now, lastly, we're given eight
roots to an eighth-order
differential equation.
An eight-order differential
equations with constant
coefficients.
So I'll just write out
the roots again.
So we're told the roots are
negative 4, negative 3,
negative 2, negative
1, 0, 1, 2, and 3.
And in general, the solution
to an eighth-order
differential equation whose
roots to the characteristic
polynomial are negative 4
through 3, the general
solution, x of t, is going to
be a constant c1 times e to
the power of the first root,
which will be minus 4t, plus
c2 e to the minus 3t.
And of course, we
take different
constants for each term.
c3 e to the minus 2t, plus c4
e to the minus t, plus c5.
And now for this term, it should
be e to the 0t, but e
to the 0t is just 1.
So the zero root is just going
to give us a constant c5.
And we have c6 to the t, plus
c7 to the e to the 2t.
And then plus c8 e to the 3t.
So the solution has eight terms
and eight constants.
And just for fun, we can ask,
does every solution to this
differential equation go to
0 as t goes to infinity.
And the answer is no.
In fact, although each term with
a negative root does go
to zero as t goes to infinity,
there are three terms that go
to positive infinity as t goes
to infinity, and there's one
term that just stays constant.
So in general, as t grows, goes
to infinity, these terms
will become very large and won't
necessarily go to 0.
Well, they'll never go to 0.
So I'd just like to conclude
there, and I'll
see you next time.