PROFESSOR: Welcome back.
So in this session we're going
to cover homogeneous constant
coefficient equations
for any roots.
So we're told to assume that z
of t is equal to exponential
minus 3t times cosine
plus i of sine t.
And to assume that this complex
number is a solution
to this differential equation,
which is second order with
constant coefficients m, b,
and k, which are real, and
from this assumption
give two real
solutions to this equation.
In the second part, we're
asked to find a general
solution for this other
differential equation, which
is the same form as that seen
in part a, with now the real
values for b equals to
6, m equals to 1,
and k equals to 10.
And then we're asked of this
system that would be captured
by this differential equation is
overdamped or underdamped.
In the last part we switch gears
and we're given a series
of roots, eight roots to an
eighth degree polynomial, and
we're asked to write down the
general solution for that
polynomial.
Note that here we have repeated
roots, which is
basically where the trick is.
So why don't you take a few
minutes, and we'll come back
to solve these problems.
Welcome back.
So for the first part, we're
given a complex number clearly
split into its real part
and its imaginary part.
So this is the imaginary
part z, and this is the
real part of z.
Now, the differential equation
that we are given is constant
value, differential equation
second order, linear, and
homogeneous.
So there is no right-hand
side.
So clearly you can see that if
a complex number that can be
written as real part plus i
imaginary part is a solution
to this equation, then both
sides independently are also
solutions to this equation.
So by giving us this complex
number, we are actually given
two types of solutions that we
can then write down as two
linearly independent
solutions.
So the general solution to this
differential equation can
then be written in the form of
one constant coefficient is
undetermined, minus 3t cos
t plus another constant
coefficient minus
3t sine of t.
Where basically, we're
introducing linear combination
of two linearly independent
solutions that were just taken
from the original complex
number we were given.
So for the second part now, we
are asked to find a general
solution for the ODE.
We'll just rewrite
here for now.
So again, constant
coefficient, homogeneous equation.
And we're just asked to find
a general solution.
So we learned from the class
notes that we can use the
characteristic polynomial method
to solve this equation.
And the characteristic
polynomial here
will have this form.
And basically, we just need
to find the roots of this
characteristic polynomial to
be able then to express the
solutions of this homogeneous
constant coefficient equation
in terms of function,
exponential to whatever routes
we will find.
So I just want to write down
the discriminant of this
polynomial.
So what do we have here?
What was the question again?
So we're asked then
to just find the
discriminant for this equation.
So b squared minus 4t, which
is basically minus 4.
So we have a discriminant
that is negative.
And the roots for our polynomial
here are just going
to be the roots absolute value
of the discriminant with the
complex number i out, because
we had a negative
discriminant.
So these couple of solutions,
plus or minus, tell us that we
are going to have oscillations
as solutions for this
differential equation, and that
it's also going to be
actually damped oscillations,
because we have first the real
part of the number
being negative.
So let me just write down the
pair of solutions that we
would have. We will have this
that comes out of the real
part, cosine.
I'll put the root
of 4 is just 2.
And so we have cosine
t, that's 1.
6/2, of course, is just 3.
So here I switched directly to
writing them in cosine and
sine in the forms. But we could
also have kept it in the
complex form if we were solving
the equation in
complex space.
And then we would just have
complex exponentials here with
the frequencies omega,
angular frequency 1.
So this is the homogeneous
equation, the homogeneous
solution for this homogeneous
constant coefficient
differential equation.
Now, what do we see?
We can see that it's exactly
the same form that the
solution that we
had previously.
And so the question here is this
oscillator overdamped or
underdamped?
And as we see here, we're going
to have oscillations
that are damped by a pre-factor
of decaying
exponential minus 3t
for both cases.
So this is decaying.
So there is definitely
damping.
And we can see that here,
because we had a positive
value for b, which is
the damping term in
the oscillator system.
But there are still
oscillations, because we had a
discriminant that was negative,
which introduces
complex numbers, hence cosines
and sines, so basically,
oscillations.
Therefore we're in the case of
an underdamped response, an
underdamped system.
The discriminant was negative.
So for the last part of this
problem, we now leave this
differential equation, which was
second order, and move to
higher order differential
equations of eighth order.
And we're given eight roots.
4 minus 5i.
We have the root of 3, which
is real, which is repeated
three times, and a root 4 plus
or minus 5i, which is
repeated two times.
So we saw before then when we
have repeated roots, that
means that we would have, let's
say, in a second order
differential equation.
We would have in this case a
discriminant that would be
equal to 0.
And we would need to introduce
in a different type of
solution, because instead of
introducing an exponential of
plus rt exponential minus
rt, now we don't
have the minus rt.
So we need to seek another
type of solution.
And we'll multiply the
exponential by t.
So one type of solution for this
unique root that would
come out would be just 2t.
For the first of the tripled
root, it would be a 3t.
For the second one, we would
have t through t.
For the third one, we need
to go higher order, 3t.
Now we have complex roots, so
that gives us solutions of the
same form that we found
in questions a and b.
So I'm going to just write them
here, where now we have
the e4t cosine 5t plus
e4t sine 5t.
And for the repeated root,
it's the same game.
Even though we're in complex
roots to the same idea, we
need to multiply
all of it by t.
So these are the families of
linearly independent solutions
that would come out
of these roots.
So now the general solution is
simply the linear combination
of all these linearly
independent functions.
So we will introduce different
constants.
c5, c6, c7, and c8.
And we have eight undetermined
coefficients to deal with,
because these would be eight
roots of an eighth order
polynomial.
And so if we were to solve an
initial value problems like
that, we would need eight
different types of initial
conditions to determine the
values of these constants.
So to summarize, we used the
characteristic polynomial
method to solve these problems
introducing higher order
equations than the first
order differential
equations we saw before.
And what is important to
remember is that the different
types of solutions that you get,
depending on the roots of
the characteristic polynomial
and the sine of the
discriminant.
So whether the roots are real or
pure imaginary or imaginary
numbers will give three types
of the behavior, the
critically damped behavior.
If it's real then
it's going to be
just overdamped behavior.
And if the roots are complex,
then it would
be underdamped behavior.
Now when we are given different
types of roots, with
repeat roots it's important to
know how to construct the
solutions as well.
And that's by introducing new
types of functions where we're
multiplying by polynomial in t
in front of the exponential.
So that ends the session
for today.