PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
We've been talking in lecture
about antiderivatives.
So I have here a problem
for you.
Just an exercise about computing
an antiderivative.
So the question is
to compute an
antiderivative of this big fraction.
So on top it's got x to the
eighth plus 2x cubed minus x
to the 2/3 minus 3, that whole
thing over x squared.
So just a quick linguistic
note about why I said an
antiderivative instead of the
antiderivative and then I'll
let you work on it a little.
So an antiderivative.
There are many functions whose
derivative is this function.
Right?
So they all differ from each
other by constants.
So I would be happy
with and one as an
answer to this question.
That's why I chose the word
an antiderivative.
So I'm looking for a function
whose derivative is equal to
this function.
So why don't you take a couple
minutes, work this out, come
back and you can check your
answer against my work.
OK, welcome back.
So we were just talking about
this antiderivative here.
So one thing you'll notice about
this function is that
I've written this in a
sort of a silly form.
And it's probably a lot easier
to get a feel for what this
function is if you break this
fraction apart into its
several pieces.
So for example, x to
the eighth over x
squared is just x--
So, well OK, so let me, this
antiderivative that I'm
interested in, antiderivative
of x to the eighth plus 2x
cubed minus x to the 2/3 minus
3, over x squared dx.
So I've written this in a silly
form and you can get it
in a nicer form if you just
realize that, you know, this
is just a sum of powers of x
that I've put over this silly
common denominator.
So our life will be a little
simpler if we write this out
by splitting it up into the
separate fractions.
So if I do that, this is just
equal to the antiderivative of
well, x to the eighth
over x squared.
That's x to the sixth.
And 2x cubed over x
squared is just x.
So I have x-- sorry 2x--
plus 2x.
Now, OK so x to the 2/3
over x squared.
So that's x to the
2/3 minus 2.
Which is x to the minus 4/3.
And minus 3 over x squared, so
OK, so we could write that as
minus 3 over x squared, or
maybe it's a little more
convenient to write it as minus
3x to the minus 2 dx.
So far I haven't really done
anything, you know.
A little bit of algebra here.
OK, but now we know that we've
seen a formula for
antidifferentiating a
single power of x.
I mean we know how to
differentiate a single power
of x, and so to do an
antiderivative is just the
inverse process.
And we also know that when you
have the derivative of a sum,
it's the sum of derivatives.
And so consequently, if you have
the antiderivative of a
sum, it's just the sum of
the antiderivatives.
So we can write this out into
its constituent parts.
So it's the antiderivative of
x to the sixth dx plus--
now of course you don't
have to do this.
You could probably proceed just
from this step onwards,
or, but I don't see any
harm in actually
splitting it up myself.
So antiderivative of 2xdx minus,
OK, x to the minus 4/3
dx plus minus 3x to
the minus 2 dx.
So I've just split it up
into a bunch of pieces.
I guess this one I sort of
pulled the minus sign out and
this one I didn't.
But you know, whatever.
Either way.
OK so now we just need to
remember our formulas for
taking the antiderivative
of a power of x.
So in order to that, so when
you take a derivative, the
power goes down by one.
So if you take an antiderivative
to the power
will always go up by one.
So in this case you get,
so you're going to
get x to the seventh.
And now when you differentiate
x to the seventh, a 7 comes
down in front, right?
You get 7x to the sixth.
So in order to get just x to
the sixth, we have to also
divide by that 7 there.
So x to the sixth, the
antiderivative is x to the
seventh over 7.
2x, so that's going to give
us plus 2x squared over 2.
Or if you like, you could just
recognize right away that 2x
is the derivative
of x squared.
Minus--
OK now we've got minus powers.
Rather negative powers, so
that always is a little
trickier to keep track of.
So again, the same thing
is true though.
You have to, you add one
to the exponent.
The exponent goes up by
one when you take an
antiderivative.
It goes down by one when
you take a derivative.
So when you add 1 to minus
4/3 you get minus 1/3.
So we have x to the minus 1/3.
And now I have to divide
by minus 1/3.
When I take a derivative here we
get, of x to the minus 1/3,
I get minus 1/3 x to
the minus 4/3.
So I need to divide
by that minus 1/3.
OK.
And finally here so minus
3x to the minus 2.
So OK, so just like this first
one, you might recognize that
right off as the derivative
of x to the minus 3.
So this is plus--
Oh!
Ha ha!
You could do that if you were
completely confused like me.
So right, so x to the minus
2, it increased by one.
Increases by 1.
So when it increases by 1, you
get minus 1 not minus 3.
Oh!
OK, good.
So this is minus 3 times x to
the minus 1 over minus 1.
OK.
That's much better.
And if you like, right, so, OK,
so we could, any constant
we add to this, it'll still
be an antiderivative.
And now we can do a little bit
of arithmetic to arrange this
into nicer forms
if you wanted.
So you could rewrite this as
say, x to the seventh over 7
plus x squared plus 3x to the
minus 1/3 plus 3x to the minus
1 plus a constant.
Now, suppose you got here and
suppose that you did the same
mistake that I just made.
And you had accidentally thought
that this was going to
be a minus 1/3 power instead
of a minus first power.
So how would you, is there any
way that you can prevent
yourself making that mistake?
Well there actually is.
So one nice thing about
antiderivatives is that it's
really easy to check
your work.
After you've computed an
antiderivative, or something
that you think is
antiderivative, you can always
go back and take the derivative
of the thing that
you've computed and check
that it's equal to
what you started with.
So if you, if you're ever
worried that you made a
mistake computing an
antiderivative, one thing you
can always do is take a
derivative of what you've got
at the end.
So if we take a derivative of
here we get x to the sixth
plus 2x minus x to the minus 4/3
minus 3x to the minus 2.
OK?
So that was just using our rule
for powers one by one.
And OK, so you say that out loud
or write it down and then
you just check.
Right?
So I said that, so that's
exactly the same thing we've
got right here.
Yeah?
So x to the sixth plus 2x minus
x to the minus 4/3 minus
3x to the minus 2.
So one of the nicest things
about antiderivatives, they
can be difficult to figure out
in the first place, but after
you've got something that you
think is antiderivative it's
very easy to go back and check
whether you did it correctly
by taking the derivative and
making sure that it matches
the thing that you
were trying to
antidifferentiate at the beginning.
So that's that.