Problem number 4.
26-21.
I have a 12 volt battery
and it has a
capacitance of 60 amp hours.
It has an internal resistance
of 0.31 ohm.
And it takes 4 hours to
charge it at 15 amps.
It's a given.
You get 60 amp hours.
Now here is one end
of the battery.
Here is the negative side
Here the positive side.
Here is the 12 volts.
Let's call this point 'b'.
Then here is the internal
resistance of the battery,
which you know.
And then here is the terminal
of the battery.
These are the only two points
that you have access to.
Now you are going to charge
this battery.
But how are you going to
charge this battery?
You are going to put
in here a current.
A charge current given
to be 15 amperes.
Clearly, if you want to
discharge the battery through
some flashlight or something
else, the current will flow in
this direction and the battery
would discharge.
Therefore, if you charge the
battery you have to put the
current in the opposite
direction, which is exactly
what I am doing here.
And the question now is, what is
'Vc', if I call this point
'c', minus 'Va'?
To while I'm charging, what is
this potential difference?
Well, 'Vc' minus 'Va'
is ''Vc' minus 'Vb''
plus ''Vb' minus 'Va''.
But this is 12 volts.
And this is that charging
current of 15 amperes times
the internal resistance.
You know 'i', you know 'Ri', you
know 12, and so you find
immediately that
'Vc' minus 'Va'
happens to be 16.65 volts.
And it shouldn't surprise
you that you
have to use a battery.
Because effectively what you're
doing is you're going
to, of course, attach
a battery to here.
[WHISTLES]
With the plus side here and the
minus side here to drive
that current through this
battery against its own will,
so to speak.
That this battery needs a larger
EMF of 16.65 volts in
order to charge up this battery,
which itself will
only deliver 12 volts.
Reason being this internal
resistance.
What is now the total
energy that is
supplied during charging?
Well, during charging the total
energy, the total power,
I should say, that is supplied
is the total voltage that I
applied, which is the 16.65,
times the total power,
which is the 15.
And if I did not make
a mistake, I
believe it is 250 watts.
You better check that.
So this is the total power
that is delivered to the
battery during the charging.
Now in 4 hours, which is 4
times 3,600 seconds, the
amount of joules that I pump
into the battery is, of
course, the time times
the power.
And that, I found, is 3.6 times
10 to the sixth joules.
That's almost a little more
than 3.5 million joules.
But now comes an interesting
question under c.
As I am charging, how much
energy is dissipated in that
internal resistance
in the battery?
Well, that is of course, the
time, which is the same as 4
times 3,600 seconds, times the
current squared through that
internal resistance, which is
your 15 amperes, times the
internal resistance itself,
which you also know is 0.31
ohms.
And you find now that this
is a huge amount.
That this is 1 million joules.
So you put in 3.6.
But as you put in 3.6 in
the whole system--
that means you put it both
in the battery and in the
internal resistance--
1 million of that gets lost in
terms of heat of that internal
resistance.
Internal resistance gets
hot and its gone.
You're heating up
the universe.
1 million joules.
So when the battery is
completely discharged, and I
do that through a external
resistor.
Here is your 'Ri'.
Here is your 12 volts.
Your terminals of
your battery.
And I'm going to, here, put now
an external resistance.
This charging this battery.
And I'm going to discharge this
battery at a current of
15 amperes--
that's what you're
being told--
and it will take 4 hours because
the battery has a
capacity of 60 amp hours.
So for 4 hours, will
this continue?
Let's assume that the current
remains constant, which is a
little bit naive to think
because this value for 'Ri'
will probably go up with time.
But we ignore that for
now for convenience.
And now what we are being asked
is what now is this
external resistance?
Well, I would suggest that
we use Kirchhoff's Law.
We start here, we go all the
way around the circle, and
then the sum of all potential
differences--
I will write that down in
shorthand notation--
going all the way around must
be 0 in this problem.
Now, I'm going to make an
agreement with you.
Whenever I go uphill--
that means whenever I
go up in potential--
I call that plus, and then
whenever I go downhill I call
that minus.
You don't have to do that.
You can reverse this and your
answer will be no different.
So I'm going to start here,
and I'm going to go around
counter clockwise.
If you prefer to go around
clockwise it would make no
difference.
So be careful.
The current comes to me.
The resistance is
'R external', so
I'm going up in potential.
The potential here is
higher than here.
Uphill is plus.
So I've got 15 times
are 'R external'.
Now the current here is
also coming to me.
So I also go from a lower
potential to a higher potential.
So I get plus 0.31 times
the same, 15 amperes.
But here now I go down
in potential.
And when I go down in potential
we agreed it would
be a minus sign.
So this is minus 12 equals 0.
I know everything in this
equation except this.
And I find, I believe, 0.49
ohms. So that is now the
external resitor.
And now comes the question, how
much energy is supplied to
this external resistor
during the discharge?
Well, the discharge
takes 4 hours.
There you go.
I must multiply that by ''i'
squared R' going through that
external resistor, times the
external resistor itself.
You know all numbers.
And what do you find?
1.6 times 10 to the
sixth joules.
And now the question is, where
is all this energy now?
To charge it up we needed
3.6 million joules.
But while we were charging we
lost 1 million to this stupid
internal resistor.
In terms of heat.
And now we are discharging
and it seems that we
lot another 1 million.
Because we only end
up with 1.6.
Here.
3.6 went to 1.6.
So where did this other 1
million go to when I was
discharging?
So what it comes down
to is, we lost 2
million joules somehow.
And I would like you to
tell me exactly when
and where and how.