JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about planes and
their equations and various
different geometric problems
relating to them.
So I have an example of
such a problem here.
So I've got a point, which
happens to be the origin--
which I'm going to call P--
0, 0, 0.
And I've got a plane which has
the equation 2x plus y minus
2z is equal to 4.
And what I'd like you to do is
compute the distance from that
point to that plane.
So just to remind you, so there
are lots of points on a
plane, of course.
And our point in question has
a distance to each of them.
When we talk about the distance
between a point and a
plane, what we mean is the
shortest distance.
So the perpendicular distance.
So if we have the plane and we
have the point, so we want to
drop a perpendicular from the
point to the plane, and then
we're asking for that length
of that segment.
So that's the distance between
the point and the plane.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a little while to
figure this out, come
back, and we can
figure it out together.
So hopefully you had some luck
working out this problem.
Let's think about
it a little bit.
We have a point and we have a
plane, and we want to figure
out what the perpendicular
distance from the point
to the plane is.
So one thing that's going
to be important then is
definitely knowing what
direction that vector is.
Right?
We have the plane and we want
to find a perpendicular
segment to it.
And so in order to do that,
it's useful to know what
direction is that segment
pointing in.
So luckily, we're given
the plane in this
simple equation form.
So the normal to the plane--
and when you're given
an equation of a
plane in this form--
the normal vector is just given
by the coefficients of
x, y, and z.
So in our case, the plane is 2x
plus y minus 2z equals 4,
so the normal vector to
this plane is the
vector 2, 1, minus 2.
So this is the direction in
which we need to go from our
point P in order to get
to the plane by
the shortest distance.
So now what we need is we need
to know the component of-- or
sorry, rather-- we need to know
the actual distance we
have to travel in
that direction.
So one way to do this is
if we go back to our
little picture here.
We don't know what
this point is.
We don't know when we start
from P and head in the
direction perpendicular to the
plane, we don't know what
point we're going to land
on the plane at.
But what we could do is,
if we knew some other
point on the plane--
somewhere--
we could look at the vector
connecting P to that other
point, and then we
could project it
onto the normal direction.
So we could take the component,
so let's call this
other point Q. So if we choose
any point Q in the plane that
we're looking at, we could take
the vector PQ and we can
project it onto this
normal vector.
And if we take the component
of this vector, project it
onto that normal vector--
if we take the component of this
vector in the direction
of the normal vector--
what that will give
us is exactly the
length of this segment.
Yeah?
That projection will be exactly
the perpendicular
segment we're looking for.
And its length, the
component--
or the absolute value of the
component, perhaps--
will be exactly that distance.
So good.
So then we just have to compute,
well we need to find
a point Q and we need to
compute a component.
So we need any point
on the plane.
So, actually I'm going to
walk back over here.
And to find a point on the
plane, we can just do this by
looking at the equation.
So one way to go about this, for
example, is that you pick
a variable that appears
in the equation.
So x appears in the equation.
And now you could just
set all the other
variables equal to 0.
And that will give you something
you can solve for x.
So in particular, you know,
there's a point on this plane
with y equals z equals 0, and
that point has 2x equals 4.
So we can take, for example,
Q to be the point 2, 0, 0.
So this is a point
on the plane.
So this is our point on the
plane, and so we have, what we
want to do is we want
to project--
so PQ, the vector from P to PQ,
we get by subtracting the
coordinates of P from those of
Q. Q minus P. So this is the
vector 2, 0, 0.
And we want the component of
PQ in the direction N.
So the distance in
question is the--
and really, when I say component
in this case, I mean
the positive component I want.
Because the distance
has to be positive.
So if I get a negative
component, I really want its
absolute value here.
So the distance is the positive
component in the
direction N.
So what's that equal to?
Well, it's just equal to the
absolute value of-- so we know
the component of PQ in the
direction N is what we get
when we take--
PQ and we dot it with N divided
by the length of N,
and then to make sure it's
positive at the end, I want to
throw in these absolute
values signs.
So OK.
So this is, and this is now, you
know, we have our vector
PQ and we have our vector
N, so it should be
straightforward to compute
this final expression.
So we know that N is equal
to 2, 1, minus 2.
So the length of N-- which is
in the denominator here--
is equal to the square root of
2 squared plus 1 squared plus
minus 2 squared.
And in the numerator, we have
the absolute value of PQ dot
N. So PQ dot N is going to be
2 times 2, plus 0 times 1,
plus 0 times minus 2.
OK.
And so if we-- and this is
just a fraction bar here.
And so we simplify that
a little bit.
So up top, we just have 4--
plus 0 plus 0 is 4.
And on the bottom, we have the
square root of 2 squared plus
1 squared plus 2 squared.
That's going to be the square
root of 9, which is 3.
So this is just equal to 4/3.
So there we go.
The distance in question
is 4/3.
The way we got it is we realized
that that distance is
just the component
of any segment--
any vector--
connecting our point P
to the plane in the
direction of the normal.
So you choose any vector PQ.
So, you know, you just have to
come up with a point Q on the
plane, which you can do by
inspection from the equation.
So that gives you a vector that
gets you from P to some
point on the plane, and then
you choose the component in
the normal direction.
And so once you do that,
you get this
distance: your answer.
So I'll end there.