JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've begun
learning about various
different ways to describe
planes in
three dimensional space.
In particular, there are
equations and ways you can
translate between other
characterizations.
So I have here four different
planes for you described in
four different ways, and what
I'd like you to do is try and
figure out what the equations
for each of
these four planes are.
So let me see what they are.
So we've got the first
one-- part a--
we have a plane where I'm giving
you its normal vector
N, which is the vector
1, 2, 3.
And I'm going to tell you that
the plane is passing through
the point 1, 0, minus 1.
In part b, I'm telling you that
the plane passes through
the origin, and also that it's
parallel to two vectors.
It's parallel to the vector 1,
0, minus 1, and to the vector
minus 1, 2, 0.
In part c, I'm telling you that
a plane passes through
the points 1, 2, 0--
3, 1, 1--
and 2, 0, 0.
And in part d, I'm telling you
that the plane is parallel to
the plane in part a, and also
that it passes through the
point 1, 2, 3.
So what I'd like you to do is
try for each of these four
descriptions, figure out what
the equation of the
associated plane is.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a few minutes,
work those all out, come
back, and we can
work them out together.
So hopefully you had some luck
working on these problems.
Let's get started.
So we may as well start
with the first one.
So in part a, we're given that
the normal vector N is the
vector i plus 2j plus 3k, or
1, 2, 3 and that it passes
through the point P--
which I'm going to call P--
1, 0, minus 1.
So this is a form you
learned in lecture.
And so it's pretty
straightforward to write down
the equation here.
The thing to remember is that
if a point x, y, z is on the
plane, then we have to have
that the vector N--
the normal--
is orthogonal to the vector
connecting the point x, y, z
to the point we know.
So that's the vector x
minus 1, y minus 0--
which is just y--
z plus 1.
So N and this vector that lies
in the plane have to be
orthogonal, so their dot
product has to be 0.
And now you just multiply
this out.
So in our case, so N is 1, 2,
3, and you take the dot
product with x minus 1, y, z,
and you get 1 times x minus 1,
plus 2 times y, plus 3 times
z plus 1, equals 0.
So that's the equation
of the plane.
You could also rewrite this
a bunch of different ways.
For example, you could multiply
through and collect
all the constants together.
So you could write this
as x plus 2y plus 3z--
and then we've got a minus 1
plus 3, so that's plus 2--
equals 0.
So these are two different
possible
forms for that equation.
And you can, you know, sometimes
people write the
constant over on this
side instead of
leaving 0 over there.
All right.
So several different, equivalent
ways to rewrite it.
All right.
So there's the equation
for part a.
Now let's take a
look at part b.
So for part b we have--
let's go just back and
remind ourselves what
the question was--
so we have a plane that passes
through the origin.
So we know a point on the plane,
and we know that it's
parallel to the two vectors 1,
0, minus 1, and minus 1, 2, 0.
OK.
So we've got a point and we have
two direction vectors.
And so that definitely describes
a plane for us, as
long as the two directions
aren't parallel, which they
aren't in this case.
So the question is how do we
figure out what the equation
for that plane is?
Well, we have this nice way of
figuring out equations for
planes when we know a
point and a normal.
And we know a point, so what
would be great is if we could
come up with a normal direction
to this plane.
So OK.
So we have two vectors in the
plane, and we want to find a
vector that's perpendicular
to the plane.
Well, we have a nice tool when
you're given two vectors to
figure out a vector
perpendicular to both of them,
and that's to take the
cross product.
So our normal vector should be
the cross product of these two
vectors, or, you know,
any multiple of
it would do as well.
So for part b, the normal N
should be the cross product of
the two vectors that are in the
plane, so it should be the
cross product of 1,
0, minus 1, and--
what's the other one--
minus 1, 2, 0.
So, all right, so we just have
to compute what that cross
product is.
So this is a determinant whose
first row is i, j, k, and
whose second and third
rows are the two
vectors we're crossing.
And OK, so we can
expand this out.
So, if you like,
so this is i--
the coordinate of i is going
to be 0 minus minus
2, so that's 2.
The coordinate of j is going
to be the negative of the
determinant of this minor,
which is 0 minus minus
1 times minus 1.
So the determinant of the
minor is minus 1, so the
coordinate of j is going
to be plus 1.
And the coordinate of k is the
determinant of this minor,
which is just 2.
So the normal vector in this
case is the vector 2, 1, 2.
So OK.
So now we've got a normal vector
and we have a point.
We were given that the plane
passes through the origin.
So the equation, using
the same idea as in
the previous question.
So the origin is just 0, 0, 0.
That's a nice point to know
it passes through.
So the equation is just 2x plus
y plus 2z is equal to 0.
So this is the equation
in part b.
All right.
So part c, we're given
that the plane passes
through three points.
So once again, three points.
So we have a point
in particular.
We have three of them.
And so what we need then
to get to the equation
is we need a normal.
And we saw in part b that we
could get a normal if we knew
two vectors that lay
in the plane.
So in this case, we
have three points.
So what we'd like is to find
two vectors that lie in the
plane, and then use those two
vectors to come up with a
normal to the plane.
So in our case that's
particularly--
well, in any case--
that's not that hard.
You have three points, right?
So you have three points
somewhere, P, Q, and R. And so
if you want to know two vectors
in the same plane as
these three points, well, you
could just take the vectors
that connect one of the points
to two of others, for example.
So in our case, the plane--
since the plane passes through
the points 1, 2, 0, and 3, 1,
1, and what's the last
one, 2, 0, 0.
So the plane is parallel to--
well, it doesn't matter which
one we choose, so for example,
we can say the vector that
goes from here to here, so we
take this and subtract that
from it, so that would give
us, for example--
2, minus 1, 1.
And we could say the vector from
here to here, so we take
this and subtract
that from it.
And that will give
us 1, minus 2, 0.
So from three points we could
get two vectors that are
parallel to the plane.
And we have a choice
of a point to use.
We could use, for example,
the same point 1, 2,
0 as our base point.
And so then we can go back
and do exactly what
we did in part b.
So with those two vectors, you
can take their cross product,
and find a normal vector
to the plane.
So I'm not going to
do that for you.
I'll leave that for you
as an exercise.
Finally, in part d, we have a
plane that's parallel to the
plane in part a, and passes
through 1, 2, 3.
The point 1, 2, 3.
So let me just rewrite over
here, parallel to-- so the
plane in part a had equation--
x plus 2y plus 3z plus 2 equals
0, and passing through
the point 1, 2, 3.
All right.
So this is the information that
we know about our plane
in this case.
We know that it's parallel to
the plane with this equation,
and that it passes through
the point 1, 2, 3.
Well, it's parallel
to this plane.
Two planes are parallel exactly
when they have the
same normal vector.
So remember that the normal
vector here is always going to
be encoded by these coefficients
of x, y, z.
In part a, this plane had normal
vector 1, 2, 3, and
that 1, 2, 3 shows up in the
coefficient of x, coefficient
of y, and coefficient of z,
which are 1, 2, and 3,
respectively.
So to get parallel planes when
you have the equation already,
one thing you could do is you
can just say, oh, so that just
means I leave these coefficients
the same, and I
have to change the constant.
Another thing you could do is
you could just go back to our
definition and say, OK, so
we know that the normal
vector is 1, 2, 3--
the vector 1, 2, 3--
and that it passes through
the point 1, 2, 3.
Either of these two
methods will work.
So let me describe, let me show
you what this second,
this new method I
mentioned is.
So we know that the equation of
the plane has to be x plus
2y plus 3z plus something--
that's a big question
mark there--
equal to 0.
We know that the equation of the
plane is going to have to
look like this.
Because it has the same normal
vector, it has to be parallel
to this plane.
And so then we just need to
figure out what goes into this
box in order to make this the
equation of the right plane.
Well, what else do we know?
We know that it passes through
the point 1, 2, 3.
So when we put in 1 for x, 2
for y, and 3 for z, this
equation has to be true.
This point 1, 2, 3 has to be a
solution to this equation.
So when we put in 1, 2, and 3,
we have to have that 1, plus 2
times 2, plus 3 times 3, plus
that same question mark, is
equal to 0.
Well, this part is 1 plus 4
plus 9 is 14, so 14 plus
whatever goes in here has to be
equal to 0, so this better
be equal to negative 14.
Negative 14.
So the equation for the plane in
that case is exactly x plus
2y plus 3z minus 14 equals 0.
Now, if you didn't like that
method, the other thing you
can do-- which I said before,
let me just repeat it-- is
that since it's parallel to this
plane, it has the same
normal vector.
And we knew that the normal
vector to this
plane was 1, 2, 3.
So you have a normal vector--
the vector 1, 2, 3-- and you
have a point--
the point 1, 2, 3-- and so you
can just use the usual process
given a point and
a normal vector.
So just to recap, we
had four different
characterizations of a plane.
We had a plane given in terms
of its normal vector and a
point that it contains.
We had a plane given in terms
of a point and two vectors
parallel to it.
We had a plane given in terms
of three points on it.
And we had a plane given in
terms of a point and of
another plane parallel to it.
So we have in all these
different cases, we can apply
different methods to compute
the equation of our plane.
So in the first case, we just
do this very straightforward
computation that you saw
on lecture here.
Where you just realize that the
normal vector has to be
orthogonal to the vector
lying in the plane.
So you take their dot product
and that gives you the
equation right away.
In the second case, where you
had two parallel vectors--or
sorry, yeah--
two parallel vectors to the
plane-- two vectors lying in
the plane--
you need to come up
with a normal.
And you can always come up
with a normal by taking a
cross product of those
two vectors, as
long as you're careful.
If you accidentally chose your
two vectors parallel to each
other, that wouldn't work.
You'd just get 0 here,
and that's no good.
But, so you have to choose two
non-parallel vectors in the
plane in order to
make this work.
In the third case, you
have three points.
And so with three points what
you can do is you can choose
two vectors connecting
some of those points.
And that gives you two vectors
that lie in the plane, and
that reduces to the case of the
previous part, and then
again, you can take
a cross product to
get a normal vector.
Finally, we did this fourth
problem where we were given a
plane parallel to it.
And so you can read off the
normal vector from the
coefficients of x, y, and
z in the equation.
And then either use the very
first method with a point and
normal vector, or just realize
that you just have to find the
appropriate value of the
constant so that this point
actually lies on the plane.
So I'll end there.