CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I want us to work
on the following problem,
which is to show that this
vector field is not
conservative.
And the vector field is minus
yi plus xj all divided by x
squared plus y squared.
So you can think about this in
two separate components, if
you need to, as minus y divided
by x squared plus y
squared i plus x over x squared
plus y squared j.
So that's really exactly
the same thing.
So your object is to show that
this vector field is not
conservative.
And why don't you work on that
for awhile, pause the video,
and then when you're ready to
see my solution you can bring
the video back up.
So welcome back.
Well, maybe some of you thought
I had a typo in this
problem initially, and I wanted
you to show it , in
fact, was conservative, but it
actually is not a conservative
vector field.
And let me explain how we can
show it is not conservative
and why probably what you
did initially to try
and show it was not--
didn't work.
So maybe that wording was a
little confusing, but let me
take you through it.
So the first thing I would
imagine you tried is you
looked at m sub y and n sub x.
So m in this case is
negative y over x
squared plus y squared.
And N in this case, capital N in
this case, is x divided by
x squared plus y squared.
So if you worked that out, you
probably did or maybe you
didn't, and I'll
just show you.
M sub y-- let me just
double check--
is y squared minus x squared
over x squared plus y squared,
I think with an extra
squared on it.
Yeah.
And that's also equal
to N sub x.
Right?
So what you know so far, what
you might have thought
immediately, was well, N sub x
minus M sub y is the curl of F
and that's equal to 0, and
therefore this vector field is
conservative.
But the problem is the theorem
you were thinking about
referencing doesn't hold.
And the reason is because there
are two hypotheses in
that theorem.
And one is that if I define this
vector field, if I call
it capital F, the
vector field--
or the theorem is that capital F
defined everywhere, and curl
of F equal to 0, implies
F conservative.
OK.
So that's the theorem you might
have been trying to use.
You see from this the curl of F
equals 0, but the problem is
the first part of this
statement, that F being
defined everywhere,
is not true.
In fact, there's one place in r2
where this vector field is
not defined, and that is
when x is 0 and y is 0.
Because at that point,
obviously, the denominator is
zero and we run into trouble.
So you cannot use this theorem
to say F is conservative
because it's not defined
everywhere.
Or I should be careful
how I say that.
There is somewhere that
it is not defined.
So even though the curl of F
equals 0, the first part of
the statement is not true.
So you cannot get anything
out of this theorem.
So knowing the curl of F equals
0 doesn't tell you
whether it's conservative
or not.
OK?
So now what I'm going to do
is I'm going to show--
I told you we want to show
it's not conservative.
I'm going to show you how
we can show that.
And what we're going to do is
we're going to find a loop, a
closed loop.
So a closed curve in R2 that
when I integrate this vector
field over that closed curve,
I don't get zero.
And then we would know that
the vector field is not
conservative.
So that's what we're
going to do.
So let me write it out
explicitly and then we'll
figure out the curve we want
and then we'll parameterize
the curve appropriately.
So I'm going to show for
some closed curve.
I'm going to pick my curve and
I'm going to integrate over
the closed curve and I'm going
to integrate this.
Minus y over x squared plus
y squared dx plus x over x
squared plus y squared dy.
And I'm going to show that if
I pick a certain curve, I'm
going to get something that's
not equal to zero, OK?
And the curve I'm going to
pick is the unit circle.
So we're going to let C
be the unit circle.
Let C equal--
I'll just write the
unit circle.
But how can I parameterize
the unit circle easily?
I can parameterize the unit
circle easily by x equal to
cosine theta and y equal
to sine theta.
So let me do that.
And why am I picking
the unit circle?
We'll see why that
is in a second.
So we're going to let x
equal cosine theta and
y equal sine theta.
And so now we know what
goes here and we
know what goes here.
By the way, what is x squared
plus y squared?
It's cosine squared theta plus
sine squared theta, which is
equal to 1.
This is exactly the square of
the radius and since we're on
the unit circle, that's 1.
That's why I picked the unit
circle because I wanted the
denominator to be very simple.
So I've got the x's
and the y's.
Now what's dx?
dx is going to be equal to
minus sine theta d theta.
And what's dy?
I'll just write it right
underneath here.
dy is going to equal cosine
theta d theta.
So let me just point out again
what we were doing here.
We want to parameterize
the unit circle.
I chose to parameterize it in
theta, which I haven't told
you what my bounds are yet, but
I've done everything else.
I needed to know what x
and y were and also
what dx and dy were.
And so now I can start
substituting in.
So let's figure out what I get
when I start substituting in.
I'm integrating now.
Again, I said I didn't
mention the bounds.
What are the bounds on theta to
get the whole unit circle?
I'm just going to integrate
from 0 to 2 pi.
So I integrate from 0 to 2 pi.
That takes me all the way
around the circle.
Minus y is negative
sine theta.
This part is 1 as I
mentioned earlier.
And then dx is minus
sine theta d theta.
So I have a minus sine theta
times a minus sine theta.
That's going to give me a sine
squared theta d theta.
And then this term, the second
term, when I integrate over
the curve, I'm going to just
rewrite another one here
separately momentarily.
x is cosine theta.
x squared plus y squared is 1.
And dy is cosine
theta d theta.
So I get cosine squared
All right?
Now here we are.
If I tried to integrate both of
these separately, it would
take potentially a very long
time and be kind of annoying.
But if you notice, because I can
add these integrals, I can
add over they have the
same bounds, so I can
put them back together.
Sine squared theta plus cosine
squared theta always equals 1.
That's a trig identity
that's good to know.
So this in fact is equal
to the integral from 0
to 2 pi of d theta.
So let me come back one more
time and make sure we
understand.
We're integrating from 0 to 2 pi
sine squared theta d theta
plus cosine squared
theta d theta.
That's just sine squared
theta plus cosine
squared theta d theta.
So that's 1.
So 1 times d theta.
But what is this?
Well, this integral from 0 to
2 pi of d theta is theta
evaluated at 2 pi and 0.
I actually get 2 pi, which
is in particular
not equal to 0, right?
So that actually shows you that
this vector field is not
conservative.
Now why does this make sense?
This makes sense because
if I really think
about what I'm doing--
actually, this is the place
where maybe it'll ultimately
make the most sense--
what you're doing is you're
looking at how theta changes
as you go all the way around
the origin once.
And theta changes by 2 pi.
If you go all the way around
one time, the theta value
starts at 0 and then
goes up to 2 pi.
And so that's exactly where
this 2 pi is coming from.
So that actually is ultimately
how you were going to be able
to show that this vector field
is not conservative.
So let me go back and just
remind you where we came from.
We started off with a vector
field and we wanted to know if
it was not conservative.
We wanted to show-- sorry--
So the first thing you might
want to check, which maybe you
did, was if the curl was zero.
And in fact the curl is zero.
And so maybe you thought, well,
she might have done
something wrong, or she might
have written something wrong.
But we can't actually appeal
to the theorem you want to
appeal to to make any conclusion
about the vector
field because the vector field
in our example is not defined
for every value of (x,y).
So for every value in the
xy-plane, we cannot define F.
There's one value for which we
cannot define F. And so we
cannot say that if the curl's
0, then the vector field is
conservative.
We can't draw any conclusions
from this theorem.
So then we had to actually find
a way to show it was not
conservative without looking
at the curl.
And that amounts to showing
there is a closed curve that
when I integrate over that
closed curve-- when I look at
what the vector field does
over that closed curve--
I get something non-zero.
And we picked an easy example.
This is actually what the
integral will look like over
the closed curve in x and y.
We let our closed curve be
the unit circle, then we
parameterized in theta.
And we see that actually what
this vector field is doing is
it's looking at what
is d theta?
It's finding out what
d theta is.
And so we find out the integral
from 0 to 2 pi of d
theta is obviously not zero.
And that gives us that the
vector field's not
conservative.
So that's where I'll stop.