PROFESSOR: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, I'd like to take a
look at solving a linear ODE
but with a periodic input.
And specifically, we're asked
to find one solution of a
particular solution which is
also the periodic solution of
the differential equation, x
dot, dot plus 2x dot plus 4x
equals the square
wave function.
So the square wave function is
a periodic function with
period 2pi is to find as minus 1
and 1 on the intervals minus
pi to 0 and 0 to pi.
And we know that the square
wave function has the
following Fourier series.
So I'll let you think about
this problem for a moment.
And I'll come back
in a second.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So the reason we've been
studying Fourier series is to
essentially solve differential
equations with complicated
forcing inputs on
the right-hand
side which are periodic.
And the reason we've been
studying Fourier series is
because we know that
differential equations with
sines and cosines as forcing
terms on the right-hand side
are relatively easy to solve.
And we want to be able to solve
the same differential
equation with a more complicated
periodic function
on the right-hand side.
So the general approach is to
first decompose the right-hand
side into a Fourier series.
And this step is essentially
already done for us.
We're told what the
Fourier series is.
And what we do is we solve
the ODE, x dot, dot
plus 2x dot plus 4x.
And I'm just going to take
one term of the Fourier
series, sine nt.
So if we know the right-hand
side is a sum of a whole bunch
of sines, what we're going to do
is we're going to solve for
any specific one
of those sines.
So we want to solve this
differential equation.
And then, we use
superposition.
So if we know what the solution
is to one sine, nt,
and we know that the right-hand
side forcing is a
sum of many sine nt's with
appropriate weight factors,
then we can use superposition to
construct a final solution.
So this is the method to
attack this problem.
So we were given step one, and
we want to solve step two.
And we can solve this
just using the
exponential response formula.
So what we're going to do is
we're just going to complexify
the right-hand side.
So if I want to solve the
differential equation, x dot,
dot plus 2x dot plus 4x equals
sine nt, I'm going to denote
the solution with
the subscript n.
And it's going to be the
imaginary part of-- and I'm
just using the exponential
response formula--
1 over the characteristic
polynomial evaluated at in e
to the int.
You might ask how
do I get that.
Well, I basically just took the
complexified equation, and
noted that sine nt was the
imaginary part of e to the
int, and then use the
exponential response formula.
And I want to take the
imaginary part at
the end of the day.
So what is the characteristic
polynomial?
In this case, it's s squared
plus 2s plus 4, which means
that p of in is going to be
negative n squared plus 4--
So I'll just group the
real terms together--
plus 2 in, so the 2in comes from
the two s terms. And then
x of n is going to be the
imaginary part of 1 over 4
minus n squared plus
2in e to the int.
And I'm going to use the
amplitude phase form.
I'm going to convert this
Cartesian complex number into
an amplitude phase form just
because it's taking the
imaginary part of the solution
very easy at
the end of the day.
So the amplitude of this complex
number is 4 minus n
squared quantity squared plus
the imaginary part squared, so
that's 4n squared,
square rooted.
And then, upstairs is eint.
And downstairs, it's
going to be ei phi.
And I'm going to put a subscript
n on the phi just
because for each complex number,
we're going to have a
different phase phi.
And that phase phi end is going
to be the arctangent of
2n divided by 4 minus n
squared, like that.
So now, I can combine phi of n
with the upstairs term, int,
in the exponent.
And when I take the imaginary
part, I'm only going to be
left with sine of
nt minus phi n.
So x of n is going to be 1 over
4 minus n squared squared
plus 4n squared quantity
squared --
square rooted --
times sine of nt minus phi n,
where phi n was given using
the arctangent formula.
And this gives us a solution,
which note is
periodic with period 2t.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Right.
I should also note that phi
of n is between 0 and pi.
And this gives us the one
solution to the differential
equation with a forcing
of sine nt on
the right-hand side.
So now what we want to do is we
want sum up many of these
solutions using the
superposition principle.
So if I go back now, I'm going
to write the original
differential equation.
So I'm just going to go back
and just rewrite this.
And I'm going to write the
right-hand side using its
Fourier series, 1 over n sine
nt, where n is odd.
And this is the problem we
originally wanted to solve.
And essentially what we've
done is we've solved the
problem for each individual
sine nt.
So how do we get the
full solution?
Well, what we have to do is we
have to multiply the solution
for each sine nt by a factor
of 4 divided by
pi and 1 over n.
And then, we have to add all of
these solutions up for all
odd values of n.
So for example, x is just going
to be 4 over pi sum of n
odd, 1 over n times the solution
to every sine nt,
which we've already
computed, and I've
denoted it as x sub n.
And x sub n is up here.
So if we want to be explicit
about it, I'll write the whole
thing out as 4 over pi n odd,
1 over 4 minus n squared
quantity squared plus 4n
squared square rooted.
We also have a factor
of n out front.
We have a sine nt minus phi n.
So there's the final answer for
a particular solution in
its full glorious detail.
We can also check that this
particular solution is periodic.
Note how each sine
nt is periodic.
And each sine nt has period
of at least 2pi.
So when we sum up a whole bunch
of functions which all
have a period of at least 2pi,
the sum is also going to be
periodic function with
at least 2pi.
And as a result, this gives us
the answer we're looking for.
Also, in addition, if we want
the full general solution to
the differential equation to
this particular solution, we
also have to add the
homogeneous piece.
So this concludes the problem.
And I'll just quickly recap.
When solving a differential
equation with a periodic
forcing function on the
right-hand side, again, to
iterate the steps, you first,
Fourier decompose the
right-hand side into summation
of sines and cosines.
You then solve the differential
equation for sine
nt cosine nt individually.
This gives you a solution for
each term on the right-hand
side of the differential
equation.
And then at the end of the day,
you use superposition to
sum up all of the solutions.
And that gives you one
final big solution.
So I hope you enjoy
this problem.
And I'll see you next time.