DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
So the problem I'd like
to work with you
today is this one here.
It's just to compute this
two-variable integral, and the
integrand that we're going
to be computing is e
to the u over u.
And what you might notice right
away is that this inner
integral, it's an integral over
u of e to the u over u,
and this is not an integral that
we have a nice formula
for from one-variable
calculus.
So I'm going to suggest that, as
you try to solve this, you
think about how can you use
the fact that this is a
multivariable integral, maybe
swapping the order of
integration, et cetera,
to solve this.
So why don't you go ahead and
work this problem on your own.
Check back with me in a
few minutes, and I'll
see how I did it.
OK, welcome back.
So as I suggested, I think what
we should do is we should
see what happens if we switch
the order of integration.
I don't know how to do this
inside integral, and so maybe
if we switch the order of
integration, then something's
going to work out.
So in order to get started doing
that, we need to draw
the region of integration,
so why don't we
do that over here.
So I'll just walk over here.
So we've got--
our variables are t and
u, so I've drawn the
t- and u-axes here.
And now, let's look at the
region of integration.
So t is running from 0 to 1/4.
So we'll just draw
1/4 about there.
And now the range for u, the
bottom range is the square
root of t, so I'm going to
draw the curve u is the
square root of t.
It just looks like a parabola
on its side.
And then the top bound
is at u equals 1/2.
And notice that when t is 1/4,
that means that u is 1/2,
because u is just the
square root of t.
And so what we're really
interested in is this region
here, the region between u is
the square root of t and
between u is 1/2, so
this is our region.
So let's rewrite the integral
by swapping the order of
integration, so I'll
do that here.
So now on the outside, we want
to put the range of u first.
So the range of u, we can see
on the graph here, u ranges
from 0 to 1/2, so that's
going to be easy.
And now t, so t is always
starting right here at t
equals 0, and it's always ending
at this curve, which is
t equals u squared.
So we have these little
integrals here.
And so our ranges for t is going
to be t is running from
0 to u squared.
Then we have the same integrand
e to the u over u,
and now we have dt du.
All right.
Now we see that this was a
nice thing to do, because
look: The first integral that we
need to take is an integral
in t, but our integrand doesn't
involve the variable
t, so this is going to be a very
easy integral to take.
So I just take that integrand
and I just multiply it by the
constant t, so we just have e
to the u over u times t, and
then it's a definite integral
which ranges from u
squared to 0 du.
And so this is just
going to be--
1/2 here--
this is really just going to be
ue to the u du, all right?
So let me write that
up over here again.
So we're at integral from
u equals 0 to 1/2
of ue to the u du.
And now we want to remember the
method of integration by
parts from one-variable
calculus.
So integration by parts, you'll
remember, will tell us
that the integral of ue to the
u is going to be ue to the u
minus e to the u.
So that's just applying
integration by parts.
And then this is a definite
integral, so we have a
range 1/2 to 0.
Well, now, we can just plug this
in, so we get 1/2e to the
1/2 minus e to the 1/2 minus the
quantity, so we just get 0
minus e to the 0.
And so altogether, we have--
let's see, we have a negative
e to the 1/2 and then
we have a plus 1.
And negative e to the 1/2 over
2, because we had 1/2 and a
minus a whole, and
then plus 1.
And that's our solution.