PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
I have here a little bit of
a strange problem for you.
So let me just tell it to you,
and then I'll give you some
time to work on it.
So I want to define a function,
g of x, and I want
to define it piecewise.
So when x is positive, I just
want g of x to be 1 over x.
But when x is negative, I want
g of x to be 1 of x plus 2.
So I've got a little graph
here of the function.
So you've got, you know, when x
is positive, it's just your
usual, y equals 1 over x.
But when x is negative,
I've taken, I've
shifted it up by 2.
So this is a perfectly
good function.
It's not defined as 0.
OK?
So what I would like you to do
is to compute the derivative
of this function, wherever
it's defined.
And you'll notice when you get
there that you'll have some,
you'll get some answer, and
maybe you'll notice something
a little weird about
that answer.
So if you notice something weird
about it, what I want
you to do is try and explain
why this is true.
And if you don't notice
something weird, then, you
know, come back and we'll
talk about it together.
So why don't you pause the
video, go do that computation,
and think about what, if there's
something strange
going on here.
And then come back and we can
talk about it together.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you had some fun
working on this problem and
thinking about it.
So let's do the first part,
which is just the
computational part.
Let's have a go at it.
So, because this function is
defined piecewise, when we
compute a derivative, we can
just compute the derivative on
the different pieces.
So the function isn't defined at
0, so of course, it doesn't
have a derivative at 0.
And so, but then we can compute
a derivative when x is
positive, and we can compute a
derivative when x is negative.
So when x is bigger than 0, g
prime of x, well, that's just
d over dx of 1 over x.
So that's something we're
familiar with.
Its minus 1 over x squared.
So that's for x positive.
When x is less than 0, g prime
of x is d over dx of 1 over x
plus 2, because that's
what g of x is.
And, OK, and so this is, well,
the plus 2 gets killed, and so
then we have the derivative
of 1 over x.
That's minus 1 over x squared.
So one thing you've noticed is
that this is minus 1 over x
squared here, and it's minus
1 over x squared here.
So although we defined this
piecewise, we could, we can
summarize this by saying so the
derivative is minus 1 over
x squared always, so for all
x0 equals-- you know, it
doesn't have a derivative
at x equals 0.
It's not defined at 0, it can't
have a derivative there.
So, but we don't need the
piecewise definition, anymore.
So that was kind of interesting
that we can
summarize the derivative of this
piecewise function in a
non-piecewise way.
Now, the thing is, we've
learned what the
anti-derivative of
this function is.
So we know that the
anti-derivative of minus 1
over x squared dx is 1 over
x plus a constant.
So we know that the functions
whose derivative is minus 1
over x squared are
of the form, 1
over x plus a constant.
The thing is, this function g
that we just talked about,
this function g isn't
of that form.
Right?
You don't get this function by
taking the function 1 over x
and just shifting
it up or down.
You, something weird happens.
You've shifted it up on
one piece and not
on the other piece.
And yet, it's still true that
the derivative of g is equal
to minus 1 over x squared.
So this is a little bit
of a head scratcher.
And I wanted to talk about
why this happens.
And the thing is that there's
a sort of theoretical reason
for this, which is that you
remember that the reason that
we know that anti-derivatives
have this form, a function
plus a constant, is because we
know that constants are the
functions with derivative 0.
And so we were able to apply
the mean value theorem in
order to show that if two
functions have the same
derivative, then they differ
by each other, differ from
each other by a constant.
If two functions have
the same derivative,
they differ by a constant.
And we used, as a really crucial
step in that proof,
the mean value theorem.
Now the thing is, the main value
theorem has, as one of
its assumptions, as one of its
hypotheses, that the functions
that you're working with are
continuous and differentiable
in some interval.
OK?
So what's happened here is that
the functions that we're
talking about, the function 1
over x and the function minus
1 over x squared, those
functions are continuous and
differentiable on certain
intervals.
So if we look, if we go back
to this picture here we see
that this function g of x, just
like the function 1 over
x, it's continuous and
differentiable for positive x,
it's continuous and
differentiable for negative x,
but at 0, there's
a discontinuity.
So there's no interval that
crosses 0 on which this
function is continuous
or differentiable.
As a result, the mean value
theorem can't tell us anything
about intervals that cross 0.
So if the mean value theorem
doesn't tell us anything in
that case, it means the
conclusion isn't true and we
get a situation--
sorry.
I should rephrase that.
It means the conclusion doesn't
have to be true.
Our proof doesn't work in
a case where we have a
discontinuity.
And what happens, in fact, is
right what we have here, which
is that when you have a
function that has a
discontinuity and you look at
its anti-derivatives, what you
can do is that, in addition to
shifting the whole thing up
and down, you can shift the
pieces on either side of the
discontinuity separately.
Just like in this case we can
shift the piece to the left of
0 separately from the piece to
the right of 0 and get a
function whose derivative is
still what we started with.
So this function, g of x we, get
by shifting part of 1 over
x up, and it gives us a function
whose derivative is
still minus 1 over x squared.
So this is true anytime you
have a function with a
discontinuity.
So one consequence of this--
I'm going to go back over here
and just write down one
special case of this--
is that to say, we say that the
anti-derivative of 1 over
x dx is equal to ln of the
absolute value of x plus c.
What this really means is that
when x is positive, we have a
single kind of anti-derivative,
and they're
of the form, ln x
plus a constant.
And when x is negative, we have
a single anti-derivative,
that's, or single family of
anti-derivatives, of the form
ln of minus x-- remember,
absolutely value of x is minus
x when x is negative--
plus c.
But if we consider x to be
positive and negative at the
same time, the two
constants don't
necessarily have to agree.
You can have the same situation
that you had before
where one side can shift up and
down independently of the
other because there's that
discontinuity at 0 there.
So this is just something
to keep in mind.
It also means you have to
be careful with certain
substitutions.
You don't want to do
substitutions that have
discontinuities.
If you do substitutions that
have discontinuities, you
might accidentally introduce a
discontinuity and bad things
can happen that I won't
go into now.
You can make, end up with
statements that don't make any
sense by making a substitution
where the function that you're
substituting has a discontinuity
in it.
So you, or another way of
saying it is you have to
restrict to some interval on
which it really is continuous.
And then on each of those
intervals it makes sense, but
bad things could happen
when you cross those
discontinuities.
So this is a little bit
theoretical, but I think it's
a nice thing to be aware of, a
nice thing to keep in mind
when you're working with some
of these expressions.
So I'll end there.