CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
to recitation.
Today what I'd like us to do
is look at the inequality
tangent x bigger than x for
the x values between
0 and pi over 2.
We want to show that that is
definitely true using the mean
value theorem.
And I want to point out that
this was actually something
that Joel used when he was
a graphing tangent x and
arctangent x on the
same x, y plane.
He used this fact in order to
get the right-looking graph.
So what I'd like you to do,
again, is I want you to show
that for any x between 0 and
pi over 2, tangent x
is bigger than x.
And use the mean value
theorem to do it.
I'll give you a little time to
think about it, to work on it,
and then I'll be back and
we'll do it together.
OK.
Welcome back.
So I'm going to take us through
how to do this problem.
And what I want to do is
I want to point out
a few things initially.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to remind us of the form
of the mean value theorem
that we need.
And the form that we need will
be f of x is equal to f of a
plus f prime of c
times x minus a.
And here, remember, c has
to be between a and x.
So in this case, what we want to
consider is the region from
0 up to some x value.
So always, this is, if you think
about it, the a and the
x, well, a will be 0 and x will
be the right hand region,
always less than pi over 2.
So what we need to check is, I'm
going to consider f of x
equal tangent x.
And what I need to consider is,
does tangent x satisfy the
hypotheses of the mean
value theorem on
the region of interest?
And so our region of interest
will always be a equals 0 and
b is equals to x, which is
less than some pi over 2.
And it is true, tangent x is
continuous between 0 and any
value less than pi over 2.
And it's also differentiable
between 0 and any value less
than pi over 2.
So I can apply the mean value
theorem to tangent x.
So in order to do this now, what
I'd like to see is what
kind of things I need
for the right hand
side of this equation.
So I obviously need to know what
the output is at a, which
is equal to 0.
So let's recall f of 0.
Well, tangent 0 is 0-- it's
sine of 0 divided
by cosine of 0.
And then I need to evaluate
the derivative somewhere
between a, which is
0, and pi over 2.
x can be any value less
than pi over 2.
So let's evaluate what the
derivative is in terms of x.
We did this, actually, in
another recitation.
The derivative of tangent
x is secant squared x.
And so now let's plug in what we
know and then see what else
we need to do in order to finish
solving this problem.
OK.
So what we have. f of x, I'm
actually going to write
tangent x, so we can see
what's happening here.
f of x is tangent x, and then I
have that that equals, well,
f of a is 0 plus f prime
evaluated at c--
so that's going to be
secant squared c--
times x minus a.
Well, a here is 0, so this
is just times x.
So we're very close.
We're very close to showing
tangent x is
always bigger than x.
In fact, you can see
very easily what
ultimately we need to show.
We just need to show that secant
squared c is bigger
than 1 in our region of
interest. And that would do
it, because then this would
be bigger than 1 times x.
The right hand side would be
bigger than 1 times x, so that
would be sufficient
So let's make sure we understand
what secant squared
c can look like.
Or what the values can be.
So we have c is between
0 and x, which is less
than pi over 2.
Right?
That's where c is.
So we always need to remember
what values c could possibly
have.
And then let's think about
what we know about
secant of c, there.
Well, secant of c is equal
to 1 over cosine of c.
So if you can't remember what
secant's values are, think
about the values of cosine
in that region.
So I'm going to draw a rough
sketch of the value of cosine
between 0 and pi over 2.
The value of cosine does
something like this.
This is 0, this is pi over 2.
This is a very rough sketch.
But this output is 1.
So between 0 and pi over
2, cosine of c is
always less than 1.
So 1 over cosine of c is
always bigger than 1.
OK?
Because we're taking that
reciprocal value.
So again, cosine of c from 0
to pi over 2, not including
0's, always strictly
less than 1.
And so 1 over cosine c
is always strictly
greater than 1.
And so now I have the
information I need to come
back and finish the problem.
So again, we were looking at
the expression, we have
tangent x is equal to secant
squared c times x.
Well, now I know secant c is
bigger than 1, so now I know
this whole thing is bigger than
1 times x, which is just
equal to x.
So if you noticed, on the left
hand side we have a tangent x
equals something which
is bigger than x.
So we've just shown that, for
any value of x between 0 and
pi over 2, tangent x
is bigger than x.
And I think we'll stop there.