PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video we'd like to do
another optimization problem.
This one's a little bit harder
than the distance problem.
So the question is
the following--
consider triangles formed by
lines passing through the
point x, h, 4-- sorry--
the x-axis and the y-axis.
Find the dimensions that
minimize area.
So what does this fist
sentence mean?
It really means use this
point to draw a line
through this point--
I'll give you an example, it's
kind of a wiggly line, but
hopefully it looks like
a line to you--
and it makes a triangle
with this line, the
x-axis, and the y-axis.
We can certainly calculate the
area of that triangle.
So the problem is asking you to
find the dimensions of the
triangle that minimize the area
with the constraint that
the line, the hypotenuse goes
through the point 8, 4.
I'm going to give you a couple
minutes to work on it.
Why don't you pause video here
and then when you're ready,
restart the video, I'll come
back, and I'll help you solve
the problem.
Welcome back.
So again, we're doing an
optimization problem.
And we want to optimize--
because it says minimize area,
we know the optimizing
equation is area.
So let's be very clear.
Always, when you're doing these
problems, you have,
again, as we've said previously,
you have a
constraint equation and you have
an optimizing equation.
The optimizing equation now,
we've already said, is area.
And area, the easiest way to
write area in this form is--
notice that this distance, we
could write it as base times
height or we could write it as
x times y-- so the base here
is x and the height here is y.
So the area of the triangle
is 1/2 base times height.
So the area is 1/2 x times y.
That's the thing we
want to optimize.
The problem is that we know
when we're doing these
optimization problems we want
to take a derivative of area
with respect to a variable,
but right now we have two
variables and so that's
where the constraints
equation comes in.
So now we have to figure out
how we're going to use a
constraint equation here.
The constraint is that it has to
go through this point 8, 4.
So what does our line
have to look like?
Well, our line has to look
like ultimatlely--
let's do, maybe, the
point-slope form--
y is equal, or sorry.
I said point-slope form.
y minus 4 is equal to
m times x minus 8.
Right?
Notice I couldn't
pick what m was.
Because the m completely
determines the line.
So hopefully that make sense,
that you can see that.
Now, in fact, let's look at how
this problem will work.
The m is going to determine this
point and it's going to
determine this point.
If you can't see that, well,
let's look back here.
This point is when y equals 0.
Right?
So I can put in y equals 0 and
I get x in terms of m.
If I come back over here and
look at this point, this is
when x equals 0.
So if I put in 0 for x, I can
find y in terms of m.
So these two values, the x
value and the y value,
completely determine on the
slope of this line.
That hopefully makes sense just
even if you look at the
geometric picture.
When I turn about this point at
8, 4 these values change.
So the x and y values are
completely determined by the
slope of the line.
In fact, the area, then, is
completely determined by the
slope of the line.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to use the
constraint equation to find
x and y values, all in
terms of the slope.
So let's do that.
I said when y is 0, what
do we get for x?
We get negative 4 over m
plus 8 is equal to x.
Let me double check my math so I
don't have to re-shoot this.
When y is 0 I divide by m.
I add 8, I get x.
So that is the x value I'm
interested in down here.
When x is 0--
let's see what I get--
when x is 0 I get negative
8m plus 4 is y.
Right?
x is 0, negative 8m plus 4.
So now what I'm going to do is
plug these two things into the
area equation.
Area is now equal to
1/2 of x times y.
So 1/2 of 8 minus
4 over m times--
you know what I'm going to do?
I'm going to take this 1/2 and
kill off terms in there so I
don't have to worry
about it anymore--
negative 4m plus 2.
So this is x and this
is 1/2 of y.
So just to make it simpler I'm
not carrying through the 1/2--
I'm killing off half of the
things, dividing every
term in y by 2.
And again, what are
we trying to do?
We're trying to optimize.
So now we want to take the
derivative of area with
respect to the slope.
So this is, maybe to simplify
first, let's multiply through.
So this is just a little bit
of algebra really quick.
8 times 4 is 32, so I get
negative 32m plus 16.
And then here, negative times
negative is a positive.
4 times 4 is 16.
m divided by m, I just get 16.
And then here I get
negative 8m.
So I had to do a little bit of
algebra first, but this is
much easier to take a derivative
and not make
mistakes than this one.
Because you'd have a product
rule and then you'd still have
to multiply.
So we might as well multiply
out first.
So now let me just take the
derivative of this.
And again, I'm taking the
derivative with respect to m.
So here I just get
negative 32.
0, 0.
And then what's the
derivative of--
this is a minus 8m--
well, the derivative of 1 over
m, if you remember, is
negative 1 over m squared.
I have another negative here, so
this is going to be plus 8
over m squared.
Right?
Optimizing, we want to set the
derivative equal to 0.
So if I set the derivative equal
to 0 and solve I get 32m
squared equals 8, or m squared
is equal to 8 over 32, which
is 1/4, or m is equal to 1/2.
Or I should say, plus
or minus 1/2.
We need to be aware.
I would run into problems if
I didn't put the minus.
So solving this problem, I see
that-- again, what did I do?
I set area prime equal to 0,
move the 32 over, multiply by
m squared, do some algebra, and
I get m is equal to plus
or minus 1/2.
And now we need to see which of
these things make sense and
then we just need to think about
what happens as m goes
to its extreme values.
So let's come back and look at
the picture and from there we
can probably tell which of
these answers we need.
So it's m equals 1/2 or m equals
minus 1/2 that we want
to know which of these
do we need.
So I'm going to use some
different colored chalk to
draw what's happening here.
Notice the slope of this
line is negative.
Right?
If I were going to do a positive
sloping line, which
would be the case where m is
equal to 1/2, I would get
something that's headed
in this direction.
And notice that that's not going
to make a triangle with
the x- and y-axis.
And so immediately m equals
1/2 isn't even in this
problem, isn't allowed
to work.
OK, now where did
it come from?
It came because somewhere I was
multiplying m by itself,
which maybe isn't actually
in the original part.
I was introducing a new thing
happening, there, so I'm not
going to get into it too much
because we can immediately see
that we don't have to worry
about m equals 1/2.
m equals minus 1/2 looks good.
That's sloping in
this direction.
And in fact, that would give
us a nice triangle.
The extreme values in this case
are obviously when m is
sloping all the way up to being
vertical, or when m is
sloping to being horizontal.
And in both of those cases you
notice that the area is
getting arbitrarily large, it's
headed towards infinity
in both cases.
So I don't need to worry about
looking at the extreme values.
There aren't end points
really in this case.
But the extreme values, they're
both going to positive
infinity, the areas.
Which convinces me even more
that where m is equal to minus
1/2 is going to be a minimum.
You could also take the second
derivative and run the second
derivative test, but even
geometrically, we can see in
the picture that at m equals
negative 1/2 we actually get a
negative sign for the--
or, sorry-- a
minimizer for the area.
And now the question asks
to find the dimensions.
How do I go back and find
the dimensions?
I'm not going to do any more on
this problem, but you can
do it to finish it off.
Finding the dimensions,
I know what m is.
I also know what x is in
terms of m and what y
is in terms of m.
So I just evaluate x at the m
and evaluate y at that m.
That gives me the dimensions
that will
complete the problem.
But I think I'll stop there.