CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
Today we're going to work on
an optimization problem.
So the question I want us to
answer is, what point on the
curve y equals square root
of x plus 4 comes
closest to the origin?
I've drawn a sketch
of this curve.
The scale in this direction--
each hash mark is one unit in
the x direction, each hash
mark here is one unit
in the y direction.
Just want to point out two easy
places to figure out the
distance to the origin.
Over here, where the curve
starts at negative 4, 0 the
distance to the origin
is 4 units.
And here at 0, 2 the distance
to the origin is two units.
It's probably, we could safely
say, further away here.
So we're anticipating that
somewhere along the curve in
this region is where we should
find our place that's closest
to the origin.
The only reason I point that out
is that, when you're doing
these problems on your own
you should always try and
anticipate roughly where things
should happen in what
kind of region so that you
don't, you don't start
thinking if you do something
wrong and you get x equals 100
and then you come back and look
at the curve, you realize
right away, well, that doesn't
make any sense.
So we want to always be thinking
as we're solving the
problems, does my answer
make sense?
So I'm actually going to give
you a little bit of time to
work on this yourself and then
I'll come back and I'll work
on it as well.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you were able to get
pretty far into this problem.
And so I will start
working on it now.
So again, the question is that
we want to optimize--
in this case, minimize--
the distance to the origin
from this curve.
And so what we're really trying
to do is we have a
constraint , the constraint is
we have to be on the curve,
and then we also have something
we're trying to minimize.
And the thing we're trying
to minimizes is distance.
And so we have to make sure
that we understand the two
equations that we need--
the optimization, or constraint
equation and the
optimizing equation.
So to optimize we need to know
how to measure distance in
two-dimensional space.
And one point I want to make
is that if you want to
optimize distance you might as
well optimize the square of
distance because it's
much easier.
So let me justify that briefly
and then we'll go on.
So I want to optimize
the distance
squared to the origin.
It's, well distance, you
remember first in general,
between two points x y and a b
is something in this form.
Distance squared is the
difference between the x value
squared plus the difference
between the y value squared.
This is, should remind you of
the Pythagorean theorem,
ultimately.
So in this case, in our case,
distance to the origin is x
squared plus y squared.
The distance squared is x
I just told you that instead
of trying to optimize
distance, we can optimize
distance squared.
Why is that?
Well, remember that when you
optimize, what you're looking
for is a place where the
derivative of the function of
interest is equal to 0.
So what I want to point out
is that when you take the
derivative of distance squared
and find where that's 0, it's
going to be the same as the
place where the derivative of
distance is equal to 0.
So let's notice that.
So this is a little sidebar
justification.
Notice g squared prime is
equal to 2d d prime.
Where did that come from?
That's this is implicit
differentiation with respect
to x and this is
the chain rule.
So if I want d prime to equal
0, I can also find where d
squared prime equals 0.
I'm assuming-- notice the
distance is never at the
origin-- so distance
is never 0.
So I don't have to
worry about that.
So that's a small sidebar,
but just to justify
why we can do that.
Now let's come back into
the problem at hand.
What is our optimization
problem, equation that we want
to minimize?
We want to minimize this
equation with respect to a
certain constraint.
What's the constraint?
The constraint is what y is.
y depends on x.
And so when I solve these
problems I'm going to have to
substitute in my constraint.
So y squared is the square
root of x plus 4 quantity
squared so I just
get x plus 4.
So now I have my optimization
equation.
How do I find a minimum
or a maximum?
I take the derivative and
set it equal to 0.
So let me come give myself
a little more room and
do that over here.
So d squared prime, now I get
derivative of x squared is 2x.
The derivative of x is 1, and
the derivative of 4 is 0.
This will be optimized when
this is equal to 0.
So 0 equals 2x plus 1.
So x is equal to minus 1/2.
Does this pass, as we would
say maybe, the smell test?
Does it smell OK to us?
The answer will be yes.
Because remember, we said
somewhere in this x region is
where we expect that we will
have a distance closest, point
closest to the origin.
And so we're right here
on the x value.
Now we have to find what
the y value is
to finish the problem.
But this is not, so far,
very surprising.
It seems like maybe
the right thing.
Now we have x.
So now how do we find y?
Well, we know what y is.
y is equal to the square root of
x plus 4, so it's equal to
the square root of negative 1/2
plus 4, which simplified
is 3 and 1/2, which
I think is 7/2.
So the point is negative 1/2
comma square root of 7/2.
And then you just want to double
check and make sure,
did I ask for the distance or
did I ask for the point?
And right now we have the point,
so let's come over and
make sure what point
on the curve comes
closest to the origin.
So now we know that we've
answered the correct question.
So again, it was a maximize--
sorry, it was a minimizing
problem.
It was an optimization
problem where we
wanted to minimize distance.
We had a constraint equation.
We had the thing we wanted
to minimize.
And then we took the derivative
of the minimizer
set it, or of optimizing
equation, set it equal to 0,
solved for x, and then found
the answer to the specific
question by then finding
the y value.
And I think I'll stop there.