PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
Today we're going to do a
couple of exercises on
computing average values
and probabilities using
integration.
So for this problem, I'm going
to let R be the name of the
region that's bounded above by
the curve, by the line I
guess, y equals x and below by
the curve y equals x cubed.
So I have a little picture of
r here, it, you know, lives
all in the first
quadrant there.
It's just this little sliver.
So the first part of the
question is, if I look at all
the points in r, what's
that average
x-coordinate of those points?
What's the average value
of the x-coordinate?
And the second problem is, if
I choose a point at random
somewhere in R, what's the
probability that its
x-coordinate is larger
than 1/2?
So what's the probability that
it lies on the right
hand side of R?
So why don't you pause the
video, take a couple minutes
to work through these problems.
Come back and we can
work on them together.
Alright, welcome back.
So hopefully you've had a chance
to get some good work
done on these questions.
So let's start to work
through them.
So remember, to compute the
average value of a function
over some region what you need
to do is you need to compute a
weighted average.
And the weighting here is that
you have to consider the fact
that, you know, for x very near
zero, there aren't very
many points in r in this
little corner.
Right?
And for x very near 1, there
aren't very many
points there either.
In the middle, this region is a
little higher, so there are
more points there.
So those points will sort of
weigh more when you take the
average of all points, than
the points near the edges.
So the way we account for that
is we have this weight
function that is the, in our
case, since we're interested
in the x-coordinate, the weight
at a given x-coordinate
is the slice of the-- how much
of the region lies above that
x-coordinate.
What, you know, the area of a
little rectangle above that
x-coordinate says, tells you
how many of the points have
that x-coordinate.
So then we want to average
the function x, right?
Because we're interested in
the x-coordinate, so the
function we're averaging is x.
Over this region, with
that weighting.
So, all right, so let's write
down what that means.
So we have want average of the
function f of x, and the thing
we're computing the average of
is just the x-coordinate, so
it's just the function value x
over R. So we want the average
of this function, f of x over R.
So what we need to compute
is the, so we have two integrals
we need to compute.
We need one integral that is
the numerator and so that
numerator-- so I'm going to
just write average for the
average that we want.
So the numerator is
the integral--
OK, and so we have to integrate,
we have to take all
possible x values into
consideration.
So x going, In this case that's
x going from 0 to 1 and
now we want to multiply the
function that we're averaging,
which in this case is x, by the
appropriate weight function.
And the weight function is
how much of the region is
associated with that x value.
And that's the height of this
little rectangle, which in
this case is x minus
x cubed dx.
OK.
But then, this is an average, we
have to divide by the total
weight of the region.
The weight, in this case,
is just the area.
So we have to divide by the
integral from 0 to 1 of just
this x minus x cubed dx.
OK, so we have to compute these
two integrals and then
we have to take their ratio.
So let's do them separately.
So the first one is--
well, the second one is actually
a little simpler.
The one in the denomenator, so
let's handle that first. The
integral from 0 to 1 of
x minus x cubed dx.
Well, this is a pretty
easy integral.
It's x squared over 2 minus
x to the fourth over 4
between 0 and 1.
So that's 1/2 minus 1/4 minus,
well when you put in 0 you
just get 0.
So that's 1/4.
And the first one, the top, the
numerator is the integral
from 0 to 1.
OK, we can multiply through, so
that's x squared minus x to
the fourth dx.
So that integral from 0 to 1
again is x cubed over 3 minus
x to the fifth over
5 between 0 and 1.
When we put in 0 we get 0, put
int 1 we get 1/3 minus 1/5.
So that's common
denominator 15.
2/15.
So the numerator of our average
value is 2/15, the
denomenator is 1/4.
So the average value we're
interested in is 2/15 divided
by 1/4, which is 8/15.
So the average x-coordinate is
just, so 8/15 is just a tiny
bit larger than 1/2.
So this is saying somehow the
average x-coordinate is just
slightly shifted to
the right of 1/2.
So this, I may have drawn this
region sort of symetrically,
but in fact it's a little bit
shifted to the right there.
So that's the the first
part of the problem.
For the second part, we want to
compute the probability--
so OK, so we choose a point at
random in this set R and we
want to know what's the
probability that its
x-coordinate is larger
than 1/2.
Well, since all points are, you
know, equally likely, all
regions the probability is just
has to do with the area
of the region.
What we really want to know is,
what's is area of R to the
right of the line
x equals 1/2.
So that's the good region, and
then we want to know how much
of the entire region is that.
So we want to know the area of
the good region to the right
of 1/2 divided by
the total area.
Now luckily we've already
computed the
total area, right here.
This was this denominator
that we had over here.
So we just need the numerator
of that fraction.
So let's go over here, let
me write that down.
So the probability equals--
I'm going to put good area
in quotation marks--
so what I mean by good area is
the area of the set of points
that satisfies our condition.
And in our case, the
good area is just--
so a point we're interested in,
if it's x-coordinate is
bigger than 1/2, so we just want
to take the part of this
region to the right of 1/2.
So in order to compute that,
we just take this integral
from 1/2 to 1 instead
of from 0 to 1.
So we're only counting those
points to the right of 1/2 and
then we want the, you know,
the area between these two
curves on that region.
OK, so, and again
this is a fairly
simple integral to compute.
So this gives me x squared over
2 minus x to the fourth
over 4 between 1/2 and 1.
All right, so this is maybe a
tiny bit hairy, so this gives
me 1/2 minus 1/4 minus-- well we
put in 1/2 here we get 1/8
minus 1/2 to the fourth is 1/16
divided by 4 is 1/64.
So this is all going to
be in sxty-fourths.
So OK.
So let's see, 32/64 minus
16/64 minus 8/64 plus 1.
If I just put it all over
that common denominator.
All right, so I think that
looks like 9/64,
if I did that right.
So, OK.
So that's the good area.
And then the probability that
I want, I have to divide the
good area by the total area.
And we saw before that the
total area was 1/4.
And that was what this
computational was.
So the total area's 1/4,
so the probability--
I'm just goint to write
pr for probability--
that we're interested in
is 9/64 divided by
1/4 which is 9/16.
OK, so this says--
also 9/16 is also a little
bit bigger than a half.
So this is a different way of
saying, our region, there's a
little bit more of it
to the right then
there is to the left.
You know, so it's slightly
more likely that a random
point is to the right of the
line y equals 1/2 than it is
to the left of that line.
So just to sum up, we had these
two different problems
that we did concerning this
region R. So first we computed
the average value of the
x-coordinate of a point in
this region.
So that was part a.
We computed the average value of
the x-coordinate, and that
was over here.
So we had to, you know, do this,
the weighted average of
the x-coordinate divided
by the total area.
And then second, we computed
the probability that a
randomly chosen point has
x-coordinate larger than 1/2.
And we did that over here.
And for that we needed to
compute the area of the good
region, which was the part to
the right of the line y equals
1/2 and then we needed to divide
it by the total area.
So I'll end there.