PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video segment, what I'd
like us to do is work on
this following problem.
Find d dx of the integral from
0 to x squared, cosine t dt.
I'm going to give you a moment
to think about it and then
I'll come back and show
you how I do it.
OK, welcome back.
Hopefully you were able to make
some headway on this.
Let's look at the problem
and see how we
would break it down.
Well we know from the
fundamental theorem of
calculus that you saw in the
lecture, that if up here
instead of x squared we had an
x, then the problem would be
easy to solve.
We'd just use the fundamental
theorem of calculus, the
answer would be cosine x.
But of course, we don't have
an x, we have an x squared.
That's why I gave you
this problem.
And we need to figure out how
to solve this problem when
there's a different function
up here besides just x.
What we're going to use is we're
going to combine the
fundamental theorem of calculus
and the chain rule.
So, let's start off with how
we would do this if it were
the integral from 0 to
x, as I mentioned.
So we'll define capital F of x
to be equal to the integral
from 0 to x cosine t dt.
And then we know that f prime
of x is equal to cosine x.
Now the problem is,
we don't just
have this, as I mentioned.
What we actually have--
let me write this down--
we have f of x squared.
Right?
That's what this-- sorry let
me highlight what I mean--
this boxed thing is
f of x squared.
So we took f of x and we
evaluated it at x squared.
That's what we get in the box.
And so if we want to find d dx
of f of x squared, it really
is just the chain rule.
We really want to think
of this as a
composition of functions.
The first, the outside function
is capital F and the
inside function is x squared.
So just in general, how do we
think about the chain rule?
Well remember what we do--
let me come back here
for a second--
remember what we do is we take
the derivative of the outside
function, we evaluate it at the
inside function and then
we take the derivative of the
inside function and we
multiply those two together.
So all I have to do is figure
out, is what is
the following thing?
We know d dx, the quantity f of
x squared should be equal
to F prime evaluated at
x squared times 2x.
That's just what we said
earlier, right?
It's the derivative of F
evaluated at x squared times
the derivative of x squared.
So now I just have to figure
out what this is.
Well let's go back to the other
side and see what we
wrote F prime was.
If we come over here, we see F
prime at x is just cosine x.
So F prime at x squared is
going to be this function
evaluated at x squared.
That's just cosine
of x squared.
So we see over here, we just get
cosine x squared times 2x.
And because I'm a mathematician,
I want to write
the 2x in front before
I finish.
Becaues otherwise
I get confused.
So the answer here is just 2x
times cosine x squared.
Now I want to point out really
what we did here.
This is the answer to this
particular problem, but we can
now solve problems in general
when I put any function up
here, any function
of x up here.
Right?
Ultimately, all I did was I used
the fundamental theorem
of calculus and the
chain rule.
So any function I put
up here, I can do
exactly the same process.
I would define f of x to be this
type of thing, the way we
would define it for the
fundamental theorem of calculus.
I would know what F
prime of x was.
And then I would have to
evaluate F at a, at this
function up here, whatever
I put up there.
So in this case it
was x squared.
I could have made it
natural log x.
I could've made it some big
polynomial or something more
complicated.
Right?
And once I do that, I just
follow this same process.
Now, instead of the x
squared here I would
have that other function.
So I'd evaluate capital F at
whatever function that is
times the derivative
of that function.
It's exactly the same process.
So I want to point out that
this is a bigger situation
than I had before, or a bigger
situation than just this
little problem.
So, just so you understand
that.
OK?
So again, I just want to
say one more time.
Now you know how to solve
problems where you have any
other function of x up here
and you want to take the
derivative of this kind of
expression of an integral with
another function
of x up there.
All right, I think
I'll stop there.