PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video I want us to work
on the following problem.
So we're going to assume
little f is
a continuous function.
And if we know that the integral
from 0 to x of f of t
dt is equal to x squared
sine pi x, I want us to
find little f of 2.
So I'm going to give
you a little while
to work on the problem.
When you're ready, come back and
we'll take a look at how I
do the problem.
Welcome back.
So again, we're working on a
problem where we know that f
is a continuous function.
We know that the integral from
0 to x is f of t dt is equal
to a certain function.
And we want to find f of 2.
So what we're going to use,
because we know little f is
continuous, we can
actually use the
fundamental theorem of calculus.
And we know that d dx of this
whole expression here is
actually little f of x.
So let's just remind us--
I'll write it down formally.
FTC implies that d dx, the
interval from 0 to x f of t dt
if equal to f of x.
Right?
We know that.
So, we know that d dx of the
right-hand side and d dx of
the left-hand side
are the same.
And so we know that if we take
d dx of the right-hand side,
we'll get little f of x.
Because d dx of the left-hand
side of this equation is
little f of x.
Do d dx of the right-hand side
is also little f of x.
So now all we have to do is
apply what we know about
taking derivatives to
find little f of x.
Then once we find little f of
x we can evaluate it at f
equal 2, at 2--sorry--
at x equal 2.
Sorry about that.
So let's come over to the right
part of the board and
we'll find d dx of this
function here.
So what do we have to use?
We have to use the product rule
and then we'll have to
use a little chain rule, a
really simple chain rule in
the second term.
I'm going to write it
down below, so we
have some room here.
So the first term, we
get 2x sine pi x.
The second term we
get x squared.
Derivative of sine is cosine.
pi x.
And then we have to
pull out a pi.
Which I'll just put, well I'll
put it here for the moment.
The pi comes from taking
the derivative of pi x.
And now all we need, this
is then f of x, right?
So I just will remind
us this is f of x.
Let me put it right here,
a little f of x.
So if I want to find f of 2, all
I have to do is evaluate
this at x equal 2.
So f of 2 is going to equal--
2 times 2 is 4--
sine 2 pi plus 4--
I'll bring the pi in front--
4 pi cosine 2 pi.
So what do I get?
Sine 2 pi is 0.
Cosine 2 pi is 1.
So ultimately, I
just get 4 pi.
So, hopefully you were able to
solve this problem and get the
same answer.
Now let me remind you, one
more time what we did.
Let's come over here.
We started with a function that
we knew was continuous.
We knew the integral from 0 to
x of that function was equal
to a certain function of x.
And we wanted to evaluate this
function at a certain, at a
certain point.
So what we exploited was the
fundamental theorem of calculus.
And the fundamental theorem of
calculus tells us that d dx,
of the left-hand
side is f of x.
And so that we can take d dx
of the right-hand side and
figure out what f of x is.
And then we just evaluate.
So I think I'll stop there.