PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video I'd like us to
work on the following problem.
We're going to let capital F of
x equal the integral from 0
to x of little f of t dt.
And I want us to find the
quadratic approximation for
big F near x equals 0 in
terms of the little f.
And then I want us to answer
this question.
What assumptions do we have
to make about little f?
You'll see we're making some
assumptions about little f.
I want to know what those
assumptions are.
So I'm going to give you a
little bit of time to work on
this problem.
And then I'll be back and I
will work on it with you.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you were able to make
some good headway with
this problem.
So again, what we're trying to
do, is we've defined capital
F. And we want to find the
quadratic approximation for it
near x equals 0 in terms
of little f.
Knowing that capital F of x is
equal to the integral from 0
to x of little f of t dt.
And then at the end, we'll
talk about what are the
assumptions we've made.
So to start off, what I actually
want to do is remind
us what is the quadratic
approximation for capital F,
just in terms of itself?
Of capital F?
So let me come over to the right
and we'll write down
what the quadratic
approximation is,
near x equals 0.
So, this gives us that f of x is
approximately f of 0 plus f
prime of 0 times x plus
F double prime at 0
over 2 times x squared.
This is just the quadratic
approximation of capital F at
x equals 0.
That's what it is.
So now all we need to do, I've
asked you to write it in terms
of little f.
So what we need to do is figure
out what each of these
things actually is.
What capital F of 0 is, what
capital F prime of 0 is, and
what capital F double prime
of 0 is, in terms of the
function little f.
So let's see.
Well first, let's figure out
what capital F of 0 is.
Let's write down what it is.
The integral from 0
to 0 of f of t dt.
Well we know, when you take the
integral from a to a of a
function, you should get 0.
So capital F at 0 is just 0.
So we have one piece.
Now, let's figure out what
capital F prime is.
Well, capital F prime of x, we
know using fundamental theorem
of calculus--
let's just write it down so
we can see it easily--
we know this is just
little f of x.
So if I wanted capital F prime
at 0, I just come over here.
That's just going to
be little f at 0.
So now, if we look back up at
what we have at the top, we
filled in this part-- or we
know that part, that's 0--
we know this part.
So now all we need is capital
F double prime
evaluated at x equals 0.
And then we'll be done.
Now, how are we going
to do this?
Well we know what capital
F prime is.
So let's come in, sort of
up here, and look again.
We know what capital
F prime is.
We know it's little f.
So if I want to take a second
derivative, of capital F-- let
me write that down here--
that's going to be taking a
derivative of little f.
Right?
That'll be, that's d dx
of little f of x.
So I can just write this
as little f prime of x.
So again, let me show you
where that came from.
We knew big F prime was
equal to little f.
So when I take another
derivative of this, I have to
take a derivative of this.
So that's why capital
F double prime is
equal to little f prime.
So we're almost there.
I think I'm about to run out of
room down here, so let me
come over a little
bit further.
So now, we just need to
evaluate this at 0.
Well, that's just going
to be evaluating
little f prime at 0.
So now I have all the pieces.
Let's come back in and fill
it in one more time.
So what do I get?
I get-- let me, now I
have all the pieces.
Now to answer the question.
Little f-- or sorry--
Big F of x, its quadratic
approximation is going to be
big F of 0, which
we said was 0.
So let's come over and look.
Here's big F of 0.
I know that's 0.
And then I'm going to add to
that big F prime at 0 times x.
That's little f of 0 times x.
Let's come back over
and do that.
So we add to that little
f at 0 times x.
And let's come back.
One more thing we're
going to need.
We need one more term.
That's big F double prime at
0 over 2 times x squared.
That I've left big F double
prime at 0 is
little f prime at 0.
So that's f prime at 0 over
2 times x squared.
So we had all the pieces.
We just had to put them in.
This does not look like an
approximately by the way.
Sorry.
There we go.
So what do we get?
This expression above
is equal to--
well why did I write
the 0 again?
Sorry I was trying to
avoid writing the 0.
It's equal to f of 0 times
x plus f prime of 0
over 2 times x squared.
So the quadratic approximation
of capital F in terms of
little f is exactly this.
Now what assumptions are we
making about little f?
Well to apply the fundamental
theorem of calculus, you need
little f is continuous.
But we actually need
more than that.
Because what have we done?
We've actually taken a
derivative of little f.
So we need that this function,
little f, is actually
differentiable.
So that is, that actually
includes, of course, that
little f is continuous.
So we don't even have to say
continuous in the assumptions.
We just have to say, we're
assuming little f is
differentiable, at
least near 0.
So let's go back and just remind
ourselves what we did.
I'm going to go all the way
over, remind ourselves of the
problem and kind of bring
us back through.
So we started off with this
definition of big F. And I
wanted us to find a quadratic
approximation for it
near x equals 0.
And then we just mentioned,
what are the assumptions?
So I reminded you, first,
of what is the quadratic
approximation of big F in terms
of itself, in terms of
big F. And we just
write it out.
And then we had defined what is
this in terms of little f,
what is this in terms of little
f, and what is this in
terms of little f?
And so what do we look at?
Well, we evaluate f of 0.
That's easy enough.
We found big F prime in
terms of little f.
That's fundamental theorem
of calculus.
And then we evaluate
that at x equals 0.
And then we know that if we
want to take a second
derivative of this function, we
need to take a derivative
of the little f.
And so we get big F
double prime is
actually little f prime.
So we evaluate that at 0 to get
big F double prime at 0.
And then we come in and
we just fill in
everything we needed.
And so ultimately, this is the
final answer of the quadratic
approximation of big F
in terms of little f
near x equals 0.
So I think that's where
we'll stop.