This is the first lecture in
MIT's course 18.06,
linear algebra,
and I'm Gilbert Strang.
The text for the course is this
book, Introduction to Linear
Algebra.
And the course web page,
which has got a lot of
exercises from the past,
MatLab codes,
the syllabus for the course,
is web.mit.edu/18.06.
And this is the first lecture,
lecture one.
So, and later we'll give the
web address for viewing these,
videotapes.
Okay, so what's in the first
lecture?
This is my plan.
The fundamental problem of
linear algebra,
which is to solve a system of
linear equations.
So let's start with a case when
we have some number of
equations, say n equations and n
unknowns.
So an equal number of equations
and unknowns.
That's the normal,
nice case.
And what I want to do is --
with examples,
of course -- to describe,
first, what I call the Row
picture.
That's the picture of one
equation at a time.
It's the picture you've seen
before in two by two equations
where lines meet.
So in a minute,
you'll see lines meeting.
The second picture,
I'll put a star beside that,
because that's such an
important one.
And maybe new to you is the
picture -- a column at a time.
And those are the rows and
columns of a matrix.
So the third -- the algebra way
to look at the problem is the
matrix form and using a matrix
that I'll call A.
Okay, so can I do an example?
The whole semester will be
examples and then see what's
going on with the example.
So, take an example.
Two equations,
two unknowns.
So let me take 2x -y =0,
let's say.
And -x 2y=3.
Okay.
let me -- I can even say right
away -- what's the matrix,
that is, what's the coefficient
matrix?
The matrix that involves these
numbers --
a matrix is just a rectangular
array of numbers.
Here it's two rows and two
columns, so 2 and -- minus 1 in
the first row minus 1 and 2 in
the second row,
that's the matrix.
And the right-hand -- the,
unknown -- well,
we've got two unknowns.
So we've got a vector,
with two components,
x and x, and we've got two
right-hand sides that go into a
vector 0 3.
I couldn't resist writing the
matrix form, right -- even
before the pictures.
So I always will think of this
as the matrix A,
the matrix of coefficients,
then there's a vector of
unknowns.
Here we've only got two
Later we'll have any number of
unknowns.
And that vector of unknowns,
well I'll often -- I'll make
that x -- extra bold.
A and the right-hand side is
also a vector that I'll always
call b.
So linear equations are A x
equal b and the idea now is to
solve this particular example
and then step back to see the
bigger picture.
Okay, what's the picture for
this example,
the Row picture?
Okay, so here comes the Row
picture.
So that means I take one row at
a time and I'm drawing here the
xy plane and I'm going to plot
all the points that satisfy that
first equation.
So I'm looking at all the
points that satisfy 2x-y =0.
It's often good to start with
which point on the horizontal
line --
on this horizontal line,
y is zero.
The x axis has y as zero and
that -- in this case,
actually, then x is zero.
So the point,
the origin -- the point with
coordinates (0,0) is on the
line.
It solves that equation.
Okay, tell me in --
well, I guess I have to tell
you another point that solves
this same equation.
Let me suppose x is one,
so I'll take x to be one.
Then y should be two,
right?
So there's the point one two
that also solves this equation.
And I could put in more points.
But, but let me put in all the
points at once,
because they all lie on a
straight line.
This is a linear equation and
that word linear got the letters
for line in it.
That's the equation -- this is
the line that ...
of solutions to 2x-y=0 my first
row, first equation.
So typically,
maybe, x equal a half,
y equal one will work.
And sure enough it does.
Okay, that's the first one.
Now the second one is not going
to go through the origin.
It's always important.
Do we go through the origin or
not?
In this case,
yes, because there's a zero
over there.
In this case we don't go
through the origin,
because if x and y are zero,
we don't get three.
So, let me again say suppose y
is zero, what x do we actually
get?
If y is zero,
then I get x is minus three.
So if y is zero,
I go along minus three.
So there's one point on this
second line.
Now let me say,
well, suppose x is minus one --
just to take another x.
If x is minus one,
then this is a one and I think
y should be a one,
because if x is minus one,
then I think y should be a one
and we'll get that point.
Is that right?
If x is minus one,
that's a one.
If y is a one,
that's a two and the one and
the two make three and that
point's on the equation.
Okay.
Now, I should just draw the
line, right, connecting those
two points at -- that will give
me the whole line.
And if I've done this
reasonably well,
I think it's going to happen to
go through -- well,
not happen -- it was arranged
to go through that point.
So I think that the second line
is this one, and this is the
all-important point that lies on
both lines.
Shall we just check that that
point which is the point x equal
one and y was two,
right?
That's the point there and
that, I believe,
solves both equations.
Let's just check this.
If x is one,
I have a minus one plus four
equals three,
okay.
Apologies for drawing this
picture that you've seen before.
But this -- seeing the row
picture --
first of all,
for n equal 2,
two equations and two unknowns,
it's the right place to start.
Okay.
So we've got the solution.
The point that lies on both
lines.
Now can I come to the column
picture?
Pay attention,
this is the key point.
So the column picture.
I'm now going to look at the
columns of the matrix.
I'm going to look at this part
and this part.
I'm going to say that the x
part is really x times -- you
see, I'm putting the two -- I'm
kind of getting the two
equations at once --
that part and then I have a y
and in the first equation it's
multiplying a minus one and in
the second equation a two,
and on the right-hand side,
zero and three.
You see, the columns of the
matrix, the columns of A are
here and the right-hand side b
is there.
And now what is the equation
asking for?
It's asking us to find --
somehow to combine that vector
and this one in the right
amounts to get that one.
It's asking us to find the
right linear combination -- this
is called a linear combination.
And it's the most fundamental
operation in the whole course.
It's a linear combination of
the columns.
That's what we're seeing on the
left side.
Again, I don't want to write
down a big definition.
You can see what it is.
There's column one,
there's column two.
I multiply by some numbers and
I add.
That's a combination -- a
linear combination and I want to
make those numbers the right
numbers to produce zero three.
Okay.
Now I want to draw a picture
that, represents what this --
this is algebra.
What's the geometry,
what's the picture that goes
with it?
Okay.
So again, these vectors have
two components,
so I better draw a picture like
that.
So can I put down these
columns?
I'll draw these columns as they
are, and then I'll do a
combination of them.
So the first column is over two
and down one,
right?
So there's the first column.
The first column.
Column one.
It's the vector two minus one.
The second column is -- minus
one is the first component and
up two.
It's here.
There's column two.
So this, again,
you see what its components
are.
Its components are minus one,
two.
Good.
That's this guy.
Now I have to take a
combination.
What combination shall I take?
Why not the right combination,
what the hell?
Okay.
So the combination I'm going to
take is the right one to produce
zero three and then we'll see it
happen in the picture.
So the right combination is to
take x as one of those and two
of these.
It's because we already know
that that's the right x and y,
so why not take the correct
combination here and see it
happen?
Okay, so how do I picture this
linear combination?
So I start with this vector
that's already here -- so that's
one of column one,
that's one times column one,
right there.
And now I want to add on --
so I'm going to hook the next
vector onto the front of the
arrow will start the next vector
and it will go this way.
So let's see,
can I do it right?
If I added on one of these
vectors, it would go left one
and up two, so we'd go left one
and up two, so it would probably
get us to there.
Maybe I'll do dotted line for
that.
Okay?
That's one of column two tucked
onto the end,
but I wanted to tuck on two of
column two.
So that -- the second one --
we'll go up left one and up two
also.
It'll probably end there.
And there's another one.
So what I've put in here is two
of column two.
Added on.
And where did I end up?
What are the coordinates of
this result?
What do I get when I take one
of this plus two of that?
I do get that,
of course.
There it is,
x is zero, y is three,
that's b.
That's the answer we wanted.
And how do I do it?
You see I do it just like the
first component.
I have a two and a minus two
that produces a zero,
and in the second component I
have a minus one and a four,
they combine to give the three.
But look at this picture.
So here's our key picture.
I combine this column and this
column to get this guy.
That was the b.
That's the zero three.
Okay.
So that idea of linear
combination is crucial,
and also -- do we want to think
about this question?
Sure, why not.
What are all the combinations?
If I took -- can I go back to
xs and ys?
This is a question for really
-- it's going to come up over
and over, but why don't we see
it once now?
If I took all the xs and all
the ys, all the combinations,
what would be all the results?
And, actually,
the result would be that I
could get any right-hand side at
all.
The combinations of this and
this would fill the whole plane.
You can tuck that away.
We'll, explore it further.
But this idea of what linear
combination gives b and what do
all the linear combinations
give,
what are all the possible,
achievable right-hand sides be
-- that's going to be basic.
Okay.
Can I move to three equations
and three unknowns?
Because it's easy to picture
the two by two case.
Let me do a three by three
example.
Okay, I'll sort of start it the
same way,
say maybe 2x-y and maybe I'll
take no zs as a zero and maybe a
-x 2y and maybe a -z as a -- oh,
let me make that a minus one
and, just for variety let me
take, -3z, -3ys,
I should keep the ys in that
line, and 4zs is,
say, 4.
Okay.
That's three equations.
I'm in three dimensions,
x, y, z.
And, I don't have a solution
yet.
So I want to understand the
equations and then solve them.
Okay.
So how do I you understand
them?
The row picture one way.
The column picture is another
very important way.
Just let's remember the matrix
form, here, because that's easy.
The matrix form -- what's our
matrix A?
Our matrix A is this right-hand
side, the two and the minus one
and the zero from the first row,
the minus one and the two and
the minus one from the second
row,
the zero, the minus three and
the four from the third row.
So it's a three by three
matrix.
Three equations,
three unknowns.
And what's our right-hand side?
Of course, it's the vector,
zero minus one,
four.
Okay.
So that's the way,
well, that's the short-hand to
write out the three equations.
But it's the picture that I'm
looking for today.
Okay, so the row picture.
All right, so I'm in three
dimensions, x,
y and z.
And I want to take those
equations one at a time and ask
-- and make a picture of all the
points that satisfy --
let's take equation number two.
If I make a picture of all the
points that satisfy -- all the
x, y, z points that solve this
equation -- well,
first of all,
the origin is not one of them.
x, y, z -- it being 0,
0, 0 would not solve that
equation.
So what are some points that do
solve the equation?
Let's see, maybe if x is one,
y and z could be zero.
That would work,
right?
So there's one point.
I'm looking at this second
equation, here,
just, to start with.
Let's see.
Also, I guess,
if z could be one,
x and y could be zero,
so that would just go straight
up that axis.
And, probably I'd want a third
point here.
Let me take x to be zero,
z to be zero,
then y would be minus a half,
right?
So there's a third point,
somewhere -- oh my -- okay.
Let's see.
I want to put in all the points
that satisfy that equation.
Do you know what that bunch of
points will be?
It's a plane.
If we have a linear equation,
then, fortunately,
the graph of the thing,
the plot of all the points that
solve it are a plane.
These three points determine a
plane, but your lecturer is not
Rembrandt and the art is going
to be the weak point here.
So I'm just going to draw a
plane, right?
There's a plane somewhere.
That's my plane.
That plane is all the points
that solves this guy.
Then, what about this one?
Two x minus y plus zero z.
So z actually can be anything.
Again, it's going to be another
plane.
Each row in a three by three
problem gives us a plane in
three dimensions.
So this one is going to be some
other plane -- maybe I'll try to
draw it like this.
And those two planes meet in a
line.
So if I have two equations,
just the first two equations in
three dimensions,
those give me a line.
The line where those two planes
meet.
And now, the third guy is a
third plane.
And it goes somewhere.
Okay, those three things meet
in a point.
Now I don't know where that
point is, frankly.
But -- linear algebra will find
it.
The main point is that the
three planes,
because they're not parallel,
they're not special.
They do meet in one point and
that's the solution.
But, maybe you can see that
this row picture is getting a
little hard to see.
The row picture was a cinch
when we looked at two lines
meeting.
When we look at three planes
meeting, it's not so clear and
in four dimensions probably a
little less clear.
So, can I quit on the row
picture?
Or quit on the row picture
before I've successfully found
the point where the three planes
meet?
All I really want to see is
that the row picture consists of
three planes and,
if everything works right,
three planes meet in one point
and that's a solution.
Now, you can tell I prefer the
column picture.
Okay, so let me take the column
picture.
That's x times -- so there were
two xs in the first equation
minus one x is,
and no xs in the third.
It's just the first column of
that.
And how many ys are there?
There's minus one in the first
equations, two in the second and
maybe minus three in the third.
Just the second column of my
matrix.
And z times no zs minus one zs
and four zs.
And it's those three columns,
right, that I have to combine
to produce the right-hand side,
which is zero minus one four.
Okay.
So what have we got on this
left-hand side?
A linear combination.
It's a linear combination now
of three vectors,
and they happen to be -- each
one is a three dimensional
vector,
so we want to know what
combination of those three
vectors produces that one.
Shall I try to draw the column
picture, then?
So, since these vectors have
three components -- so it's some
multiple -- let me draw in the
first column as before --
x is two and y is minus one.
Maybe there is the first
column.
y -- the second column has
maybe a minus one and a two and
the y is a minus three,
somewhere, there possibly,
column two.
And the third column has --
no zero minus one four,
so how shall I draw that?
So this was the first
component.
The second component was a
minus one.
Maybe up here.
That's column three,
that's the column zero minus
one and four.
This guy.
So, again, what's my problem?
What this equation is asking me
to do is to combine these three
vectors with a right combination
to produce this one.
Well, you can see what the
right combination is,
because in this special
problem,
specially chosen by the
lecturer, that right-hand side
that I'm trying to get is
actually one of these columns.
So I know how to get that one.
So what's the solution?
What combination will work?
I just want one of these and
none of these.
So x should be zero,
y should be zero and z should
be one.
That's the combination.
One of those is obviously the
right one.
Column three is actually the
same as b in this particular
problem.
I made it work that way just so
we would get an answer,
(0,0,1), so somehow that's the
point where those three planes
met and I couldn't see it
before.
Of course, I won't always be
able to see it from the column
picture, either.
It's the next lecture,
actually,
which is about elimination,
which is the systematic way
that everybody -- every bit of
software, too -- production,
large-scale software would
solve the equations.
So the lecture that's coming
up.
If I was to add that to the
syllabus, will be about how to
find x, y, z in all cases.
Can I just think again,
though, about the big picture?
By the big picture I mean let's
keep this same matrix on the
left but imagine that we have a
different right-hand side.
Oh, let me take a different
right-hand side.
So I'll change that right-hand
side to something that actually
is also pretty special.
Let me change it to -- if I add
those first two columns,
that would give me a one and a
one and a minus three.
There's a very special
right-hand side.
I just cooked it up by adding
this one to this one.
Now, what's the solution with
this new right-hand side?
The solution with this new
right-hand side is clear.
took one of these and none of
those.
So actually,
it just changed around to this
when I took this new right-hand
side.
Okay.
So in the row picture,
I have three different planes,
three new planes meeting now at
this point.
In the column picture,
I have the same three columns,
but now I'm combining them to
produce this guy,
and it turned out that column
one plus column two which would
be somewhere -- there is the
right column -- one of this and
one of this would give me the
new b.
Okay.
So we squeezed in an extra
example.
But now think about all bs,
all right-hand sides.
Can I solve these equations for
every right-hand side?
Can I ask that question?
So that's the algebra question.
Can I solve A x=b for every b?
Let me write that down.
Can I solve A x =b for every
right-hand side b?
I mean, is there a solution?
And then, if there is,
elimination will give me a way
to find it.
I really wanted to ask,
is there a solution for every
right-hand side?
So now, can I put that in
different words -- in this
linear combination words?
So in linear combination words,
do the linear combinations of
the columns fill three
dimensional space?
Every b means all the bs in
three dimensional space.
Do you see that I'm just asking
the same question in different
words?
Solving A x -- A x -- that's
very important.
A times x -- when I multiply a
matrix by a vector,
I get a combination of the
columns.
I'll write that down in a
moment.
But in my column picture,
that's really what I'm doing.
I'm taking linear combinations
of these three columns and I'm
trying to find b.
And, actually,
the answer for this matrix will
be yes.
For this matrix A -- for these
columns, the answer is yes.
This matrix -- that I chose for
an example is a good matrix.
A non-singular matrix.
An invertible matrix.
Those will be the matrices that
we like best.
There could be other -- and we
will see other matrices where
the answer becomes,
no -- oh, actually,
you can see when it would
become no.
What could go wrong?
How could it go wrong that out
of these -- out of three columns
and all their combinations --
when would I not be able to
produce some b off here?
When could it go wrong?
Do you see that the
combinations -- let me say when
it goes wrong.
If these three columns all lie
in the same plane,
then their combinations will
lie in that same plane.
So then we're in trouble.
If the three columns of my
matrix -- if those three vectors
happen to lie in the same plane
-- for example,
if column three is just the sum
of column one and column two,
I would be in trouble.
That would be a matrix A where
the answer would be no,
because the combinations -- if
column three is in the same
plane as column one and two,
I don't get anything new from
that.
All the combinations are in the
plane and only right-hand sides
b that I could get would be the
ones in that plane.
So I could solve it for some
right-hand sides,
when b is in the plane,
but most right-hand sides would
be out of the plane and
unreachable.
So that would be a singular
case.
The matrix would be not
invertible.
There would not be a solution
for every b.
The answer would become no for
that.
Okay.
I don't know -- shall we take
just a little shot at thinking
about nine dimensions?
Imagine that we have vectors
with nine components.
Well, it's going to be hard to
visualize those.
I don't pretend to do it.
But somehow,
pretend you do.
Pretend we have -- if this was
nine equations and nine
unknowns, then we would have
nine columns,
and each one would be a vector
in nine-dimensional space and we
would be looking at their linear
combinations.
So we would be having the
linear combinations of nine
vectors in nine-dimensional
space, and we would be trying to
find the combination that hit
the correct right-hand side b.
And we might also ask the
question can we always do it?
Can we get every right-hand
side b?
And certainly it will depend on
those nine columns.
Sometimes the answer will be
yes -- if I picked a random
matrix, it would be yes,
actually.
If I used MatLab and just used
the random command,
picked out a nine by nine
matrix, I guarantee it would be
good.
It would be non-singular,
it would be invertible,
all beautiful.
But if I choose those columns
so that they're not independent,
so that the ninth column is the
same as the eighth column,
then it contributes nothing new
and there would be right-hand
sides b that I couldn't get.
Can you sort of think about
nine vectors in nine-dimensional
space an take their
combinations?
That's really the central
thought -- that you get kind of
used to in linear algebra.
Even though you can't really
visualize it,
you sort of think you can after
a while.
Those nine columns and all
their combinations may very well
fill out the whole
nine-dimensional space.
But if the ninth column
happened to be the same as the
eighth column and gave nothing
new, then probably what it would
fill out would be -- I hesitate
even to say this --
it would be a sort of a plane
-- an eight dimensional plane
inside nine-dimensional space.
And it's those eight
dimensional planes inside
nine-dimensional space that we
have to work with eventually.
For now, let's stay with a nice
case where the matrices work,
we can get every right-hand
side b and here we see how to do
it with columns.
Okay.
There was one step which I
realized I was saying in words
that I now want to write in
letters.
Because I'm coming back to the
matrix form of the equation,
so let me write it here.
The matrix form of my equation,
of my system is some matrix A
times some vector x equals some
right-hand side b.
Okay.
So this is a multiplication.
A times x.
Matrix times vector,
and I just want to say how do
you multiply a matrix by a
vector?
Okay, so I'm just going to
create a matrix --
let me take two five one three
-- and let me take a vector x to
be, say, 1and 2.
How do I multiply a matrix by a
vector?
But just think a little bit
about matrix notation and how to
do that in multiplication.
So let me say how I multiply a
matrix by a vector.
Actually, there are two ways to
do it.
Let me tell you my favorite
way.
It's columns again.
It's a column at a time.
For me, this matrix
multiplication says I take one
of that column and two of that
column and add.
So this is the way I would
think of it is one of the first
column and two of the second
column and let's just see what
we get.
So in the first component I'm
getting a two and a ten.
I'm getting a twelve there.
In the second component I'm
getting a one and a six,
I'm getting a seven.
So that matrix times that
vector is twelve seven.
Now, you could do that another
way.
You could do it a row at a
time.
And you would get this twelve
-- and actually I pretty much
did it here -- this way.
Two -- I could take that row
times my vector.
This is the idea of a dot
product.
This vector times this vector,
two times one plus five times
two is the twelve.
This vector times this vector
-- one times one plus three
times two is the seven.
So I can do it by rows,
and in each row times my x is
what I'll later call a dot
product.
But I also like to see it by
columns.
I see this as a linear
combination of a column.
So here's my point.
A times x is a combination of
the columns of A.
That's how I hope you will
think of A times x when we need
it.
Right now we've got -- with
small ones, we can always do it
in different ways,
but later, think of it that
way.
Okay.
So that's the picture for a two
by two system.
And if the right-hand side B
happened to be twelve seven,
then of course the correct
solution would be one two.
Okay.
So let me come back next time
to a systematic way,
using elimination,
to find the solution,
if there is one,
to a system of any size and
find out -- because if
elimination fails,
find out when there isn't a
solution.
Okay, thanks.