PROFESSOR: Hello, I'm Linan.
Welcome to Recitation
of Linear Algebra.
It's my great pleasure to guide
you through the first
recitation.
In the first lecture,
we learned
some important concepts.
We discussed how to view a
linear system of equations
from different points.
And we discussed the concepts
such as row picture, column
picture, and the
form in matrix.
Some of them may
be new to you.
So today, we're going to use
this simple example to review
those concepts.
We're going to work with this
simple system of two equations
with two unknowns.
So I would like you to first
solve it, and then to find out
the associated row picture
and column
picture with this system.
After you're done, we're also
going to discuss the matrix
form of this linear system.
Why don't you pause the video
now and try to work them out
on your own.
A good suggestion would be,
you can try to sketch your
answer in an xy coordinate
like this.
OK, I'll see you in a while.
I hope you have just had
some fun with it.
Let's work on it together.
Well, we're going to solve
these equations.
As you can see, we have
two unknowns, x and y.
And they have to satisfy
these two
equations at the same time.
How would you solve it?
A very simple way would
be you substitute x by
y, in terms of y.
So let's do it this way.
So we use the second equation
to rewrite x as 2y minus 1.
So 2y minus 1.
Then you plug this into
the first equation.
This implies twice.
x would be replaced by this.
2 times 2y minus 1 plus
y is equal to 3.
When you simplify this equation
here, you will arrive
at that 5y minus 2
is equal to 3.
That simply tells you
y is equal to 1.
If y is equal to 1, then we
go back to this formula.
We see that x is also
equal to 1.
That's it.
This is the answer to
this linear system.
And it's easy enough.
Both x and y are 1.
Now, let's try to
find out its row
picture and column picture.
So I'm going to work on this
xy coordinate here.
First, let's look
at row picture.
Please review what
a row picture is.
So by row picture, I mean you
have to look at this linear
system according to each row.
So what is the first row?
Well, the first row is an
equation with two unknowns.
So 2 times x plus
y is equal to 3.
What is this equation,
exactly?
As you may remember, this
equation actually gives you a
straight line in xy plane.
So now let's put
the line here.
I want a line that satisfies
2x plus y is 3.
Let's first set x to be 0.
If x is 0, by the first
equation, y should
be 3, which is here.
Now, let's set x to be 1.
If x is 1, then y is also 1.
So what I have now are two
points on the line.
And this is enough, because on
the xy plane, two points will
uniquely determine
a straight line.
And that's the line
we're looking for.
So all we need to do is to
connect these two points.
We try to draw this
line straight.
So this is the line that
is given by 2x plus
y is equal to 3.
This is the easiest way
to determine a line.
You just need to pick two points
that are on the line.
Then you connect them,
and here you have
the straight line.
So that's the first row.
Now let's look at
the second row.
The second row is x minus
2y is equal to -1.
Same thing.
We're going to locate two points
on the second line.
So again, let's set x to be
0 first. If x is 0, then y
should be 1/2, right?
So this line has to
cross this point.
That's x, 0, y, 1/2.
Then let's put x
to be 1 again.
So if x is 1, then
y is also 1.
So we're going to use
the same point here.
Now we have two points in the
second line to connect them.
So by connecting them, I will
have my second straight line.
So this is the line
corresponding to
x minus 2y is -1.
This is the row picture, because
we have separated the
two equations, and we look
at them respectively.
The first equation gives me
this line, and the second
equation gives me this line.
Then what do I mean by solving
this linear system?
Well, we are putting these two
lines together, and we are
looking at a point which is on
the first line and second line
at the same time.
Then clearly, that's the point
where they intersect, right?
We can see from the answer over
there, the coordinate of
this point should be 1,1.
This is also clear from the
construction of the two lines.
We have noticed that this point
is on the first line and
the second line at
the same time.
Two lines meeting at
the point 1,1.
That's the row picture of
this linear system.
Now, let's move on to
the column picture.
Again, I will need
an xy coordinate.
So, where can I find
my columns?
If you look at the two
equations, then you focus on
the coefficient in front
of x in both equations.
What would that be?
Well, in the first equation,
I have 2 in front of x.
In the second equation, I
have a 1 in front of x.
I want to put them together
as a column vector.
Let me call it V1.
And I'm going to do the same
thing to the coefficients in
front of y.
In the first equation, I
have a 1 in front of y.
In the second equation, I
have a -2 in front of y.
Put them together.
Call it column vector V2.
These are the columns
I'm looking for.
Then what does that
linear system say?
Well, I have extracted the
coefficients in front of x.
Now I can consider x to be the
coefficient of this vector.
And same thing, I'm going to
view y as the coefficient of
this vector.
Then what that linear
system is doing is
just to sum them up.
That gives you the left-hand
side of the linear system.
What is the right-hand side?
Again, you put the two constants
as a column vector,
which is 3, -1.
That is the right-hand side.
So what I'm doing here is I'm
taking the linear combination
of V1 and V2.
And the coefficients are given
by x and y, respectively.
And I want the result of this
combination to be 3, -1.
Now let's incorporate this
into this picture.
I have a V1, so I'm going
to draw a vector V1.
x is 2, y is 1, so V1 is here.
That's V1.
And I need a V2.
x is 1.
y is -2.
So that's my V2.
I want to take the sum of
x multiple of V1 and
y multiple of V2.
And I want the result
to be 3, -1.
Well, taking a hint from the
previous consideration, we
know that both x and
y should be 1.
So I'm actually summing one copy
of V1 and one copy of V2.
So how do you indicate the
sum of these two vectors?
You complete the parallelogram
spanned by these two vectors.
Then the vector given by
the diagonal is the
sum of V1 and V2.
Is this vector going
to be 3, -1?
Well, we can check.
The x-coordinate will be
2 plus 1, which is 3.
That's 2 plus 1, 3.
And the y-coordinate
will be 1 minus 2.
So 1 minus 2, which
should be -1.
That's it.
That's one multiple of V1
and one multiple of V2.
The sum will be 3, -1.
And that's the row picture.
Where does that that
"x is equal to y is
equal to 1" come from?
It comes from solving
the linear system.
It comes from the row picture.
So here, we have found out the
row picture and the column
picture of this linear system.
What I would like to mention
is the matrix form of this
linear system.
So what is the matrix form?
What if I put these two column
vectors together?
So I want to put them back
to back, V1 and V2.
And I call this matrix to be A.
So if you write it out, A
should be given by
2, 1, 1, -2.
Matrix A has V1 and V2 as its
column vectors, and it's a
2-by-2 matrix.
If I consider if I take this
into account, then what will
be the left-hand side of
the linear system?
In other words, what would
be the left-hand
side of this equation?
This is actually matrix
A multiplying a
vector given by xy.
So that's 2, 1, 1, -2,
multiplying x and y.
So you put both unknowns
together as a column vector.
That's the left-hand side
of the equation.
And again, the right-hand side
is given by this column
vector, 3, -1.
This is the matrix form
of this linear system.
We can actually solve
this directly.
In other words, we can get this
unknown vector at once,
both x-coordinate and
y-coordinate.
Let's recall, if you have a
scalar equation like this--
let's say a is some constant
times x is
unknown is equal to b--
if a is non-zero,
what would be x?
So clearly, x should
be b over a.
I can also write it as
a inverse times b.
That's what we do when
we have numbers.
So here, what we want to
apply is a similar
idea but to a matrix.
What you want to find is a
matrix A inverse such that A
inverse times A is equal
to an identity matrix
which is 1, 0, 0, 1.
This may be new to you, but as
you go further into this
course, this idea will become
more and more natural.
If such an inverse matrix
exists, then what would be
this vector here?
Then xy will simply be A
inverse times 3, -1.
That will give you the answer.
Here, I'm not going to go into
detail, but we will return to
this later in this course.
I hope this simple example is
helpful to you in reviewing
what you've learned
in the lecture.
Thank you for watching, and
I'm looking forward
to seeing you again.