ANA RITA PIRES: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about the properties
of determinants.
To remember, there were three
main properties, and then
seven more that fall
out of those three.
I'll tell you what
these three were.
The first one was the
determinant of the identity
matrix is always equal to 1.
If you switch two rows in a
matrix, the determinant
switches sign, and the
determinant is
a function of each--
it's a linear function of
each row separately.
And there's seven more.
We'll use them here.
Today's problem is about finding
the determinants of
matrices by using these
properties.
So here you have
four matrices.
A has lots of 100s, 200s,
and 300s numbers.
B is called a Vandermonde
matrix.
It has a very nice structure
with 1s, and then abc, a
squared, b squared, c squared.
It can be bigger, and you'll
just have cubes and more
letters down here.
C is given by the product
of these two,
and D is this matrix.
Good luck.
Hit pause, work on them, and
when you're ready, come back
and I'll show you
how I did it.
Did you get some?
OK, let's do it.
Starting with matrix A. I have
lots of big numbers.
I suggest that we do a little
bit of elimination, because as
you know, doing elimination
steps, except for permuting
rows, doesn't change the
determinant in the matrix.
So let's do determinant
of A is equal to 101.
201.
301.
Then if I subtract off the first
row from the second one,
I'll get 1, 1, 1, which
is very convenient.
And actually, if you subtract
the second row from the third
one, you'll get 1, 1, 1.
Here's the property of
the determinant.
If you have two equal rows on
your matrix, the determinant
is automatically
equal to zero.
All right.
All done with one of them.
Let's work on the second one.
The determinant of B. Well let's
try elimination again.
1, a, a squared.
1 minus 1 is 0, b minus a, and
b squared minus a squared.
b squared minus a squared--
let me factor that into b
minus a, b plus a, which
will be very
convenient in the next step.
And then I'm going to subtract
the first row again
from the third one.
I'll get 0, c minus a.
And again, I'll get c squared
minus a squared, c
minus a, c plus a.
Let's use that third property
that was the determinant is
linear on each row separately.
So what I'm going to do is, see
this factor of b minus a?
It shows up in every
entry of this row.
Well it's a 0, so it's the
0 multiple of b minus a.
So I'm going to pull out this
factor of b minus a, and this
row is going to become
0, 1, b plus a.
I will also, in the same
step, do the same thing
with the third row.
I'll pull out a factor of c
minus a, and it will become 0,
1, c plus a.
Here's one factor from
the second row.
Another factor from
the third row.
And 1, a, a squared.
0, 1, b plus a.
0, 1, c plus a.
Now what?
Well remember, you know how to
do the determinant of upper
triangular matrices because all
that you do is multiply
the pivots.
This is almost upper
triangular, except
there's a 1 over here.
So let's do another
elimination step.
b minus a, c minus a,
1, a, a squared.
0, 1, b plus a.
0, 0, c plus a minus b
plus a is c minus b.
So the determinant of this
matrix is now 1 times 1
times c minus b.
So we get b minus a, c minus
a, c minus b, which has a
really nice formula.
This is called the Vandermonde
determinant.
It's always like this, even if
your matrix is bigger than 3
by 3, if it's 4 by 4, or 5 by
5 and so on, you just have
more differences of all
the letters that
show up in your matrix.
On to matrix number 3.
C equals 1, 2, 3.
1, -4, 5.
How did you get the determinant
for this one?
Well remember, this is a rank
one matrix because it's a
column vector times
a row vector.
So if you write out what the
matrix is it'll be a 3 by 3
matrix where we can think
about it this way.
The first row will be
1 times 1, -4, 5.
The second row will be 2
times those numbers.
And the third row will be three
So all the rows are going to
be linearly dependent, or
another way of saying the
matrix is singular.
When the matrix is singular,
the determinant is always
equal to 0.
That's also one of
the properties.
C is 0.
Onto the next matrix.
Last one.
D is equal to 0, 0, 0.
1, -1, 3, -3, 4, -4.
Maybe you didn't get that from
just looking at the matrix the
first time, but did you see
how I wrote it down?
It has 0's down the diagonal.
And then for each entry, I
have minus that entry.
That means that this matrix
is skew symmetric.
What that means is if you do
D transpose, it will not be
equal to D, but it will be equal
to minus D. D transpose
is equal to minus D.
Now, what does this give
us for a determinant?
Well if these two matrices
are the same matrix, this
determinant is equal to
that determinant.
One of the properties is that
the determinant of a transpose
of the matrix is equal
to the determinant of
the original matrix.
How about this side?
Well first temptation would
be to just write that.
Is that always true?
No.
The determinant is linear
on each row separately.
That means that you can't pull
out the factor that is
multiplying the matrix.
You have to pull it out once
for each row of the matrix.
So what I should have
written was -1,
that's my factor minus.
How many rows do I have?
One, two, three.
Pull it out once for each row
times the determinant of D.
Well fortunately, -1 to the
third is simply equal to -1.
So here we go.
It was correct, in fact.
We have determinant of D is
equal to minus determinant of
D. What is the only number
that is equal
to minus that number?
0.
Determinant of D is
equal to 0 again.
Let me ask you one
last question.
Is it true that all skew
symmetric matrices have the
determinant equal to 0?
It was true for this one.
Is it true in every case?
Well the key factor here was
that I had -1 to the third
power and I got a minus sign
here, determinant of D is
equal to minus determinant
of D.
What if this number had
been an even number?
Then I would just have the
determinant of D is equal
minus 1 to an even number,
D. That's 1.
So I would have determinant of
D is equal to determinant of
D. There's nothing I can
say about that number.
It can be your favorite number,
not necessarily 0.
All right.
We're done for today.
Thank you.