DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
So today I want to practice
doing some computings of
integrals with you at
polar coordinates.
So we have these three integrals
set up here.
And the way the integrals are
given to you, they're given to
you in rectangular
coordinates.
So the first thing you need to
do is to re-express these in
polar coordinates.
And so for the first one, part
a, I want you to completely
compute the integral.
For part b and c, we have this
function f, which we haven't
specified yet.
So the exercise is to
set up the integral.
We won't actually compute
it, we'll just set it up
completely.
So rewrite it in terms
of r and theta.
So why don't you pause the video
and get started on that.
And check back with me and we'll
work it out together.
Welcome back.
Let's get started.
So for all of these, when
we're transferring from
rectangular to polar
coordinates, the most
difficult part is understanding
what region
we're integrating over.
And if we can understand that,
then the rest of it is just
straightforward calculation.
So in part a, let's try to think
about what this region
is that we're given.
So we're given the region from
x equals 1 to x equals 2.
So let's draw those lines. x
equals 1 and x equals 2.
OK, so that's how x varies
in between this band.
And now the y varies from
0 to the function x.
So we'd better draw the
line y equals x.
OK, so this is the
And the region that we're after
is in between this band
and in between these two lines,
so it's this region
right here.
That's the region
that we want.
All right.
So now that we have that, what
we need to do to express
something in polar coordinates
is we need to sweep out rays
of constant angle, and
then measure the
radius along the ray.
So let's see what
I mean by that.
So we can kind of see that if
we're inside this region here,
the smallest value that theta
can be is just theta equals 0.
Because, sprint is right here is
a point at theta equals 0.
And then theta runs
all the way up.
And this whole line here is
where theta reaches its
maximum, and that's at
theta is pi over 4.
So this tells us that it's
easiest to write the theta
integral on the outside.
And we're going to have theta
running from 0 to pi over 4.
OK, very good.
Now, in order to get the r
ranges, it's going to be a
little bit more subtle, because
what we need to do is
we need to fix some arbitrary
theta in the middle here.
So I'll just draw kind of
a representative theta.
It would be like
this one here.
So there is a representative
theta.
And what we need to do is, we
need to describe how r varies
along this pink line here.
So that's the line that
we really want.
OK.
So in order to do that, we just
need to do some simple
trigonometry now.
So let's see.
So r turns on at this
line right here.
At the line x equals 1: that's
where r turns on.
So let's see what the value
of r is at that line here.
So, the pont is that we
have --so let me draw
this triangle here--.
Let me blow this triangle up.
OK.
So this is our line x equals
1, and this is
this triangle here.
We just put a magnifying
glass on it.
So we have this angle theta.
OK.
So this x-value is 1, because
we're on the line x equals 1.
So the length of this leg
is 1, and this is
r that we're after.
OK?
So in basic trigonometry
we know that cos
theta is equal to--
so cosine is adjacent
over hypotenuse--
is equal to 1 over r.
OK, so that tells us that
r is equal to sec theta.
OK?
So what that means is that this,
for any given theta,
this pink band turns on at
precisely r equals sec theta.
And so that's what we need to
write in the bottom here.
OK?
Now, you can see that it turns
off at r equals 2 sec theta.
Because now instead of going
over length 1, we
go over length 2.
And so our integral becomes
the integral from
0 to pi over 4.
And r equals sec theta
to 2 sec theta.
OK, and now we need to
re-express our original
function in terms
of r and theta.
So our original function was,
so let's go back over to the
formula here.
So we have x squared plus
y squared to the 3/2.
So x squared plus y squared
to the 1/2 that's r.
And so x squared plus
y squared to the
3/2 that's r cubed.
So this is 1 over r cubed.
So this is 1 over
r cubed in here.
And as we know, dy dx becomes
r dr d theta.
OK.
So this is the integral that
we need to compute, and now
that we've done all the
geometry, this is going to be
a straightforward integral
to compute.
So let's do it together.
I'll just rewrite
it over here.
So we have theta running from 0
to pi over 4, and r running
from sec theta to 2 sec theta.
And we have 1 over r squared,
dr d theta.
OK.
So that equals--
taking the inside
integral first--
we get negative 1 over r from
2 sec theta to sec theta.
OK?
And now this is nice,
because sec theta--
if we plug it in for 1 over r--
it's just going to turn
back into a cosine, right?
So this is just the integral
from theta equals
0 to pi over 4.
OK, because we have this minus
sign here, we're going to get
cos theta minus--
1 over 2 sec theta becomes--
1/2 cos theta, d theta.
And this we can compute to be
the square root of 2 over 4.
So this is an elementary
integral that we can compute:
the square root of 2, over 4.
OK.
And that's it.
That's all there is to a.
So notice that the difficult
part is figuring out how the
boundary curves of your original
region re-express in
the r and theta coordinates.
So let's see if we can get more
practice with that on
parts b and c.
So in part b--
let me just recall--
we're taking the integral
x equals 0 to 1.
And y equals x squared
to x, f dy dx.
So let's draw this
region again.
So the bottom curve is y equals
x squared and the top
curve is y equals x, and
x runs from 0 to 1.
So this is the region
that we're after.
OK.
So once again in this case, it's
pretty easy to figure out
the range for theta.
Because you see this parabola
here, as it approaches the
origin, it becomes flat.
So the theta, as we get
closer and closer to
the origin, is 0.
So the initial bound
for theta is 0.
It doesn't matter that we have
this curve here, it's still 0.
And then the top bound,
again, is pi over 4.
OK?
Now, for this curve y equals x
squared, what we just have to
do is we just have to use our
polar change of coordinates
and re-express this curve.
So y equals x squared.
Well, y is r sine theta.
And x is r cos theta.
So this is altogether r squared
cos squared theta.
OK?
And now all we need to do is
just solve for r here.
So we get r equals-- so I can
cancel that r with that one--
and it looks to me like we get
r equals tan theta secant
theta by solving.
OK.
So that's the r-value
at each of these
points along the curve.
So that is going to
be our top bound.
So if we draw little segments
of constant theta, they all
start at r equals 0, because we
have this sharp point here
at the origin.
And they all stop at this
curve: r equals
tan theta sec theta.
All right?
And so now f we're just
going to leave put.
And then finally we
have r dr d theta.
OK.
So that's our answer to b.
All right.
Now c is going to be a
little bit tricky.
What's tricky about c is drawing
a picture, but we'll
see what we can do about that.
So let me just remind you. y
ranges from 0 to 2, and x
ranges from 0 to the square root
of 2y minus y squared.
And then we have f dx dy.
OK.
Well, the y bounds are pretty
straightforward, 0 to 2.
This function, when I first saw
this, I didn't recognize
this function right away.
So let's see what we can
make out of this curve.
So the top curve for x is
going to be x equals the
square root of 2y
minus y squared.
And this looks like
it wants to be the
equation of a circle.
So let's see if we can
turn this into an
equation of a circle.
So if we square both sides of
this equation, then we get x
squared equals 2y
minus y squared.
And now this over here, 2y minus
y squared, so if we add
this over to the other side,
we have x squared plus y
squared minus 2y equals 0.
And now the thing that I notice
about this expression
here is it really looks
almost like the
quantity y minus 1 squared.
Yeah?
If there were a plus 1 here,
then that would be the case.
So this is actually x squared,
plus y minus 1 squared--
except the left-hand side is not
quite equal to that-- it's
equal to that, minus 1.
So this equation
just equals 0.
So this equation is just
equivalent to that one.
And that's good news, because
this says that, this is the
equation if I add this 1 over
to the other side--
let me go over here--
we have x squared, plus y minus
1 squared, equals 1.
And this, we know
what this is.
This is a circle which is
centered not at the origin,
but at the point 0 comma
1 in the y-direction.
So if we draw this, well,
this is the equation
for the entire circle.
But we only want the positive
half, because we were told
that x starts at 0 and goes up
to this positive number.
So we only want the positive
half here.
OK.
So this is the region that
we're integrating.
And now that we know this, we
can again figure out the
values of theta and
the values of r.
So first of all, theta is going
to range again from 0,
because this bottom curve, as
it comes into the origin, it
comes in flat.
So we have points of arbitrarily
small angles.
So theta is going to start a
0, and theta is going to go
all the way up until pi over
2, because theta can be
pointing straight up.
OK?
And now we have to think about
these lines of constant angle,
and we need to think about
what r does in there.
So we can see from the picture
that r always starts at 0 and
it stops at this curve.
So we need to figure out what
the r-value is along this
curve in terms of theta.
So what we want to do
is use the equation.
So we had it over here.
So x squared plus y squared
minus 2y equals 0.
So that was one of the
equivalent equations that we
got for our curve.
And now this is nice, because
this here is just r
squared, isn't it?
So this is r squared.
And this is minus 2y, and
y is r sine theta.
OK.
So we get r squared minus
2r sine theta equals 0.
Solving this for r, we get that
r is just 2 sine theta.
OK.
So r equals 2 sine theta.
That is the equation in r,
theta coordinates, which
describes this semicircle
here.
And so altogether, we get the
range is from r equals 0 to r
equals 2 sine theta.
And f just comes along
for the ride, and
we have r dr d theta.
And I'll leave it at that.