May I just read out some
problems and,
let me bring the board down,
and let's start.
OK.
Here's a question.
This is about a 3-by-n matrix.
And we're given -- so we're
given -- given -- A x equals 1 0
0 has no solution.
And we're also given A x equals
0 1 0 has exactly one solution.
OK.
So you can probably anticipate
my first question,
what can you tell me about m?
It's an m-by-n matrix of rank
r, as always,
what can you tell me about
those three numbers?
So what can you tell me about
m, the number of rows,
n, the number of columns,
and r, the rank?
OK.
See, do you want to tell me
first what m is?
How many rows in this matrix?
Must be three,
right?
We can't tell what n is,
but we can certainly tell that
m is three.
OK.
And, what do these things tell
us?
Let's take them one at a time.
When I discover that some
equation has no solution,
that there's some right-hand
side with no answer,
what does that tell me about
the rank of the matrix?
It's smaller m.
Is that right?
If there is no solution,
that tells me that some rows of
the matrix are combinations of
other rows.
Because if I had a pivot in
every row, then I would
certainly be able to solve the
system.
I would have particular
solutions and all the good
stuff.
So any time that there's a
system with no solutions,
that tells me that r must be
below m.
What about the fact that if,
when there is a solution,
there's only one?
What does that tell me?
Well, normally there would be
one solution,
and then we could add in
anything in the null space.
So this is telling me the null
space only has the 0 vector in
it.
There's just one solution,
period, so what does that tell
me?
The null space has only the
zero vector in it?
What does that tell me about
the relation of r to n?
So this one solution only,
that means the null space of
the matrix must be just the zero
vector, and what does that tell
me about r and n?
They're equal.
The columns are independent.
So I've got,
now, r equals n,
and r less than m,
and now I also know m is three.
So those are really the facts I
know.
n=r and those numbers are
smaller than three.
Sorry, yes, yes.
r is smaller than m,
and n, of course,
is also.
So I guess this summarizes what
we can tell.
In fact, why not give me a
matrix -- because I would often
ask for an example of such a
matrix -- can you give me a
matrix A that's an example?
That shows this possibility?
Exactly, that there's no
solution with that right-hand
side, but there's exactly one
solution with this right-hand
side.
Anybody want to suggest a
matrix that does that?
Let's see.
What do I -- what vector do I
want in the column space?
I want zero,
one, zero, to be in the column
space, because I'm able to solve
for that.
So let's put zero,
one, zero in the column space.
Actually, I could stop right
there.
That would be a matrix with m
equal three, three rows,
and n and r are both one,
rank one, one column,
and, of course,
there's no solution to that
one.
So that's perfectly good as it
is.
Or if you, kind of,
have a prejudice against
matrices that only have one
column, I'll accept a second
column.
So what could I include as a
second column that would just be
a different answer but equally
good?
I could put this vector in the
column space,
too, if I wanted.
That would now be a case with
r=n=2, but, of course,
three m eq- m is still three,
and this vector is not in the
column space.
So you're -- this is just like
prompting us to remember all
those things,
column space,
null space, all that stuff.
Now, I probably asked a second
question about this type of
thing.
Ah.
OK.
Oh, I even asked,
write down an example of a
matrix that fits the
description.
Hm.
I guess I haven't learned
anything in twenty-six years.
CK.
Cross out all statements that
are false about any matrix with
these -- so again,
these are -- this is the
preliminary sta- these are the
facts about my matrix,
this is one example.
But, of course,
by having an example,
it will be easy to check some
of these facts,
or non-facts.
Let me, let me write down some,
facts.
Some possible facts.
So this is really true or
false.
The determinant -- this is part
one, the determinant of A
transpose A is the same as the
determinant of A A transpose.
Is that true or not?
Second one, A transpose A,
is invertible.
Is invertible.
Third possible fact,
A A transpose is positive
definite.
So you see how,
on an exam question,
I try to connect the different
parts of the course.
So, well, I mean,
the simplest way would be to
try it with that matrix as a
good example,
but maybe we can answer,
even directly.
Let me take number two first.
Because I'm -- you know,
I'm very, very fond of that
matrix, A transpose A.
And when is it invertible?
When is the matrix A transpose
A, invertible?
The great thing is that I can
tell from the rank of A that I
don't have to multiply out A
transpose A.
A transpose A,
is invertible -- well,
if A has a null space other
than the zero vector,
then it -- it's -- no way it's
going to be invertible.
But the beauty is,
if the null space of A is just
the zero vector,
so the fact -- the key fact is,
this is invertible if r=n,
by which I mean,
independent columns of A.
In A.
In the matrix A.
If r=n -- if the matrix A has
independent columns,
then this combination,
A transpose A,
is square and still that same
null space, only the zero
vector, independent columns all
good, and so,
what's the true/false?
Is it -- is this middle one T
or F for this,
in this setup?
Well, we discovered that -- we
discovered that -- that r was n,
from that second fact.
So this is a true.
That's a true.
And, of course,
A transpose A,
in this example,
would probably be -- what would
A transpose A,
be, for that matrix?
Can you multiply A transpose A,
and see what it looks like for
that matrix?
What shape would it be?
It will be two by two.
And what matrix will it be?
The identity.
So, it checks out.
OK, what about A A transpose?
Well, depending on the shape of
A, it could be good or not so
good.
It's always symmetric,
it's always square,
but what's the size,
now?
This is three by n,
and this is n by three,
so the result is three by
three.
Is it positive definite?
I don't think so.
False.
If I multiply that by A
transpose, A A transpose,
what would the rank be?
It would be the same as the
rank of A, that's -- it would be
just rank two.
And if it's three-by-three,
and it's only rank two,
it's certainly not positive
definite.
So what could I say about A A
transpose, if I wanted to,
like, say something true about
it?
It's true that it is positive
semi-definite.
If I made this semi-definite,
it would always be true,
always.
But if I'm looking for positive
definite, then I'm looking at
the null space of whatever's
here, and, in this case,
it's got a null space.
So A, A -- eh,
shall we just figure it out,
here?
A A transpose,
for that matrix,
will be three-by-three.
If I multiplied A by A
transpose, what would the first
row be?
All zeroes, right?
First row of A A transpose,
could only be all zeroes,
so it's probably a one there
and a one there,
or something like that.
But, I don't even know if
that's right.
But it's all zeroes there,
so it's certainly not positive
definite.
Let me not put anything up I'm
not sh- don't check.
What about this determinant?
Oh, well, I guess -- that's a
sort of tricky question.
Is it true or false in this
case?
It's false, apparently,
because A transpose A,
is invertible,
we just got a true for this
one, and we got a false,
we got a z- we got a
non-invertible one for this one.
So actually,
this one is false,
number one.
That surprises us,
actually, because it's,
I mean, why was it tricky?
Because what is true about
determinants?
This would be true if those
matrices were square.
If I have two square matrices,
A and any other matrix B,
could be A transpose,
could be somebody else's
matrix.
Then it would be true that the
determinant of B A would equal
the determinant of A B.
But if the matrices are not
square and it would actually be
true that it would be equal --
that this would equal the
determinant of A times the
determinant of A transpose.
We could even split up those
two separate determinants.
And, of course,
those would be equal.
But only when A is square.
So that's just,
that's a question that rests on
the, the falseness rests on the
fact that the matrix isn't
square in the first place.
OK, good.
Let's see.
Oh, now, even asks more.
Prove that A transpose y equals
c -- hah-God,
it's -- this question goes on
and on.
now I ask you about A transpose
y=c.
So I'm asking you about the
equation -- about the matrix A
transpose.
And I want you to prove that it
has at least one solution -- one
solution for every c,
every right-hand side c,
and, in fact -- in fact,
infinitely many solutions for
every c.
OK.
Well, none -- none of this is
difficult, but,
it's been a little while.
So we just have to think again.
When I have a system of
equations -- this is -- this
matrix A transpose is now,
instead of being three by n,
it's n by three,
it's n by m.
Of course.
To show that a system has at
least one solution,
when does this,
when does this system -- when
is the system always solvable?
When it has full row rank,
when the rows are independent.
Here, we have n rows,
and that's the rank.
So at least one solution,
because the number of rows,
which is n, for the transpose,
is equal to r,
the rank.
This A transpose had
independent rows because A had
independent columns,
right?
The original A had independent
columns, when we transpose it,
it has independent rows,
so there's at least one
solution.
But now, how do I even know
that there are infinitely many
solutions?
Oh, what do I -- I want to know
something about the null space.
What's the dimension of the
null space of A transpose?
So the answer has got to be the
dimension of the null space of A
transpose, what's the general
fact?
If A is an m by n matrix of
rank r, what's the dimension of
A transpose?
The null space of A transpose?
Do you remember that little
fourth subspace that's tagging
along down in our big picture?
It's dimension was m-r.
And, that's bigger than zero.
m is bigger than r.
So there's a lot in that null
space.
So there's always one solution
because n i- this is speaking
about A transpose.
So for A transpose,
the roles of m and n are
reversed, of course,
so I'm -- keep in mind that
this board was about A
transpose, so the roles -- so
it's the null space of a
transpose, and there are m-r
free variables.
OK, that's, like,
just some, review.
Can I take another problem
that's also sort of
-- suppose the matrix A has
three columns,
v1, v2, v3.
Those are the columns of the
matrix.
All right.
Question A.
Solve Ax=v1-v2+v3.
Tell me what x is.
Well, there,
you're seeing the most
-- the one absolutely essential
fact about matrix
multiplication,
how does it work,
when we do it a column at a
time, the very,
very first day,
way back in September,
we did multiplication a column
at a time.
So what's x?
Just tell me?
One minus one,
one.
Thanks.
OK.
Everybody's got that.
OK?
Then the next question is,
suppose that combination is
zero -- oh, yes,
OK, so question (b) says --
part (b) says,
suppose this thing is zero.
Suppose that's zero.
Then the solution is not
unique.
Suppose I want true or false.
-- and a reason.
Suppose this combination is
zero.
v1-v2+v3.
Show that -- what does that
tell me?
So it's a separate question,
maybe I sort of saved time by
writing it that way,
but it's a totally separate
question.
If I have a matrix,
and I know that column one
minus column two plus column
three is zero,
what does that tell me about
whether the solution is unique
or not?
Is there more than one
solution?
What's uniqueness about?
Uniqueness is about,
is there anything in the null
space, right?
The solution is unique when
there's nobody in the null space
except the zero vector.
And, if that's zero,
then this guy would be in the
null space.
So if this were zero,
then this x is in the null
space of A.
So solutions are never unique,
because I could always add that
to any solution,
and Ax wouldn't change.
So it's always that question.
Is there somebody in the null
space?
OK.
Oh, now, here's a totally
different question.
Suppose those three vectors,
v1, v2, v3, are orthonormal.
So this isn't going to happen
for orthonormal vectors.
OK, so part (c),
forget part (b).
c.
If v1, v2, v3,
are orthonormal -- so that I
would usually have called them
q1, q2, q3.
Now, what combination -- oh,
here's a nice question,
if I say so myself -- what
combination of v1 and v2 is
closest to v3?
What point on the plane of v1
and v2 is the closest point to
v3 if these vectors are
orthonormal?
So let me -- I'll start the
sentence -- then the combination
something times v1 plus
something times v2 is the
closest combination to v3?
And what's the answer?
What's the closest vector on
that plane to v3?
Zeroes.
Right.
We just imagine the x,
y, z axes, the v1,
v2, th- v3 could be the
standard basis,
the x, y, z vectors,
and, of course,
the point on the xy plane
that's closest to v3 on the z
axis is zero.
So if we're orthonormal,
then the projection of v3 onto
that plane is perpendicular,
it hits right at zero.
OK, so that's like a quick --
you know, an easy question,
but still brings it out.
OK.
Let me see what,
shall I write down a Markov
matrix, and I'll ask you for its
eigenvalues.
OK.
Here's a Markov matrix -- this
-- and, tell me its eigenvalues.
So here -- I'll call the matrix
A, and I'll call this as point
two, point four,
point four, point four,
point four, point two,
point four, point three,
point three,
point four.
OK.
Let's see -- it helps out to
notice that column one plus
column two
-- what's interesting about
column one plus column two?
It's twice as much as column
three.
So column one plus column two
equals two times column three.
I put that in there,
column one plus column two
equals twice column three.
That's observation.
OK.
Tell me the eigenvalues of the
matrix.
OK, tell me one eigenvalue?
Because the matrix is singular.
Tell me another eigenvalue?
One, because it's a Markov
matrix, the columns add to the
all ones vector,
and that will be an eigenvector
of A transpose.
And tell me the third
eigenvalue?
Let's see, to make the trace
come out right,
which is point eight,
we need minus point two.
OK.
And now, suppose I start the
Markov process.
Suppose I start with u(0) -- so
I'm going to look at the powers
of A applied to u(0).
This is uk.
And there's my matrix,
and I'm going to let u(0) be --
this is going to be zero,
ten, zero.
And my question is,
what does that approach?
If u(0) is equal to this --
there is u(0).
Shall I write it in?
Maybe I'll just write in u(0).
A to the k, starting with ten
people in state two,
and every step follows the
Markov rule, what does the
solution look like after k
steps?
Let me just ask you that.
And then, what happens as k
goes to infinity?
This is a steady-state
question, right?
I'm looking for the steady
state.
Actually, the question doesn't
ask for the k step answer,
it just jumps right away to
infinity -- but how would I
express the solution after k
steps?
It would be some multiple of
the first eigenvalue to the k-th
power -- times the first
eigenvector, plus some other
multiple of the second
eigenvalue, times its
eigenvector, and some multiple
of the third eigenvalue,
times its eigenvector.
OK.
Good.
And these eigenvalues are zero,
one, and minus point two.
So what happens as k goes to
infinity?
The only thing that survives
the steady state -- so at u
infinity, this is gone,
this is gone,
all that's left is c2x2.
So I'd better find x2.
I've got to find that
eigenvector to complete the
answer.
What's the eigenvector that
corresponds to lambda equal one?
That's the key eigenvector in
any Markov process,
is that eigenvector.
Lambda equal one is an
eigenvalue, I need its
eigenvector x2,
and then I need to know how
much of it is in the starting
vector u0.
OK.
So, how do I find that
eigenvector?
I guess I subtract one from the
diagonal, right?
So I have minus point eight,
minus point eight,
minus point six,
and the rest,
of course, is just
-- still point four,
point four, point four,
point four, point three,
point three,
and hopefully,
that's a singular matrix,
so I'm looking to solve A minus
Ix equal zero.
Let's see -- can anybody spot
the solution here?
I don't know,
I didn't make it easy for
myself.
What do you think there?
Maybe those first two entries
might be -- oh,
no, what do you think?
Anybody see it?
We could use elimination if we
were desperate.
Are we that desperate?
Anybody just call out if you
see the vector that's in that
null space.
Eh, there better be a vector in
that null space,
or I'm quitting.
Uh, ha- OK, well,
I guess we could use
elimination.
I thought maybe somebody might
see it from further away.
Is there a chance that these
guys are -- could it be that
these two are equal and this is
whatever it takes,
like, something like three,
three, two?
Would that possibly work?
I mean, that's great for this
-- no, it's not that great.
Three, three,
four -- this is,
deeper mathematics you're
watching now.
Three, three,
four, is that -- it works!
Don't mess with it!
It works!
Uh, yes.
OK, it works,
all right.
And, yes, OK,
and, so that's x2,
three, three,
four, and, how much of that
vector is in the starting
vector?
Well, we could go through a
complicated process.
But what's the beauty of Markov
things?
That the total number of the
total population,
the sum of these doesn't
change.
That the total number of
people, they're moving around,
but they don't get born or die
or get dead.
So there's ten of them at the
start, so there's ten of them
there, so c2 is actually one,
yes.
So that would be the correct
solution.
OK.
That would be the u infinity.
So I used there,
in that process,
sort of, the main facts about
Markov matrices to,
to get a jump on the answer.
OK.
let's see.
OK, here's some,
kind of quick,
short questions.
Uh, maybe I'll move over to
this board, and leave that for
the moment.
I'm looking for two-by-two
matrices.
And I'll read out the property
I want, and you give me an
example, or tell me there isn't
such a matrix.
All right.
Here we go.
First -- so two-by-twos.
First, I want the projection
onto the line through A equals
four minus three.
So it's a one-dimensional
projection matrix I'm looking
for.
And what's the formula for it?
What's the formula for the
projection matrix P onto a line
through A.
And then we'd just plug in this
particular A.
Do you remember that formula?
There's an A and an A
transpose, and normally we would
have an A transpose A inverse in
the middle, but here we've just
got numbers, so we just divide
by it.
And then plug in A and we've
got it.
OK.
So, equals.
You can put in the numbers.
Trivial, right.
OK.
Number two.
So this is a new problem.
The matrix with eigenvalue zero
and three and eigenvectors --
well, let me write these down.
eigenvalue zero,
eigenvector one,
two, eigenvalue three,
eigenvector two,
one.
I'm giving you the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors instead of
asking for them.
Now I'm asking for the matrix.
What's the matrix,
then?
What's A?
Here was a formula,
then we just put in some
numbers, what's the formula
here, into which we'll just put
the given numbers?
It's the S lambda S inverse,
right?
So it's S, which is this
eigenvector matrix,
it's the lambda,
which is the eigenvalue matrix,
it's the S inverse,
whatever that turns out to be,
let me just leave it as
inverse.
That has to be it,
right?
Because if we went in the other
direction, that matrix S would
diagonalize A to produce lambda.
So it's S lambda S inverse.
Good.
OK, ready for number three.
A real matrix that cannot be
factored into A -- I'm looking
for a matrix A that never could
equal B transpose B,
for any B.
A two-by-two matrix that could
not be factored in the form B
transpose B.
So all you have to do is think,
well, what does B transpose B,
look like, and then pick
something different.
What do you suggest?
Let's see.
What shall we take for a matrix
that could not have this form,
B transpose B.
Well, what do we know about B
transpose B?
It's always symmetric.
So just give me any
non-symmetric matrix,
it couldn't possibly have that
form.
OK.
And let me ask the fourth part
of this question -- a matrix
that has orthogonal
eigenvectors,
but it's not symmetric.
What matrices have orthogonal
eigenvectors,
but they're not symmetric
matrices?
What other families of matrices
have orthogonal eigenvectors?
We know symmetric matrices do,
but others, also.
So I'm looking for orthogonal
eigenvectors,
and, what do you suggest?
The matrix could be
skew-symmetric.
It could be an orthogonal
matrix.
It could be symmetric,
but that was too easy,
so I ruled that out.
It could be skew-symmetric like
one minus one,
like that.
Or it could be an orthogonal
matrix like cosine sine,
minus sine, cosine.
All those matrices would have
complex orthogonal eigenvectors.
But they would be orthogonal,
and so those examples are fine.
OK.
We can continue a little longer
if you would like to,
with these -- from this exam.
From these exams.
Least squares?
OK, here's a least squares
problem in which,
to make life quick,
I've given the answer -- it's
like Jeopardy!,
right?
I just give the answer,
and you give the question.
OK.
Whoops, sorry.
Let's see, can I stay over here
for the next question?
OK.
least squares.
So I'm giving you the problem,
one, one, one,
zero, one, two,
c d equals three,
four, one, and that's b,
of course, this is Ax=b.
And the least squares solution
--
Maybe I put c hat d hat to
emphasize it's not the true
solution.
So the least square solution --
the hats really go here -- is
eleven-thirds and minus one.
Of course, you could have
figured that out in no time.
So this year,
I'll ask you to do it,
probably.
But, suppose we're given the
answer, then let's just remember
what happened.
OK, good question.
What's the projection P of this
vector onto the column space of
that matrix?
So I'll write that question
down, one.
What is P?
The projection.
The projection of b onto the
column space of A is what?
Hopefully, that's what the
least squares problem solved.
What is it?
This was the best solution,
it's eleven-thirds times column
one, plus -- or rather,
minus one times column two.
Right?
That's what least squares did.
It found the combination of the
columns that was as close as
possible to b.
That's what least squares was
doing.
It found the projection.
OK?
Secondly, draw the straight
line problem that corresponds to
this system.
So I guess that the straight
line fitting a straight line
problem, we kind of recognize.
So we recognize,
these are the heights,
and these are the points,
and so at zero,
one, two, the heights are
three, and at t equal to one,
the height is four,
one, two, three,
four, and at t equal to two,
the height is one.
So I'm trying to fit the best
straight line through those
points.
God.
I could fit a triangle very
well, but, I don't even know
which way the best straight line
goes.
Oh, I do know how it goes,
because there's the answer,yes.
It has a height eleven-thirds,
and it has slope minus one,
so it's something like that.
OK.
Great.
Now, finally -- and this
completes the course -- find a
different vector b,
not all zeroes,
for which the least square
solution would be zero.
So I want you to find a
different B so that the least
square solution changes to all
zeroes.
So tell me what I'm really
looking for here.
I'm looking for a b where the
best combination of these two
columns is the zero combination.
So what kind of a vector b I
looking for?
I'm looking for a vector b
that's orthogonal to those
columns.
It's orthogonal to those
columns, it's orthogonal to the
column space,
the best possible answer is
zero.
So a vector b that's orthogonal
to those columns -- let's see,
maybe one of those minus two of
those, and one of those?
That would be orthogonal to
those columns,
and the best vector would be
zero, zero.
OK.
So that's as many questions as
I can do in an hour,
but you get three hours,
and, let me just say,
as I've said by e-mail,
thanks very much for your
patience as this series of
lectures was videotaped,
and, thanks for filling out
these forms, maybe just leave
them on the table up there as
you go out
-- and above all,
thanks for taking the course.
Thank you.
Thanks.