PROFESSOR: Today, we're going to
be solving a problem from a
final exam.
And here it is.
It's about a matrix, A. 1,
0, 1, 0, 1, 1, 1, 1, 0.
And we know that this matrix has
two eigenvalues 1 and 2.
And we also know that if we do
elimination, the first two
pivots will be 1 and 1.
And here are two questions
about this matrix.
The first one is find lambda 3
in d3, the third eigenvalue in
the third pivot.
And the second one asks you,
what is the smallest a33?
So if you can change this entry,
what is the smallest
number that you can put there
that will make the matrix A
positive semidefinite?
And also, if instead of changing
that entry, you do A
plus cI, what is the smallest
number, c, that will make that
matrix a plus cI positive
semidefinite?
There's also a third part to the
question, but we'll get to
that later.
Why don't you hit pause and
work on these two parts?
And when you're ready, come
back and I'll show
you how I did it.
Hi.
I hope you managed to
do parts A and B.
Let's work on it together.
Part A. Well, we want to know
what the third eigenvalue is.
And you know what the
first two are.
What else do you know about
eigenvalues and the matrix?
You know that the sum of all the
eigenvalues of the matrix
is equal to the trace
of the matrix.
So lambda 1 plus lambda 2 plus
lambda 3 is equal to the trace
of the matrix.
In this case, you have 1
plus 2 plus lambda 3
equals to the trace.
The trace is the sum of
the diagonal entries.
So, come over here.
The trace is 1 plus 1 plus 0.
The trace is equal to 2.
So we have 3 plus lambda
3 is equal to 2.
So lambda 3 is equal
to minus 1.
Onto the third pivot.
We don't really want
to do elimination.
That would take too long.
So there must be some trick
that we can use.
Well, we have the first
two pivots, and we
want to know the third.
Remember, when you do
elimination steps, that does
not change the determinant
of the matrix.
And you're left with an
upper triangular.
So the determinant of that
matrix will be d1
times d2 times d3.
And it will still be equal to
the determinant of A. I guess
there's a small caveat that
I should point out.
The pivots are not always
the diagonal entries.
It might be that one of the
diagonal entries will be 0.
That happens if the matrix
is singular.
But here, all my three
eigenvalues are non-zero.
They are 1, 2, and -1.
So that won't happen.
So this is actually
possible to do.
The product of the three pivots
will be equal to the
determinant of A. And the
determinant of A is the
product of the eigenvalues.
1 times 2 times -1.
So it's equal to -2.
1 times 1 times d3
is equal to -2.
Here is your third pivot, d3.
That finishes part A. Is that
the result that you got?
Let's do part B. What is the
smallest a33 entry that would
make the matrix positive
semidefinite?
Well, first of all, note
that A is not positive
semidefinite yet.
The eigenvalues are
1, 2, and -1.
-1 is negative, so the matrix
is not positive definite and
not even positive
semidefinite.
Positive semidefinite means that
all the eigenvalues will
be either positive or 0.
That is, non-negative.
So our matrix will be 1,
0, 1, 0, 1, 1, 1, 1.
And we're allowed to change
this third entry.
How do we figure out if this
matrix is positive
semidefinite or not?
Well, I was talking about
the eigenvalues.
But maybe the easiest way is
to do the determinant test.
The determinant of the small
one by one left uppermost
matrix is 1.
The determinant of the two by
two upper leftmost matrix is 1
times 1 minus 0 times 0.
1, also positive.
So we need to check that the
determinant of the whole
matrix will also be
non-negative.
So what is the determinant
of this matrix?
It is equal to the three
by three matrix.
So do you know how
to do it quickly?
There's this way that only works
for three by three and
not for bigger.
Which is, the determinant will
be 1 times 1 times a33.
plus 0 times 1 times 1.
That's 0.
Plus 1 times 0 times 1.
That's 0 again.
Minus 1 times 1 times 1 minus
1 times 1 times 1 minus a33
times 0 times 0.
That's 0.
So this is the determinant.
It's a33 minus 2.
And I want it to be greater
than or equal to 0.
This will guarantee that
the matrix is positive
semidefinite.
So a33 must be bigger
than or equal to 2.
The smallest value for a33
that will make the matrix
positive semidefinite is 2.
There's another part to the
question still, which is what
is the smallest c that will
make the matrix A plus cI
positive semidefinite?
How should we do this?
The quickest way is to do the
eigenvalue test. A has
eigenvalues 1, 2, and -1.
So A plus cI has eigenvalues.
Well, you're just adding
cI to the matrix.
And in this particular case,
you should know by now that
that keeps the eigenvectors the
same and adds the number c
to each of the eigenvalues.
And I want each one of these
to be non-negative.
For that to be true, I have
to have c greater
than or equal to 1.
c greater than or equal to 1.
So the smallest value that c
can take that will make the
matrix A positive semidefinite
is 1.
That solves parts A and
B of this question.
There is a part C to
this question.
Let me show it to you.
It's says, starting with one of
these three vectors, 3, 0,
0, 0, 3, 0, or 0, 0, 3, and with
uk plus 1 equals to 1/2A
times uk, what is the
limit behavior of uk
as k goes to infinity?
I've written the matrix 1/2 of
A here for your convenience.
And now, you can hit pause
and work on it.
And when you're ready,
we'll get back
and solve it together.
I hope you managed to
solve this one.
Now let's do it together.
Well, if you've noticed
the matrix
1/2A is a Markov matrix.
So there are all these results
about Markov matrices in
steady states and so on.
Usually, Markov matrices have
a unique steady state, but
that is only true when there
are no non-zero entries.
But here, there are.
So we can't guarantee that
there's a unique steady state.
What we can do is look at the
eigenvalues and see if this is
still true nonetheless.
What are the eigenvalues of A?
Of 1/2A?
Well, if you remember from part
A, the eigenvalues of A
were 1, 2, and -1.
So the eigenvalues of 1/2A--
taking a multiple does not
change the eigenvector.
But it changes the eigenvalue
by the same multiple.
It would be 1/2, 2 divided
by 2 is 1, and minus 1/2.
So here are the eigenvalues
of A. And there's only one
eigenvalue that has absolute
value equal to 1.
So you actually still get a
unique steady state vector.
So everything is fine.
We can proceed as usual.
And the usual procedure is
you find the eigenvector
corresponding to that
eigenvalue, 1.
And that will be the limit
behavior as k goes
to infinity of uk.
So what is the eigenvector
corresponding to 1?
Eigenvector.
Well, you already know how to do
this, so I will just write
the solution.
It is 1, 1, 1.
That means that uk, as k goes to
infinity, will converge to
some appropriate multiple of
this eigenvector 1, 1, 1.
How do you know which
multiple to use?
Well, as usual in Markov
matrices, when you do an
iteration of the process, when
you do uk plus 1 is equal to
1/2A times uk, that does not
change the sum of the entries
of the vector uk.
So whatever the sum
was here, it will
still be the same here.
If you go all the way back and
you start with u0, whatever
the sum of the entries was here,
that's what it will be
all the way through u1, u2, u3,
and so on, all the way to
the steady state, u infinity.
So whatever the multiple of 1,
1, 1, it has to have the sum
of these entries add up to 3.
Well, that's already there.
We already happened to pick the
correct eigenvector, so
that's very convenient.
The correct multiple is simply
the vector 1, 1, 1.
So the limit behavior of uk
as k goes to infinity is u
infinity equal to 1, 1, 1.
We're done.
Thank you.