CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
We're going to practice using
some of the tools you
developed recently on taking
derivatives of exponential
functions and taking
derivatives
of logarithmic functions.
So I have three particular
examples that I
want us to look at.
And I'd like us to find
derivatives of
the following functions.
The first one is f of x is
equal to x to the pi
plus pi to the x.
The second function is g of x
is equal to natural log of
cosine of x.
And the third one is--
that's an h not a
natural log--
h of x is equal to natural log
of e to the x squared.
So you have three functions
you want to take the
derivative of with
respect to x.
I'm going to give you a moment
to to work on those and figure
those out using the the tools
you now have. And then we'll
come back and I will work them
out for you as well.
OK, so let's start off
with the derivative
of the first one.
Ok, now, the reason in
particular that I did this
one, it might have seemed simple
to you, but the reason
I did this one is because
of a common
mistake that people make.
So the derivative of x to the pi
is nice and simple because
that is our rule we know
for powers of x.
So we can write this as that
derivative is, pi times x to
the pi minus one.
OK, but the whole point of this
problem for me, is to
make sure that you recognize
that pi to the x is not a
power of x rule that needs
to be applied.
It's actually an exponential
function right, with base pi.
So if you wrote the derivative
of this term was x times pi to
the x minus one, you would not
be alone in the world.
But that is not the correct
answer, all the same.
Because this is not a power of
x, this is x is the power.
So this is an exponential
function.
So the derivative of this, we
need the rule that we have for
exponential, derivatives of
exponential functions.
So that's natural log of
pi times pi to the x.
That's the derivative
of pi to the x.
So that's the answer
to number one.
OK.
Number two, I did for
another reason.
I think it's an interesting
function once you find out
what the derivative is.
So, this is going to require
us to do the chain rule.
Because we have a function
of a function.
But you have seen many times
now, when you have natural log
of a function, its derivative
is going to be 1 over the
inside function times
then the derivative
of the inside function.
So again, what we do
is we take the
derivative of natural log.
Which is 1 over cosine x.
So we take the derivative of
the natural log function,
evaluate it at cosine x.
And then we take the derivative
of the inside
function, which is the
derivative of cosine x.
So you get negative sine x.
So you get this whole thing is
negative sine over cosine.
So this is negative tangent x.
So the reason I, in particular,
like this one is
that we see, "Oh, if I wanted
to find a function whose
derivative was tangent x,
a candidate would be the
negative of the natural log of
cosine of x." That in fact
gives us a function whose
derivative is tangent x.
So it's interesting, now
we see that there are
trigonometric functions that
I can take a derivative of
something that's not just
trigonometric and get
something that's
trigonometric.
So that's kind of a
nice thing there.
And then the last one,
example three, I'll
work out to the right.
There's a fast way and there's
a slow way to do this.
So I will do the slow way first.
And then I'll show you
why it's good to kind of pull
back from a problem sometimes,
see how you can make it a lot
simpler for yourself, and then
solve the problem.
So, I'll even write down
this is the slow way.
OK, the slow way would be, well
I have a composition of
functions here.
I have natural log of something
and then I have e to
the something else.
Right?
And then that function
actually, is not
just e to the x.
So I have some things I
have to, I have to use
the chain rule here.
OK, so let's use
the chain rule.
So I'll work from
the outside in.
So the derivative of the natural
log function, the
derivative of the natural
log of x is 1 over x.
So I take the derivative of the
natural log function, I
evaluate it here.
So the first part gives me 1
over e to the x squared.
And then I have to take the
derivative of the next inside
function, which the next one
inside after natural log, is e
to the x squared.
And the derivative of that,
I'm going to do
another chain rule.
I get e to the x squared times
the derivative of this x
squared, which is 2x.
OK, so again, this part is the
derivative of natural log
evaluated at e to
the x squared.
This part is the derivative
of e the x squared.
This one comes just from the
derivative of e to the
x is e to the x.
And so I evaluate
it at x squared.
And then this is the
derivative of
the x squared part.
So I end up with a product of
three functions, because I
have a composition of
three functions.
So I have to do the chain
rule with three
different pieces basically.
So, but this simplifies,
right?
e to the x squared divided by
e to the x squared is 1.
So I get 2x.
OK, so what's the fast way?
That's our answer, 2x.
But what's the fast way?
Well, the fast way is to
recognize that the natural log
of e to the x squared-- let me
erase the y here-- e to the x
squared is equal to x squared.
OK?
Why is that?
That's because natural log
function is the inverse of the
exponential function
with base e.
Right?
This is something you've
talked about before.
So this means that if I take
natural log of e to anything
here, I'm going to get that
thing right there.
Whatever that function is.
So natural log of e the x
squared is x squared.
OK?
If you don't like to talk about
it that way, if you
don't like inverse functions,
you can use one of the rules
of logarithms, which says that
this expression is equal to x
squared times natural
log of e.
That's another way to think
about this problem.
And then you should remember
that natural log of
e is equal to 1.
So at some point you have to
know a little bit about logs
and exponentials.
But the thing to recognize is,
that h of x is just a fancy
way of writing x squared.
And so the derivative
of x squared is 2x.
So sometimes it's better to see
what can be done to make
the problem a little easier.
But that is where we will
stop with these.