The following is provided under
a Creative Commons License.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or to view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
Professor: In today's lecture I
want to develop several more
formulas that will allow
us to reach our goal of
differentiating everything.
So these are derivative
formulas, and they
come in two flavors.
The first kind is specific, so
some specific function we're
giving the derivative of.
And that would be, for
example, x^n or (1/x) .
Those are the ones that we did
a couple of lectures ago.
And then there are general
formulas, and the general ones
don't actually give you a
formula for a specific function
but tell you something like, if
you take two functions and add
them together, their derivative
is the sum of the derivatives.
Or if you multiply by a
constant, for example, so (cu),
the derivative of that is
(cu)' where c is constant.
All right, so these kinds of
formulas are very useful,
both the specific and
the general kind.
For example, we need both
kinds for polynomials.
And more generally, pretty much
any set of forumulas that we
give you, will give you a few
functions to start out with and
then you'll be able to generate
lots more by these
general formulas.
So today, we wanna concentrate
on the trig functions, and
so we'll start out with
some specific formulas.
And they're going to be the
formulas for the derivative
of the sine function and
the cosine function.
So that's what we'll spend the
first part of the lecture on,
and at the same time I hope to
get you very used to dealing
with trig functions, although
that's something that you
should think of as
a gradual process.
Alright, so in order to
calculate these, I'm gonna
start over here and just
start the calculation.
So here we go.
Let's check what happens
with the sine function.
So, I take sin (x
delta x), I subtract sin x
and I divide by delta x.
Right, so this is the
difference quotient and
eventually I'm gonna have
to take the limit as
delta x goes to 0.
And there's really only one
thing we can do with this to
simplify or change it, and that
is to use the sum formula
for the sine function.
So, that's this.
That's sin x co delta x plus
Oh, that's not what it is?
OK, so what is it?
Sin x sin delta x.
OK, good.
Plus cosine.
No?
Oh, OK.
So which is it?
OK.
Alright, let's take a vote.
Is it sine, sine, or
is it sine, cosine?
Audience: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: OK, so is this
going to be... cosine.
All right, you better remember
these formulas, alright?
OK, turns out that
it's sine, cosine.
All right.
Cosine, sine.
So here we go, no gotta do
x here, sin (delta x).
Alright, so now there's lots of
places to get confused here,
and you're gonna need to
make sure you get it right.
Alright, so we're gonna put
those in parentheses here.
Sin (a + b) is sin a (cos b)
cos a (sin b).
All right, now that's what I
did over here, except the
letter x was a, and the
letter b was delta x.
Now that's just the first part.
That's just this part
of the expression.
I still have to
remember the - sin x.
That comes at the end.
Minus sin x.
And then, I have to
remember the denominator,
which is delta x.
OK?
Alright, so now...
The next thing we're gonna
do is we're gonna try
to group the terms.
And the difficulty with all
such arguments is the following
one: any tricky limit is
basically 0 / 0 when you
set delta x equal to 0.
If I set delta x equal to
0, this is sin x - sin x.
So it's a 0 / 0 term.
Here we have various things
which are 0 and various
things which are non-zero.
We must group the terms so
that a 0 stays over a 0.
Otherwise, we're
gonna have no hope.
If we get some 1 / 0 term,
we'll get something
meaningless in the limit.
So I claim that the right thing
to do here is to notice, and
I'll just point out
this one thing.
When delta x goes to 0,
this cosine of 0 is 1.
So it doesn't cancel
unless we throw in this
extra sine term here.
So I'm going to use this
common factor, and
combine those terms.
So this is really the only
thing you're gonna have to
check in this particular
calculation.
So we have the common factor of
sin x, and that multiplies
something that will cancel,
which is (cos delta
x - 1) / delta x.
That's the first term, and now
what's left, well there's a cos
x that factors out, and then
the other factor is (sin
delta x) / (delta x).
OK, now does anyone remember
from last time what
this thing goes to?
How many people say 1?
How many people say 0?
All right, it's 0.
That's my favorite
number, alright?
0.
It's the easiest
number to deal with.
So this goes 0, and that's what
happens as delta x tends to 0.
How about this one?
This one goes to 1, my second
favorite number, almost as
easy to deal with as 0.
And these things are
picked for a reason.
They're the simplest
numbers to deal with.
So altogether, this thing as
delta x goes to 0 goes to what?
I want a single person to
answer, a brave volunteer.
Alright, back there.
Student: Cosine
Professor: Cosine, because
this factor is 0.
It cancels and this factor
has a 1, so it's cosine.
So it's cos x.
So our conclusion over here -
and I'll put it in orange -
is that the derivative of
the sine is the cosine.
OK, now I still wanna label
these very important
limit facts here.
This one we'll call A, and this
one we're going to call B,
because we haven't
checked them yet.
I promised you I would
do that, and I'll have
to do that this time.
So we're relying on those
things being true.
Now I'm gonna do the same thing
with the cosine function,
except in order to do it
I'm gonna have to remember
the sum rule for cosine.
So we're gonna do almost
the same calculation here.
We're gonna see that that will
work out, but now you have to
remember that cos (a + b) = cos
cos, no it's not cosine^2,
because there are two
different quantities here.
It's (cos a cos b)
- (sin a sin b).
All right, so you'll have to
be willing to call those
forth at will right now.
So let's do the cosine now.
So that's cosine ((x + delta
x) - cos x) / delta x.
OK, there's the difference
quotient for the
cosine function.
And now I'm gonna do the same
thing I did before except I'm
going to apply the second
rule, that is the
sum rule for cosine.
And that's gonna give me
(cos x cos delta x) -
(sin x sin delta x).
And I have to remember again
to subtract the cosine
divided by this delta x.
And now I'm going to regroup
just the way I did before, and
I get the common factor of
cosine multiplying ((cosine
delta x - 1) / delta x).
And here I get the sin x
but actually it's - sin x.
And then I have (sin
delta x) / delta x.
All right?
The only difference is
this minus sign which
I stuck inside there.
Well that's not the only
difference, but it's
a crucial difference.
OK, again by A we get that this
is 0 as delta x tends to 0.
And this is 1.
Those are the properties
I called A and B.
And so the result here as
delta x tends to 0 is that
we get negative sine x.
That's the factor.
So this guy is negative sine x.
I'll put a little box
around that too.
Alright, now these formulas
take a little bit of getting
used to, but before I do that
I'm gonna explain to you
the proofs of A and B.
So we'll get ourselves
started by mentioning that.
Maybe before I do that though,
I want to show you how A and B
fit into the proofs
of these theorems.
So, let me just make
some remarks here.
So this is just a remark but
it's meant to help you to frame
how these proofs worked.
So, first of all, I want to
point out that if you take the
rate of change of sin x, no
let's start with cosine because
a little bit less obvious.
If I take the rate of change of
cos x, so in other words this
derivative at x = 0, then by
definition this is a certain
limit as delta x goes to 0.
So which one is it?
Well I have to
evaluate cosine at 0
delta x, but that's
just delta x.
And I have to subtract
cosine at 0.
That's the base point,
but that's just 1.
And then I have to
divide by delta x.
And lo and behold you can see
that this is exactly the limit
that we had over there.
This is the one that we know is
0 by what we call property A.
And similarly, if I take the
derivative of (sin x) at x= 0,
then that's going to be the
limit as delta x goes to 0
of sine delta x / delta x.
And that's because I should
be subtracting sine of
0 but sine of 0 is 0.
Right?
So this is going to be
1 by our property B.
And so the remark that I want
to make, in addition to this,
is something about the
structure of these two proofs.
Which is the derivatives of
sine and cosine at x = 0
give all values of d/dx
sin x, d/dx cos x.
So that's really what this
argument is showing us, is that
we just need one rate of change
at one place and then we work
out all the rest of them.
So that's really the
substance of this proof.
That of course really then
shows that it boils down to
showing what this rate of
change is in these two cases.
So now there's enough suspense
that we want to make sure
that we know that those
answers are correct.
OK, so let's demonstrate
both of them.
I'll start with B.
I need to figure
out property B.
Now, we only have one
alternative as to a type of
proof that we can give of this
kind of result, and that's
because we only have one way of
describing sine and cosine
functions, that is
geometrically.
So we have to give
a geometric proof.
And to write down a geometric
proof we are going to
have to draw a picture.
And the first step in the
proof, really, is to replace
this variable delta x which is
going to 0 with another name
which is suggestive of what
we're gonna do which is the
letter theta for an angle.
OK, so let's draw a picture
of what it is that
we're going to do.
Here is the circle.
And here is the origin.
And here's some little angle,
well I'll draw it a little
larger so it's visible.
Here's theta, alright?
And this is the unit circle.
I won't write that down on here
but that's the unit circle.
And now sin theta is this
vertical distance here.
Maybe, I'll draw it in a
different color so that
we can see it all.
OK so here's this distance.
This distance is sin theta.
OK?
Now almost the only other thing
we have to write down in this
picture to have it work out is
that we have to recognize that
when theta is the angle, that's
also the arc length of this
piece of the circle when
measured in radians.
So this length here is
also arc length theta.
That little piece in there.
So maybe I'll use a different
color for that to indicate it.
So that's orange and that's
this little chunk there.
So those are the two pieces.
Now in order to persuade you
now that the limit is what it's
supposed to be, I'm going to
extend the picture
just a little bit.
I'm going to double it, just
for my own linguistic sake and
so that I can tell you a story.
Alright, so that
you'll remember this.
So I'm going to take a theta
angle below and I'll have
another copy of sin
theta down here.
And now the total picture
is really like a bow and
its bow string there.
Alright?
So what we have here is a
length of 2 sin theta.
So maybe I'll write it
this way, 2 sin theta.
I just doubled it.
And here I have underneath,
whoops, I got it backwards.
Sorry about that.
Trying to be fancy with
the colored chalk and I
have it reversed here.
So this is not 2 sin theta.
2 sin theta is the vertical.
That's the green.
So let's try that again.
This is 2 sin theta, alright?
And then in the denominator I
have the arc length which is
theta is the first half and
so double it is 2 theta.
Alright?
So if you like, this is
the bow and up here we
have the bow string.
And of course we can
cancel the 2's.
That's equal to sin
theta / theta.
And so now why does this tend
to 1 as theta goes to 0?
Well, it's because as the angle
theta gets very small, this
curved piece looks more and
more like a straight one.
Alright?
And if you get very, very close
here the green segment and
the orange segment
would just merge.
They would be practically
on top of each other.
And they have closer and closer
and closer to the same length.
So that's why this is true.
I guess I'll articulate that
by saying that short curves
are nearly straight.
Alright, so that's the
principle that we're using.
Or short pieces of curves, if
you like, are nearly straight.
So if you like, this
is the principle.
So short pieces of curves.
Alright?
So now I also need to
give you a proof of A.
And that has to do with
this cosine function here.
This is the property A.
So I'm going to do this by
flipping it around, because it
turns out that this numerator
is a negative number.
If I want to interpret it as
a length, I'm gonna want
a positive quantity.
So I'm gonna write down (1 -
cos theta) here and then I'm
gonna divide by theta there.
Again I'm gonna make some
kind of interpretation.
Now this time I'm going to draw
the same sort of bow and arrow
arrangement, but maybe I'll
exaggerate it a little bit.
So here's the vertex of the
sector, but we'll maybe
make it a little longer.
Alright, so here it is, and
here was that middle line
which was the unit...
Whoops.
OK, I think I'm going
to have to tilt it up.
OK, let's try from here.
Alright, well you know on your
pencil and paper it will look
better than it does
on my blackboard.
OK, so here we are.
Here's this shape.
Now this angle is supposed
to be theta and this
angle is another theta.
So here we have a length
which is again theta and
another length which
is theta over here.
That's the same as in the
other picture, except we've
exaggerated a bit here.
And now we have this vertical
line, which again I'm gonna
draw in green, the bow string.
But notice that as the vertex
gets farther and farther away,
the curved line gets closer
and closer to being
a vertical line.
That's sort of the flip
side, by expansion, of
the zoom in principle.
The principle that curves
are nearly straight
when you zoom in.
If you zoom out that would
mean sending this vertex
way, way out somewhere.
The curved line, the piece
of the circle, gets
more and more straight.
And now let me show you where
this numerator (1 - cos
theta) is on this picture.
So where is it?
Well, this whole distance is 1.
But the distance from
the vertex to the green
is cosine of theta.
Right, because this is theta,
so dropping down the
perpendicular this distance
back to the origin
is cos theta.
So this little tiny, bitty
segment here is basically the
gap between the curve and
the vertical segment.
So the gap = 1 - cos theta.
So now you can see that as this
point gets farther away, if
this got sent off to the Stata
Center, you would hardly be
able to tell the difference.
The bow string would coincide
with the bow and this little
gap between the bow string and
the bow would be tending to 0.
And that's the statement
that this tends to 0
as theta tends to 0.
The scaled version of that.
Yeah, question down here.
Student: Doesn't the
denominator also
tend to 0 though?
Professor: Ah, the question is
"doesn't the denominator also
tend to 0?" And the
answer is yes.
In my strange analogy with
zooming in, what I did was
I zoomed out the picture.
So in other words, if you
imagine you're taking this and
you're putting it under a
microscope over here and you're
looking at something where
theta is getting smaller and
smaller and smaller
and smaller.
Alright?
But now because I want my
picture, I expanded my picture.
So the ratio is the
thing that's preserved.
So if I make it so that
this gap is tiny...
Let me say this one more time.
I'm afraid I've made life
complicated for myself.
If I simply let this theta tend
in to 0, that would be the same
effect as making this closer
and closer in and then the
vertical would approach.
But I want to keep on blowing
up the picture so that I can
see the difference between
the vertical and the curve.
So that's very much like if you
are on a video screen and you
zoom in, zoom in, zoom
in, and zoom in.
So the question is what
would that look like?
That has the same effect
as sending this point out
farther and farther in that
direction, to the left.
And so I'm just trying to
visualize it for you by leaving
the theta at this scale, but
actually the scale of the
picture is then changing
when I do that.
So theta is going to 0, but I
I'm rescaling so that it's of a
size that we can look at it,
And then imagine what's
happening to it.
OK, does that answer
your question?
Student: My question then is
that seems to prove that
that limit is equal to 0/0.
Professor: It proves more
than it is equal to 0 / 0.
It's the ratio of this
little short thing to
this longer thing.
And this is getting much, much
shorter than this total length.
You're absolutely right that
we're comparing two quantities
which are going to 0, but one
of them is much smaller
than the other.
In the other case we compared
two quantities which were both
going to 0 and they both end up
being about equal in length.
Here the previous one
was this green one.
Here it's this little tiny bit
here and it's way shorter
than the 2 theta distance.
Yeah, another question.
Student: (Cos theta -1) /
(cos theta) is the same as
(1- cos theta) / theta?
Professor: Cos
theta - 1 over...
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: So here, what I
wrote is (cos delta x - 1) /
delta x, OK, and I claimed
that it goes to 0.
Here, I wrote minus that, that
is I replaced delta x by theta.
But then I wrote this thing.
So (cos theta - 1) - 1 is
the negative of this.
Alright?
And if I show that this goes to
0, it's the same as showing
the other one goes to 0.
Another question?
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: So the question
is, what about this
business about arc length.
So the word arc length, that
orange shape is an arc.
And we're just talking about
the length of that arc, and so
we're calling it arc length.
That's what the word are
length means, it just means
the length of the arc.
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: Why is
this length theta?
Ah, ok so this is a very
important point, and in fact
it's the very next point
that I wanted to make.
Namely, notice that in this
calculation it was very
important that we used length.
And that means that the way
that we're measuring theta, is
in what are known as radians.
Right, so that applies to both
B and A, it's a scale change in
A and doesn't really matter
but in B it's very important.
The only way that this orange
length is comparable to this
green length, the vertical is
comparable to the arc, is if
we measure them in terms of
the same notion of length.
If we measure them in degrees,
for example, it would
be completely wrong.
We divide up the angles into
360 , and that's wrong
unit of measure.
The correct measures is the
length along the unit circle,
which is what radians are.
And so this is only true
if we use radians.
So again, a little warning
here, that this is in radians.
Now here x is in radians.
The formulas are just wrong
if you use other units.
Ah yeah?
Student: [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: OK so the second
question is why is this
crazy length here 1.
And the reason is that the
relationship between this
picture up here and this
picture down here, is that I'm
drawing a different shape.
Namely, what I'm really
imagining here is a much,
much smaller theta.
OK?
And then I'm blowing
that up in scale.
So this scale of this picture
down here is very different
from the scale of the
picture up there.
And if the angle is very, very,
very small then one has to be
very, very long in order for
me to finish the circle.
So, in other words, this
length is 1 because that's
what I'm insisting on.
So, I'm claiming that that's
how I define this circle,
to be of unit radius.
Another question?
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
the ratio between 1 - theta
and theta and theta will
get closer and closer to 1.
I don't understand [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: OK, so the question
is it's hard to visualize
this fact here.
So let me let me take you
through a couple of steps,
because I think probably other
people are also having trouble
with this visualization.
The first part of the
visualization I'm gonna
try to demonstrate on
this picture up here.
The first part of the
visualization is that I should
think of a beak of a bird
closing down, getting
narrower and narrower.
So in other words, the angle
theta has to be getting smaller
and smaller and smaller.
OK, that's the first step.
So that's the process that
we're talking about.
Now, in order to draw that,
once theta gets incredibly
narrow, in order to depict that
I have to blow the whole
picture back up in order
be able to see it.
Otherwise it just
disappears on me.
In fact in the limit theta
= 0, it's meaningless.
It's just a flat line.
That's the whole problem
with these tricky limits.
They're meaningless right
at the (0, 0) level.
It's only just a little away
that they're actually useful,
that you get useful geometric
information out of them.
So we're just a little away.
So that's what this picture
down below in part
A is meant to be.
It's supposed to be that
theta is open a tiny
crack, just a little bit.
And the smallest I can draw it
on the board for you to
visualize it is using the whole
length of the blackboard
here for that.
So I've opened a little tiny
bit and by the time we get to
the other end of the
blackboard, of course
it's fairly wide.
But this angle theta is
a very small angle.
Alright?
So I'm trying to imagine what
happens as this collapses.
Now, when I imagine that I
have to imagine a geometric
interpretation of both the
numerator and the denominator
of this quantity here.
And just see what happens.
Now I claimed the numerator is
this little tiny bit over here
and the denominator is actually
half of this whole length here.
But the factor of 2 doesn't
matter when you're
seeing whether something
tends to 0 or not.
Alright?
And I claimed that if you stare
at this, it's clear that this
is much shorter than that
vertical curve there.
And I'm claiming, so this is
what you have to imagine, is
this as it gets smaller and
smaller and smaller still that
has the same effect of this
thing going way, way way,
farther away and this vertical
curve getting closer and closer
and closer to the green.
And so that the gap between
them gets tiny and goes to 0.
Alright?
So not only does it go to 0,
that's not enough for us, but
it also goes to 0 faster
than this theta goes to 0.
And I hope the evidence is
pretty strong here because it's
so tiny already at this stage.
Alright.
We are going to move forward
and you'll have to ponder
these things some other time.
So I'm gonna give you an even
harder thing to visualize
now so be prepared.
OK, so now, the next thing
that i'd like to do is to
give you a second proof.
Because it really is important
I think to understand this
particular fact more thoroughly
and also to get a lot of
practice with sines
and cosines.
So I'm gonna give you a
geometric proof of the formula
for sine here, for the
derivative of sine.
So here we go.
This is a geometric
proof of this fact.
This is for all theta.
So far we only did it for
theta = 0 and now we're going
to do it for all theta.
So this is a different
proof, but it uses exactly
the same principles.
Right?
So, I want do this by drawing
another picture, and the
picture is going to describe Y,
which is sin theta, which is if
you like the vertical position
of some circular motion.
So I'm imagining that something
is going around in a circle.
Some particle is going
around in a circle.
And so here's the circle,
here the origin.
This is the unit distance.
And right now it happens
to be at this location P.
Maybe we'll put P a
little over here.
And here's the angle theta.
And now we're going to move it.
We're going to vary theta
and we're interested in
the rate of change of Y.
So Y is the height P he
but we're gonna move it
to another location.
We'll move it along
the circle to Q.
Right?
So here it is.
Here's the thing.
So how far did we move it?
Well we moved it by an
angle delta theta.
So we started theta, theta is
going to be fixed in this
argument, and we're going to
move a little bit delta theta.
And now we're just gonna
try to figure out how
far the thing moved.
Well, in order to do that we've
got to keep track of the the
height, the vertical
displacement here.
So we're going to draw this
right angle here, this
is the position R.
And then this distance
here is the change in Y.
Alright?
So the picture is we
have something moving
around a unit circle.
A point moving around
a unit circle.
It starts at P it moves to Q.
It moves from angle
theta to angle theta
delta theta.
And the issue is how
much does Y move?
And the formula for
Y is sin theta.
So that's telling us the rate
of change of sin theta.
Alright, well so let's just
try to think a little
bit about what this is.
So, first of all, I've already
said this and I'm going
to repeat it here.
Delta Y is PR.
It's going from P and
going straight up to R.
That's how far Y moves.
That's the change in Y.
That's what I said up in the
right hand corner there.
Oops.
I said PR but I wrote PQ.
Alright, that's
not a good idea.
Alright.
So delta Y is PR.
And now I want to draw the
diagram again one time.
So here's Q, here's
R, and here's P, and
here's my triangle.
And now what i'd like to do is
draw this curve here which is a
piece of the arc of the circle.
But really what I want to keep
in mind is something that I did
also in all these
other arguments.
Which is, maybe I should have
called this orange, that
I'm gonna think of the
straight line between.
So it's the straight line
approximation to the curve that
we're always interested in.
So the straight line is much
simpler, because then we
just have a triangle here.
And in fact it's a
right triangle.
Right, so we have the geometry
of a right triangle which
is going to now let us do
all of our calculations.
OK, so now the key step is this
same principle that we already
used which is that short pieces
of curves are nearly straight.
So that means that this piece
of the circular arc here from P
to Q is practically the same as
the straight segment
from P to Q.
So, that's this principal.
Well, let's put it over here.
Is that PQ is practically
the same as the straight
segment from P to Q.
So how are we going
to use that?
We want to use that
quantitatively in
the following way.
What we want to notice is that
the distance from P to Q is
approximately delta theta.
Right?
Because the arc length along
that curve, the length of
the curve is delta theta.
So the length of the
green which is PQ is
almost delta theta.
So this is essentially delta
theta, this distance here.
Now the second step, which is
a little trickier, is that
we have to work out
what this angle is.
So our goal, and I'm gonna put
it one step below because I'm
gonna put the geometric
reasoning in between, is I need
to figure out what
the angle QPR is.
If I can figure out what this
angle is, then I'll be able to
figure out what this vertical
distance is because I'll know
the hypotenuse and I'll know
the angle so I'll be able to
figure out what the side
of the triangle is.
So now let me show you why
that's possible to do.
So in order to do that first of
all I'm gonna trade the boards
and show you where
the line PQ is.
So the line PQ is here.
That's the whole thing.
And the key point about this
line that I need you to realize
is that it's practically
perpendicular, it's almost
perpendicular, to
this ray here.
Alright?
It's not quite because
the distance between
P to Q is non-zero.
So it isn't quite, but
in the limit it's going
to be perpendicular.
Exactly perpendicular.
The tangent line to the circle.
So the key thing that I'm going
to use is that PQ is almost
perpendicular to OP.
Alright?
The ray from the origin is
basically perpendicular
to that green line.
And then the second thing I'm
going to use is something
that's obvious which is
that PR is vertical.
OK?
So those are the two pieces of
geometry that I need to see.
And now notice what's happening
upstairs on the picture
here in the upper right.
What I have is the angle
theta is the angle between
the horizontal and OP.
That's angle theta.
If I rotate it by ninety
degree, the horizontal
becomes vertical.
It becomes PR and the other
thing rotated by 90 degrees
becomes the green line.
So the angle that I'm talking
about I get by taking this guy
and rotating it by 90 degrees.
It's the same angle.
So that means that this angle
here is essentially theta.
That's what this angle is.
Let me repeat that
one more time.
We started out with an angle
that looks like this, which
is the horizontal that's
the origin straight
out horizontally.
That's the thing labeled 1.
That distance there.
That's my right arm
which is down here.
My left arm is pointing up
and it's going from the
origin to the point P.
So here's the horizontal
and the angle between
them is theta.
And now, what I claim is is
that if I rotate by 90 degrees
up, like this, without changing
anything - so that was what
I did - the horizontal
will become a vertical.
That's PR.
That's going up, PR.
And if I rotate OP 90
degrees, that's exactly PQ.
OK?
So let me draw it
on there one time.
Let's do it with
some arrows here.
So I started out with this and
then, we'll label this as
orange, OK so red to orange,
and then I rotate by 90 degrees
and the red becomes this
starting from P and the orange
rotates around 90 degrees and
becomes this thing here.
Alright?
So this angle here is the
same as the other one
which I've just drawn.
Different vertices
for the angles.
OK?
Well I didn't say that
all arguments were
supposed to be easy.
Alright, so I claim that the
conclusion is that this angle
is approximately theta.
And now we can finish our
calculation, because we have
something with the hypotenuse
being delta theta and the angle
being theta and so this segment
here PR is approximately the
hypotenuse length times
the cosine of the angle.
And that is exactly
what we wanted.
If we divide, we divide by
delta theta, we get (delta
Y) / (delta theta) is
approximately cos theta.
And that's the same thing as...
So what we want in the limit is
exactly the delta theta going
to 0 of (delta y) / (delta
theta) = cos theta.
So we get an approximation on
a scale that we can visualize
and in the limit the
formula is exact.
OK, so that is a geometric
argument for the same result.
Namely that the derivative
of sine is cosine.
Yeah?
Student: [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: You will have to
do some kind of geometric
proofs sometimes.
When you'll really need
this is probably in 18.02.
So you'll need to make
reasoning like this.
This is, for example, the way
that you actually develop
the theory of arc length.
Dealing with delta x's and
delta y's is a common tool.
Alright, I have one more thing
that I want to talk about
today, which is some
general rules.
We took a little bit more time
than I expected with this.
So what I'm gonna do is just
tell you the rules and we'll
discuss them in a few days.
So let me tell you
the general rules.
So these were the specific ones
and here are some general ones.
So the first one is
called the product rule.
And what it says is that if you
take the product of two
functions and differentiate
them, you get the derivative of
one times the other plus
the other times the
derivative of the one.
Now the way that you should
remember this, and the way that
I'll carry out the proof, is
that you should think of it
is you change one at a time.
And this is a very useful way
of thinking about
differentiation when you have
things which depend on more
than one function.
So this is a general procedure.
The second formula that I
wanted to mention is called
the quotient rule and
that says the following.
That u / v' has a
formula as well.
And the formula is
((u'v - uv' ) / v^2).
So this is our second formula.
Let me just mention, both of
them are extremely valuable and
you'll use them all the time.
This one of course only
works when v is not 0.
Alright, so because we're of
time we're not gonna prove
these today but we'll prove
these next time and you're
definitely going to be
responsible for these
kinds of proofs.