PROFESSOR: Welcome
to this session
on separable equations.
So in this problem, you're asked
in the first question to
solve the initial value problem,
dydx equals y squared
with the initial condition
y of zero equals 1.
In the second part of the
problem, you're asked to find
the general solution where no
initial condition is imposed.
So here you need to remember
your method of separation of
variables to tackle the
first question.
And then in the second part of
the problem, remember all the
types of solutions and
conditions that you applied
the first part to recover
the lost solutions.
So why don't you take a minute,
pause the video, work
through questions a and b.
And then we'll continue together
when I come back.
Welcome back.
So in the first part of the
problem, we'll be solving the
equation dydx equals
y squared.
So here the method of separation
of variables tells
us that we should regroup the
variables of the same kind, so
all the y variables on one side
and dx variable on the
other side of the equation
and then
integrate from this point.
So here for this step, notice
that I divided by y squared,
which means that we need to
impose the condition y naught
equal to zero from now on.
So from this step, we just use
indefinite integrals to
integrate both sides
of the equation.
So the left-hand side is the
integral dy over y squared.
So integral of this gives
us minus 1 over y.
And the right hand side,
integral dx, is just x.
Both sides would give us
constant of integrations, but
we only need one because
this is a first-order
differential equation.
And so we group them together
on the right-hand side with
constant c.
So from this point, given that
we're interested in variable
y, we need just to invert
the expression.
And that gives us partial
answer, which is y of x equals
minus 1 over x plus c.
So now we need to use our
initial condition, y of zero
equals to 1 to determine the
value of c for this particular
initial value problem.
So our initial condition
was y of zero equals 1.
So if we substitute this in the
expression that we just
obtained, we just have zero plus
c, which then only gives
us c equal to 1.
So we end up with the value
for our constant of
integration, c equals minus 1.
And so the solution to this
problem is y of x equals 1
over 1 minus x.
So if you examine this
expression, you see right away
that we have a problem for x
equals 1 because at x equals
1, we have 1/0 which means that,
then, the solution blows
up and we have a vertical
asymptote.
So let me draw this here.
So we're going to have an
asymptote at x equals 1 and a
solution that passes through
our initial condition, y
equals 1, going to infinity when
approaching x equals 1.
But then on the right side of
the value x equals 1, we have
another part of the solution
that goes to zero
as x goes to infinity.
And that diverges to minus
infinity when x approaches 1.
So by convention, the solutions
of differential
equations are defined on
one single interval.
So we need here to realize that
the solution we had is
basically two parts, the parts
on the left of the asymptote
and the part on the right
of the asymptote.
So the solution to our initial
value problems needs to be the
solution that passes through the
imposed initial condition,
which was y of zero
equals to 1.
So it needs to be
this solution.
So now, if we move on to the
solution of the second part of
the problem b, we were asked to
find the general solution
of the problem, which means that
we need to account now
for all the solutions,
regardless of
their initial condition.
So we already answered this
partially during the solution
of part a where we solved using
indefinite integrals and
arrived to the solution minus 1
over x plus c, where here we
had, basically, an undetermined
constant of
integration.
So this is one general
solution.
But remember that we need
to give all the
solutions of the problem.
So when we arrived at the
solution, we excluded the
solution y equals zero, which
was basically a lost solution
because we had to impose the
condition y not equal to zero.
So we need when we give the
general solution to this
differential equation to recover
the lost solution.
And then we basically have one
kind of solution, minus 1 over
x plus c, that excludes y equal
to zero and another kind
of solution that is simply
the zero solution.
So to summarize, the important
points of this problem is to
remember the separation of
variables and how to use it
and the fact that using it
imposes conditions that
require us to recover lost
solutions at the end of the
problem if we're asked to
give general solution.
Another point to remember is
that even a simple ODE can
lead to relatively complex
behavior which drives the
presence of this vertical
asymptote that you need to
then know how to deal with and
determine which part of the
solutions that you've obtained
is the real solution to the
initial value problem
that you're given.
So I hope that you are OK with
this problem and you will use
these approaches many times for
the rest of the course.