So far, we have only discussed
in this course,
electricity.
Calm down.
But this course is about
electricity and magnetism.
Today, I'm going to talk about
magnetism.
In the fifth century B.
., the Greeks already knew that
there are some rocks that
attract bits of iron.
And they are very plentiful in
the
district of Magnesia,
and so that's where the name
"magnet" and "magnetism" comes
from.
The rocks contain iron oxide,
which we will call,
uh, magnetite.
In eleven hundred A.
., the Chinese used these
needles of magnetite to make
compasses, and in the thirteenth
century, it was discovered that
magnetites have two places of
maximum attraction,
which we call poles.
So if you take one piece of
magnetite,
it always has two poles.
Let's call one pole A,
and the other B.
A and A repel each other,
B and B repel each other,
but A and B attract each other.
There is a huge difference
between electricity and
magnetism.
With electricity,
you also have two polarities,
but you are free to choose a
plus or a minus pole.
With magnetism,
you don't have that choice.
The poles will always come in
pairs.
Isolated magnetic poles
do not exist -- or,
as a physicist would say,
magnetic monopoles do not
exist, as far as we know.
If anyone finds a magnetic
monopole -- and don't think that
people are not looking -- that
would certainly be worth a Nobel
Prize.
In principle,
they could exist,
but as far as we know,
they don't exist,
they have never been seen.
Electric monopoles do exist.
If you have a plus charge,
that's an  electric monopole.
You have a minus charge,
electric charge,
that is an electric monopole.
If you have a plus and a minus
of equal strength,
that is an electric dipole.
Whenever you have a magnet,
you always have a magnetic
dipole.
There is no such thing as a
magnetic monopole.
In the sixteenth century,
Gilbert discovered that the
Earth is really a giant magnet,
and he experimented with
compasses, and he was,
effectively,
the first per- person to map
out the elec- the magnetic field
of the Earth.
And if you take one of those
magnetite needles,
and the needle is pointing in
this direction,
which is the direction of
Northern Canada,
then, by convention,
we call this side of the needle
plus -- uh, not plus -- north,
and we call this side of the
needle south.
Since A repels A,
and B repels B,
but A and B attract each other,
in north Canada is the magnetic
South Pole of the Earth,
not the magnetic North Pole.
That's a detail,
now, of course.
So this is the way that we
define the direction,
north and south,
of these magnetite needles.
A crucial discover was made in
eighteen nineteen by the Danish
physicist Oersted.
And he discovered that a
magnetic needle responds to a
current in a wire.
And this linked magnetism with
electricity.
And this is arguably,
perhaps, the most important
experiment ever done.
Oersted concluded that the
current in the wire produces a
magnetic field,
and that the magnetic needle
moves in response to that
magnetic field which is produced
by the wire.
And this magnificent discovery
caused an explosion of activity
in the nineteenth century --
notably by Ampere,
by Faraday, and by Henry -- and
it culminated
into the brilliant work of the
Scottish theoretician Maxwell.
Maxwell composed a Universal
Field Theory,
which connects electricity with
magnetism.
And that is at the heart of
this course.
Maxwell's equations.
You will see them,
all fear -- all four,
by the end of this course.
If I have a current,
a wire, let's say the wire is
perpendicular to the blackboard,
and the current goes into the
blackboard, I put a cross in
there.
If the current comes out of the
blackboard, I put a dot there.
And there is a historical
reason for that.
You're always talked about
vectors, in eighteen oh one,
and in other courses,
but you're never seen a vector.
And I'm going to show you a
vector.
This is a vector.
And this is where it comes to
you.
That's when you see a dot.
And this is where it goes away
from you.
That's when you see a cross.
So this current,
when it's going into the
blackboard, I can put these
magnetite needles in its
vicinity, and they will then do
this.
And when I put it here,
it will go like this.
And they follow the tangents of
a circle, and this it eh way
that we define
magnetic fields,
and the direction of the
magnetic field,
namely, that the magnetic field
-- for which we always write the
symbol B, magnetic fields -- is
now in the clockwise direction.
By convention,
current goes into the
blackboard.
And, if you ever forget that,
use what we call the right-hand
corkscrew rule.
If you take a corkscrew,
and you turn it clockwise,
the corkscrew goes in the
board.
That connects the B with the
current.
IF you take a corkscrew and you
rotate it counterclockwise,
then the corkscrew would come
to you, comes out of the cork.
And that's how you find the
magnetic field going around
current wires.
It's just a convention.
I want to show you how a
magnetic
needle responds to a current.
I have here a wire through
which I'm going to run a
fabulous amount of current,
something like three hundred
amperes, and you're going to see
that wire there -- I'm going to
get my lights right,
see how I want it to go,
this is the way I want it to
go, get you optimum light there.
When I draw a current -- here,
you see the  the magnetite,
the -- we call it a compass,
nowadays -- and it's lined up
in the direction of the magnetic
fields of the Earth.
We're going to run three
hundred amperes through here,
and it will change the
direction, it will change the
direction which is -- there's
going to be a magnetic field
around the wire,
like this.
So it will go like this.
The current that I run is so
high that things begin to smell
and smoke within seconds.
The battery is not going to
like it when I draw such a high
current.
I can, therefore,
only do it for a
few seconds.
So this compass will swing in
this direction,
and it starts to oscillate,
I can't keep the current so
long that it stops the
oscillation.
So I will stop it by hand,
and convince you that that's
really the equilibrium position.
So if you're ready for that --
so we get, now,
connection, watch it three,
two, one, zero.
There it goes.
Now I'll stop it -- the current
is still going.
You see, that's the -- that is
the equilibrium position.
And I will stop the current.
And now I will reverse the
current, in the opposite
direction, now you will see that
it swings backwards.
It -- hundred and eighty
degrees in a different
direction.
Three, two, one,
zero.
There it goes,
I will stop it,
[sniffs], few seconds,
that's the equilibrium
position, and I'll let it go.
So you've seen that,
indeed, the magnetic needle
responded to the magnetic field
that was produced by the wire,
this was the great discovery by
Oersted, the discovery -- this
demonstration,
all by itself,
may not be very spectacular for
you, but, historically,
it is of enormous importance.
I would argue,
perhaps, the most important
demonstration,
the most important research
ever done in physics,
because it connects electricity
with magnetism.
It was the foundation of the
creation of the whole concept of
a field theory.
Actually, [unintelligible]
reaction,
and that means that if a wire
that runs a current has a force
on a magnet, then,
of course, the magnet must also
exert a force on the wire.
And I'm going to demonstrate
that to you, too,
but now, I have a much more
potent magnet,
fro which I will use this one,
and the magnet will not move,
it's so heavy that it can't
move -- so now you will only see
the wire  move.
And the basic idea is then as
follows, here is that magnet.
Oh, I turned it off instead of
This is the north pole of the
magnet, and this is the south
pole -- I don't remember which
is which, to be frank with you
-- so the magnetic field would
run, then, like so,
and I have, here,
a current wire,
a wire that runs a current
through it -- the wire is
perpendicular to the blackboard.
If, when I turn the current on,
if the current is coming out of
the blackboard -- and I have
fifty percent chance,
because I really don't remember
whether this is north or south
-- but let's assume that this is
the configuration,
that the current is coming out
of the blackboard,
then you will see this wire
experience a force up.
It is an experimental effect
that the force  on the wire is
always in the direction of I
cross B.
These are unit vectors.
And since I is coming out of
the blackboard,
if I cross I with B,
I get a force in this
direction.
And so if I reverse,
now, the current -- if the
current goes like this -- then,
of course, the wire wants to go
down.
And I will show you both.
But I don't know which one will
come first, because I didn't
mark the poles.
Ahh -- uhh.
So you see it,
now, slightly different from
the way I
have drawn it.
I've drawn you the magnet
looking this way,
but it's, of course,
much nicer fro you to see it
this way.
So you see the wire,
and there is the magnet,
and now I'm going to run a few
hundred amperes through that
wire, and then it either will
jump up, or it will jump down,
and then I will reverse the
current, and then the opposite
thing will happen.
OK.
We ready for this?
Three, two, one,
zero.
Notice, there was a distinct
force down, the force was so
high that it even pulled down
the supports.
So now I can predict that if I
reverse the current from this
experiment, that now the wire
will jump up.
Here we go -- I know now,
exactly, because I switched it
this way, so now I will switch
it this way, and the wire will
jump up.
That's the first drawing you
see.
Three, two, one,
zero.
Very clear.
You saw it come out.
OK.
Let me take this down.
All right.
If I have a  a wire,
through which I run a current
-- let's say I run a current I
one  through this wire -- it
will produce a magnetic field,
right-hand corkscrew,
right here, that magnetic field
will be in the blackboard
-- I'll call it B one -- right
here, it will be out of the
blackboard.
But that's irrelevant right
now.
But it is out of the
blackboard.
Here, it's in the blackboard.
And here, I have another wire,
I'm going to run a current I
two.
There will be a force now,
on this wire,
in the direction I cross B.
Take your hands,
I cross B [krrk],
that force is up.
So this wire will experience a
force up.
But of course,
if this wire experiences a
force up, since action equals
minus reaction,
this wire will experience a
force down.
So they will go towards each
other.
They will be attracted by each
You can in an independent way
confirm that the force here is
down.
That this is the force.
For me, it would be enough to
say action equals minus
reaction, Newton's Third Law.
But if you want to put in here,
the magnetic field B two,
which is the result of this
current, which is,
of course, out of the
blackboard -- remember the
right-hand corkscrew rule --
then you will see that this
force, now, here,
must be in the direction of I
one, crossed with B two.
And that's down,
which is exactly what I
predicted.
So the two wires will go
towards each other.
However, if I leave everything
the same, but I reverse the
direction of I two -- so now the
two currents are in opposite
direction --
then the forces will flip over,
and so now the two wires repel
each other.
And I will demonstrate that to
you.
I have those two wires here,
and you will see them there on
the screen.
I will explain what you're
looking at in some detail.
The two wires run vertically --
this is one wire,
and this is the
other wire -- and when I run a
current in the same direction,
then they will attract each
other.
And you will see that shortly.
Three, two, one,
zero.
See?
They go towards each other.
I will do it again,
now.
If I run the current in
opposite directions,
they will repel each other.
Now I run them in opposite
directions.
They repel each other.
I'll do it again,
three, two, one,
zero.
They repel each other.
The reason why I showed you
this demonstration is a
different one.
What I want you to appreciate
that if I  have this conducting
plate of aluminum -- it's a
conductor -- and I put that in
between the two
wires, and I repeat the
experiment, that exactly the
same thing will happen.
And that tells you that
magnetic fields are really very
difference from electric fields,
because electric fields would
be heavily affected by a
conducting sheet like this.
Magnetic fields are not.
So what I'm going to do now is
I'm going to put this plate in
between, and then I'm going to
again put the currents in
opposite directions,
and so we will see the wires
repel each other as if the plate
were not there.
Three, two, one,
zero.
There you go.
So magnetic fields have a very
interesting story to tell.
However, electricity and
magnetism are connected.
How do we define the strength
of a magnetic field?
With electricity,
we defined the strengths of
electric fields in the following
way --
we measured the force,
the electric force,
on a charge,
on an electric charge,
and then the electric force is
the charge times the electric
field.
That determines the strength of
the electric field.
Wouldn't it be nice if we could
now say, "OK,
the magnetic force is a
magnetic charge times the B
field.
So that would then define the
magnitude of the B field.
That would be nice.
But as long as
we haven't found a magnetic
monopole, we can't do it.
If you come with a magnetic
monopole tomorrow,
I can do this.
But we have no magnetic
monopoles, and so it cannot be
done this way.
How is magnetic field then
defined?
Well, it is defined in the
following way.
I take an electric charge,
and the electric charge is Q.
And if that electric charge
moves with a velocity V,
and there is a magnetic field
where the electric charge is
moving, then it is
an experimental fact that the
force  is always perpendicular
to V.
If you want to call that B,
with a magnetic indication,
that's fine.
So there is a magnetic field,
the charge is moving with this
velocity, and there is a force
on that charge which is always
perpendicular to V.
The magnitude of that force is
proportional to the speed of the
particle, and it is also
proportional to the charge
itself.
If I double the charge,
then the
force doubles.
If I double the speed,
then the force doubles.
And so the way that we define,
now, magnetic field strength,
is this way.
The force -- and I give it a B
to remind you -- magnetic,
is Q, is the electric charge,
V is the velocity of the
electric charge,
the cross-product with B.
And you see that the force is
always
perpendicular to V,
and that it is linearly
proportional with the speed,
and linearly proportional with
the charge Q.
And this is often called the
Lorenz force after the Dutch
physicist.
This equation is completely
sign-sensitive.
If you change from a positive
charge to a negative charge,
then the force flips over,
a hundred eighty degrees.
You change the direction of V,
force flips over.
Change the direction of B,
So it's a completely
sign-sensitive equation.
The unit for magnetic field
strength follows from this
equation, this is Newton's,
Q is Coulombs,
and V is meters per second.
So this would be the unit for
magnetic field strength,
but no one would ever say that.
In SI units -- this would be SI
units -- we call that one Tesla,
for which we write one capital
T.
A Tesla is an extremely strong
magnetic field.
The magnetic field of this
magnet is only two-tenths of a
Tesla.
And that's a very strong
magnet.
We often use,
therefore, a unit,
which is the gauss,
which is not an SI unit,
but you will see it often in
books, and one t- gauss is ten
to the minus four Tesla.
The Earth's magnetic field is
roughly half a gauss.
And so this magnet is about two
kilogauss.
But the SI unit is Tesla.
If you look at a  television,
or the screen of your
computer, you have a fluorescent
screen -- and in a television,
there are electron guns that
raster scan this fluorescent
screen -- on a television
screen, you have five hundred
and twenty five lines,
and the electron guns scan that
it one-thirtieth of a second.
And the intensity changes of
these electron beams create
images.
So if you look at the tube from
the side, then there are
electrons -- one moment in time,
they may move like this,
another moment,
they may be here,
in the raster scan -- and so
it's clear that if you bring a
strong magnet in the vicinity of
your television screen,
that you will distort the
image,
because you are now affecting
the motion of these currents,
of these electrons.
And there is a very famous
artist, Nam June Paik who used
this for his art,
and almost every major museum
in this world has a work by Nam
June Paik, with distorted images
using magnets and using
television screens.
I don't want to compete with
Nam June Paik,
but I do want to show this to
you.
I have there,
television sets,
and I have a very strong
magnet, and I will try to
distort that image and give you
the best lights that we know how
to.
And I suggest we try to find a
program that we hate.
So here is my magnet -- oh,
man -- this is an extremely
strong magnet,
and let's turn on the
television,
and let's see what we can get
first.
Oh, I turned it off instead of
on.
Ah, I hate commercials.
Now, watch it closely.
Here comes my magnet,
there's the image.
[background] You see that?
that [background] so you've
seen that we can,
with a magnet and a moving
charge, that we can change the
direction of the moving charge.
Force on the moving charges.
If you have an electric field
as well as a magnetic field,
then, of course,
you have also the electric
force.
And so the total force on a
moving charged particle would
then be Q
times the electric field
vector, plus V cross B.
And this, of course,
we've seen before.
An electric field can do work
on a charge.
Remember, Q delta V.
Can be positive,
can be negative,
but it can do work.
It can change the kinetic
energy of the charge.
Magnetic fields can never do
work on a moving charge.
And the reason is that the
force is always perpendicular to
the velocity
V.
And so if the force is always
perpendicular to the motion,
you can change the direction of
the motion, but you can't change
the kinetic energy.
So that's a fundamental
difference between the electric
force and the magnetic force.
So now I want to calculate,
with you, the force on a
current that runs a wire I
through it, and we have a
magnetic field B.
So we're going to be slowly --
we're going to be more and more
quantitative.
This, by the way,
is often -- also called the
Lorenz force,
just a combination of the two.
That one certainly is.
So let is start with a -- a
wire, and a wire  that runs a
current through,
here is the wire,
and the current is I.
And let's say,
at this point here,
we have a magnetic field B.
And the magnetic field could be
difference along the wire,
in principle.
Here, I have a charge,
plus D Q, and this charge is
running through the wire with a
drift velocity V D.
Let's first think about what
happens if the current is zero.
If the current is zero,
at room temperature,
the free electrons in these
wires have huge speeds.
Three million meters per
second.
Way larger than the drift
velocity.
But they are in all chaotic
directions.
Random motion,
it's a thermal motion.
And so on each individual
charge, there will be a force.
But they average out to be
zero.
It's not until I run a current
that these charges are going to
walk through with a very slow
drift velocity,
and now, of course,
the net force is not zero.
So let's have this charge D Q
that moves in this direction,
and so that gives me a current.
And let this angle be theta
between them.
Say, that's going to be
important, because it's a
cross-product between velocity
and B.
That means the sine of this
theta comes in later.
You will say -- I hope you will
say, "Well, listen,
man, this is ridiculous.
Uh, positive charges don't move
through wires.
It is the electrons that move
They are responsible for the
current.
And electrons have a negative
charge, and they go in this
direction.
You're right.
Perfectly fine.
However, a negative charge
going in this direction is
mathematically exactly the same
as a positive charge going in
that direction.
In both cases,
do we agree that the current is
in this direction.
So I have preferred,
for mathematical reasons,
to take a plus D Q charge going
in this direction rather than
taking a minus D Q charge that
goes with the
drift velocity in that
direction.
But there is no difference at
all in the outcome that you will
see.
So on this charge,
there is a force,
D F -- that's this -- this
magnetic force,
and that is the charge D Q,
that equation,
times V cross B.
Well, V was that drift
velocity,
and here is the magnetic field,
at this location.
The current through the wire,
everywhere on the wire,
must be D Q D T.
Because that's the definition
of current, how many Coulombs
per second.
Current is always D Q D T.
So I can also write this as I D
T times V D cross B.
But I remember eight oh one,
that V D times D T,
that is speed times a time is a
distance.
And I call that distance D L.
It's a distance along the wire.
I will put a distance in here
now, because I don't want to
clutter up my -- my drawing.
So this charge,
in time D T,
moves over that distance,
that's a
vector.
Eight oh one.
So I can write down for this
product, I can write down D L.
So I can also write down that D
F of B equals I times D L cross
B.
What is this telling you?
This is the force of a wire
over a small segment
of the wire which has length D
L, I is the current through the
wire, and B is the local
magnetic field at that location
D L, that's what it means.
And if you want to know the
entire force on the wire,
you have to do the integral
along the whole wire.
And so you have to do an
integral along the entire wire,
and at every portion D L,
you have to determine what B
is, and you get,
then, a force,
which is
a vector, and you have to add
those vectors vectorially.
Could be a pain in the neck,
but that's the basic idea.
So now, I want to calculate
what the force was on this wire,
roughly, when we ran three
hundred amperes through there.
Oh, I turned it off instead of
And I make a geometry so simple
that we can execute that
integral.
This was the wire,
and we had a current running
through here which was three
hundred amperes,
roughly.
And we have a magnetic field,
which was right in the gap
there, that magnetic field B,
and that was two-tenths of a
Tesla.
Two kilogauss.
And that magnetic field was
only operating here.
It wasn't operating there.
And I
make the assumption -- which is
a simplifying assumption -- that
that magnetic field was constant
over the portion of the wire
which was, say,
only ten centimeters.
And so I assume here that I
have a length which is oh point
one meters, and that in  during
-- in this range here,
the magnetic field is constant.
I just want to get a rough
number for the force on that
wire.
So now I can integrate that
equation very easily,
because I have assumed that the
magnetic field is perpendicular
to the direction D L -- because
D L is now in this direction --
so the sine of theta is one,
so I don't have to worry about
that -- and so I simply get that
the force on this section F --
of this section L,
that force -- call it F of B if
you want to -- is the current I,
which we have there,
we get the length L,
which is this length,
multiplied by the magnetic
field.
There is no sine I anywhere
because the angels are ninety
degrees.
And so I find that that force
is three hundred times oh point
one times oh point two,
so it is thirty times point
two, that is about six Newton.
Six Newton is more that the
weight of one pound.
And so it is not so surprising
that when I turn this current
on,
that something,
all of a sudden,
that something all of a sudden
pulls that wire down with a
weight that is equivalent of a
little more than a pound,
almost a pound and a half,
actually.
And so it's not so surprising
that these supports fell over.
So you see that you can turn
this quantitatively,
provided that you make some
simplifying assumptions about
the uniformity of the magnetic
field, and about where the
magnetic field
is present.
Now, I want to talk about the
great eight oh two motor
contest.
We are about to start on this
great eight oh two motor
contest, you got an envelope
today, and I'm going to start to
tell you, slowly,
about the physics.
The goal is,
ultimately, to build a
motor.
If I have a current loop --
here is a current loop.
Current comes in at A,
and I'll try to make it -- make
you look at it
three-dimensionally,
which is not so easy.
This is -- current goes out
here, at D.
This is a current loop.
Current go through here,
go through here,
and we turn here.
And we have a magnetic field,
we will assume that the
magnetic field is constant
throughout, in this direction.
There is a force right here on
this wire, in the direction I
cross B.
That force is up.
There is a force here,
on this wire,
which is, of course,
down.
Magnetic field is in the same
direction, the current is in the
opposite direction,
so the force is down.
If this wire has a length A,
this wire has a length A,
that force
-- the magnitude of that force
is the current through the wire
times the length of the wire
times the B field.
We just derived that.
There's that integral,
we just assume that the
magnetic field is constant
everywhere here,
there, at ninety-degree angles,
so the sine of theta is one,
and so that's the force.
What is the force here and what
is the force here?
Well, it's zero.
Zero here, and it is zero here.
Why is that?
Because the cross-product is
zero.
No matter how you look at it,
you can say D L and B are
either in the same direction or
in opposite directions.
You can also say the drift
velocity and B are either in the
same or the opposite direct- it
is all the same thing.
There is no force here,
and there is no force here.
Because that equation that we
had that gives us the magnetic
force becomes zero.
The sine of that angle is zero.
So what's going to happen with
this thing?
Well, there is a torque on this
system.
There is no net force,
because this force up is the
same as this force
down, but there is a torque
which wants to rotate in
counterclockwise direction.
And the magnitude of that
torque is, of course,
this force -- you remember from
eight oh one -- times the
perpendicular distance between
these two forces,
and so the magnitude of that
torque is I times A B times B at
this moment in time,
when the forces are this far
apart.
Now, this is going to rotate,
and so as they rotate,
these forces come closer,
and so the torque will become
less.
Still, it wants to rotate
counterclockwise.
And there comes a time,
ninety degrees later,
that the torque is zero.
And I will try to make you see
that, again, in a
three-dimensional way,
it's not so easy for me.
Now, this is D,
this has become D,
a current always leaves at D.
I'll try to make you see this
three-dimensionally.
It goes like this,
current comes in here,
at A, so we get this,
and we get this.
It doesn't look so bad.
And the magnetic field B has
not changed, uniform B in the
same direction.
So the current now comes in
through A, it has not changed,
the only thing is that the loop
has rotated ninety degrees.
If, now I ask you what the
forces are, you have to go I
cross
B.
I cross B.
If you do I cross B here,
I cross B, you get a force
which is towards you.
Here, you get forces which are
in the blackboard.
Here you get forces which are
up, and here you get forces
which are down.
At home, you will have some
time to use your right hand,
and do the I cross B,
and you will see,
then, that, indeed,
all these forces are in the
direction that I put them.
So now, there is,
again, no net force on the
system.
There was no net force here,
either.
But now, there is no torque
So now, the torque has become
zero.
If we rotate it a little
further, it is possible,
then we start this motor,
starts to rotate counter
clockwise, comes to this
position, torque goes to zero,
but it has enough inertia so it
rotates a little further.
And now the torque will
reverse.
And this is something that I
leave you alone with,
I don't want to make another
drawing and convince you that it
reverses.
But it's easy to see,
because, take this thing,
and just flip it over hundred
eighty degrees.
The magnetic field hasn't
changed, but the currents in
these two sides have changed
direction now,
because whatever is D is here
and A is here.
And so the torque reverses,
and so it goes like this,
[wssshhht], and then [wsshht]
it comes back.
And that's not much of a motor.
Current meters are very
frequently used,
they are in your cars,
many more than you think,
your, um, your fuel gauge and
your temperature,
of the cooling water,
are current meters.
And a current meter works as
follows.
We attach to this loop a
needle, a handle,
and we calibrate it here.
And you can read how many
amperes
are going through this meter.
It wants to go
counterclockwise.
Here, we attach a spring,
and the spring produces a
counter-torque,
and so the needle will start to
deflect, but come to a halt.
But if you double the current,
it will go further.
That's the way that a current
meter works.
And your fuel gauge in your car
is a current meter,
except that the level of the
fuel is somehow converted into
an electric
signal, and then it's sent to a
current meter,
and that's what you're reading.
And it is, of course,
calibrated in terms of how much
fuel you have.
And your temperature gauge is
calibrated in terms of degrees,
whatever, Fahrenheit or
whatever.
So these current meters are
very common, even when we're
dealing with something that has
nothing to do with current.
How do you build,
now, a motor that works?
How do you get over this torque
reversal?
Well, it's not only the torque
reversal that is a problem,
but there is also the problem
that if you could keep this
going around,
that these two wires would
intertwine, and they would
break.
You roll it around a hundred
times, you can see what happens
at A and D, it will break.
So you have to think of a
design whereby you have slipping
contacts -- we call them
brushes.
Suppose I have,
here, a conductor which is
connected with A,
physically soldered to the wire
at A.
And here, I have a conductor
which is D.
So the -- the loop is where you
are.
Soldered wires coming out the
loop is here.
But now the battery -- plus
side of the battery is here,
and the minus side of the
battery of here,
and this is a slipping contact.
In practice,
we call them brushes.
So that immediately takes care
of the problem,
that the wires wind up.
But there is something else
which is very clever about this
design.
If the gap between A and D is
an insulator,
then, what's going to happen
when this rotates hundred eighty
degrees?
A, which now is on the positive
side of the battery -- this is
negative, of course,
heh?
-- A is now on the positive
side of the battery,
if you -- if you rotate hundred
eighty degrees,
A will be on the negative side
of the battery.
So now every rotation,
the current will,
all by itself,
change direction.
And we call that a commutator.
And so now, what's going to
happen is, now the torque
reversal will not occur.
If, at the right moment,
the current switches direction,
the torque will always want to
rotate the loop in exactly the
same direction.
That's the idea behind a
commutator.
The great eight oh two motor
contest.
You have an envelope,
when you open it up -- don't do
it
now -- you will find in there a
copper wire, two meters
insulated copper wire,
two magnets,
two paper clips,
and some wood.
And the idea is that you try to
build a motor that runs as fast
as possible.
For every hundred RPM -- an RPM
is a rotation per minute -- for
every hundred -- hundred RPM,
I'll give you one credit point,
with a maximum of twenty credit
points.
So if your motor runs t- two
thousand RPM or more,
you get twenty credit points.
That is equivalent to two
homework assignments.
And these credit points count
over and above your course
grade.
You have my word for that.
I'll give you a final course
grade, the way that you've seen
in the ground rules,
in the first handout,
and we add your motor contest,
what you deserved.
For every hundred RPM,
you get one point,
plus, with a maximum of,
uh, of twenty.
And we're going to test these
motors on these second of April,
an I gave you a handout in
which I give you some hints,
some ideas.
There is one idea that I gave
you which you may ignore,
and that is to overcome the
torque reversal,
you can build a commutator.
But that's, uh,
that's really not easy.
Not only is it not easy,
but when you built a
commutator, your system may get
a lot of friction,
and you may lose more than you
gain.
There is an alternative
solution, which I mentioned in
my handout that you picked up
today, and that is that you
design your motor in such a way
that when the
reversal, when the torque
reversal occurs,
that there is no current
running any more.
And when it is half a rotation
further, the torque is there
again, the current is there
again.
So for half the time,
you stop the current,
you will see that's very easy,
I give you some hints how you
do that.
So you have to weigh that
against the possibility of
building a commutator.
The bottom line is,
the maximum is twenty credit
points.
That's an equivalent of two
homework assignments.
You get it over and above your
course grade.
And it's also great,
fun, believe me.
What more do you want?
To do physics,
get credit, and have fun.
That's what I do every day,
that's the great thing about
physics.
We have five minutes left,
and in those five minutes,
I'm going to demonstrate to you
a motor.
What you see there is a current
loop -- I'll try to make you see
it three-dimensionally -- this
is the current loop,
and we're going to run a
current in this direction,
and we, here,
have a magnet,
north, south,
magnetic field is in this
direction.
And we, here,
have a magnet,
north, south,
magnetic field is also in this
direction.
I'm going to run a current
through here,
and if the current is in the
blackboard,
I cross B -- I is in,
cross B, force is up.
This side wants to go up.
If this side wants to go up,
since the magnetic field is the
same direction here,
but the current is hundred
eighty degrees in opposite
direction, this force will be
down.
And so there's a torque on this
motor.
And you will see that.
You will see that go like this.
However, when it's hundred
eighty degrees and it swings
here, by, it wants to go back,
because of
the torque reversal.
That's the first thing that I
want to show you.
And I think I don't need any
changes in the light.
So here, we have this loop,
and here we have the two
magnets -- the magnetic field
is, by no means,
uniform, by the way,
it's very strong here,
and it's very strong there.
And now I have to power that.
Hmm, there we go.
I can't -- yes,
I think I know that this one
will come up this side,
I'm fairly sure that I have the
directions right.
Let's first take a look at it.
There it goes.
So when it's here,
notice, it goes up.
But now, if I power it here
again, wants to go back.
So here, wants to go up,
and here, it wants to go back.
So we've got to do something.
And that something is a
commutator.
So if we can somehow reverse
the current when it's here,
then it wants to go down again.
I'll show you that.
So now it's here.
And I'll drive the current in
the other direction.
You ready for that?
Did you notice?
It now wants to go down.
Now it wants to go down.
But when it's here,
I have to reverse the current,
it wants to go up.
And if I do that with my hands,
I can see whether I can keep
this rotating.
It may take me a while,
but I'll do my best I can.
There it goes.
Switch, switch,
switch, switch,
switch.
Yes, got it,
yes I got it.
I'm a commutator!
This motor is going at least
sixty RPM, that's one credit
point for me for this course.
Thank you.