PROFESSOR: Welcome to
this recitation
on the phase portrait.
So you're given matrix A, a
two-by-two matrix with entries
minus 1, minus 1, 1 minus c,
where c is a constant we will
be varying, and minus 1.
As c increases from 0 to other
positive values, determine the
path of the system on the trace
determinant diagram that
we saw in previous recitations
and draw the phase portraits
that corresponds to the critical
points and the nature
of the critical points.
So here, we're basically talking
of a system that would
be a two-by-two system where we
have derivatives of entry
xy for vector equals to this
matrix, Ac, multiplying the
unknown vector xc.
So take a few minutes and work
out through this problem and
I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So I already prepared the trace
determined diagram for you.
So here as a reminder, this is
the parabola that determines
whether we're going to have
repeated eigenvalues or not.
Above this parabola, we have
two complex conjugate
eigenvalues.
Below this parabola, we have
real eigenvalues, either of
the same signs, positive
or negative, or
of different signs.
And then, we have the
borderline cases.
In our case here, we're looking
in a matrix A with a
trace equals to minus 1 minus
1, So it's minus 2, and a
determinant that is equal
to 2 minus c.
So here, we are basically along
this dotted line where
the trace equals to minus 2.
So either we're going to have
complex values with negative
real parts or negative
eigenvalues.
So we're in stable
configurations.
So we're going to be moving
at c equal to
0 from a case where--
I'm just going to label
this point 1.
For example, we have the matrix,
minus 1, 1, 1, minus 1
with the trace equals
to minus 2, and the
determinant equals to 2.
So clearly, we are this point.
And we are just going to be
increasing the value of c and
moving along these lines,
crossing this first boundary
case where we will have either
defective or not case.
And I'll discuss very briefly
what we have.
And then, we have other value
where we are basically in this
area where we have real
eigenvalues, both of them
negative, so we have
stability.
And it would basically
be in sync.
And then we cross this other
borderline case where the
determinant is equal to 0.
And here, we have one eigenvalue
that is equal to 0
and one that is negative.
And then, we get to do the part
of the diagram where the
determinant is negative, and
the trace is negative.
And we basically have a saddle
structure where we have one
eigenvalue as negative
and another
eigenvalue that is positive.
So let's get through
these five cases.
And I'll just do more
detailed picture
illustrating what I just said.
So just write down a bit more in
detail the first case here.
So we have the case where the
eigenvalues are both complex
conjugate, and we have their
real part being negative.
So basically, we have spirals,
asymptotically stable spirals.
And the spirals could be
either clockwise or
counterclockwise.
And one way of determining the
direction of these spirals is
to look at the sign of the
velocity vector of the
trajectory in the face space.
So the face space basically
diagram here where we have x
and y as the axes
of this space.
So let's look, for example, at
a particular point here that
would be velocity vector 1, 0.
And this position vector 1,
0 would give us a velocity
vector of minus 1 and plus 1.
So basically, this vector would
be directed upward,
which means that we are in the
case where we would have a
spiral coming this way toward
the critical point and
basically with the velocity
vector here going this way.
You don't have to actually do
all this to figure out which
direction of the spiral
you should choose.
You can just look for these
cases two-by-two matrices at
the entry at the lower left
part of your matrix.
And if the coefficient here
is positive, then it will
determine the direction of the
velocity vector at this point.
So if it's positive in this
case, you would have this
counterclockwise direction of
rotation of the spiral.
So now we can move
on and do the
following cases a bit faster.
So the second case, we are in
the case where we now have two
repeated eigenvalues.
Both of them are negative.
So we can have either
a complete case.
If we had a matrix that was
diagonal, we would have
basically a star.
But that's not the case,
because if we pick, for
example, the value c equals
to 1 that puts us on the
parabola, we can see that the
matrix Ac is not diagonal.
So we are in a defective case.
The defective case, if you
compute the eigenvalues in
eigenvector would give
you something
that looks like that.
The first rate of the
eigenvector corresponding to
your eigenvalues would be in
the direction of 1, 0.
We have negative eigenvalues,
so it's going to 0.
And basically, to determine the
direction, you have to see
that we are also following a
transition here on the trace
determined diagram.
And so basically, we will
have a spiral that
would look like this.
What am I doing?
Am I doing the same thing?
And it would basically rotate,
as you can see here, in the
same direction as the case
that we had just before.
Because we basically have the
transition of the structure of
the critical point.
And the arrows are pointing
toward the critical point
again because our two
eigenvalues are basically here
at negative, which is
just a repeated
eigenvalue that is negative.
So now we can move on to a third
case where here we move
into the wedge area where we
have the two eigenvalues now
being real, and both of
them are negative.
So for example, we would have
two eigenvalues that would
give us two eigenvectors that
are basically, they're rays.
The direction of the
trajectories on these two rays
would be toward the critical
point, because we have, again,
negative eigenvalues.
And the trajectories then would
be following the lambda.
So if I, for example, pick
lambda 1 less than lambda 2,
then I would have something
like this going to 0.
And we would have this
trajectory corresponding to
the eigenvalue that
is closer to 0.
And again, the arrows would
be going toward
this critical point.
So we can now move on.
And if we keep increasing c, we
reach now the point 4 where
we are in the special case,
again, a boundary case where
the determinant is 0.
But the trace is non-zero.
If the determinant is 0, which
is the product of the two
eigenvalues, it means that we
have one eigenvalue that is
equal to 0 and another
eigenvalue that is actually,
in this case, minus 2,
so just negative.
So what happens here?
What happens is that we have
now the eigenvector that
corresponds to the eigenvalue
equals to 0 is basically just
defining a whole line
of critical points.
So all the points on this line
that would correspond, so for
example, to lambda 0 are
all critical points.
So we don't need to actually
draw arrows here.
All the points would
be critical points.
And another direction or ray
would be determined by the
second eigenvalue
value, lambda 2.
And we would have, for example,
directions in this way.
It would correspond to
the direction of V2.
So all these would be
parallel to V2.
And we would have the
trajectories going toward all
the critical points
on this line.
So in this case, we're in a case
where we actually don't
have one localized critical
point like in the previous
case that we saw.
We've actually have a whole
line of critical points.
So let's move one
more point down.
So here, another value of c, we
now are in the lower part
of the diagram where we now have
two eigenvalues that are
again real.
But now, the determinant
is negative.
Determinant is the product
of the two.
So basically we know that one is
positive and the other one
is negative.
So for example here, we would
have one positive, the
negative eigenvalue value.
So we would have the positive
eigenvalue and the negative
eigenvalue here.
So here, again, we're just
moving in the structure of the
critical point.
So we should have a smooth
transition between the
diagrams going 1 to 5.
And so here, what we see is that
we actually have the ray
that is basically the stable
space here that would give us
the trajectories going to 0.
But it's the only region where
we have stability.
And all the trajectories will
just then be tangent in minus
infinity to the rate V1
corresponding to the negative
eigenvalue and going towards the
direction of the ray with
a positive eigenvalue
at plus infinity.
So we would have something
like that, that would
correspond to a saddle.
This would be a palm.
This is basically a sink or
basically a stable node.
This would be defective
stable node.
And here, we just have a
asymptotically stable spiral.
So basically here what you could
see is by just changing
the value of the constant c had
moved the structure of the
critical point of the system
from the phase
diagrams one to five.
And the transitions can be seen
to be smooth if you had a
continuum of values for c.
So that ends this recitation.