LYDIA BOUROUIBA: Welcome to this
presentation on the trace
determinant diagram.
So here, you're asked to label
the regions and lines of the
trace determinant diagram for a
2 x 2 general system, return
the form x prime equals Ax, and
to indicate the stability
on your diagram.
So here, as a reminder, this
system is simply a system of
two differential equations in
vector form the derivative xy
equals abcd, a 2 x 2 matrix,
multiplying the vector xy.
Or in another form, it would be
x-dot equals f of xy, and
y-dot equals j of xy, where the
T wouldn't appear in f and
j here, functions, which means
that the system would be
autonomous, and we're dealing
with linear systems.
So why don't you pause
the video.
Take a few minutes remind
yourself what the trace
determinant diagram is and
how to label it, and
I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So let's remind ourselves where
this trace determinant
diagram comes from.
So initially, what we saw
before was to solve this
system, we need to find the
eigenvalues of the matrix A.
The eigenvalues are solutions of
this equation, which can be
written in the form lambda
square minus trace of lambda
plus determinant of
a equals to 0.
Let's call this D, and this T.
And the trace of A is just the
sum of the diagonals of the
matrix, and the determinant is
just, in this case for
a 2 x 2, ad minus cb.
So the solutions for--
I'm going to call them
plus and minus--
for this second order polynomial
will simply be T
plus or minus the root of the
determinant of second order
polynomial, which is
T square minus 4D.
So the sign of T square minus
4D is going to determine
whether we are dealing with real
eigenvalues or complex
eigenvalues, or simply repeated
eigenvalues if we
have this determinant under
the root being equal to 0.
So just as a reminder here, if
we have T square over 4 equals
to D, we are in the case, well,
this is equal to 0.
Lambda plus or minus are the
same, and they're just equal
to the trace over 2.
So the sign of the trace is
going to determine whether we
have two repeated negative
eigenvalues or two repeated
positive eigenvalues.
Now, if we have the determinant
of the matrix A is
larger than T square over 4,
then we are above the curve
determined by this equation,
which is a parabola, which
I'll draw in a minute.
And in this case, we have the
number under the root being
negative, so we're dealing
with complex eigenvalues.
And basically, they're
just complex
conjugate of each other.
And you can notice here that
the trace would be also the
sum of the two eigenvalues, and
basically we would just
have 2 times the real part of
both lambda plus or minus,
just as a note.
And in the third case, where we
have that the determinant
is below T square over 4, we're
in the case where this
number under the root is
positive, so we're dealing
with two real eigenvalues.
So here, I should mention
this is real.
Lambda plus, lambda
minus real.
And we can have multiple
cases.
We can have lambda
plus larger than
lambda minus, both positive.
We can have lambda
plus, less than
lambda minus, both negative.
Or we can have lambda
plus positive and
lambda minus negative.
And each case will give
us a different
behavior of the system.
So let's first summarize this in
this following determinant
trace diagram, and then we'll
start labeling this diagram.
I should probably keep a
little more space here.
So this is basically D equal T
square over 4 in our trace
determinant diagram.
I'm going to also erase this
part and just keep it in dots.
So in the first case that we
looked at, we are in the case
where we are right
on this parabola.
So that's the case where
we have lambda plus
equal lambda minus.
And you can see that if the
trace is positive, so if we
are on the right hand side of
the diagram, that we're going
to have two positive eigenvalues
that are both
real, and they are repeated.
So we can have multiple cases.
We can have the case where we
have a defective matrix, where
basically here we only have
one eigenvector associated
with this repeated eigenvalue.
And we have a defective case
where we need to come up with
a second eigenvector using the
generalized eigenvector formula.
And I'm not going to write this
here, but I'm going to
just to do the diagram.
So for example, we would have
one direction, V1, where we
would have in this case lambda
1 and lambda minus positive.
So in the phase base, in yx, the
little diagram would show
us that the solution are
escaping from the critical
point, the equilibrium point.
And the second solution that
we build would have a
dependence in TV1, plus the
second eigenvector V2 also
directed by the positive
eigenvalue.
And so, we would have a
solution, for example, that
would look like this, with the
solution escaping from the
critical point because, again,
we are in the case where the
two eigenvalues are positive.
And so here, we could have it
in this form, or we can also
have the diagram in the
other direction.
And I'll to it in the other
direction on the other wing of
the diagram.
So this is the defective case.
Defective node.
The other possibility that we
could have on this parabola--
and I'm going to just
to it here--
will be the case where we
actually have all the
direction could be eigenvectors
associated with
this eigenvalue.
And this would be, for example,
for a diagonal matrix.
In which case, all the
directions would be escaping--
all the trajectories
would be escaping--
from the critical point.
And this would be a star.
Obviously here, we are in the
unstable case for the
defective node, and we are also
in the unstable case for
the star, because all the
solutions are escaping and
basically going away.
So if I start at the equilibrium
and I perturb it a
little bit, the solutions would
want to escape from that
equilibrium point.
On the other side here, it
would be exactly the same
structure, except that I would
have stability because the
trace is negative.
So I would have asymptotically
stable star.
Why asymptotically?
Because basically, it's when
T goes to infinity that the
trajectories reach the
critical point.
And this is again in the
phase base yx diagram.
For the defective node, we
would have this time, for
example, direction V1 attracting
the solutions,
there ray V1.
And the new trajectory that we
will be constructing based on
V1 again would be DV1 plus V2
generalized eigenvector.
Both of them would give us
solutions that converge toward
the equilibrium,
because the two
eigenvalues here are negative.
And so, we have that for large
time, minus infinity follows
V1, for plus infinity it's going
toward the equilibrium
points also follows V1.
So the solutions would have to
look like this, for example.
And this would be asymptotically
stable
defective node.
OK.
So we're done with the points
on the parabola.
So now let's look at the other
points, and I'll go maybe a
bit less in the details.
So for the case where we have
the determinant larger then T
square over 4, so we are just
above this parabola now, we
have the case where we have
two complex eigenvalues.
They are two complex
conjugates.
So let's assume that we can just
expand our solution and
write it in terms of the
exponential, in terms of the
real part of the eigenvalue.
So it would be determined,
again, the trace will give us
the sign of the real part of the
eigenvalue, multiplying a
cosine and a sine.
So we have something that is
rotating in phase base,
because we have basically
the periodicity.
But the distance to the critical
point is changing,
and it's either growing, if we
have a positive real part for
our eigenvalues, so if
we are on this side.
Or decaying if we are on the
left side of the diagram.
So that gives us typically
spirals.
So for example, that would be
a spiral, going toward 0,
toward the equilibrium
point in phase base.
And here, we would be in the
case where we have instability
due to the fact that the real
part of the eigenvalue
determining stability
is positive.
And so the solution of the
trajectories escape from the
critical point.
And similarly here, we could
have the same structure, but
I'm just going to draw it
in another direction.
Where here, we would
have stability.
Oops.
They should not cross.
This is not the right
way to draw this.
And it would be going toward
the critical point.
So here, just a quick note.
You can have this trajectory
being drawn this way.
So here, we have basically
a clockwise motion.
But we could also have it be
drawn in the other way for
both cases, giving us
another direction of
rotation in phase base.
And the direction that you
choose will be determined by
the lowest left entry of your
matrix A, and I will just
explain quickly how
we do that.
OK.
So we have basically here in
stable spiral mode, and here
it's again asymptotically
stable a spiral.
So what happens now if
we are in this case.
We're still above the parabola,
so we have still
complex eigenvalues.
However, we have now the fact
that the trace is equal to 0,
which means that the
eigenvalues don't
have any real part.
So basically, we have
pure oscillation.
And in the phase base, that
corresponds to closed
trajectories that
could be circles
or ellipses, basically.
And so for example, we would
have something in this form
that would be called
the center.
And here again, you can have
either counterclockwise or a
clockwise rotation in phase base
depending on the signs of
the entries of your matrix.
So one thing I want to note is
that here, the stability for
the center we say that it's
simply stable, and not
asymptotically stable, because
the solution never actually
reaches the critical point, but
stays in the region around
the critical point.
So we're left with a few other
cases that are now all below
the parabola.
And for that, we just have
real eigenvalues.
So let's look at the case where
the eigenvalues have two
different signs.
So for that, we have
to have the
determinant being negative.
So this whole lower part of
the diagram, because the
determinant is the product
of the two eigenvalues.
So if they have different signs,
we're in this region.
So in this case, we could
have, for example, one
eigenvalue with associated
eigenvector V1 being negative.
So the trajectories along this
ray would be going toward
equilibrium point.
And then the other eigenvalue
will be positive.
So for example, lambda 2 here
would correspond to this other
eigenvector V2.
And so here, we would have
solutions that would be close
to V1 when we're coming, for
example, from minus infinity
approaching the critical
point.
And then going back, approaching
V2 when we go at T
plus infinity, for example.
And so it gives us
pseudo-hyperbola form
here, of this form.
And this is said to be unstable,
because all those
solutions do not go to
the critical point.
But we have some stable
manifolds.
For example, the V1.
If we start on this ray, we
would be going toward the
critical point.
And if we start at the critical
point itself, it
would stay at the
critical point.
But it is unstable.
So now what happened
in these two
different regions to finish.
In these two different
regions--
and I'm going to have a little
bit more space here--
AUDIENCE: It's called
a saddle.
LYDIA BOUROUIBA: Oh, yeah.
Thank you.
And this would be a saddle,
and it's just
because of the shape.
I'm going to just add a little
bit of space here, so that we
can complete the diagram.
I'll be basically looking at the
regions here in the wedge,
where we are below
the parabola.
And I'm looking for
another color.
Maybe I'll just use white.
Now we are in the case where we
would have two eigenvalues.
Both real, so no oscillation.
But let's say both positive,
because we're basically on the
region where the trace
is positive.
Let's say that we have
one ray, V1.
One ray, V2.
The trajectories are going away
from the critical point,
because the two eigenvalues
are positive.
And now, what do the
other trajectories
do, where they follow--
so for example, they would
be following V2.
And I'm going to explain how.
So here, we're in the case
where obviously we're
unstable, because again, the
solution, the trajectories are
going away from the
critical point.
And here, how do you pick which
ray do you follow when
you get closer to the
critical point?
Where in this case, we would
be in a situation where we
have lambda 2 smaller than
lambda 1, larger than 0.
So basically, the lambda 2 that
is the closer to 0-- and
that's also the case for the
positive and the negative
eigenvalues--
is the one that determines the
solution closer to the
critical point.
And the larger in absolute
eigenvalue and its ray then
determines the behavior--
Oh, sorry.
There's a mistake here.
It should be lambda 1.
I said it, but I think
I wrote it reversely.
Yeah The eigenvalue closer to
0 is the one that determines
the behavior at 0.
So here, when we're going
to infinity, the larger
eigenvalue lambda 2 will
determine the behavior, and
the trajectories will become
more and more parallel to V2.
So what happens on this side
would be exactly the same
diagram, and I'm just going
to do it with the same--
let's say, V2 here.
Except that we would have our
trajectories going toward the
critical point.
And the trajectory here again
would be closer to V1, which
means that we would have a case
where we have lambda 1
less than 0 and larger
than lambda 2.
So that finishes roughly
the diagram.
I didn't detail a few
borderline regions.
For example, the region where
the determinant equals to 0.
And we will discuss that
in another recitation.
And the case also at which the
determinant and the trace are
equal to 0.
So we'll detail that also.
But try to think about it
to complete the diagram.
So the key points here were
to remember what is the
determinant trace diagram, how
to basically deduce the nature
of the eigenvalues based
on T and D, their sign.
And where to place the different
structures on this
determinant trace diagram.
And that ends this recitation.