The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: One example will be
what happens when the battery
runs up on the computer
and what bubbles
up when it's running.
And there's certain computers
that might [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
hard drives.
Some computers just keep it in
RAM when you restart it.
There's no big difference.
What happens when an IM window
pops up in the middle of the
game and leaves the
control screen?
And all the keys start
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
IM window.
Ideally, they give you pop
ups that doesn't work.
But catching those is one of our
favorite things that we do
when we're making digital games
here in the lab is like
slamming all of our fingers on
the keyboard at once and see
what happens.
And we're kind of looking
for those things.
We're also looking for subtler
things like is the amount of
RAM that those games are taking
up in the computer
slowly going up all the time?
And of course, comparing it
against a spec grade.
So a character is supposed to
be able to create a certain
file hold style or something
when you enter this key
sequence, and 99 times out of
100 that works and that 1 out
of 100 doesn't and we need
to figure out why.
That's our feat.
So in a lot of those situations,
what happens is
that output comes back in the
form of other parts and-- how
many of you actually
do programming?
Oh, OK.
How many of you have found
a book report?
OK, not that many.
There are a couple of best
practices where you follow a
book report and this one
translates a little bit into
when you're really working
in a team in a game.
How do you communicate that
something is wrong to someone
else who is also responsible
for the game, but may not
necessarily have seen
the problem?
First of all, you describe what
you were expecting to
happen and what you
were doing.
I was expecting to go right when
I push the right button.
And then you write down
what happened.
You try to get as much detail as
possible for the person to
re-release this problem.
Now, when it comes to war games,
in many situations, the
kind of detail that you need
to provide largely comes up
against it.
So 'a' had this much money, 'b'
had that much money, they
try to do this game mechanic
and no one knew what to do
because the way the rules are
written there's only one way
to interpret it.
And that gives your team enough
information to be able
to start acting on it.
Because you are bargaining and
your rules are kind of right
out there in the open, there's
usually less of a mystery to
see where the problem occurs.
But you know there's problem
and it could end and you
largely see where it lies.
You may not know what to do
to correct it, and that's
actually where beta
testing comes in.
So but I'll get to the
testing shortly.
But technical testing, a lot
of it again is comparing a
given spec.
Sometimes that spec is created
from your team.
This is what we want
our game to do.
This is what we expected to
happen when we made this game.
We expect that mid in the game,
a certain game mechanic
will start to take priority
over other mechanics.
Early on, everyone's buying
property is a monopoly.
Later on, everyone's going to
be building houses and then
even at the end, people start
to mortgage stuff.
That's what we kind of
expected out of it.
And then you play the game and
you start realizing you
mortgaging something way too
early here, something's out of
whack here.
So that's the kind of technical
testing you do in games.
This is what we expect, why
isn't it happening?
The other side over here is
kind of like being the
defender of the player, being
the player's advocate.
How, can you be the person on
the team that is actively
looking for things in your game
that are going to hurt
your players and then mentioning
it and saying,
maybe we should do something
about that.
It's as simple as, here's the
information that we want our
players to have at
a certain time.
Here's the game state.
Your characters have
a certain state.
They are this close to winning,
but are this far away
from winning to have
these results here.
Do the players understand
that?
Have you provided them with
enough information to be able
to make a good decision?
If they know the game state, do
they know what options they
have in front of them?
So as we play more and more
board games this semester, you
can actually look at the way
how rules are presented
redundantly.
Sometimes they're written up in
the rule sheet, but and of
course you've got your index
card-sized thing which goes
through step one, two, three,
four, these are the four
things you've got to remember
every single turn.
You've got to get it, and
everybody has a copy right in
front of you because somebody on
the team decided that that
was a good idea.
How did they come to
that conclusion?
Occasionally, they are doing it
because they see there's a
problem right away.
There's too much information,
and you just don't expect any
player is ever going to be
able to grasp all this
information.
So that's come out with a couple
of ways to simplify it.
Sometimes that involves taking
up the mechanics, making
something that was written up a
text graphic report and some
icons, reducing all the numbers
by two so the math
becomes easier.
But sometimes, you do it by
usability testing, and that's
one kind of testing
that often comes
together with beta testing.
I've invited Sara Verrilli, our
development director, to
come in here and talk about the
kind of pre-testing that
you can do, which is illustrated
by this picture.
And the book goes through
several different kinds of
environments where you do
pre-testing that's sitting
one-on-one with people
and doing site
testing for the group.
Because this style is all about
board games and card
games, for the most part, we're
designing games for
three or four people
to play at a time.
The chances are, almost every
single test that you're going
to do [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
at a single time.
That's just the environment
you're in
that's meant to be played.
That's why you end
up testing it.
Obviously, a single-play
computer game, that's not
necessarily the environment
you're testing in.
Actually, before I transition
over, there is one thing I
want to mention about
technical testing.
Sometimes the specs you're
testing against are not the
ones that came up that would
necessarily come up
with phi over t.
If you're doing a
computer game--
say for an Xbox or
a PS3 or a Wii.
There are these things called
technical [? evaluation ?]
requirements, which are
basically huge lists of things
that your game must do before
Microsoft will sign your title
or allow it to be released
under that title.
PC obviously doesn't have this,
but if you release it on
speed or something, then chances
are, you'll have
requirements.
It could be something as
simple as generally, it
doesn't crash--
and games do crash, even
on PS3 and Xbox--
you get things like what happens
when you're playing a
game on the PS3 or Xbox--
I guess more the PS2 and the
first Xbox-- and someone yanks
out the cable?
All you're thinking is that
you're-- and then the keyboard
comes out, what happens?
Does it continue?
STUDENT: It buzzes.
PROFESSOR: It goes into
pause, right?
And usually it tells you, your
controller is disconnected.
And that's a requirement.
Someone had to write that code
specifically to detect that
situation and then throughout
the suite across the game.
And the reason everybody had
to do that was because
Microsoft and Sony
and Nintendo--
well, not so much Nintendo
nowadays
because Nintendo is wireless--
but these are the kinds of
requirements that they expect.
If you lose your connection to
Xbox live halfway through the
game then something's
going to happen.
And so again, for that kind of
technical testing, you're sort
of comparing it against spec,
but spec may not necessarily
be something that you're
keeping up with.
It may be something that the
publisher or your platform
developer, platform manufacturer
mandated.
How does it affect the board
games is that sometimes, board
games are actually going
to require half the
requirements to that.
If you're responsible for the
design of the box, for
instance, there are things
they're going to require on
the outside of the box, like
what ages are the game
applicable for, how long is it
meant to be played, how many
people are going to be
playing your game.
I think Days of Wonder, which
is a publisher, actually
requires a character
to be on the box.
Even if your game has no
characters, there must be a
human-like presence on the box
or your players are on the box
because they think that it
increases sales, and they
probably have the numbers
to back it up.
That's why if you look at things
like Ticket for Ride,
for instance, has people.
If you play Ticket to Ride, it
has no people in it, but it
has people on the box because
they want people to think
that's what users are.
So that's just an example of
things that a board game
publisher may require
you to do.
Very common that you'll have to
do translations in a range
of different translations for
the different countries it's
going to be released in.
It may not be your job to do it,
the publishers may end up
being the ones helping you with
the translation, getting
all the publishing data
formatted decently, but
someone along the stage is
making sure that happens
before the game hits
the shelf.
OK, that's technical testing.
That's a little bit about
becoming a player and so let's
talk about data center a bit.
SARA VERRILLI: Let me bump
you a little here,
if you don't care.
PROFESSOR: Oh, right.
SARA VERRILLI: OK.
Let's see.
Let's actually go ahead.
So focus testing.
This is a very similar track for
the summer program folks.
I have about 10 minutes to go
back and relook at my notes
and relook at the lecture, so
if it's a little stumbly in
parts, it's because I haven't
given it for a while and
haven't thought about it.
It's much more geared, the
original talk is much more
geared towards computer
testing, and testing
specifically single-player
computer games than it's
testing board games, which
are almost a multi-user.
So first of all, focus testing
is actually dissimilar.
Focus testing is only a specific
case of user testing,
which is to say, you're testing
your game using actual
users, not your development
team, not people who play
board games 12 hours a day
because that's what they love
to do all the time, but more the
sort of average person who
might want to pick up your game
off the shelf, go buy it
and then go play it with their
family and then go out to
dinner at Chuck E. Cheese
or something.
Another type of user tester is
usability testing, which is
fairly similar to focus testing
in as much as you're
still using users for it.
Focus testing is usually much
more geared towards are people
enjoying your game?
Do people want to
play your game?
Are people going through the
sort of play experiences you
want them to have as they
play their game?
Because usually when you
create a game, you're
thinking, oh, like for Settlers
of Catan, you expect
people to spend a lot of time
talking with each other
trading things back and forth.
When you're making Diplomacy,
you expect people to spend a
lot of time arguing with each
other over well, if you invade
that country, I'll invade that
country and we'll gang up on
him and we'll all come out of
the game and then we'll just
divide four between the two of
us and win while you're making
secret underhanded arrangements
with the other
guys, but OK, so he's going to
attack you on this ground, we
both know that, that sort of
thing, as opposed to, say,
Transamerica which is just more
putting pieces down and
it's pretty much independent
play in many ways.
Usability testing is much more
about how you easy is it for
people to play your game.
Do they understand your rules?
Are the mechanics clear?
When they sit down and start
sorting out the tokens, can
they tell which tokens are the
player pieces and which cards
are which and how
you use those?
Do the icons on your game
make sense to people?
Do they understand them?
Things like that.
It's not really about whether
or not people like your game
or are enjoying your game.
It's about can people understand
your game and start
playing it.
So here we go.
One big problem we run into when
people sit down and we
have people playing your game
and giving lots of comments,
this was really fun or this
really sucked, or I hate this
part where I have to spend
time talking to the other
players, I want to be able to
stare at just my cards and
board completely without
interacting with anyone else.
Focus testers will give you
lots and lots of feedback,
some of it is useful,
some of it is not.
And you need to remember that
focus testers are not actually
people building the game.
Focus testers are the people
who you are trying to get
information about your game from
and one problem that we
often see in experienced game
developers and people making
games doing is, oh, the focus
tester said we have to make
the whole game red, quick, let's
make everything red.
So and that's usually,
that's not a very
good solution, right?
Who knows what the problem with
this actually was, but
what you need to do is find out
why did the players want
to make everything red?
Is it because they don't
like the artistic
design of the game?
Is it because someone in
the game is colorblind?
Someone playing the game
currently is colorblind, is
having a hard time telling
things apart so they'd like
everything to be the same color
so everyone's having the
same problem they are.
I mean, who knows?
It's hard to tell what
people are thinking.
When they give you advice, and
when they give you these
comments, you have to have
some way to filter those
comments, some way to think
about them and some way to
decide what actually is the
right reaction to take in view
of what you want your game to do
and how you want people to
play the game.
Since you're the game designers
and developers, you
have to make those decisions.
Focus testers can only
give you data.
You shouldn't ask them to design
your game for you.
Maybe you actually have good
ideas that you want to use,
but you want to make sure that
they're good ideas that you do
want to use.
So you may notice, these are
both my lectures, and these
are pictures that Mike
[? Dropho ?] drew for a
poster, and we love
him so much.
So in the ideal focus testing
situation, you're really
trying to get as much data as
you can about your player
playing the game without
spoiling the information.
What you'd really like to
recreate in a lot of ways is,
so you just bought
the game and have
gotten home, what happens?
And that's what this picture is
all about, there's somebody
luring somebody to play the game
without any information.
So things to think about when
you're planning your focus
testing is, what are
you testing?
What questions do
you want to ask?
What information do you
want to get out of it?
How are you going to test it?
How many players do you need?
What kind of interactions
do you want to see?
On the backhand, who are
you testing with?
What kind of people are going
to make your game?
Are you making a game for
children age 9 to 15?
Are you making it for
college-age students?
Are you making a game that you
think that older players will
want to play?
Because if you're making a game
that you think is going
to be popular with the senior
citizens market, testing it
with a bunch of elementary
school kids probably isn't
going to go very will.
Trivial Pursuit Classic Edition,
a game that came out
about 20-odd years ago, I
suspect that if you sat down a
group of high school students
with it and had them play it,
about three quarters of the
questions they'd just stare at
you and be like, I've
never heard of that.
So, that's certainly where
the audience comes in.
So, the what, planning out the
questions that you think
you're going to get
information for.
When you know what information
for focus testing, it's a lot
easier to know what to keep
track of, how to take notes,
what reactions you're most
interested in as people are
playing the game.
So, what questions are
you going to ask?
What data it takes to answer
your question?
And how are you going
to get that data?
Are you going to go all through
observation taking notes?
Are you going to just step
in and out of questions?
So why did you move that
character from there, just out
of curiosity I'm wondering
why you made that move.
Will you tell me about it?
Or, you can ask them to fill
out a questionnaire
at the end of it.
Depending on what data
you want, different
methods will work best.
In general, usually the best way
to do it is observation.
As soon as you ask someone
questions, you sort of perturb
the system and when you ask
them to fill out a survey,
it's after they've done it.
They've kind of forgotten
what they were doing.
They may not exactly remember,
and to be perfectly honest,
people would really rather
play your game
than fill out a form.
So they'll be more engaged
more interested and more
interactive when they're playing
a game and that's when
you're going to get
your best data.
But there are times when you
want to ask someone something
sort of analytical and you
don't want someone to be
thinking analytically while
they're playing the game in a
lot of ways , and so there are
times when that reflection
comes out so much better and
it's better to have that
written down and get it
in your own words.
STUDENT: You would hope it plays
better than a survey.
SARA VERRILLI: If your game is
better than a survey, you
probably already observed a
problem right there and you're
probably glad you found it.
So how?
In order to get all that data,
you're going to have to
actually interact with the user,
someone who's never seen
your game before, someone who
doesn't actually care whether
or not you get good
information out of
playing this game.
They came here to sit down and
play the game, and while they
would like to help you by giving
you information, that's
not their primary goal
in a lot of ways.
Usually, their primary goal is
to sit down, and play the
game, and have a good time.
So you need to be able to
structure the interaction with
them so that getting the
data to you is as
easy for them as possible.
So we need to think about what
this player needs before he or
she sits down to play.
Usually, in a board game
or a card game,
that's the set of rules.
In a computer, it's
always trickier.
Usually when we're bringing in
people to test the first
prototypes, we have a game that
works, but we don't have
any instructions in game.
If we're going to have a
tutorial or anything like
that, that's usually one of the
last things that goes in.
So when you're testing computer
games early in the
process, usually you end up
sitting down and writing out,
well, this is what the tutorial
would look like if we
had it, so read this and then
sit down and play it.
With board games and card games,
it's actually a little
bit easier, because you can say,
a ha, this is the rules
that are going to package
with the games.
Give you the rules, step back
and see what happens.
So, it's actually an
easier aspect for
testing board games.
And finally, treat the
players politely.
When they find a misspelling
in your rules or when they
discover that you've left out
six of the key cards to play
the game, oh, yeah, you're
right, thank you for pointing
that out, I wouldn't have
noticed that if you hadn't
shown it to me.
Whether you would have or not
doesn't really matter.
They're doing you a favor by
playing your game that isn't
quite working well, so you want
them to know that their
contribution is invaluable and
you appreciate the time and
effort they've put into it.
A few things, the more they talk
about your game and the
mechanics they find that break
or that do or don't work,
that's all data right there,
That's all great.
Another great advantage of
testing board games is you
usually get groups of players,
like two or three or four
players, and when you have
multiple players, they'll talk
to each other about it.
Oh, I noticed this.
Did you notice this strategy?
Yeah, I did, but I noticed that
if you add that strategy
that you can do this thing and
this other thing and that's
all really neat.
When you're testing
single-player computer games
like we usually do in the summer
program, you've got a
single user that is sitting
there between
them and the computer.
You have to watch and figure
out what they're thinking.
When you have a group, it's not
usually that hard to get
them talking about what they're
doing and what they're
thinking, and so that's a
really good way to try
and get more data.
So yeah, here's sort
of the end summary.
Have a specific question
and questions in mind.
Know what you're doing in focus
testing, know why you're
doing usability testing.
If you don't know what you're
trying to test for, then your
data is going to be a
lot harder to figure
out what to do with.
So you always want to we have
that question in mind.
That's actually a
really big one.
What data you need to answer
that question so you can
collect it and know how to
collect it, and make sure that
you can give the information to
the players, a standardized
set of information to the
players and step away so
you're not sort of coloring
the information and giving
them the things you're talking
about by, oh I forgot to
mention, oh and did I say, so
you've actually got sort of a
standardized standard size play
group scenario set down.
OK, I think that's actually
what [? I came for. ?]
PROFESSOR: So a couple of
words about when to be
testing, which is really
as soon as possible.
Usually, before you think it's
possible, you should be
already starting to plan your
fist test because at that
point, you're probably going for
the lowest-hanging fruit,
which will be probably somebody
else in this class
because they're going to give
you feedback anyways, you can
use that favor in exchange.
The whole point of making
testing as simple as possible
is you want to be able to get
information while you still
have time to fix it, to do
something with that data.
What has happened a lot of times
in this class is we have
a project team where they come
up with a game requires say,
generating so many cards or that
they're going to spend
most of the project deadline
actually creating those cards.
They'll test it, but they'll
test it on themselves because
the team already gets
it and they're not
looking for other people.
They have a plan to ask their
friends to come in for a
specific time, they've
set aside an hour or
something like that.
So what happens is that the
last week comes around and
they start playing it with
people who haven't seen the
game before and then discovered
problems.
Unfortunately, the game
has 100 cards that all
now need to be fixed.
This is a problem because
you just discovered
that problem too late.
A couple of ways to handle
that, though, one, don't
decide on a game where making
changes across the entire game
is going to take you more time
than to test it because that's
going to make it impossible
to fix anything.
But the other one is
just testing early.
As soon as you've got a couple
of key mechanics down, sure
you are planning to play
this game with 100
cards, start with 20.
Start with a small of group of
cards, hence your core can see
people and understand that
they're going to discover
things in the production of
those 20 cards and in the
testing of those 20 cards that
maybe you don't want to be
doing for the next test and you
can redo those 20 cards
pretty quickly the way that
you can't redo 100 cards.
Just an example.
I'm really not encouraging
people to do a 100-card game,
by the way.
A regular poker deck, 52 cards,
that's all you need for
a really interesting game.
Let's see.
Some other things.
Say you're doing a test,
but it's not with
your entire team present.
Say it's just you and your
teammates are all living in
different dorms and you
decided to play with
those in your dorm.
That's great, because it's a
cool game and you've got your
feedback, how do you
communicate that
back to your team?
I talked a little bit about
writing up a little report,
but here's a couple of other
tips because one thing you
have to remember is that chances
are, every single idea
in the game, somebody in your
team is probably really
passionate about it and what
you're basically trying to do
is try to convince someone in
your team that maybe this idea
should be changed.
And your game will probably be
better for it, but there are
some tactful was of
telling that.
So let's see.
Keep it short, this also applies
to book reports.
I talked about you giving people
enough information to
reproduce what the problem was
so that they can understand
the state of the game and why
the problem is occurring.
And the flip side of that is not
too much information, not
more information than is
necessary to keep it short.
Little [? farm ?] codes, give
them something that's easy for
people to scan.
Don't make them read and essay
for them to figure out what
comments will be solved.
Now actually, one thing to keep
in mind and if you keep
in mind and think about what
Sara said earlier about the
data that you decide to collect,
one problem with
board games is with all the
interesting conversations
happening around the table and
multiple players suggesting
strategies to each other, you
can come up with reams of
notes in a single play
test session.
How do you decide to digest
that is really important.
And you're the only person
there and you're the only
person on your team, you need
to try to let the rest
of your team know.
You need to put in the work
of digesting all of that
information before necessarily
giving it over to your team.
SARA VERRILLI: One possible
solution also is you can get
permission from play testers
for a tape recorder.
Just get a digital recorder
and record all of the
conversation as it goes on.
PROFESSOR: But you still want
to pick out the keys, you
don't want to revisit the
entire conversation.
Because if the game took an
hour, and every single one of
your team members visits, by now
you've lost three hours.
So you want to find that, do
that little bit of work to
save yourself the detail.
But that's the way because you
can focus, you can take down
notes on the main points and
just let the tape recorder
record all the details so that
you don't have to worry about
recording and really, the main
points are the things that you
want to make sure you get
across to your team.
The tape recorder is
just evidence.
You could use video depending on
who you're recording with.
Sometimes people get kind
of antsy when they
know there's a camera.
That being said--
SARA VERRILLI: And also, just
put the video tilted at the
board so you're not recording
the players, you're
recording the game.
PROFESSOR: Actually webcams
are really good for
that sort of thing.
SARA VERRILLI: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: You don't run out of
tape, just record straight
to hard drive.
SARA VERRILLI: Easy to fast
forward through, also.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, with
your editing tools.
Let's see.
So when you're reporting to
other people, think like
bullet points for instance.
Huge long paragraphs of
prose, not so much.
Let's see.
Try to avoid using the following
words, broken,
problem, unusable, confusing,
kind of odd, you can get more
specific than that, but these
are words that kind of like
imply not only is there a
problem, someone made a
mistake in his design
of the game.
And truth be told, most of the
time it wasn't a mistake, you
just didn't have the complete
play testing, you probably
just had the designer.
But you don't want to make
someone feel like they've made
a mistake because that makes
them defensive and then
they're going to try to defend
how what they wrote in the
first place is actually correct,
which is actually not
correct either.
You can talk about features
that need attention.
With attention, this feature
could be confused.
I guess that's actually
on the edge there.
So but just generally, pick your
words carefully and one
thing that Sara mentioned
earlier was that testers are
not designers and key designers
are actually not a
good testing team.
So for the most part, you are
immediately going to exclude
yourself from your target
audience because you know too
much of the game.
This is also covered
in your book.
As soon as you've played through
your game once or
twice, that's it.
Your kind of work is finished.
You can still be a good
technical tester, I guess.
You can still check whether some
mechanics are working the
way that you want to work, but
you can't tell whether the
dynamics in your settings
are working anymore.
You have to get your
focus testing done.
SARA VERRILLI: You also really
can't tell, you can never
tell-- you can never share
your usability tester.
It will always make
sense to you.
It's amazing that what makes
sense to you is completely
incomprehensible to the very
intelligent person you give
the game to.
Really, truly, I've
been thinking
about this one myself.
PROFESSOR: Usability testing,
by the way, is one of those
things that even if you only
have the chance to do a pop-up
partial test like, all I have
is this one card, the game's
not complete, but grab someone
walking down the corridor on
the way to the washroom and say,
come in here and take a
look at this thing
I'm working on.
Even that is better
information.
STUDENT: Hey kid,
come in here.
Come in here, I have something
to show you?
I have a surprise for you.
[LAUGHTER]
SARA VERRILLI: Actually, you
can get going testing for
[? serious. ?]
STUDENT: Free candy.
PROFESSOR: [? Mona ?] actually
calls it employee kidnapping.
[LAUGHTER]
Of course, he's the creative
director, so he can do that.
SARA VERRILLI: It works best
if you're accosting people
whom you have power over.
PROFESSOR: The audio thing, by
the way, is one of those
things that could be really
useful if people are difficult
[? pundits ?].
And so it might be one of those
things that you want to
keep in reserve, it's like, OK,
there is a problem here
and the team goes, I don't think
there's a problem here.
I don't understand why anyone's
having problems here.
Then you quit, because it's
kind of a bludgeon
actually on the team.
On one hand, if you have a good
agent team, they're going
hear it and go, oh my god, we
have a problem and immediately
try to fix it.
But it's awesome.
On the other hand, it's like,
well, do you need to do a
recording for every single
offer that we have?
That's something to
be known about, so
keep that in reserve.
I think that's pretty much it.
I have an exercise, but I
think [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
so I can turn that off.
Do you have any questions
while I
graph the data segments?
No?
OK.