PROFESSOR: Welcome in
this recitation.
So we're going to talk about
linear systems of equations.
So in the first question,
we are
given a system of equations.
X dot equals 6x plus 5y.
Y dot equals x plus 2y.
We're asked to write this
system in matrix form.
The second part asks us to
convert a differential
equation of second order, x dot
dot plus 8x dot plus 7x
equals to zero into matrix form,
basically into system of
ODEs, similar to
the first part.
In the third part of the
problem, we're asked to
interpret the population model,
x dot equals 2x minus
3y, y dot equals x minus y.
So here, x and y are modeling
either a prey or predator.
And you're asked to think about
the interpretation of
the system to determine
which of x or y is
the prey or the predator.
So why don't you take
a few minutes?
Think about these three
questions, and
I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So for the first question,
basically, we're asked to
write this system
in matrix form.
So we have xy derivative for
that left-hand side.
You need to write this in
the form of a matrix
multiplying x and y.
So here, we would
have 6, 5, 1, 2.
And that would be our system of
differential equations in
matrix form.
And what we would be solving
for would be the vector xy.
The second part of the problem,
we need to do the
opposite, go from the second
order differential equation
into matrix form.
So to do that, we introduced a
new variable, y equals x dot.
And from that point, we can
then write x dot, dot.
So if I'm going to just start
with what we know about the
equation, x dot, dot equals--
let me write it in a system
first before I do it in a
vector form.
We would write x dot, dot equals
minus 7x minus 8x dot.
But we introduced a new variable
x dot equals 2y.
So we have minus 7x minus 8y.
So now, the other equation we
need is the one that tells us
what this y is.
So we have x dot equals to y,
which is the new variable that
we introduced here.
And so we go from a second order
differential equation
into a system of two
differential equations that we
can write now in vectorial form
in matrix form, like we
did for the first part, as
x, x dot which is just y.
I'm just going to write this
like this, it's just from what
we defined, equals to, again,
x,y like we did previously.
And now we have to read off
our system to find the
coefficient of this matrix.
So x dot equals to y means that
there is zero coefficient
in front of the x, a 1
in front of the y.
X dot, dot equals minus 7x.
So we will have a minus 7
multiplying the x and minus 8
multiplying the y.
And so that's how we convert a
differential equation, so I
can order into the systems of
differential equations in
matrix form.
And this matrix would be
referred to the companion
matrix of these differential
equations.
OK, so that ends the
second part.
So now for the third question,
we're asked to interpret this
population dynamics system
of equation.
Minus 3y, y dot equals
x minus y.
So the question was, we
have two species.
Which one is the prey, which
one is the predator?
So how do we go about
figuring this out?
Let's look at how x dot varies
with y or basically variable x
varies with y.
Here, we can see that we have a
coefficient that is minus 3.
It is negative, which means that
when y increases, we have
a more and more negative x
dot, which means that the
value of x goes down.
So as the population y
increases, we have a decrease
of population x, which suggests
that y is a predator
eating up population x.
And if you look at the
equation for y, we
have x minus y.
And here, what we see is that
when x increases, the
population y then increases.
So that definitely confirms that
y is our predator that
basically increases by feeding
on the population x.
And as it feeds on population
x, y increases, which means
that here this term becomes more
and more negative, which
means x decreases in turn.
And these two terms could be
modeling, for example, here
just the growth of the
population, so
birth term of the prey.
And these minus y here could
be your small link, for
example, a death rate
of these predators.
And so we have x prey
and y predator.
So from this recitation, we
learned how to convert a
system of differential equations
to matrix form.
We learned how to convert a
second order differential
equation into also matrix form,
or basically system
differential equation
introducing notion of
companion matrix.
And we learned how to interpret
a system of
differential equations in terms
of what populations
could it be modeling or what
dynamics it could be modeling.
So that ends the recitation.