Problem one is 33-5.
It deals with a traveling
electromagnetic wave.
I told you earlier that I wasn't
joking that I know very
few equations in physics.
I can derive many from
the few that I know--
I know Mach's law equations.
Yes, I do--
certainly after this course.
I also know some of the
consequences of Mach's law
equations related to
travelling waves.
I will share those with you,
and if you remember those--
because it would be
rather silly to
derive them every timee--
then it's very easy to
write down traveling
electromagnetic waves.
With the vectors in the right
direction, and the amplitudes
all correct, and the plus
and minus signs correct.
The first thing that I happen to
remember is that that the E
vector is always perpendicular
to the B vector.
The second is that E, as well
as B, are both perpendicular
to the direction of
propagatation.
The third is that E and
B both are in phase at
all moments in time.
What does that mean?
It means if one reaches is the
maximum value, the other
reaches is a maximum value at
the same moment in time, but
at right angles, and if one
goes through 0, the other
goes through 0.
That's what it means--
always in phase.
B 0, which is the amplitude of
the magnetic field vector
equals E 0 divided by C when the
electromagnetic radiation
is in vaccuum.
Independent of electromagnetic
waves, what always holds is
that the pointing vector,
which tells you how much
energy per second flows per
square meter out of a
particular surface, and equals
E across B divided by mu 0.
This is energy per second
flowing through each square
meter, and I will
call that flux--
it's an energy flux.
What also always holds--
lambda equals c times the period
of one oscillation, and
don't confuse this
T with tesla.
This is also c divided by the
frequency of the radiation F.
What you will often see
introduced is a wave number k,
which has nothing to
do with the unit
vector in the c direction.
Nothing--
that k equals 2 pi divided by
lambda, and that has as a unit
1 over meter.
Since omega equals 2 pi times
the frequency F, it follows
immediately that omega divided
by k also is the speed of
light, the speed at which
electromagnetic radiation
propagates itself in vaccuum.
Now, if you can remember all
these things, that would help.
I happen to remember them.
We have here in problem one: we
have a frequency which is
4.0 times 10 to the thirteenth
hertz, so if follows
immediately that omega equals
2.5 times 10 to the fourteenth
radians per second.
It follows that lambda
equals 7.5 times 10
to the minus 6 meters--
75,000 angstroms, if
you like that unit.
This is infrared radiation.
We are also being told that the
direction of v is in plus
y, and we're being told that the
B vector oscillates in the
direction of x-- plus, minus,
plus, minus, plus, minus with
that angular velocity omega.
You know B 0, whatever
that is.
The B vector, if we write that
down in terms of x, y, and z,
and all moments in time, would
be the amplitude of the B
vector times cosine omega t--
this indicates the oscillatory
character--
minus k y in the x direction.
Here k means simply 2 pi
divided by lambda--
if you want to write for this
k 2 pi divided by lambda, be
my guest.
Let's look at these things:
this minus sign
is absolutely crucial.
If this were a plus sign, the
wave would not be propagating
in the plus y direction.
You can immediately check
that for yourself--
increase t by a teeny
weeny little bit.
If you want the cosine function
to be exactly the
same, you would have to increase
y by a teeny weeny
little bit, so that omega t
minus k y remains the same.
For this wave to propagate in
the plus y direction, it is
important that this sine here
and this sine here have an
opposite sign.
If they both have
the same sign--
minus minus or plus plus--
then the wave would run in
the minus y direction.
This x tells you simply that to
B vector oscillates in the
x direction-- sometimes
plus, sometimes minus.
Omega, you already know.
If you are interested in k, by
any chance, then I believe
that is 8.38 times 10 to
the 5 meters minus 1.
Now since you know B 0, you
also know E 0, because E 0
equals b 0 times c.
If we write down now the E
vector as a function of x, y,
z, and t, then we will get E 0
here, which you know, and then
I get exactly this same
argument, omega t minus k y.
Why?
Because I mentioned earlier that
E and B are always, at
any moment in time, exactly
in phase, and that's only
possible if this is
identical to that.
Now comes the question--
what is the direction that
I should put here?
What is the unit vector that
For that, I'm going
to make a drawing.
I'm going to make
a drawing of a
right-handed coordinate system.
Always make a drawing of a
A right-handed coordinate system
is a coordinate system
whereby x cross y equals z--
don't even think of ever doing
in another way, because you
get into deep trouble.
Let this be x, let this be y,
and then this would be z--
convince yourself that x cross
y would then be z.
Now pick any moment in time, and
let us assume that the B
vector is in this direction.
Of course, it's not only along
the x direction in this
direction, but since
it's a plane wave,
it's everywhere here--
the same magnitude and
the same direction.
This wave propagates
to the right.
A little later in time-- half a
period in time, if we assume
that this is the maximum value
B possible in this direction,
it will be pointing down.
With a quarter period in time,
it will go through 0, and they
will all go through 0 at
exactly the same time.
In what direction at this moment
in time should I now
point E so that--
and this is one of my
statements that I made earlier--
so that E cross B is in
the direction of B?
That means, in this case, is the
direction of positive y.
That should not give
you any problems--
the only way that you can do
that is when E is in the plus
z direction.
Convince yourself that only then
is E cross B in the plus
y direction.
That means that if we now have
to finish this vector notation
for E, we have to write it
down here in z roof,
and it's all done.
I can now ask the question--
suppose we wanted to move that
wave in the other direction,
not in plus y, but in minus y?
What would we have to change?
We could change this minus sign
to a plus sign, and this
minus sign to a plus sign.
What counts is--
actually, it's not so much that
this becomes a plus, but
that these two signs here and
here are the same, but that's
not enough.
If you want E cross B to be in
the opposite direction, you
also must either put a minus
sign here so that you get a
minus x, and leave the plus
here, or you put a minus sign
here in the minus E direction,
and leave the plus there.
Whenever you have to change
the direction of
propagatation, keep in mind that
it is not enough to only
change the signs inside the
brackets of the cosine terms,
but you also have to take into
account that E cross B must
change direction.