PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
This'll be the last video
where we do an
optimization problem.
And this one's a little bit
different than the other two.
So I'm going to give you
the problem now.
The problem is the following--
a cylinder has a fixed volume.
What ratio between radius and
height minimizes surface area?
Before I give you time to think
about that, I'm going to
remind of the two formulas
for volume and
surface area of a cylinder.
So volume of a cylinder
is pi r squared h.
And surface area is 2 pi
r squared plus 2 pi rh.
So with that information, I'll
give you some time to work on
this problem and then
I'll be back.
Welcome back.
OK, what we're doing, again,
is we're trying to solve an
optimization problem.
And so we know now the
constraint equation, it's a
little different than the other
situations because the
constraint equation is just
we're told that there's a
fixed volume but we're
not told what it is.
That actually will not change
how we work on this problem,
but it does change the kind of
answer I can ask of you.
And notice the answer I ask is
not about exact values for
radius and height, but what
ratio between them will
minimize surface area.
So this is, you'll see at
the end, things will
look a little different.
But ultimately we still have our
optimizing equation, which
is surface area.
And we still have
our constraint
equation, which is volume.
So again, we're going to
do what we always do.
We're going to take our
optimization equation and use
our constraint equation to get
rid of a variable so that we
can write the right hand side
here in terms of one variable.
Let me point out V is
not a variable here.
V is a constant because
the volume is fixed.
So when you see V, it's
not a variable.
It's a constant.
So what do I do?
Let me write, first, let me
write surface area in terms of
just a function of r.
And I'm going to do something
a little tricky which maybe
you didn't think of doing, but
ultimately you should end up
with the same answer once
you've simplified.
Notice that this term
has a pi rh.
This term also has a pi rh.
In fact, I can rewrite the
volume equation as V over r is
equal to pi rh.
So what I'm going to do is
take that pi rh here and
replace it by a V over r.
Now again, you might
not have done this.
You should ultimately get the
same answer that I do when
we're finished.
And even sooner, probably
some simplification
would be the same.
The only thing I've done here is
I've simplified right away.
So by looking at the problem and
kind of pulling back from
the problem I see, oh, there's
something here that looks
exactly like something
over here.
So I just want to
point that out.
That it's not wrong to just
substitute for h, but it's
maybe a little faster.
So now the new surface area
equation becomes 2 pi r
squared plus 2V over r.
So now we have everything in
terms of r, because again, V
is a constant.
Now let me point out
what happens.
When r goes to infinity this
term goes to 0, but this term
goes to infinity.
So as r gets very large
service area is
getting very large.
As r goes to 0 this term
goes to 0, but this
term goes to infinity.
V is fixed, and when r goes
to 0 this term blows up.
So when r gets as small as we
allow or as large as we allow,
either way, surface area is
going to be getting big.
So where this, where surface
area has a derivative with
respect to radius it's going
to have to be a minimum.
So we don't have to
check anymore.
Now we've checked sort of the
what's happening towards the
boundary at the extreme
values of r.
So now we can, now we can
actually solve the problem.
Well, what do we do?
We're using our optimization
equation.
We want to take a derivative and
set it equal to 0 and find
what value for r gives that.
But again, let me point out one
more time that in the end
I'm asking for a ratio between
radius and height.
So I'm not going to get all
the way to where I have r
equals something.
You'll see I'm going to
do another trick.
But let me first take the
derivative I need.
Surface area prime, this is
derivative with respect to r.
I have 2 pi r squared.
That derivative with respect
to r is 4 pi r.
And this derivative with respect
to r, I'm going to
keep the 2V, and the denominator
1 over r, its
derivative is negative
1 over r squared.
So I'm going to have 4 pi r for
the first term and then
minus 2V over r squared.
If I set this equal to 0, the
derivative equal to 0 and
solve, I get to 2V over r
squared is equal to 4 pi r,
which is the same as--
going to put it on this side--
r cubed is equal to 2 pi over
V. Let's just check.
If I multiply both sides by
r squared, divide by 4 pi.
Oh, I did it backwards.
I think it should actually be
pi over 2V. Let me double
check that all my signs
are correct.
That's r cubed, divide by 4 pi,
I should get pi over 2V. I
should not.
I've been told from the audience
I made a mistake.
Sometimes you'll see when you're
at the board and on
video, scary things
can happen.
2V--
oh.
Multiply through by
r, I get r cubed.
Oh, I have the 2V in
the numerator.
I apologize.
The 2V is in the numerator,
the 4 pi is in the
denominator.
So I get V over 2 pi.
Does that look better,
audience?
The audience tells me
that looks better.
OK.
So here I am.
I have r cubed is equal
to V over 2 pi.
Now, if I wanted to I could
take the cube root of both
sides and get r explicitly
in terms of V and 2 pi.
V is a constant, pi is a
constant, I would be done.
But I didn't ask for
what r actually is.
I asked for a ratio.
So let's make this
problem simpler.
All I need in the end
is r divided by h.
Let's go back to a formula we
have and see if we can figure
out a way to get
r divided by h.
Look at this formula for
V. It has an r squared
and it has an h.
So if I divide by r squared h on
this side, I'll end up with
an r over h.
Hopefully you buy that.
I'm going to even
write it out.
I'm going to take r cubed and
divide it by r squared h.
That in the end, is r over h.
Let's go back here look
at what that equals.
r squared h is equal
to V over pi.
Right?
r squared h is equal
to V over pi.
So I can divide this side by r
squared h and divide this side
by V over pi and it's
the same thing.
Which is, by the way, the same
thing as multiplying by pi
over V. Right?
So I can multiply this side by
pi over V, and what do I get?
I get the V's divide out, the
pi's divided by, divide out,
and I get 1/2.
So the result is that the
ratio between radius and
height should be 1 to 2.
Let me one more time explain
what we were doing here.
In the end, the answer, the
question just asks, what is
the ratio between radius
and height that
minimizes surface area?
And I had an r cubed, I wanted
to get r divided by h.
So I divided by two r's--
I divided by r squared--
and then h again.
But r squared h is V over pi, so
if I divide by r squared h
I'm dividing by V over pi.
So I can do on the right hand
side the same thing that I do
on the left--
I divided by V over pi, which
is multiplying by pi over V.
The pi's divide out, the
V's divide out, and
I'm left with 1/2.
And so this was an optimization
problem where the
constraint equation did not have
a number in it, but it
did have, it did have
a fixed constant.
So I couldn't ask you for an
exact value for the radius and
an exact value for the height,
but I could ask you for how
they relate.
And that's ultimately
what I did.
And I think that's
where we'll stop.