PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So today we'd like to tackle a
problem in Fourier series.
And specifically, we're just
going to compute the Fourier
series for a simple function.
So the function we're interested
in is f of t, which
we're told is periodic
with period 2pi.
F of t is 1 from minus pi
to 0, and then it's
minus 1 from 0 to pi.
So first off, we're interested
in sketching f of t.
Secondly, we'd like to compute
the Fourier series for f of t.
And then thirdly, we'd like to
sketch the first non-0 term of
the Fourier series.
And we can specifically sketch
this single term
on top of f of t.
So I'll let you think about this
problem for now, and I'll
be back in a moment.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So let's take a look at
sketching f of t.
So for part a, we have
our axes, t.
And we're told f of t within
some interval.
So we might as well plot f
of t on that interval.
So minus pi, pi and 0, we
know that f of t is 1
from minus pi to 0.
We're also told that it's
minus 1 from 0 to pi.
And now to fill in the blanks or
to complete the picture of
f, we're told that it
has a period of 2pi.
So note that they've told us
what f looks like over the
range of minus pi to pi, which
is the length of 2pi.
So basically what we can do is
we can use this as a stamp and
just pick up this entire
picture, shift it over one
period 2pi, and just thinking of
this picture in stamping it
in multiple places.
So just filling this in it's
going to look like a square
wave, which jumps between
minus 1 and 1 at every
multiple of pi.
So this concludes part a.
For part b, which is the real
meat of the problem, we're
interested in computing a
Fourier series for f of t.
Now, we can always write down
a Fourier series for any
periodic function.
And specifically in this case,
for part b, the periodic
function we're interested
in has period 2pi.
So for the class notes,
we've identified L
with half the period.
So in this case, L is
2pi divided by 2,
which gives us pi.
And just to recall what a
Fourier series is, what we do
is we try and take our function
f of t and write it
down as a summation of
sines and cosines.
So in this case for function f
of t, which is 2pi periodic,
it's going to look something
like this.
It's going to a of 0 plus
sum from n equals 1.
And there's going to be
infinitely many terms, but in
this case we have a of
n times cosine of nt.
And it's nt here because
we have period 2pi.
Plus bn sin nt.
So this is the general form.
And when asked to compute the
Fourier series of a function,
the main difficulty is
to compute these
coefficients an and bn.
However, that essentially
boils down to
working out some integrals.
So let's take a look
at what a of 0 is.
So the formula for
a0 is 1 over 2L.
So in this case, it's 1 over
2pi, times the integral over 1
period of the function,
from minus pi to pi,
of just f of t.
So notice how a0 is just the
average of the function.
So if we take a look at the
function f of t, f of t spends
exactly half of its time
at 1 and half of its
time at minus 1.
So immediately we could guess
that the average value of f of
t is going to be 0.
If you wanted to work it out
specifically, we would have 1
over 2pi minus pi to 0, f of t
takes on the value of plus 1.
And then from 0 to pi, f of t
takes on the value of minus 1.
So we would end up getting
pi minus pi, which is 0.
For an, the formula is 1
over half the period.
So note how a of 0 is
just a special case.
We always have the full period
in a0, but in an and bn, the
factor that divides the integral
is always going to be
half the period times minus pi
to pi f of t cosine nt dt.
And I should point out that,
in general, we only need to
integrate over one period
of the function.
So in some sense there's
nothing special about
minus pi and pi.
It's just very often these
are the easiest bounds of
integration to integrate over.
But in practice, we could have
used 0 to 2pi or any other
interval, as long as
it's exactly one
period of the function.
So in this case, I'd just like
to take a look at the
symmetry of f of t.
And we note that the function
f of t is actually odd about
the origin.
So if f of t is odd and cosine t
is an even function, then an
odd times an even function is
going to be an odd function.
And when you integrate an odd
function from minus any value
to the same positive value, so
in this case minus pi to pi,
we always get 0.
So this is actually 0, because
we're integrating an odd
function over a symmetric
interval.
So lastly, we have the values
of bn, which are 1 over pi
minus pi to pi f of
t of sine nt dt.
And if we were to look at just
the symmetry argument again, f
of t is an odd function, sine
t is an odd function, an odd
times an odd function
is an even function.
When you integrate an even
function over a symmetric
bound, you will essentially
get twice the value of the
integral from 0 to one
of the bounds.
So b of n in this case doesn't
vanish, which means we
actually have to do some work.
So what we do?
Well, we know the value of f
of t on two intervals, so
we're just going to have to
work out each interval.
Minus pi is 0, it takes
on the value of 1.
So we have sine nt.
And then from 0 to pi, f of t
takes on the value of minus 1
sine nt dt.
And you'll note that
these integrals are
actually the same.
So this is negative 2 over pi
zero to pi sine nt dt, which
if we integrate is negative 1
over n cosine nt evaluated
between 0 and pi.
So if I work this out, we get
minus and a minus, minus 1
over n cosine n pi
plus 1 over n.
So note that cosine
of 0 is just 1.
And now if we take a look at
cosine n pi, we see that
cosine n pi oscillates between
minus 1 and 1.
So cosine of pi is negative 1,
cosine of 2pi is 1, cosine of
3pi is minus 1.
So this term right here is
actually negative 1 to the n.
So we have 2 over n pi 1 minus
negative 1 to the n.
And now if we just plug in some
values of b of 1, b of 2,
b of 3, b of 4, we can see what
pattern merges in the bs.
So b of 1, if I plug in 1,
I get 1 minus negative 1.
It's going to be 2.
So I get minus 4 over pi.
b of 2 it's going to
be 1 minus minus 1
squared is just 1.
So this vanishes.
b of 3 is going to be 1 minus
minus 1 cubed, which is
negative 1.
So again, we get negative
4 over 3pi.
b of 4 is going to be 0.
So it's sometimes useful the
write out what the Fourier
series looks like.
So I'll just write it
out right here.
So we have f of t is going to
be negative 4 over pi times
sine of t plus 1/3 sine of
3t plus 1/5 sine of 5t
plus dot, dot, dot.
So this concludes part b.
And now lastly, for part c,
we're asked to sketch what
does the first Fourier
term look like.
So in this case, the first
Fourier term is going to be
negative 4 over pi
times sine t.
So I'm going to go back to
our diagram from part a.
So let's go back to our
diagram from part a.
Now what is minus 4 over
pi sine t look like?
Well, it's a sine wave that has
exactly period 2pi, and
it's going to line up exactly
with this square wave. In
addition, minus 4 over pi is
just slightly larger than 1.
So we're going to end up with
sin, which peaks just slightly
above 1 and slightly below 1.
It's going to go through 0, and
it's going to go through
each multiple of pi.
So it might look something
like this.
So this is the first Fourier
term in the series.
And notice how this first
Fourier term is actually
pretty good approximation to the
square wave, considering
it's just one term
in a series.
As we add more terms in the
series, we're going to get
something which looks
closer and closer to
a square wave function.
So I'd just like to
quickly recap.
When computing the Fourier
series for a periodic
function, the first useful thing
to do is just write down
the formula for a Fourier
series, and then write down
the formulas for the
coefficients
of the Fourier series.
So write down the formulas
for a0 an, bn.
When computing a0, you can often
just look at the average
of the function.
When computing an and bn, it's
also useful look at the
symmetry of your function.
And if it's either even or odd
symmetric then typically,
either all the ans or all
the bns will vanish.
And then when you work at the
integrals, you can then
reconstruct the Fourier
series.
So I would like to conclude
here, and I'll
see you next time.