DAVID SHIROKOFF: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So today we're going to tackle a
problem in complex matrices.
And specifically, we're going
to look at diagonalizing a
complex matrix.
So given this matrix A, we're
asked to find its eigenvalue
matrix lambda, and its
eigenvector matrix S.
And one thing to note about this
matrix A is that if we
take its conjugate transpose,
it's actually equal to itself.
So in Professor Strang's book,
he combines this notation to
be superscript H to mean
conjugate transpose.
So if you were to take the
transpose of this matrix and
then conjugate all the elements,
you would find that
A equals its conjugate
transpose, and we call this
property Hermitian.
So I'll let you think about this
for a moment and I'll be
back in a second.
OK, welcome back.
So what's the first step in
computing the eigenvectors and
eigenvalues of the matrix
is to take a look at the
characteristic equation.
So specifically, we take det
of A minus lambda i.
And quite possibly, the only
thing new with this problem is
that the entries of the
matrix A are complex.
Now, you may have already seen
that lambda's being complex,
but we're going to work
this out explicitly.
So if I take the determinant, we
get det of 2 minus lambda,
3 minus lambda, we have
1 minus i, 1 plus i.
We want to set this to 0.
This then gives us a polynomial
for lambda.
1 plus i, 1 minus i,
set it equal to 0.
We can expand out this term.
You get 6 minus 5 lambda
plus lambda squared.
These two terms you'll
note are complex
conjugates of each other.
This tends to make
things simple.
So we have minus 1 minus i
squared is going to give us 2.
Because they're differences of
squares, the cross terms
involving i cancel, and we get
the characteristic equation.
Lambda squared minus 5 lambda
plus 4 equals 0.
And specifically, we can
factorize this equation.
We see that there's roots of
minus 1, or factorizes into
factors of lambda -1 and lambda
-4, which then give us
roots of lambda is 1
and lambda is 4.
So when one curious point to
note is that the eigenvalues
are real in this case.
1 and 4 are real, whereas the
matrix that we started with
was complex.
And this is a general property
of Hermitian matrices.
So even though they might be
complex matrices, Hermitian
matrices always have
real eigenvalues.
So this is the first step when
asked to diagonalize a matrix.
The second step is to find
the eigenvectors.
And to do that what we have to
do is we have to look at the
cases for lambda equals 1 and
lambda is equal 4 separately.
So let's first look at the case
of lambda is equal to 1.
And specifically, we're going
to be looking for a vector
such that A minus lambda i
times the vector v is 0.
And if we've done things
properly, this matrix A minus
lambda i should be singular.
So if we take A minus lambda
i, we're going to get 1 1
minus i, 1 plus i
3 minus 1 is 2.
And I'll write out components
of v, which are v1 and v2.
And we want this to be 0.
And you'll note that it's almost
always the case that
when we work out A minus lambda
i, the second row is
going to be a constant multiple
of the first row.
And this must be the case
because these two rows must be
linearly dependent on each other
for the matrix A minus
lambda i to be singular.
So if you look at this you might
think that these two
rows aren't necessarily
linearly independent.
But the point is that there's
complex numbers involved.
And indeed, actually if we were
to multiply this first
row by 1 plus lambda, we would
get 1 plus lambda and 2.
And you note that that's
exactly the second row.
So this second row is actually
1 plus lambda
times the first row.
So these rows are actually
linearly
dependent on each other.
So what values of v1
and v2 can we take?
Well we just need to make this
top row multiplied by v1 and
v2 equal to 0.
And then because the second row
is a constant multiple of
the first row, we're
automatically guaranteed that
the second equation holds.
So just by looking at it, I'm
going to take v1 is equal to 1
minus i, and v2 is negative 1.
So we see that 1 times 1 minus
i minus 1 times 1 minus i is
going to give us 0.
So this is one solution.
And of course, we can take any
constant multiple times this
eigenvector, and that's also
going to be an eigenvector.
So I'll just write this out.
1 minus i, minus 1 is the
eigenvector for lambda is
equal to 1.
For lambda is equal to 4, again,
A minus lambda i, is
going to give us negative 2, 1
minus i, 1 plus i, 3 minus
lambda's going to be minus 1.
And I'll call this
vector u1 and u2.
And again, we want u1
and u2 equal to 0--
or sorry, the matrix
multiplied by u1,
u2 is equal to 0.
And just by looking at this
again, we see that the second
row is actually a constant
multiple of the first row.
For example, if we were to
multiply this row by negative
2, and this row by 1 plus i,
we would see that they're
constant multiples
of each other.
So I can take u to be, for
example, 1, and 1 plus i.
How did I get this?
Well I just looked at the second
equation because it's a
little simpler, and I said well
if I have 1 plus I here,
I can just say multiply
it by 1.
And then minus 1 times 1
plus I when I add them
up is going to vanish.
So this is how I get
the second one.
Now there's something curious
going on, and this is going to
be another property of
Hermitian matrices.
But if you actually take a look
at this eigenvector, it
will be orthogonal to this
eigenvector when we conjugate
the elements and dot the
two vectors together.
So this is another very special
property of complex
Hermitian matrices.
OK, so the last step now is to
construct these matrices
lambda and S. Now we already
know what lambda is because
it's the diagonal matrix with
the eigenvalues 1 and 4.
So we have 1 0, 0 and 4.
Now I'm going to do something
special for S. I've noted that
these two vectors u and v are
orthogonal to each other.
So what do I mean
by orthogonal?
Specifically, if I were to take
v conjugate transpose and
multiply it by u, we would end
up getting 1 plus i minus 1.
This would be v conjugate
transpose.
1, 1 plus i, and we see
that when we multiply
these out we get 0.
So when we have orthogonal
eigenvectors, there's a trick
that we can do to build up this
matrix S and S inverse.
What we can do is we can
normalize u and v. So
specifically, we can take any
constant multiple of u and v,
and it's still going to
be an eigenvector.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to take u and v and
multiply them by their length.
So for example u, the
amplitude of its top
component is 1.
The amplitude of its bottom
component is 2.
So notice that the modulus
of the complex
number 1 plus I is 2.
So we have--
sorry, it's root 2, the complex
modulus is root 2.
So the amplitude of the entire
vector is root 3.
It's 1 plus 2 squared quantity
squared rooted,
so it's root 3.
So what we can do is we can
build up this matrix S using a
normalization factor
of 1 over root 3.
And I'm going to take the first
column is the first
eigenvector that corresponds
to eigenvalue 1.
And then the second column is
the second eigenvector which
corresponds value 4.
And the reason I put in this
root 3 here is to make this
column unit length 1, and this
column unit length 1.
And the reason I do this is
because now this matrix S,
it's possible to check that
this matrix S is actually
unitary, which means that its
inverse is actually just equal
to it's conjugate transpose.
So this is a very special
property of the eigenvectors
of a Hermitian matrix.
And then lastly, I'm just
going to write down the
diagonalization of A. So if I
have A, because I have its
eigenvector matrix S, and its
eigenvalue matrix lambda, it's
possible to decompose
A into a product
of S lambda, S inverse.
And because S is unitary, its
inverse is actually its
conjugate transpose.
So just to put the pieces
together, we have A is equal
to S, which is 1 over root 3.
1 minus i, minus 1, 1, 1 plus i
times the diagonal matrix 1
0, 0 4 times S inverse,
which is going to be
its conjugate transpose.
So what I do is I conjugate
each element, so 1 minus i
becomes 1 plus i
and vice versa.
And then I take the transpose.
So I get 1 plus i.
Transposing swaps the
minus 1 and 1.
And at the end of the day, I
get S inverse is just this
matrix here.
And if you were to multiply
these matrices out, you would
see it you actually
do recover A.
So just to summarize quickly,
even though we were given a
complex matrix A, the process
to diagonalize A is the same
as what we've seen before.
The first step is to find the
characteristic equation and
the eigenvalues.
And then the second step is to
find the eigenvectors, and you
do this in the same procedure.
But in general, the eigenvectors
can be complex.
And for this very special case,
when A is Hermitian, the
eigenvalues are real, and the
eigenvectors are orthogonal to
each other.
So I think I'll conclude here,
and I'll see you next time.