PROFESSOR: Welcome to this
recitation on pure resonance.
So here we're given an operator
pd equals d squared
plus 4i, where d is the
differential operator and i is
the identity operator.
And you're asked to consider the
equation pd applied to x
equals f0 cos omega t, where
f0 is a constant.
So the first question is what
is the natural frequency of
the system.
The second one is to use the
exponential response formula
to solve for pd x equals
f0 cos omega t.
And here you need to be careful
and do it for both
cases omega equal to 2 and omega
equals not equal to 2.
And the last question is just
to sketch the graph for the
response of this system pd
x equals cos 2t, with the
initial conditions x of 0 and
x dot of 0 equals to 0,
basically, rest initial
conditions.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a few minutes, and
work through this problem.
Welcome back.
So first what is the natural
frequency of this system?
So let's just rewrite
our system here.
This is the left-hand side.
So basically, this just gives us
an x dot dot plus 4x on the
left-hand side.
So the system that we're solving
is simply x dot dot
plus 4x equals f0 cos omega t.
So the first question asks us
for the natural frequency of
this system.
The natural frequency of this
system can be found regardless
of what you have the right-hand
side, just by
looking at the characteristic
polynomial of your equation.
The characteristic polynomial
here would be s
squared plus 4.
When this characteristic
polynomial is equal to 0, we
can solve for s and find what
are the natural frequencies of
the system, if basically we get
complex solutions, which
is the case here.
Gives us a square
equal minus 4.
So s equals plus or minus i2.
So the natural frequency of
our system would be omega
equals 2, because we only
consider frequencies that are
positive here.
Second part.
Now, we're asked to look at
the full system with the
forcing on the right-hand
side.
And using the exponential
response formula, find one
solution to this system.
So here we're talking about a
particular solution with the
exponential response formula.
So what does the ERF tell us?
The ERF, if you recall here, the
base of it for this system
for example, is the fact that
cosine is the real part of the
exponential i omega t.
So we can rewrite this whole
equation as x dot dot plus 4x
equals f0 exponential
i omega t.
And we would get then a
particular solution, if I
ignore any particular value of
omega at this point, which
would have the form of the
amplitude that we have on the
right-hand side at 0,
exponential omega t, which is
basically our forcing, over the
characteristic polynomial
of the equation.
So s squared plus 4, evaluated
at the frequence here that
would appear at the forcing in
the exponential form, so with
the i omega t.
So here you can see right away
that we would have a problem.
If you were using this formula,
if i omega t was a
pole or basically a 0, to this
characteristic polynomial.
And so that's why you were asked
to be careful with the
value of omega equals to
2 or not equal to 2.
So here let's consider omega not
equal to 2, so that I can
actually write down 1 over p i
omega, because we know that p
i2 is equal to 0.
So if omega is not equal to 2,
were out of the danger zone.
And from this point, we can
just basically plug in our
values, i omega t, and p i omega
would just give us 4
minus omega squared.
So here again, that omega
equals 2 danger zone
approaches, where we would be
dividing by 0 if we didn't
take the constraint omega
not equal to 0.
So this is the complex form of
this particular solution.
But we're dealing with a real
value problem, so we want to
take the real part of this to
have the solution to the
problem we were given.
And so that would just give us
f0 4 minus omega squared
cosine omega t.
So now let's take the case
omega equals to 2.
OK So what happens?
If omega equals to 2, this
formula that you're given
fails, and you need to seek
for the derivative of the
characteristic polynomial.
And we basically have
2i equals to 2.
So what about p prime of 2i?
So p prime of s is simply 2s.
So if we evaluate p prime at 2i,
we simply have 4i, which
is not equal to 0.
So at this point we can use
the resonant exponential
response formula that you saw.
Just change my chalk.
We're here.
We would again, same trick, the
cosine is just the real
part of the exponential.
So we can use this formula.
And we have now to introduce a
t f0 exponential i omega t,
because we're solving here for
the complex value equation.
And now we can divide by the
p prime evaluated at
2i, which is 4i.
And so basically, I
can end up with a
minus i at the numerator.
So to take now the real value
solution, we need again to
take the real part of zp.
So here now we have an i, so
we need to be careful.
We're going to have
solution in sine.
So let me just write
down what know.
t f0 over 4.
This with the Euler formula
would be cosine plus i sine.
The i sine would be multiplying
this i, the 2
minus would cancel out.
And so we would end up with
sine omega t, t f0 over 4.
And this would then give
us the solution.
And here, note that I actually
chose the value omega equals
to 2, so we can even
be more explicit.
For this case, we actually
have omega equals to 2t.
So the last part of the problem
was to sketch the
solution for the initial
conditions, x of 0 or x dot of
0 equal to 0, so the rest
initial conditions.
So here are two ways
to proceed.
The long way would be to seek
the solution to the
homogeneous equation without
the right-hand side, the
forcing cosine, introduced two
constants of integration, and
then seek these constants
of integration
on the general solution.
And you would find that these
two constants of integration
would be 0 with these
initial conditions.
The other fast way to test your
particular solution and
verify that it actually does
satisfy the initial conditions
that you were given, and so you
can then write away the
solution as being
simply sine 2t.
Here you can see that at 0, we
would have basically a 0.
And then if you do a
differentiation, you just need
to be careful here, because you
have a product function,
and you end up also with a 0.
So this actually is our general
solution for this
particular initial condition,
And to sketch
this, we can grow.
So here if I just pick f0 equal
to 1, I'm just going to
do t/4 for the envelopes.
At t equals 0, we
start with 0.
And we know that we're going to
have the first extrema at
p/4 and the first 0 at pi/2.
And so basically, we end up
with something like that.
So basically, it's sine of
circular frequency 2, and with
an envelope prescribed by t/4.
Or if we had another value
at 0, it would be f0 t/4.
So the oscillation is ongoing as
t goes to infinity with an
envelope that diverges
to infinity.
So this is basically a solution
that would not be
convergent to 0.
So this ends this recitation.
And before I finish, I just
want to point out that the
fact that it diverges is due
to the fact that we are
forcing this system very close
to its natural frequency.
And so this is a typical
phenomenon that you can
associate with a resonance,
because we're basically
forcing a system close to
its natural frequency.
So it's having this huge
amplification in the response.
And that's what these increasing
envelopes mean.
So this ends this recitation.
And the key here was to realize
how to use your
exponential response formula,
how to move on to use the
resonance exponential response
formula by testing for the
first order derivative.
And if that test failed,
you would be
going to higher orders.
And then, given an initial
condition, how to basically
sketch the function and have a
physical understanding of what
the resonance means.
That ends this recitation.