I will now enter
problem eight.
But before I enter problem
eight, I want to evaluate with
you what actually a
solenoid is doing.
And I hope I will convince you,
with two problems that I
will do in a row, that
you should never
abandon Faraday's Law.
Never amend it.
It's unwise, it's unnecessary,
it is risky and it only leads
to wrong and incorrect
answers.
It may work, once in a blue
moon because you happen to
know the answer.
But it's conceptually,
completely the
wrong way to think.
Whenever you have a known
conservative field,
Kirchhoff's law does not hold.
The one that says that the
integral of E dot dl closed
loop integral is zero,
does not hold.
Let's first evaluate how a
solenoid works, because we're
going to need that.
Suppose we have some resistor
here and we had
some battery here.
And this solenoid
had a length, l.
So this is a solenoid.
It has N, windings.
And let us assume that these
are circular, close to
circular windings, which have
surface area pi r squared.
The first question that I want
to answer is, what is the
magnetic field inside
the solenoid.
There will be a current
flowing, which
will change with time.
Because this solenoid has the
ability to influence the
increase in current.
In this case, when I
throw a switch, the
current will increase.
The solenoid will try
to hold that down.
We call that Lenz's law.
But at any moment in time that
I have a current I(t) flowing
in the circuit, through
the solenoid.
Let's assume that might B field
is pointing upwards, it
depends on the helicity
of the coil.
And that's assume that the B
field is only finite and
constant inside the solenoid.
Zero outside here, zero outside
there, and even zero
outside there, which is
a little bit of an
approximation.
So we only assume that the
B field is inside.
I now forget, for the time
being, Faraday's law.
I'm going to calculate
the B field inside.
And for that, I choose
Ampere's law.
The side y.
This also y.
And the length here
is very large.
If there's any magnetic field
here, it would be
perpendicular to the side.
Certainly inside the
solenoid it's
perpendicular to the side.
And so the dot product,
B.dl, would vanish.
So I have the closed loop
integral of B.dl equals mu
zero times I thru.
There's no displacement current
if I choose this as my
flat surface.
There's no changing electric
field going
through this surface.
The B field is only defined
inside the solenoids.
B.dl right here is zero.
There is no B field outside.
At least if I choose this far
enough away, the B field here
will be zero.
And if there's any B field here,
it will be perpendicular
so I can ignore that.
So what do I get when I make
this closed loop integral,
going around clockwise in
the direction of B?
I find that B times y equals mu
zero times I. Bu now, this
is a soap film, flat
soap film.
And the current penetrates
several times
through this soap film.
How many times does
it penetrate
through this soap film?
Y divided by l times N. This is
the number of times that it
pokes through.
I have to take that into account
in Ampere's law.
I lose my y, and I find the
result that you have seen
before, that the magnetic fields
in a solenoid equals mu
zero times I times
N divided by l.
And notice, it's independent of
the cross sectional area of
the solenoid, little r.
And it is also independent
of y.
It better be independent of y,
because Maxwell couldn't care
less about how long
you choose this.
So far so good.
We now have the magnetic field
inside the solenoid.
Now, I want to calculate, in
anticipation of Faraday's law,
a closed loop integral E.dl .
I know I'm going to need, sooner
or later, when I deal
with solenoids, this term, d/dt
times B.dA --I will ram
it down your throat
once more.--
This is a closed loop.
And this is an open surface
attached to that loop.
Now if you look at this circuit,
then the closed loop
that I will choose is the loop
that goes through the wires.
I crawl inside the wire of the
self inductance, I come out
here, I go through here,
and I enter up here.
That is my closed loop.
That is my closed group
integral E.dl
And I always go around in the
direction of the current.
That's my convention that avoids
that I get unnecessary
minus signs where I
don't want them.
But now, you have to choose a
surface which is attached to
this closed loop.
And that is very hard
to imagine.
And the way I normally do this
when I lecture 802, I did this
whole circuit in soap.
And when I did this is soap, you
get a soap film here, but
you get a very peculiar
staircase
soap film in the solenoid.
The solenoid, the surface of
the soap film is like the
surface of the staircase of a
spiral staircase that goes up.
I have a soap film here,
a soap film there.
And the soap film rotates
around, keeps going up and up
and up and up and up.
Not unlike this situation
here.
Not unlike that.
The boundary of the solenoid
is this line.
And the surface, which
is this soap film, is
the staircase itself.
Maybe we can look at
it from above.
You can see it again
a little better.
It is a very hard to
understand surface.
But what counts is, and what
is important, that the
magnetic field pokes
n time through
this staircase surface.
And therefore, when I calculate
this term, the
magnetic field, which I will
ignore here, I will assume
that even though there's a
current flowing here, that the
magnetic flux going through
this film is almost
negligible.
But here, it's very strong,
the magnetic field.
I now have to take into account,
that is magnetic
field goes n times through
this open surface.
And so what now is this term?
Well, the integral of B.dA, over
that open surface, that
staircase surface.
First of all, it is B itself.
So that is mu zero
times I times N
divided by l, as a start.
But now, I have to multiply it
by the cross sectional area of
each one of those loops.
And in a somewhat simplified
way, am I thinking now of it
as having N of these
circular loops.
Which of course is not
exactly accurate.
But it's a very good
approximation for this
staircase type surface
that moves up.
So now I must multiply it by N,
so I get an N square here.
And I know have the
current I thru.
Which pokes through N times.
And here is my pi r squared.
I already have the I, sorry.
This is B. I must multiple
B by N, that
gives me a N squared.
And I must multiply it by the
area, which is pi r squared.
That is no extra I here.
This term is called the
self inductance.
It's just a name, it's
purely geometry.
It is nothing else.
So this is simply called L times
I. And it is no surprise
that L is proportional
to N squared.
One N comes in when you
calculate the magnetic field.
That's proportional with N. And
the other N comes in when
you recognize that the
current pokes N times
through that surface.
OK, so this is the magnetic
flux going
through my open surface.
And if you ever need the time
derivative, well then you
would get L dI dt.
And of course you have here,
this minus sign.
If your solenoids, were a
toroidal system, with radius r
zero, then this L simply
became 2 pi r zero.
And if you look at page 976 of
your book, that's exactly what
you find for a toroidal
surface.
Now that we have prepared this,
and we keep in mind that
the open surface integral
B.dA equals LI.
We can now tackle, easily,
problem number eight.
Which is the last problem that
I will do today from the
assignment.
It's not the last problem that
I will do today, but the last
from the assignment.
Plus minus.
The switch as one.
Switch as two.
Resistance, R. This point
is called a, this
point is called b.
Self inductance, which
we now understand.
We call a solenoid a
self inductance.
The R was 400 Ohms and the L has
an SI value of 0.2, which
is units of Henry.
I close S1.
The current will increase
through this circuits, nothing
through here.
L will oppose the current, but
ultimately L can no longer
fight the current.
And that is going to be a
current flowing through here.
And E which is the E mf of
the battery, through
Ohm's Law equals IR.
And so I, you can easily
calculate, equals 0.3 Amperes.
At that moment, I close
S1 one and I open S2.
And let's assume I can do
that at the same time.
So my circuit now, looks
rather different.
I know have a circuit
that looks like so.
R, L, 400, 0.2.
And I have at one particular
moment in time, and the
current changes with time,
the current will decrease
in time, I of t.
There is an electric field
only in the resistor.
There is no electric field
in the self inductance.
The self inductance is made
of super conducting wire.
No electric field in here.
We call this point a.
We call this point b.
And we call this point c.
And at time, t equals zero,
we have 0.3 amperes.
L is opposing the decay
of the current.
Of course, it will decay
because there is heat
dissipation in the resistor.
But L has the ability
to oppose that.
It slows the decay down.
I use Faraday's law, which says
an induced E m f is the
closed loop integral of E.dl,
and that equals minus d / dt
times the integral over the
open surface B.dA .
Is an open surface and through
here is that peculiar
staircase surface.
Whenever I go around, I told
you earlier, I always
disciplined myself to always go
around in the direction of
the surface.
Then I never get into trouble
with positive
plus and minus signs.
I already know, by the way, that
is current is decreasing.
So clearly what the self
inductance will do, it will
try to keep the current going
in this direction.
And so it will try to introduce
an E induced in this
direction to keep the
current going.
It fights the decay
of the current.
So I've been going
around this way.
I start at point a.
Closed loop integral of E.dl,
and I'm going to cut it in
three sections.
In going from a to b, through
the resistor, E.dl plus in
going from b through c through
the self inductor, I just put
an L here, which is my
short hand notation.
Plus back from say, c to
a through the wire.
And that now equals
minus d/dt B.dA .
And this value, we already
know, equals L times I.
What is the integral a to b of
E.dl through the resistor.
There's an E field in this
direction, it is
positive, and it is IR.
At that moment in time,
but I'll drop that t.
What is the integral E.dl
through self inductor?
It's obviously zero.
Because the self inductor is
made of super conducting wire.
There is no electric field
inside the self inductor.
So this is zero.
Here again, there is
no electric field.
And so that's also zero.
And so what do I get?
I get IR equals minus
d/dt times LI.
And so, I want to stress, by the
way, that Kirchhoff's law
is for the birds.
The closed loop integral going
around all the way back to
point a, is not zero.
It is minus L dI / dt.
Know Kirchhoff's law, don't
let anyone mislead you or
persuade you.
So I get IR equals minus L
dI/dt, I bring the L dI/dt
inside, there's nothing
wrong with that.
Plus L dI/dt equals zero.
And I get as a solution, you
shouldn't have too many
difficulties finding this.
The decaying E fields.
And it decays in the
following fashion.
With a decay time tau, which
is L over R, which in our
case, equals 5 times 10 to
the minus 4 seconds.