This is problem number
four, which is 32-30.
It is a step-up transformer,
and it is an ideal
transformer--
I will come back to that several
times as to what I
mean by that.
I have a primary winding whereby
the driving EMF has
121 volts r m s, and of course,
it goes with cosine
omega T. It has N 1 windings.
On the secondary side--
you'll see in a minute
what I mean by that--
I have E 2 r m s, which
is 15,600 volts,
which is much higher.
I have N 2 windings, and I 2
must be smaller or equal to 10
to the minus 2 amperes.
If not, then the
fuse will blow.
What would a transformer
like this look like?
They are made of sheets of iron,
and these sheets have
this shape-- this is open.
The sheets are glued
together--
many of them--
and the reason why that's done
is to avoid eddy currents, and
you will learn about eddy
currents later.
Here is the primary winding,
and so here is your E 1--
E 0 1 cosine omega t--
it's driving this, and
it has N 1 windings.
Here is your secondary
winding--
there could be a
resistor here--
there would be a voltmeter v 2
here, this has N 2 windings,
and this voltmeter would read E
2, which is an induced EMF--
I'll write for that E
0 2 cosine omega t.
I assume that the two are
exactly in phase-- the whole
thing is a little bit
simplified, and I would refer
you to page 1014 if you want
to read up on this in some
more detail.
I can do the closed group
integral off E dot dl, both in
this loop, and in this loop--
Faraday's Law, because
Kirchhoff's Law is for the
birds-- it doesn't hold.
Closed loop integral of E dot
dl is not 0, but in the
primary side, it equals minus
N 1 times the magnetic flux
derivative versus time.
This phi of B is only through
the surface of
one of these loops--
through one of these spiral
staircase surfaces.
That's the way we defined
as phi of B--
that's why we have
an N 1 here.
This equals E 1, and that, of
course, equals E 0 1 times the
cosine of omega t.
Now we go to the second side.
When we go to the second side,
the integral of E dot dl
again is not 0--
again, Kirchhoff's Law is for
the birds, but now I get N 2
times the same B phi B dt.
That, of course, equals my
E 2, which is E 0 2 times
cosine omega t.
Why is it the same?
Because we make the
assumption--
the simplification--
the magnetic field generated
by this primary, which
oscillates back and forth with
omega omega and goes this way,
this way, this way, this way,
so that it stays entirely
inside this iron.
This is not an unreasonable
approximation so that is B 0
outside everywhere.
That would mean that the flux
going through one of these
open surface of one of these
open staircase surfaces is the
same as the one that goes
through here, but since I have
N 2 windings here, I have
an N 2 here, and I
only have an N 1 there.
It follows, then, immediately
by taking the ratio of these
two, that E 2 divided by E 1
equals N 2 divided by N 1.
In an ideal case, this gives
you enormous insights--
that means if you have a ratio
of the windings 1,000 to 1,
you can step up the voltage
by a factor of 1,000.
In our particular case, this
ratio is 130, so we step up
the voltage by a
factor of 130.
How much power is now delivered
to the resistor in
the secondary if I 2 has reached
its maximum value of
10 to the minus 2 amperes?
Keep in mind again that the mean
power per cycle equals
the voltage r m s of side
2 times the current
r m s at site 2.
This now is the [? 50,600 ?]
times 10 to the minus 2,
so this is 156 watts.
If the situation is ideal, which
it almost never is, that
means if there is no energy
loss, if there is no heat
loss-- which is not true,
because if you put your hands
on these transformers, they
are warm, and you can even
burn your hands.
In fact, sometimes the glue
that is used to glue these
sheets of metal together
can even melt.
If you assume that there's no
energy loss, then, of course,
this power of 156 watts must
be delivered also by the
primary site.
Therefore, you will get now for
an ideal transformer the
situation that v 2 I 2 r m s r
m s must be v 1 I 1 r m s r m
s, and this is 156 watts.
You will have no problems
calculating that I 1 r m s is
1.3 amperes.
You see now that the voltages
step up in ratio in 2 over N
1, but the currents step down in
ratio in N 1 over N 2, and
so the voltages are
proportional to
the number of windings.
The currents are inversely
proportional to the windings
in order to keep the power
delivered to the left side the
same as the power to
the right side.
Notice that this current here in
1 is substantially higher--
it's 130 higher--
than the current in the
secondary part in number two.