Welcome back to recitation.
In this video what I'd like you
to do is work on proving
the following product rule
for the del operator.
So we're going to let capital F
be a vector field and u be a
scalar function.
And we want to show the product
rule for the del
operator which, it's in quotes
but it should remind you of
the product rule we have
for functions.
And it is that del dot the
quantity u times F--
so u is the scalar function and
F is the vector field--
is actually equal to the
gradient of u dotted with F
plus u times del dot F. Where
F again is the vector field.
So why don't you take a moment
to prove this fact and you can
pause the video while
doing that.
And then when you're ready to
check if your solution is
correct, bring the video
back up and I'll
show you what I did.
OK, welcome back.
Again what we wanted to do is
prove this sort of pseudo
product rule for the
del operator.
And what we're doing is we're
trying to see what happens if
you have a vector field and you
multiply it by a scalar
function and you apply the
del operator to that.
So we're going to see if we
actually come up with what we
should on the right hand side,
which, since I'm calling it a
rule, we really hope we do.
In fact, we will.
So let me start off.
What I'm going to do is I'm
going to write symbolically
what the left hand side means.
And then we're going to break it
up into pieces and show you
get, in fact, what you would
get on the right hand side.
So symbolically what
do we have?
Oh actually, first I'm going to
call F-- the components of
F, as is usually done
in lecture--
capitals P, Q, and R. So those
will be the components of F.
That's how we've been denoting
this usually.
And notice that if we wanted F
to be a vector field in two
dimensions, we'd just make R 0,
and then we'd have a vector
field in two dimensions.
So we can certainly do that if
we want, but we're going to
prove it in a little more-- in
the three dimensional case.
So remember that del dotted
with any vector field is
supposed to be symbolically--
what was written was you should
think about this as
del, del x, comma del, del y,
comma del, del z, dotted with
this vector field.
uF.
Now what is this vector field?
Because u is a scalar, when I
multiply u by the vector field
F, the components are going
to be u capital P, comma u
capital Q, comma u capital R.
So those are my components.
Now symbolically this is what
we've seen when we're looking
at the del operator acting
on a vector field.
So what do we actually do?
Well, what we actually do, of
course, is we take the x
derivative of the first
component, we take the y
derivative of the second
component, and we take the z
derivative of the
third component.
And then we add those
together.
So it's really a symbolic
idea of a dot product.
It's not a true dot
product here.
But let's actually write
down what we get there.
We get del del x of the quantity
uP, plus del del y of
the quantity uQ, plus del del
z of the quantity uR.
That's exactly what this
symbolically means is this,
this what I've written in
the next line down.
So maybe I should write
equals again.
This is another equals.
The top thing equals the
next line down, equals
the next line down.
And just to have it nice and
even I'll put the equals
there, so when we look back
it's easy to see.
Now how do I deal with this?
Well, notice that u is a
function and P is a function.
Why is that?
Because P was a component
of a vector field.
So it is just a function that
is in the first component of
the vector field.
P, Q, and R are all individually
functions that
depend on x, y, and z.
So here at this step I can
actually take the regular
product rule we have
for functions.
And I can do it in this one,
this one, and this one.
And what I'm going to do, so I
don't have to write del del x
and del del y all over the
place, I'm going to use the
subscripts notation
for derivatives.
So I'm going to write what this
actually equals is u sub
x times P plus u P sub x.
So here the del del x is now
corresponding to a subscript.
So notice that I've just used
the product rule on functions
at this step because u is a
function and P is a function.
I can do the same thing for the
y derivative of u Q, I get
u sub y Q plus u Q sub y.
And then the last component,
I do the same thing for z.
I get u sub z R plus
u R sub z.
Now if I made a mistake it will
become very apparent in
the next moment.
But I don't think I
made a mistake.
I want to remind us where we
want to go and then we'll see
if we have the pieces
to get there.
So I'm going to go back over to
the side we have over here.
And I want to remind you, we
started off with a del
operator acting on this vector
field u times F. Capital F.
And what we'd like to see is
if we can get this to equal
the gradient of u dotted with
the vector field plus u times
the del operator acting on F.
So let's see if we can first
find components of the vector
field and components of
the gradient of u.
And let's see where those are.
They're actually very
nicely placed here.
Notice that this underlined
component is the first
component of gradient u and the
first component of F. And
this underlined component is
the second component of
gradient of u and the second
component of F. And this third
underlined component here is the
third component of grad u
and the third component of F.
So if I take those three
components together--
I'm going to write the
equals up here--
I get exactly grad u dotted
with F. That's the
first thing I get.
And then I'm going to
see what else I get.
But let me just make sure you
understand, look at these
three underlined components
together.
You get u sub x times P plus u
sub y times Q plus u sub z
times R. Well, ux, uy, uz is the
gradient vector field for
u, and P, Q, R is F. So when I
dot those, I get exactly uxP
plus uyQ plus uzR.
You notice these two, or the dot
product of this, gives you
those three components.
And now there are three
components remaining.
Notice what they all
have in common.
They all have a u in
the first spot.
And then it's multiplied by P
sub x, and then here it's
multiplied by Q sub
y, and here it's
multiplied by R sub z.
But that is exactly--
P sub x plus Q sub y plus R
sub z is exactly the del
operator acting on this vector
field F. So this is something
you've seen previously.
So I'm going to do these
as squiggles.
That's exactly equal to u times
the del operator of this
vector field F.
So again let me remind you, del
dot F actually is going to
give you P sub x plus Q
sub y plus R sub z.
And then if I multiply that by
a u, I get this u in front.
So what I have done is for
an arbitrary function u--
I guess I've assumed that
function had first derivatives
so that I could do all this
stuff, and for a vector field
that had first derivatives--
I showed that if I take the del
operator of u times the
vector field, I actually get the
gradient of u dotted with
the vector field plus u
times the del operator
of the vector field.
So that is what I
wanted to show.
If you remember, what I wanted
to show was exactly that sort
of pseudo product rule for
this del operator.
So I think that that
is where I'll stop.
I'm going to step off to the
side so you can see it all
again for a moment.
But that's it.
So that's where I'll stop.