Problem number five.
28-57.
The torque on a current loop.
Let's set up again a
right-handed coordinate system.
Always right-handed.
'x y z'.
And we have a loop, rectangular
loop, which comes
off at an angle and the
angle is theta.
It's hinging here, frictionless
about the z-axis.
This length is 'l1', and this
length is 'l2', this is also
'l2' and this is also 'l1'.
And somehow, for reasons that I
have not explained, there's
a current flowing in this
directions, the same in this
direction, in this direction,
and in this direction.
This current is 'i'.
We know the total my mass of
this whole thing because you
are being told that the mass for
unit length is 0.19 grams
per centimeter.
You know 'l1' and 'l2', so you
can calculate the mass or this
whole thing.
The force on each one of these
individual wires in the
presence of a magnetic
field would be 'i'
times 'l cross B'.
And 'B' is given is in
the '+y' direction.
Uniformly throughout.
If you analyze the forces on
each one of these four
elements, and I would like you
to do that on your own, by
carefully evaluating the
direction of 'l cross B'.
'I' is always a little
element in the
direction of the current.
So 'l dl' would be here.
And the 'dl' would be there.
Then you should be able to
convince yourself that the
force at the bottom here,
this part here,
is in the 'x' direction.
I'll call it 'F of x'.
And therefore right here, it's
the same in magnet I call it
'- x', just to tell you in
which direction it is.
This wire here experiences a
force in the '+ z' direction,
and this one experiences a force
in the '- z' direction,
and the two exactly cancel
each other out.
So I don't have to worry
about these two.
But these two do not cancel
each other out.
They do cancel each other out
in terms of the sum of all
forces being 0, but not the sum
of all torques being 0.
So there's a torque
on this system.
But yet we know that it
is an equilibrium.
So the only way that it can be
an equilibrium that there is
not a torque, this is a counter-
clockwise torque, it
has to be a clockwise torque
to hold it in equilibrium.
I'm going to now make a
drawing from the side.
I call this hinge points through
which is z-axis goes
'P', this one is 'l1', this
angle is theta and I'm going
to draw all the forces in there
that I can think of.
This is the total mass off the
loop 'mg', here is that force
'Fx' due to the magnetic
fields and the current.
Well there must be here this
force '-x', right?
I call it 'F minus x', it's the
same in magnitude as this
one, they cancel
each other out.
But since the sum of all forces
must be 0, according to
Newton, and this hinge point,
there must also be
a force 'mg' up.
So you'll see now that the sum
of all forces is now 0.
But know the sum of all
torques is also 0.
It doesn't matter which point
you take, whether you take
this point, this point, this
point, this point, or this
point, or this point, or this
point, the sum of all
torques will be 0.
I might as well choose
this points 'P'.
So I will calculate now for
you the torque relative to
point 'P' which must be 0.
When I am here, there is no
contribution to this force and
this force.
I have a clockwise contribution
due to this one.
So there is this arm
times this force.
Now the arm has a length 0.5
'l1' times the sine of theta
times 'mg'.
But that is the clockwise one.
I called this clockwise,
must be equal to the
counter-clockwise, I give them
both a positive sign.
And the counter-clockwise is
relative to this point 'P',
this distance times
this force.
And this distance is ''l1'
cosine theta' times 'Fx'.
Notice I have one equation
with one
unknown and that is 'Fx'.
Because I know all the
other things. 'l1'
cancels, by the way.
I know say theta.
But I also know that 'Fx' equals
'i' times 'l2', mind
you it is the length of this
wire here perpendicular to
'l1', times that magnetic field
'B', which is only in
the y-direction.
I know the magnetic fields,
I know 'l2', I know--
I know 'Fx', I know 'i' and I
know 'l2', so out pops the
magnetic field.
So I can calculate the
Interesting problem.
So due to this magnetic field,
this loop will come out, it
will experience a torque, but
the gravitational torque
exactly balances it, and so
it will be standing at
equilibrium at this angle.
You can argue that if you
increase the current the angle
will probably become larger,
and if you increase the
magnetic fields the angle will
probably also become larger.