PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
Today, we're going to talk about
linear transformations.
So, we've seen linear
transformations incognito all
the time until now.
We've played around
with matrices.
Matrices multiplying vectors,
say, in Rn and producing
vectors in Rm.
So really, the language of
linear transformations only
provides a nicer framework when
we want to analyze linear
operations on more abstract
vector spaces, like the one we
have in this problem here.
We're going to work with the
space of two by two matrices.
And we're going to analyze the
operation, have the matrix A,
and we produce its transpose.
OK.
So please take a few minutes to
try the problem on your own
and come back.
Hi, again.
OK.
So the first question we need
to ask ourselves is, indeed,
why is T a linear operator?
So what are the abstract
properties that a linear
operator satisfies?
Well, what happens when T
acts on the sum of two
matrices, A and B?
So we've produced--
this is the matrix.
The transpose of A plus B. But
we know that this is A
transpose, B transpose.
And so, this is exactly T
of A plus T of B. So the
transformation that we're
analyzing takes the sum of two
matrices into the sum of
their transformations.
OK.
Similarly, it takes a multiple
of a transformation into the
multiple of the transformations.
So it takes the matrix C times
A to C times A transpose,
which
is C T of A. OK.
So it is a linear operator.
Now, can we figure out
what its inverse is?
Well, what does the
transpose do?
It takes a column and
flips it into a row.
So what happens if we apply
the operation once again?
Well, it's going to take the row
and turn it back down to
the column.
So applying the transformation
twice, we come back to the
original situation.
So therefore, t squared
is the identity.
And from this, we infer that
the inverse is the
transformation itself.
Now, this was part one.
Part two, we'll compute the
matrix of the linear
transformation in the
following two bases.
So the first basis
is, in fact--
it is the standard basis
for the space
of two by two matrices.
And the way we compute the
matrix, we first compute what
T does to each of the
basis elements.
So T of v1.
Let's go back.
So here.
So T takes the transpose
of this matrix.
And we see that the transpose
of 1, 0, 0, 0 is 1, 0, 0, 0.
So it's a symmetric matrix.
So T of v1.
Here's v1.
What about T of v2?
Come back here.
So this one comes here.
0 comes here.
And so we actually get v3.
So T of v2 is v3.
Similarly, T of v3 is v2.
And finally, T of v4.
Well, v4 is a symmetric
matrix as well.
So the transpose doesn't
change it.
OK.
Now, we encode this into a
matrix in the following way.
Essentially, the first column
will tell us how T of v1 is
expressed as a linear
combination
of the basis elements.
Or in this case, it's just v1.
So it's going to be 1 times
v1 plus 0, v2 plus
0, v3 plus 0, v4.
T of v2 is v3.
So we have 0, 0, 1, 0.
T of v3 is 0 v1, 1
v2, 0 v3, 0 v4.
And T of v4 is 0 v1, 0
v2, 0 v3, plus 1 v4.
OK.
So we've written down the
matrix of the linear
transformation, T, in
the standard basis.
And you can check that this
is exactly what we want.
The representation of some
matrix, say, 1, 2, 3, 4, in
this standard basis is, it's
the vector 1, 2, 3, 4.
T takes this to its transpose
1, 3, 2, 4.
So this in the basis is
represented as 1, 3, 2, 4.
Right?
And it's not hard to see that MT
multiplies this vector, we
get exactly this vector.
So we'll pause for a bit, so
that I erase the board.
And we're going to return with
the representation of T in the
basis, w1, w2, w3, and w4.
OK.
So let's compute now the matrix
T in the basis w1, w2,
w3, and w4.
We played the same game.
We look at how T acts on each
of the basis vectors.
So T of w1--
well, w1 is a symmetric
matrix.
So T of w1 is w1.
Similarly, with w2 and w3.
They're all symmetric.
What about w4?
Well, we see that the
1 comes down here.
The negative one
comes up here.
I mean, in the end we just get
the negative of the w4.
So, let me just write
this out.
We had T of w1 equal to w1, T
of w2 equal to w2, T of w3
equal to w3, and T of w4,
was negative on w4.
So therefore, the matrix of the
linear transformation, T,
in this basis.
I'm going to call the
matrix M prime.
T has a fairly simple
expression.
The only non-zero entries
are on a diagonal.
And they're precisely 1,
1, 1, and negative 1.
And finally, let's tackle
the eigenvalues slash
eigenvectors issue.
Well, you've seen what an
eigenvector for a matrix is.
And the idea for an eigenvalue,
eigenvector for a
linear transformation is
virtually the same.
And we are looking for the
vectors v and the scale is
lambda such that T of v is
lambda of v. But if you guys
look back to what we just did
with w1, w2, w3, and w4,
you'll see precisely that w1,
w2, and w3 are eigenvectors
for T with eigenvalue 1.
And w4 is an eigenvector for T
with eigenvalue negative 1.
So yeah, we essentially have
solved the problem knowing a
very, very nice basis in which
we computed the linear
transformation, T. So I'll
leave it at that.