PROFESSOR: Hi everybody.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture you did a bunch of
examples of related rates
problems. So I have a couple
more for you to do today.
So here we've got OK, so we've
got air being blown into a
spherical balloon at a
rate of 1,000 cubic
centimeters per second.
So the question is, how fast is
the radius growing when the
radius is equal to
8 centimeters?
And then OK, so I've got a
second question, which is, how
fast is the surface area growing
at that same time?
So why don't you take a few
minutes, work this one out for
yourself, come back, and we'll
work it out together.
All right.
Welcome back.
So this question, like all
related rates questions, has
the property that the calculus
is typically very
straightforward, but that
there's some geometric or
algebraic setup.
So in this case, it's straight
up geometry.
So we have a balloon, we know
it's a perfect sphere, we know
how fast the volume
is changing.
So OK, but we need to know how
fast the radius is changing.
So in order to do that we need
to figure out a relationship
between the radius
and the volume.
And then we can just do implicit
differentiation like
we've been doing.
So for example, OK,
so for a sphere--
the setup is not so bad
for this first one--
so we know that for a sphere the
volume is equal to 4/3 pi
times the radius cubed.
So that's the fundamental
relationship between the
volume and radius of a sphere,
and it's true for every sphere
everywhere in Euclidean space.
And we're given also, that the
volume is changing at a
constant rate of 1,000
centimeters cubed per second.
So dv dt is just given
to be 1,000.
You know, leave off the
units at this point.
So the question is,
what is dr dt?
That's what we're trying
to figure out.
We're trying to figure out how
fast the radius is changing at
the moment when the radius
is equal to 8 centimers.
So how can we do that?
Well, this fundamental
relationship, it's an identity.
It always holds.
So that means we can
differentiate it.
So if we take the derivative of
this identity, well, V on
the left just becomes dv dt.
And on the right we want to do
implicit differentation.
So here r is changing with
respect to time.
r is a function of t.
Well, OK.
So 4/3 pi is a constant.
So that when we differentiate
nothing happens.
4/3 pi.
And so now we differentiate r
cubed with respect to t, so
that gives us 3r squared
times dr dt.
So that's just the chain
rule in action there.
And now what we want
is this dr dt.
Right?
That's the thing that we're
looking for, is how fast the
radius is growing.
So that's dr dt.
And we want it at the moment
when r is equal to 8.
So when r is equal to 8 this
implies that-- well, OK, so dv
dt is 1,000 always--
and it implies that--
OK, so it's equal to 1,000 is
equal to 4/3 pi times 3 times
8 squared times dr dt.
So at this moment that we're
interested in, we have this
equation to solve for dr dt,
and this is a nice, simple
equation to solve.
You just divide through by
everything on the right hand
side other than dr dt.
So this implies that dr dt is
equal to-- well, OK, so I have
to divide 1,000 by
all this stuff.
I think it works out to
something like 125 over 32 pi.
All right.
So that's the exact value.
Maybe you're interested in
sort of knowing about how
large this is.
So 32 pi is pretty close
to 100, so this
is about 1.2 something.
So, all right.
So there we go.
So that answers the
first question.
At that moment the radius is
growing at a rate of 125 over
32 pi centimeters per second.
OK.
So now how about the second
question that we've got here?
What about the surface area?
So again, we know how fast now
the radius is changing and we
know how fast the volume
is changing.
So in order to figure out how
fast the surface area is
changing, we need something that
relates the surface area
to either the volume
or the radius.
Now the relationship between
surface area and volume is
something that we could sort of
work out if we had to, but
it's a lot easier to write down
the surface area in terms
of the radius.
So let's do that.
So we have, I'm going to use the
letter S to denote surface
area of a sphere.
So again, it's a general
identity, you know, a
geometric fact that the surface
area of a sphere is
equal to 4 pi times the
radius squared.
And this is always true.
And now the thing that we want
is the rate of change of the
surface area.
So the rate of change
is the derivative.
So we want to compute the
derivative here, ds dt.
So OK, so we just do it.
So ds dt is equal to- well,
4 pi hangs around.
And again, we differentiate
r squared.
r is a function of t,
so we have to use
the chain rule here.
So this is times
2r times dr dt.
So this is an identity.
So this is true always.
And now we want to know, at
this particular moment in
time, when r is equal
to 8, what is ds dt?
And in order figure that out,
well OK, we just have to be
able to plug in for
everything else.
So when r equals 8-- all right,
well luckily, now if we
were just starting this problem
from scratch here,
we'd have a problem.
Which is we wouldn't know
what dr dt was.
But luckily, we've already
figured it out right, so in
the first part of the problem.
So we know that when r is equal
to 8, dr dt is equal to
125 over 32 pi.
Did I copy that right?
Yes, I did.
OK.
So OK, so in this case, the
equation we have to solve is
just completely straightforward.
We just plug in the values and
it's already solved for us.
So that's nice.
So that we get that ds dt at
that moment is equal to--
well, it's 4 pi times 2
times 8 is the radius
times 125 over 32 pi.
Oh boy, and all right.
So we can work this out
if we want, I guess.
That's 32 pi to cancel, so
that's equal to 250.
And I guess the units there,
better be centimeters squared
per second.
So at this moment in time the
surface area is growing by 250
centimeters squared
per second.
So that's all we had to do.
So we're all set.