JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been doing
related rates problems. I've
got another example
for you, here.
So this one's a really
tricky one.
So I'm going to give you some
time to work on it.
But I really think you
should try and work
through this one yourself.
It'll be well worth
your effort.
So we've got here, OK so
this is a mouthful.
We've got a 20 foot long
ladder and it's leaning
against a 12 foot wall.
But it's leaning
over the wall.
So 5 feet of the ladder
project over
the top of the wall.
And then the bottom of the
ladder is being pulled away
from the wall at 5
feet per second.
The question is, while this is
going on, how quickly is the
top of the ladder
going downwards?
How quickly is it approaching
the ground?
So why don't you take
a few minutes.
Well, maybe more than
a few for this one.
It took me a while to work
it out the first time.
Take a few minutes, work this
one out, come back, and we'll
see how it went.
All right.
So hopefully you've had some
luck working out this problem
on your own.
Now let's work it
out together.
So OK, so this is a sort of
classic, really tricky related
rates problem in that there's
a lot of geometric work that
you have to do at
the beginning in
order to get this right.
And then once you get the
geometry down, the calculus is
basically totally straight
forward.
You know, you compute a couple
derivatives, you use the chain
rule once, whatever.
You know.
So OK, so let's start
off by trying and
drawing a careful picture.
And then we'll have to figure
out what the quantities that
we're interested in are and the
relationships between them.
So we have here, here's
the ground.
And we have a 12 foot wall.
And we have a 20 foot ladder
leaning against the wall and
extending over it.
So my ladder.
So here's my ladder.
Here's my wall.
All right.
And this, the bottom of the
ladder here, is what's getting
pulled away from the wall
at 5 units per second.
5 feet per second.
So 5 feet per second is
how fast that's going.
And we're interested, so while
you do that, you know, the
ladder is changing position.
So the question is, how fast
is the top of the ladder
descending?
So you know, it might also
be moving in some other
directions, but we're just
interested in how quickly it's
going straight down.
So OK, so first, let's
talk about the
things that don't change.
So the height of this wall
is not changing.
The wall is staying put
the whole time.
And the length of the ladder
is not changing.
That's staying put, as well.
But what, OK, so those
are the fixed
qualities in this problem.
Basically, everything
else is changing.
So for example, this distance
between the base of the wall
and the base of the ladder,
that's changing because the
ladder is being pulled
away from the wall.
So we can give that a name.
Lat's call that, that's a
horizontal distance, so we can
call that x, say.
And the height of the top of
the ladder is changing, so
let's draw that in.
That's what we're
interested in.
It's the height, so
we can call tit y.
And let's see.
What else?
Well OK, the whole ladder isn't
changing in length, but
the amount, but as this gets
pulled, you know, this top
point is sort of sliding down
towards the wall, the amount
of the ladder that extends over
the wall is changing.
So I guess we could choose.
We could give this a variable
name or we could give this
part a variable name.
I think I'm going to give the
little one a variable name.
I'll call it d for distance,
I guess.
And OK so this is d
because the whole
ladder has length, 20.
We have that this part, this
segment has length 20 minus d.
Ok so, I think that those
quantities describe all the
possible lengths of interest
in this picture.
So now, OK.
So that's just the first,
the set up.
That's the first thing
that has to happen.
Now after we set up, we need
to figure out what the
relationships between these
different variables are.
Well, let's see.
What have we got?
Well one thing we've got is
that we've got a right
triangle here.
So the wall and the ground
and the ladder.
Those three segments form
a right triangle.
So OK.
So we can apply the Pythagorean
Theorem here.
So that's one relationship we
have, and that's going to give
us a relationship between x
and well, OK, 20 minus d.
So that'll give us a
relationship between x and d.
So this, so OK, so what does the
Pythagorean Theorem say?
So by the Pythagorean Theorem,
we have x squared plus--
that's a 1--
12 squared is equal the to
quantity 20 minus d squared.
So that's one identity that we
have, identity we have that
relates these three
quantities.
And so that's good.
Because we know how fast
x is changing.
And so with this identity, that
means we can use related
rates to figure out how fast
d is changing, as well.
So that's good.
That'll be a step in the right
direction, but what we
actually need to know is
how fast y is changing.
So right?
Because that's what the question
is asking for-- how
quickly is the top of the ladder
approaching the ground?
So how, what's the rate
of change in y
with respect to time?
So I need another identity here
in order to figure out
what the relationship with y is
and these other variables.
And there are a couple
of different
ways to go about this.
I think the one that I'm going
to do-- so there is another
right triangle here.
So you could, if you wanted to
name this segment, as well,
then you could do another
right triangle.
But then you'd need a third
relationship relating this
segment to d or something
like that.
So I'm not going to go that
route, but I'm going to go do
something related to that,
which is that this bigger
right triangle, right, which has
the height of the top of
the ladder from the ground and
the whole length of the ladder
as two of its sides, and a piece
of the ground, so that
bigger right triangle
is similar to this
smaller right triangle.
Right?
I mean, they have, they're right
triangles and they have
the same base angle there.
So they're similar triangles.
So OK, so by similar triangles--
now I have to
remember all my geometry,
right?
So the ratio of corresponding
sides are equal, so in this
case, the ratio of the
hypotenuses is equal to the
ratio of these legs.
And that'll relate.
So the hypotenuses involve d and
the vertical legs, well,
one of them is just constant
and one of them involves y.
So that'll set up a relationship
between d and y,
and so then I'll have x
linked to d and I'll
have d linked to y.
And so then we can use related
rates to figure out what the
relationship between y and x
is and figure out the thing
we're after, which is the
rate of change in y.
So OK, so I haven't actually
written anything down, yet.
So what is the similar
triangle?
So here,et's look at
the hypotenuses.
So the big hypotenuse has
length 20, and the small
hypotenuse has length
20 minus d.
Good.
So that's the ratio of the
hypotenuses, and so that has
to be equal to the ratio of
the corresponding legs.
And so the big leg is y, and
the small leg is 12.
OK.
All right, so there's
Pythagorean Theorem.
There's similar triangles.
So we now have the relationships
that we're after
relating x and y and d
all to each other.
Great.
So now we can do the calculus
part of this problem, right?
So now we know, oh, I
guess, actually, we
need a few more things.
Take it back.
So now we need, we're after, as
I said, a particular moment
in time, and at our particular
moment in time, so I haven't
used this one given, yet, that
5 feet of the wall--
oh, sorry--
5 feet of the ladder projects
over the wall.
So OK, so at our moment, so at
the key moment, we have that d
is equal to 5.
OK, so that means 20 minus
d is equal to 15.
What else does that mean?
So that means that at that
moment, x in this right
triangle is the third leg in a
right triangle with hypotenuse
15 and one leg 12.
So that's one of your three,
four, five triangles, but
blown up a little bit.
So we have at that moment,
that x is equal to 9.
And OK, so at that moment, to
figure out y, we can use this
other relationship that we have.
So 20 over 15 is equal
to y over 12, so y is equal
to 20 over 15 times 12.
So that's 4 over 3,
so that's 16.
So at our key moment in time,
these are the values that
we're going to end
up plugging in.
And also, dx dt is equal to 5.
x is being increased.
Increased?
Yeah x is, right, so as the foot
gets pulled away, x is
getting bigger.
So x is being increased
at 5 units per second.
All right, so these are
all the things we're
going to plug in.
All right, good.
So now we are after dy dt at
this moment. and we don't
have, and we know dx dt.
We don't have a direct
relationship between y and x,
but do have a direct
relationship between y and d.
So if we got dd dt-- sorry--
dd dt, then we could get dy
dt, and because of this
relationship,
we can get dd dt.
All right.
So let's start off
by doing that.
So OK, so this is an identity.
It holds always so we can
differentiate it.
And we're going to
differentiate it
with respect to t.
x and d are functions of t.
So OK.
So differentiating this
identity I get
2x times dx dt plus--
well, OK, derivative of 144
with respect to t is 0--
is equal to--
I guess I could expand this out,
but it's easier just to
use the chain rule right away--
so this is equal to 2
times 20 minus d times the
derivative of 20 minus d with
respect to t, which
is minus dd dt.
All right.
I beg the gods of
math notation to
forgive me for dd dt.
But, OK.
So, allright, so now,
this is always true.
And what we want is the value
of dd dt at our particular
moment in time.
So at our particular moment in
time we have, well let's
see,so OK, we have x, we have
the dx dt, and we have d.
So we can just plug all
those things in.
So, at our moment, let me see
how I'm going to do this.
I'll do it over here.
At our moment, so 2x is 18
times dx dt is 5 equals 2
times 20 minus d is 15
times minus dd dt.
And dd dt is what we're after.
So OK.
So divide 2 into this is 9.
45 divided by 15 is 3, so dd dt
is equal to minus 3 at the
moment that we're
interested in.
All right.
Great.
So now we have dd dt, and so
now we can go back to the
second relationship we have, the
one that relates d and y,
and we can do the
same thing here.
We can take a derivative, use
the chain rule, use, and get a
relationship between dy
dt and d and dd dt.
And then we'll be able to plug
in all these values we have
for our particular moment.
So OK, so I think I'm
just going to
differentiate this straight.
There are some simplifications
I could do first, but it'll
work fine if we just
do it straight.
So OK, so I need to compute
the derivative.
This is an identity.
I can take its derivative, so I
differentiate the left hand
side with respect to t, so I
get 20 over-- so this is a
minus first power-- so I get
minus 20 over 20 minus d
quantity squared times--
I need the derivative of the
bottom-- is minus dd dt.
And on the right hand side
I get dy dt over 12.
So I have this relationship
between d and y, I take its
derivative, now I have a
relationship that involves dy
dt, which is the thing
that I'm after.
So, whew.
So now, I'm back at this
plugging in stage.
So at our moment in time, I
know what d is, and I just
figured out what dd dt is, so
I can just plug those values
in to figure out
what dy dt is.
So OK, so let's do that.
So at this moment in
time we have--
so let me just multiply through
by the 12 and that
will let us solve-- so we have
dy dt is equal to 12 times,
well, so it's minus 20 over 15
squared, times minus, minus 3.
Times 3.
So this is--
all right.
Arithmetic.
Not my favorite thing
in the world.
So we've got two 3's here.
We're going to end up with a 5
in the denominator, and then
we've got 4 times minus 4, so
that's minus 16 over 5.
So.
All right.
So that's the answer.
Let's remember what
we've done.
So minus 16 over 5, that's
a negative number.
Why is it a negative number?
Well, as we pull this, the
bottom of this ladder here
away from the wall, the top of
the ladder is going to fall
downwards, it's going to get
closer to the ground.
And y is the vertical distance
between the ground and the top
of the ladder.
So that's shrinking; y is
shrinking and should have a
negative derivative.
OK.
Negative derivative, minus 16
over 5 feet per second.
So it would take, if this
instantaneous rate held up,
which it won't in
this situation--
if it held up it would take 5
seconds to get down, so it's
not falling very quickly.
OK.
That seems about right.
Anything else?
I guess we computed that dd
dt was also negative.
Same thing here-- when you pull
this way, this length is
going to shrink, so d is getting
smaller, so it has
negative derivative.
OK.
So at this moment in time, the
top of the ladder is falling--
the thing we're interested in--
at exactly 16 over 5 feet
per second.
And we're all set.