PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you learned about
some new tools for computing
certain limits.
In particular, you learned
about l'Hopital's rule.
So now you have the ability to
compute easily some limits
that before might have
been difficult to do.
So I have here four examples
of limits, some of which--
or maybe all of which, or maybe
none of which or, well
definitely some of which--
will be, you could use
l'Hopital's rule on.
So here they are.
Why do you pause the video and
take a few minutes to work
them all out, come back, and we
can work them out together.
Welcome back.
So we have these four
limits here.
And let's start solving
them, shall we?
So I'll just go from the first
one, and then I'll, you know,
go through them in order.
So limit a is the limit as x
goes to 1 of x to the a minus
1 over x to the b minus 1.
If we want to use l'Hopital's
rule, we have to first check
that this is a limit of
an appropriate kind of
expression.
So that's, in particular, a
limit that is a 0 over 0 or
infinity over infinity form, so
an indeterminate quotient.
And as x goes to 1, we see that
x to the a goes to 1.
So x to the a minus
1 goes to 0.
And similarly x to the b goes
to 1, so x to the b
minus 1 goes to 0.
So indeed, this is a 0 over 0
indeterminate form, so we can
apply l'Hopital's rule.
So we apply l'Hopital's rule.
And it says that the limit as
x goes to 1 of x to the a
minus 1 over x to
the b minus 1.
OK, so what do we do?
What l'Hopital's rule says is we
can take the derivative of
the top and the derivative of
the bottom, and then the limit
of the left side will be equal
to the limit of the result
provided the result actually has
an existing limit, either
a real number or infinity
or minus infinity.
So in this case, this says that
this expression is equal
to the limits-- so it's the same
limit-- as x goes 1 of--
OK, so the derivative of the
top is ax to the a minus 1,
and the derivative of the bottom
is bx to the b minus 1.
So l'Hopital's rule says that
these two limits are equal
provided that the second
limit exists.
So what is the second limit?
Well, we, OK, we can do some
simplifications here.
Here there wasn't, you know,
a lot of obvious
simplifying to be done.
But here there's an obvious
simplification step.
So this is equal to the
limit as x goes to 1.
So a over b is just
a constant.
And now the powers of x, this
is x to the a minus b.
But as x goes to 1, x to the a
minus b goes to 1 no matter
what a and b are.
So at this point, this isn't an
indeterminate form anymore.
This is nice simple limit
we can just plug in.
So this is just equal
to a over b.
OK so that's part a,
straightforward application of
l'Hopital's rule.
Let's go look it part b.
So part b asks us for the
limit as x goes to 0 of
sine 5x over x.
So I'll put that right
here, maybe I'll
draw a little border.
So the limit as x goes to 0 of
sine of 5x divided by x.
So again there's a question of,
you know, is this limit,
do we know what it is already?
and?
The answer is, maybe we
do and maybe we don't,
but suppose we don't.
So in that case, can we apply
l'Hopital's rule?
Well we check, and as x
goes to 0, sine of 5x.
So as x goes to 0, 5x goes to
0, so sine of 5x goes to 0,
and x goes to 0.
So this is another
0 over 0 form.
So we can apply l'Hopital's
rule.
So l'Hopital's rule says that
this is equal to the limit as
x goes to 0 of--
we take the derivative of the
top and divide by the
derivative of the bottom.
So the derivative of the top
is just 5 cosine 5x.
And the derivative of
the bottom is 1.
So l'Hopital's rule says the
limit here is equal to the
limit here provided
this limit exists.
And now as x goes to 0, well,
OK, 5, 1 is constant.
So we're just looking at the
limit of cosine 5x here.
As x goes to 0, that just
approaches 5 times cosine of
0, which is 1.
So this is equal to-- sorry--
the cosine of the 0 part is 1.
So it's 5 times 1, which is 5.
Now I should note that we didn't
actually really need
l'Hopital's rule for this one.
One thing you can remember is
that this limit is actually
the definition of the derivative
of sine of
5x at x equals 0.
So what we just did with
l'Hopital's rule was use the
derivative to compute the
derivative, if you like.
So we used the fact that we
already knew the derivative in
order to compute it.
We could also just say by
definition, this is the
derivative of sine 5x at 0,
which is 5 cosine of 0, which
is 1, which is 5, rather.
OK so that's part b.
Now part c asks for the limit
as x goes to 0 of x squared
minus 6x plus 2-- did
do that right--
over x plus 1.
So this limit, you can't
apply l'Hopital's rule?
Why can't you apply
l'Hopital's rule?
Well, because it's not an
indeterminate form.
This limit is really
easy to compute.
You can just plug in
x equals 0 here.
The top is going to 2, and
the bottom is going to 1.
So the whole limit is going to
2 divided by 1, which is 2.
So there's no, not only, you
don't need l'Hopital's rule,
and also you can't apply
l'Hopital's rule.
This is not a form in which
l'Hopital's rule applies.
It's not an indeterminate form,
OK, so, but OK, but the
result is very easy
to compete.
So that's 2.
And we've got our last one now
which is d, the limit as x
goes to infinity of ln of 1
plus e to the 3x quantity
divided by 2x packs plus 5.
OK, well is it obvious
what this limit is?
Not to me.
So OK, so then we can check.
It's a quotient.
So can we apply l'Hopital's
rule?
Well we can apply l'Hopital's
rule if it's an
indeterminate quotient.
So what's happening is
x goes to infinity?
Well, let's do the bottom first,
because that's easy.
As x goes to infinity, 2x
plus 5 goes to infinity.
And, OK, as x goes
to infinity, e to
the 3x goes to infinity.
So 1 plus e to the 3x
goes to infinity.
So log of 1 plus 3 to the
3x goes to infinity.
So this is an infinity
over infinity form.
That's an indeterminate form,
an indeterminate quotient.
So we can apply l'Hopital's
rule.
So l'Hopital's rule says that
this is equal to the limit of
the quotient of the ratio of the
derivatives, provided that
that limit exists.
So this is equal to the limit
as x goes to infinity of--
OK, so we need to look at the
ratio of the derivatives.
So the bottom one is easy.
That's 2.
For the top one, to compute this
derivative, we need to
use the chain rule here.
So you take the derivative
of this, and you
get, well, a log.
So on the bottom we get
1 plus e to the 3x.
And then by the chain rule, up
top you get 3e to the 3x.
Or, just rewriting this a little
bit in a nicer form,
this is the limit as x goes to
infinity of 3 over 2 times e
to the 3x over 1 plus
e to the 3x.
All right, so now the question
is what do we do from here?
Well is this limit obvious?
Well, OK, so there are
two situations here.
One is, you might look at this
and you might already know
what this limit is.
The reason you might know
that, is that x goes to
infinity, e to the 3x is going
to infinity, and 1 plus e to
the 3x is going to infinity.
So this is an infinity over
infinity indeterminate form.
And so you could apply
l'Hopital's rule to it again.
OK?
That's one thing you could do.
You might also look at and say
well, these two things are
going to infinity at exactly
the same rate.
Right?
This plus 1 is almost
totally irrelevant.
Actually for purposes of
estimating the magnitude of
this fraction, it is
totally irrelevant.
When you take you know, when 3x
is big, then e to the 3x is
like a billion or something.
So e to 3x is a billion.
So you have a billion over
a billion and 1.
So it's very, very close to 1.
It's going to get closer
and closer to 1.
So, OK, so if you didn't trust
that analysis based on
magnitudes, I mean the idea
here is just that the most
significant term in the top
is the e to the 3x.
The most significant term on
the bottom is e to the 3x.
They dominate everything else
that appears, which is just
this little 1.
So that's going to give
you a ratio of 1.
If you don't trust that
analysis, you can apply
l'Hopital's rule again, and
l'Hopital's rule will tell you
exactly the equivalent thing.
When you take a derivative,
you'll be left with 3e to the
3x over 3e to the 3x,
which is just 1.
So in either case, this
part goes to 1.
So three 3/2 times it
goes right to 3/2.
All right, so there
you have it.
Four limits computed with
l'Hopital's rule.
Well one of them was computed
without l'Hopital's rule.
Remember, you always have to
check that you actually have
an indeterminate form before
you apply l'Hopital's rule.
And that's all I have
to say about that.
So I'll end there.