The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.MIT.edu.
PROFESSOR: OK, let's see, some
administrative stuff, first of
all, Wednesday's
our play test.
So it's an internal play test.
You're going to be playing with
each other games which
means chances are you are going
to get barely enough
time to play one person's game,
and enough time for that
group to play your game.
So I'm just going to just,
basically, pair up teams.
Hopefully, I think we
have four teams.
So I think that works
out just right.
One thing I will certainly
recommend before going on to
Wednesday's class is making sure
that you had a chance to
play test with, at
least, someone
who's not in your group.
And the reason for this, what
you want to be keeping an eye
out for, are rules that you've
already agreed on in your
team, but might have to learn
it to write down somewhere.
I want the rules written down.
They don't necessarily
need to look great.
Typed is awesome because they're
easy to read, and
they're easy to revise later.
It's not actually
a requirement.
But you've got to have
them written down.
You should be able to just put
it in front of a person.
I will suggest that you bring
a copy to the office.
If you want to come in early
on Wednesday, or I could,
maybe, grab the Xerox if you
just bring a couple of copies
so that the entire group of
four people is going to be
testing your game, which means,
all users at the same
time while you're explaining
it to them.
If you're in a situation where
you already have rules that
you think could be understood
without explaining, I would
suggest not explaining at all.
Just give them the rules and
see what they make of it.
It's going to be very
informative that way.
Not every single team may
be in that situation.
They may not have that much
confidence in their
ability right now.
If you think you've gotten all
the rules written down but you
just kind of feel not quite so
confident that everything is
in there, do it anyway.
Just don't explain it.
Give it to them.
See what they're having problems
with and then you can
explain it.
It will still be informative.
You'll still be able to get that
data point of what should
we have written down as a
clarification, as a complete
omission, what needs to
be reworded before
the game ever starts.
But I do fully recognize that
there may be certain teams
that do not have a set of rules
that comprehensive yet.
In the end, you'll want to get
the operating test and time.
So it's going to take half
and hour for somebody to
understand your game just by
reading your rules, then you
do want to try and
cut that down.
Eventually, before you send me
your game you'll want to be in
a situation where someone can
understand your entire game
quickly, comprehending
the rules.
What's up?
AUDIENCE: When we're play
testing and timing, we weren't
sure or we didn't remember, or
we didn't read carefully
enough, what is the
maximum time that
the game has to take?
And does that include set up
from a complete novice, or
does that include, are you
allowed to explain the rules
and have totally experienced
players go at it, and once
experienced players go at it
they have to take a certain
amount of time?
How does your--
PROFESSOR: It was supposed to be
for novice players but I'm
just going to check the
actual syllabus.
AUDIENCE: Do we have to be able
to explain the entire
game, run through an entire play
through and all that, in
10 minutes?
PROFESSOR: That one
I wasn't sure.
I think it's actually
on your play through
but give me a second.
I'm going to look up.
AUDIENCE: I'm pretty sure
it says 10 minutes.
Yeah, 5 or 10 minutes including
setup and play.
PROFESSOR: Including
set-up and play.
But that does not
necessarily--
AUDIENCE: It shouldn't include
reading the rules.
AUDIENCE: It should not?
AUDIENCE: It should not.
10 minutes is way too short a
time to read and understand
and then play a game.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, let me
just verify that.
AUDIENCE: Walks and words.
That's about it.
AUDIENCE: Our game takes two
minutes to play at the moment.
AUDIENCE: What we'll be able
to do is take a really long
time for premium effect and
have some more information
written on these cards.
It's just taking the time to
write it so that way if
somebody's busting a move--
PROFESSOR: So it's true.
It doesn't say 10 minutes that
you need to be able to play
and understand the game
in 10 minutes.
So I'm going to say, set-up and
play has to be 10 minutes.
So it's like, every time you
reset the game and you play to
the end, that should be
under 10 minutes.
If it takes longer than
that to understand the
game, that's fine.
But frankly, if it takes more
than 10 minutes for someone to
understand your game,
you have a problem.
And the problem isn't going to
be one that's going to affect
your grade, it's going to be
one that you can use the
processes in this class to
reiterate on to improve your
game to the point where it
doesn't take that long to
understand.
Reading the rules should
not take longer
than playing the game.
There are games like that but
try not to make those games
and not when it's
the first time.
So I would say in for the
explaining of the rules should
take within 10 minutes.
Right now, it might be OK if
the actual explanation
requires someone who's actually
an expert in the game
to explain it.
By the end of this assignment
you should be definitely
getting to the point where
you don't even need that.
Just a new player with your
rules should be able to
understand and play your
game in 10 minutes.
It could involve discussion
of the entire
group of your players.
You've got four people in--
let's say it's a card game--
you have four people and they're
all looking at the
rules simultaneously, and your
friend says, where does
it say so and so?
And somebody else who has never
played your game before
answers that.
That's fine.
And that's actually how a lot
of people play games.
Sometimes people play in
quick thought rules.
This is all you need to know
to play your first round of
cards, and that actually
helps a lot of
people to get started.
And then you're picking
up the--
AUDIENCE: Lowers the
activation energy.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
In the end, more people
play your game.
That's good.
So that's on Wednesday.
Everyone please come on time
because every minute of this
time wins some recognition or
pizza [UNINTELLIGIBLE] and if
whole teams don't show up--
Who's aligning a game that has
to be played by both players.
So there's some teams.
Two?
Three?
AUDIENCE: Two or four.
PROFESSOR: Two or four.
OK.
All right.
No, that's cool.
AUDIENCE: So even if a
guy didn't show up
on time that's OK.
PROFESSOR: OK, so that's the
preparation for Wednesday now.
I do want to apologize
for Friday's lecture.
I was on a lot of meds.
You may or may not have noticed
that I was having a
splitting headache and was not
the best lecture that I have
given in my entire
teaching career.
In fact, it's probably the
worst lecture I've given.
AUDIENCE: No.
I didn't notice.
PROFESSOR: It occurred to me
that there might just be a
better way to get some of those
concepts across other
than me yammering
for three hours.
And what I'd like to do is
revisit some of them but
actually do a bit
of an activity.
I have never done this before
so this is not tested.
You guys are the first
iteration.
AUDIENCE: Oh.
I feel honored.
PROFESSOR: But basically, what
I'm going to do is I'm going
to go through these terms
again, explain
them one more time.
You guys have accurate
clarifications or anything.
And then each in a group of
about, I think two people,
we're going to pick the game
that pretty much every one in
the class should sort of know.
Maybe they don't know the exact
rules but you know of
the game, and analyze
that game across
these different axes.
And the idea of that is that,
if you get used to this then
you can do that same thing
to your own game.
And that may shed light on how
your game is balanced, how
your game is balanced especially
between chance and
skills because we get a
topic of this class.
But also question, is our
game doing what we want
our game to be doing?
So that's the general outline.
So there's one more thing
I want to mention
before I go into that.
And Jason actually brought up
a point at the end of last
Friday was that he noticed that
our two end robots, Mr.
Roboto and Badass Mofo 600.
AUDIENCE: 610.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, 610.
PROFESSOR: It's the
upgraded version.
AUDIENCE: It started at 608 and
then there were a couple
of iterations at least
on Saturday.
PROFESSOR: One of them was
purely deterministic but
horrendously complex
in the sense that--
AUDIENCE: It wasn't
that complex.
PROFESSOR: Not in the sense
that it was difficult to
explain what it was doing but
difficult to predict what it
was going to do.
This was the one that will start
it's turn order based on
the number of hit points
that it had.
AUDIENCE: And take the number
of moves based also on the
number of hit points it had.
PROFESSOR: So it's entirely
algorithmic.
It's just following it's
root every single time.
The other one was pretty
much random, right?
Who of Mr. Roboto which
should have in a
die roll every round.
And it just hit something.
And we ended up with
the closest fight
of that day, I think.
And that does drive home the
point that at some point and
time you can get complexity
through showing
deterministic rules.
That frankly, it's as hard to
predict as pure randomness.
AUDIENCE: My card game
is like that.
PROFESSOR: Your card
game is like that?
The nice thing about that is
that if you have deterministic
rules, you can see
why it happened.
You can see why, wow I didn't
expect that to happen but I
can see why it happened.
AUDIENCE: He was so sure
he was going to win.
He was so sure he was going
to win but then we--
AUDIENCE: It did not
turn out as such.
PROFESSOR: That's a
desirable trait.
It's a lot better than just
saying, well it's a die roll.
The nice thing about die rolls
is that it does take it out of
your control.
It's kind of designed to make
it not skill based and as a
result of that, you get people
who are lagging, who are
having a harder time playing and
finding the unskilled base
way of catching up.
Which is awesome if that's
what you're going for.
And then the other one is if you
just make it deterministic
but complex enough so the
behavior is just hard to
predict, but logical ones that
are actually happens then you
kind of get the same result.
It all balances out.
Die rolls are really
easy to enter.
It's difficult to actually
come up with rules that
deterministically give you the
kind of complex that you're
really looking for.
But it's a nice thing
to go for.
Of course, to get the complexity
sometimes you need
so many rules that people
just can get bored.
It's like, wow, this is
really complicated.
I'm not sure whether I can
figure out what the next step
is going to be and then
they just give up.
That's the down side
of really complex
deterministic behavior.
It's neat that you saw both of
those playing off of each
other and them behaving
in pretty much
unpredictable ways.
And yet, getting nicely
balanced results.
So the book we leave
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So now, I'm going to be actually
deeply, deeply
plagiarizing from
Salen and Crumb.
Katie Salen in Eric Zimmerman
from Rules of Play which is
one of those big thick books I
brought in on the first day.
I'm not making you read it
because I find that book takes
three pages to explain what
could have been explained in
one, which is why I have
a whole bunch of
summaries in here.
But what that book does do is
give you very, very concrete
terms that are pretty
well accepted.
They're not necessarily among
game designers, among big
people [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
experiments.
And I've got some of those
for you to refer to.
I'll touched a little bit on
information theory on Monday.
That model of how a signal goes
from someone who wants to
send it through a transmitter
and goes through some sort of
channel, is received through
some sort of
receiver to a person.
If the person who wants to send
a signal is actually the
game, the game state, and is
transferring information to a
player, who need to get
information about what's going
on in the game in order to make
a decision then, you can
see how this applies
to game design.
And in between you have
[? moints ?].
You have the thing that prevents
you from knowing
exactly what the
game state is.
And there are certain words that
are associated with that
level of uncertainty.
Uncertainty and certainty are
two word study searches to
begin with.
So the uncertainty includes both
your inability to know
what's going to happen next due
to chance or due to really
complex behavior, as you saw
in both of the robots.
It's just the degree to which
how much the game--
all the different states the
game could take, either they
need the next turn
or throughout the
entire play of the game.
And in information theory, they
actually also use the
word information almost
interchangeably.
Unfortunately this gets kind
of confusing because people
don't actually use the word
information in that sense in
day to day.
In fact, I'm going to propose a
different way of looking at
it that also uses the word
information in a completely
different way.
So I'm actually going to
stop using the word
information for now.
I'm just going to call it
uncertainty which is pretty
much all the different things
that could happen in the game,
either in their next turn
or throughout the
entirety of the game.
Certainty is the degree to which
you have knowledge about
what could happen.
Chess board pieces could be
configured in any position but
one move after the opening,
there's only a small set that
could possibly happen.
It's probably on the order of
where only one side is moving
for the first time.
Any one of the pawns
could move 20.
20?
Yeah, the knights could
move, yeah.
So there will be 20 different
possible things.
So that's kind of the degree
of certainty that you have
among all the different states,
all the uncertainty of
this chess board.
You are certain that
it's going to be
limited to this chunk.
And your knowledge of what that
ratio is, of how much you
know could be happening, based
on what you know of the game
rules, based on your experience
of the game, based
on your skill in the game, to
the stakes that the game could
possibly take is called risk.
So you can flip it the other way
around and say that if the
uncertainty of the first turn is
20 different moves but you
are certain that the guy--
let's say I'm the opening
player, I played white and I
really only know how to make
three of those openings
effective, and the person I'm
playing against knows that
really, I only know three
openings, even if I only know
two, then that person's degree
of risk is limited to the
range of possibilities that
branch out all of
that 2 out of 20.
So that's one way that you can
sort of describe risk.
Let me see whether there's a
more technical term that I can
describe that with.
I skipped a page, didn't I?
So one thing that I want you to
think about later, actually
for the analogy step
we're going to do.
I want groups of two.
2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 15.
Mostly groups of two and one
group of three, actually,
let's just do it in
groups of three.
It will be easier that way.
And just think about and pick
a game first that you think
that you can probably mention
in this class without having
to explain to everybody
else exactly how
this game is played.
It could be a computer game.
It could be a board game.
It could be a card game,
something fairly [? modern. ?]
And I want you to think about
what are the things that, what
are all the variables that you
need to know in this game.
Doing the [? variable terms ?].
If you're doing something
like a game of Caustic
Encounter or something.
Then you can say that every
single race as a unique power
without explaining to me
every single power.
I think there are 100
races in that game.
AUDIENCE: Which game?
PROFESSOR: Caustic Encounter.
Oh it's fun.
You will get a chance to play
it later this semester.
Let's see, so think about what
are the variables that you got
to keep track of.
That's kind of the degree
of uncertainty.
That's the amount of information
that could be in
the system with that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
User does all the different
range of possibilities, all
the different things they
got to keep track.
What do you know for sure a
single playing in this game?
What do you know in your first
turn and what information do
you tend to pick up
along the way?
Let's see, so let's
start with that.
You've got just five minutes.
It doesn't have to be
an exhaustive list.
So let's just split into
groups of three.
The first activity we're going
to [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
every single one of these games
through all of these
different answers.
So I'm just going to start,
actually now, and if we run
out of time to do this, we can
always do it after class and
we can talk about it.
But we're going to go
through all of them.
So I'm going to breeze
through this.
So starting with this team then,
moving all the way over
and do you want to
just talk about--
AUDIENCE: So we decided
to go for Scrabble.
And so, in terms of variables,
you have to invent it by
individual tiles.
Their tiles are uncertain and
yours are fairly certain.
The one's on the board were
certain because they're faced.
PROFESSOR: It was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Yes.
Another variable, well I used
a variable, it's the bonus
squares on the board.
Even though there's stakes on
the board, they're variable in
terms of, as more tiles get
played, some of them become
open and some of them become
closed and you don't know
which one's are going to
be working closed.
PROFESSOR: True.
True.
Yes.
So that's something as you don't
know how that's going to
turn out during the
middle of play.
So one thing that's interesting
about word games,
especially in Scrabble and
crossword puzzles, in general,
is that a lot of them rely on
the fact that the English
language, in particular, is
actually pretty redundant.
We can take about 50% of the
letters out from a word, this
very long word, and can still
figure out what it means.
That works really well in
crossword puzzles because if
you get something like 25% of
the word, you can actually
still figure why the associated
that clue.
But Scrabble rules are made
easier so that it is now
possible for you to make
connections between disparate
characters and find a word
that's going to fit that.
Of course, part of the
problem actually--
has anyone played Words
with Friends?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, against
my brother.
PROFESSOR: This one like
Scrabble, basically, right?
The same folks who made Words
with Friends made a game
called Words with Pirates.
And I have a screen shot
here of the game
I was playing yesterday.
And basically, you have
way fewer letters.
You have h, a, r, a
lot of r's, I and
an exclamation mark.
So the number of letters that
you can get, the quantity of
the letters that you get are the
same as in Scrabble, but
the range of the different
letter you can is way lower.
With means there's a lot
less uncertainty.
Because this language, this
parrot language has so much--
I want to be very careful to
use the right word here--
so if I'm using the right word
here, this is actually a very
non-redundant language because
a, r, r, r is a word.
A, r, r, r, r is a different
word which are balanced.
So there's actually very
little redundancy.
I see a, r and I think, that
could be any number of words.
And as a result you notice that
this game of Words with
Pirates it results in an
incredibly dense word.
Of course, I can show
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
But you can't do that
with Scrabble.
Scrabble spaces go empty and get
locked out because, unless
you have an incredible knowledge
of the Scrabble
dictionary, for the most part,
you don't know those exploits
that I'm going to then slide
in an extra character.
But most people's knowledge of
English doesn't happen in that
board game.
So anyway I thought that was
specifically useful for an
illustration.
OK, so Scrabble.
All right, cool.
Next game.
AUDIENCE: We did Go Fish so
some of the variables
depending on the equation we
had were like every players
hands and the pile of cards
in the middle that
you can pick from.
We thought about some of the
uncertainty being what cards
the other player has.
And the challenge that comes out
of it is them asking what
cards they want and you
asking them for cards.
And there's noise because just
because they're asking for a
certain card can imply what they
have in their hand, but
it doesn't necessarily tell
you what they have.
PROFESSOR: Right.
It only tells you what they
don't have in their hands.
Sometimes it tells you
what they don't
have in their hands.
Sometimes they give
you a card and--
I forget the rules.
If you have multiple
threes and someone
says, got any threes?
You give them all three?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, OK.
So
AUDIENCE: Why do you
have three 3's?
You put a pair down.
That would just be dumb.
AUDIENCE: That means you're
a bad player.
PROFESSOR: For the most part in
that game that's your one
channel of finding out what
the state of the game is.
The game states what everybody
has and hasn't had.
Cool?
AUDIENCE: We did Mario Kart.
AUDIENCE: There's a lot of
uncertainty and a lot of other
things to keep track of.
So the things you can't possibly
keep track of but
that are really important in the
game are what's going to
come up when you hit an item
block and what items people
around you have.
So you might think it's safe to
bump another player but if
they have three green shells
they can activate that then
and blast you out of the map.
AUDIENCE: Another one is what
position you're in because if
you're in first place and a
blue shell hits you that's
also what position you're in,
which is what other people are
in, and stuff like that.
PROFESSOR: Right.
So the probability of being hit
by the blue shell is way
higher when you're number one.
AUDIENCE: So you gather
information through your
people range which is also a
function of, basically, where
you are on the map.
And so the information you're
giving about other players
depends on where you
are, interestingly.
If they're immediately in front
of you, you have a lot
more information than if they're
behind you, you have a
lot more information than if
they're way far away from you.
PROFESSOR: Right.
Because if they're behind you
or they're way far away from
you, you don't know what weapons
they've got ahead for
you, for instance.
You generally know what position
others people are in
but that's all you got.
So [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: And then there's
different paths and levels so
you might get someone in the
same position as you but
they're not at the same
point because they're
at a different branch.
And then, good also the
very given motives
of different cars.
So in Mario Kart 64 if you take
Bowser and you're playing
as toad, you can ram into
toad until you go flat.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
I've run into Bowser before.
AUDIENCE: So one of the little
risks that you get in Mario
Kart is that the kinds of
weapons that you get are
pretty much weighted based on
where you are in the game.
If you are at the back, you get
all the awesome weapons.
Because the game--
AUDIENCE: You get the star.
The eraser on Hero station was
way more weighted than--
PROFESSOR: Sure.
There are more obvious
versions of this.
I think Super Monkeyball
axis, too, actually.
When you're right in front, I
think, all you get is bananas,
is that the only--
AUDIENCE: In Mario Karts?
Bananas and one green shell.
That's pretty much it.
PROFESSOR: You get a
pile of junk later.
AUDIENCE: And also, the
fake mystery box.
PROFESSOR: And half way through
and half way games,
the waiting is, I'm going
to guess roughly linear.
So the basic idea is one of the
things about risk is that
every time you take up a new
weapon you are, basically,
taking a gamble about what
you're going to get.
If you're already holding a
weapon sometimes you can
choose to discard that to
pick up something new.
And I believe leader iteration
you can [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
think of that.
So now, that's one element
of risk, right?
What do I know?
I know what I got.
What else do I know?
I know what position I'm in and
I know that if I run into
this box right now and I got
rid of what I had, I could
pick up a cooler weapon.
There's a probability associated
with that and
that's, yet, another
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
One way to think of it is that
there's such an outcome, which
I said a probability associated
with it, you are
going to get a weapon.
AUDIENCE: It might be cracked.
You only really gain a sense
of the hard way from
experience of playing with it.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, it's one of
those things where your
certainty of this game goes
up as the number of play.
Cool.
AUDIENCE: We did Monopoly?
PROFESSOR: Sure.
AUDIENCE: So Monopoly basically,
what's certain is
who owns what property,
essentially.
And it's technically certain
how much money everyone has
though keeping track of all
that information on a
turn-to-turn basis
can be difficult.
So there's a little bit of
relative uncertainty just due
to the quantity of information
there.
Yes, so you gain
uncertainties.
It's actually that Monopoly has
very different opening and
end games, essentially.
Towards the start of the game
there's a lot of uncertainty
about how other players are
going to value property that
you give up.
Owen was telling me.
I wasn't even aware of this.
In Monopoly when you decide not
to purchase a property it
actually goes up to auction.
It's like I have never played
with that rule.
AUDIENCE: And it's an open
auction and so you don't know
what other people's valuation
are so each time you'd be
taking a risk if you
didn't actually
want it at that price.
AUDIENCE: That actually makes
the game more interesting.
AUDIENCE: It turns out the game
is not that much more
interesting.
Even when you have the auction
system [UNINTELLIGIBLE] it's
still pretty boring.
PROFESSOR: Can you see the like
degenerate strategies.
We will get to them.
AUDIENCE: Towards the end of the
game, basically, it's also
a lot of uncertainty about what
players are going to be--
well, these aren't part of the
rules-- but whether they're
going to be willing to trade
with you, whether you can do
things like manage to get into
jail so you can stop landing
of people's properties.
Chance is, of course, another
level of uncertainty there.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, it's weird
about the risk associated with
an auction because you kind
of know the seller.
Especially in the early game,
you have a vague idea of how
much people could possibly
bid on this.
Not more than the amount of
money that you have, although
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] a mortgage
something that he had, just to
get the cash flow at auction.
But it's one of those things
that you know is fairly built
with certainty, and
so it's true risk.
Ok?
AUDIENCE: So we chose chess.
Chess has no uncertainty
in the game.
If I would say an answer to you
would be, you don't know
what you're opponent
is going to do.
So you have to make a move
assuming he's going to do
something completely
different.
And as well as risk in the game,
the only risk is also
not knowing what your opponent's
going to do.
So he could do a series of moves
which causes you to be
in a situation where you
have to lose a piece.
That's pretty much it.
PROFESSOR: That's cool.
I would argue that not knowing
what your player is capable of
is deep in uncertainty.
And in fact, it's a
usual amount of
uncertainty in the game.
It's true that the way and how
the pieces move and where the
pieces are placed, everyone
knows that.
And we're going to
get a mixed one.
It's a game of perfect
information.
The game stake is no dice.
You know exactly what's going
in the game unless you're
playing with a five year old who
didn't put the piece right
down in the square.
AUDIENCE: So I guess something
where it would be a lot more
noise for the game would be if
you're playing something like
speed chess because then it's
like oh, you just have to
think fast and it's a lot
harder to realize
what's going on.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, that is true
because now you're limited by
your own cognitive bandwidth.
So that's true.
It doesn't change the amount
of uncertainty.
The uncertainty of the game
really is your opponent and
what's in that person's head.
The knowledge of openings and
knowledge of different moves,
whether that player has seen
something that you haven't
seen or knows of a counter that
you [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Or there's another
way to give the impression
that they know exactly how to
counter if you're doing any
kind of loading like.
PROFESSOR: Sometimes other
counting on them to do
something, and then they
don't it's like, why
didn't you do that?
I would have done that.
AUDIENCE: It's like golf where
you have to pretend like you
really look like you know
what you're doing.
PROFESSOR: Or poker.
OK, so that's one way to
look at your game.
What you know, what
you don't know.
What's the probability
of the certainty and
you know the answer.
And, of course, not as you.
As a game designer you're
thinking, what do
your players know?
What do the players not know?
What can your players do?
And a reasonable guess
of what likelihood
something is going to happen.
Also, the things going
to be true.
It's like, OK, I don't know what
card that person has but
there's an 80% probability that
that person has jacks of
higher of the trump because that
person bid on the trump.
That's a fairly good guess.
A low risk guess.
OK now, we'll go to the other
schema which is the
information systems.
Now, we're talking a little
bit about perfect and
imperfect information.
Perfect information games,
you know game state.
Everyone knows games state.
No player does not know
a game state.
Imperfect is, the information,
OK, there's something you
don't know.
Maybe it's card games in
particular because
cards have two sides.
Cards are typically used
to hold back imperfect
information.
Anyone play Stratego?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: Now that's incapable
of complete,
imperfect information
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] the game.
You know every single piece.
There's nothing random
in an entire game.
There are no die rolls.
There are no random shuffles.
AUDIENCE: So when the other guy
chooses to play where he
just places pieces, it can be
perceived as random to you.
PROFESSOR: Can be perceived
as random, it is true.
But let's get really specific
about turn around.
What it is, is that it's
actually uncertain.
It's not actually random, it's a
decision made by that player
who's got the right moves.
So, actually one, objectively,
it is not random.
It is perceived as random.
It's perceived as, effectively
random because really the
person couldn't put his pieces
anywhere within the first
three rules, or something.
So however, that's kind
of a blunt tool.
Is this game a game of perfect
information or imperfect
information.
That's a yes /no question.
Does it really tell you that
much about your game.
Asking, OK, what is actually
random and what is not
actually random but may be
perceived as that, is a
slightly better question.
Because you can think, OK, if
I isn't clear I know that's
not random but it could be
anything because of what the
other player has done.
I will treat it as random.
I might as well do all.
And when you're designing for
that player and you are doing
all your calculations, just
taking it as random.
There is a game theorist-- not
game theorist-- the game
studies scholar of games, Ceila
Pierce, who works over
at Georgia Tech.
And her proposal is that a more
useful range of questions
to ask would be what's known
to all the players?
And in a game of perfect
information everything is
known to all players.
What's only known
to one player?
What's known to the game?
Especially for a computer game,
the computer knows a lot
more about game state.
Sometimes that even comes
down to rules.
So if you've ever done Force
Battles in something like
Metriod or Castlevania,
for instance.
There are rules that every
single process is going to
react to anything that you do.
Maybe it's based on time.
Maybe it's just the
sequence of action
that are already done.
Like the EIHI robot that you
guys programmed in class
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
You don't know those rules
going into the game.
Those don't prevent you
from playing the game.
In fact, part of the fun is
figuring out the rules and
figuring what the pattern
is and explaining it.
So that's an example
of a thing that's
known to the game.
Other things that are known to
the game are actually now,
maybe that's not a good one.
I'm going to stick with my
topic because randomly
generated stuff, like there
is a shuffled deck.
Shuffled decks are one of those
things where it's a
little bit unclear about whether
the game knows what's
in that stack.
It's true that you shuffled
it, so it's randomly
generated, but once it shuffled
it, it is now in a
fixed order.
So the game knows what order
that's in even though
essentially randomly generated,
it's not randomly
generated every single turn.
But it's a good question
to ask.
Even if it's not an easy
question to answer, it's a
good question to ask what's
known to the game but not
known to the rest
of the players?
And what's this randomly
generated?
Even if the game had a brain
we would have no idea what
these things turn
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] because it's
pretty terrible.
So use those games again.
Every single one of those games
they are talking about,
what's known to all players?
What's known to one player?
What's known to the
game and what's
just randomly generated?
Go.
Shall we just do the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: So we changed
our game to poker.
Texas Hold 'em now.
So know on your test.
So it's imperfect information
because you know what's in
your hand, you know what's on
the board, but you have no
idea what anyone else has.
They can try and trick you
so it's maybe perceived.
It's perceived knowledge.
So let's say they play
a large bet.
It's perceived that they must
a good hand but it's not
necessarily accurate.
So it's not really an objective
base however, it is
subjective whenever you can
finally show your hand.
Then either you've won
or you've lost.
It's not really up for debate.
AUDIENCE: So I guess it could
also be whether you know, like
again with chess, what the other
player knows, whether
the other players know
conventional poker conventions
for folding or not.
PROFESSOR: OK, let's see.
Other things that are a lot of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] especially
poker, that is known to all
players will be things like,
what are the number of
kings in the deck?
What are deposits and what are
all the different hands that
you could make, and what
are the point values?
So that's just one example of
things that need to be known
by all players.
The assumption is that all
players know that.
Sometimes all players don't
know all these.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, memorizing the
probability is a huge endeavor.
AUDIENCE: Really big player
know the objective
probabilities in
any given hand.
AUDIENCE: Actually, a lot of
casinos will let you bring in
a card with probabilities.
PROFESSOR: Really?
I'm surprised that they'd
let you do that.
OK.
All right.
I guess they couldn't--
AUDIENCE: Even blackjack.
I'm pretty sure with blackjack,
too, you can bring
in a card with probability.
PROFESSOR: So the things that
are known to the game would
be, of course, shuffle order.
I guess this happens more in
blackjack where you've got
five decks all shuffled together
and you know there's
a number of kings and they're
in there somewhere.
So if all the kings get played
out you know there's no more
kings left in there and
then you can do
computations from there.
And one thing I want
to clarify on
objective and proceed.
Objective doesn't necessarily
mean that any one player knows
whether this is good or bad.
The idea is that if there was a
third party observer who was
not playing the game and knew
all the game stake, looking to
that, looking to the hands,
knows what's coming up, or a
computer running the game, that
person, that computer
will know the extent to which
something is good or bad.
So if you've got a hand
probabilistically you can tell
well, this is a pretty darn
good hand, or this is all
ready probabilistically
a crappy hand.
It might be good for
that game, right?
It might be just like I have one
pair, but it might be good
if nobody has anything.
AUDIENCE: But probability
you're not
gonna have a good game.
PROFESSOR: But
probabilistically you want to win.
That's why you have poker
player's saying things like,
right up until this point I was
winning and then I maybe
lost in a tie game.
But it's like, probabilistically
they were
doing everything right.
And actually, a lot of
professional players have
disparages to say well, they
were doing everything right,
sure they lost a hand, but to
them they were winning every
one up until the point
when he had to fold.
OK, next game.
AUDIENCE: The Monopoly game
was run through the all
players, one player game, etc.
All players know the board
stakes so the people that are
owners of any of the
properties and
[? what's owned ?]
by the bank.
Every given player knows the
amount of money that they
have, and also what valuation
they placed on all of their
properties, which is not known
to other people except
incidentally through
their actions.
The game knows the state of
Community chance and, I'm
sorry, Community Chest and
Chance decks, and then there's
randomly generated die rolls.
PROFESSOR: Die rolls, yeah.
I'm forgetting whether Monopoly
requires you to show
your bankroll clearly.
AUDIENCE: I think so.
I'm pretty sure.
AUDIENCE: If you want to know
how much money somebody else
has they have to tell you.
PROFESSOR: It would be an
interesting thing to look up
and see what the actual
rule on that is.
AUDIENCE: Why is the
game so popular?
PROFESSOR: Good marketing.
AUDIENCE: But then again
it's very shallow and--
AUDIENCE: It's really
familiar.
I asked friends of mine who
happily play Monopoly but
don't like to play, for
instance, Settlers, and a lot
of it is really, you
don't have to think
too much about it.
It's just an excuse to sit
around and talk with people.
There's not that much that
apparently distinguishes
somebody who's like a incredibly
good player or an
incredibly bad player.
It's got a bit of that any given
Sunday feel to it so
that you always have an
opportunity to win.
There can be dramatic swings
of fate, and all
that kind of thing.
PROFESSOR: So it's kind of
like adult Candyland.
You just go through
the motions.
AUDIENCE: But I also have
friends who are like avid
Monopoly players who really
believe that there's a deep
skill to playing Monopoly.
But I'm yet to be convinced.
PROFESSOR: There
is a strategy.
I'm not sure if it's a skill.
OK, all right, cool.
Thanks.
AUDIENCE: We did Mario
Kart, again.
Except for a couple of special
stages, in general, players
are aware of their welcome
position to other players
during the race.
AUDIENCE: Everyone
knows the maps.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: You're not sure if
you know what other people,
like what their special power
ups are, because you can look
at the screen and see
what they have.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Since you're playing to other
humans there are situations
where you definitely
know what they had.
I don't think--
AUDIENCE: That's cheating.
AUDIENCE: It's a strategy.
AUDIENCE: In Mario Kart DS you
know all your opponents items.
AUDIENCE: That's true.
That's lame.
PROFESSOR: Suddenly, on a
simultaneously multi-player
game where you're screen's
divided into four or two,
yeah, you know what your
opponent has and decide if
you're going to get
into a Kart.
Same thing for Halo.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: It actually
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
And let's see what else.
So there's you perceive it as
completely random especially
if you don't pay much attention
to it but it's more
like weighted random in
what items you get.
So that's something you'll have
to figure out as you go
along, that actually, as you're
further up, you get
worse items.
I actually think it's a good
strategy in that game to
remain in second place
for most of the race
and then go to first.
PROFESSOR: Now, the game knows
those probabilities anyway.
AUDIENCE: The game definitely
knows that.
The game also knows who's going
to get hit by a red
shell, for example, when
you launch it.
It's not entirely clear to me
as a player, when there's
multiple people in front of me,
who it's going to pick.
When I shoot a green shell back
behind me, the game knows
what's going on.
I don't.
Is that my field of view?
I hear it.
Am I getting a result?
Am I not?
PROFESSOR: The game definitely
understands the physics way
better than any human player
can possibly understand.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
For sure.
AUDIENCE: The game knows all
the player's positions and
dull leads but it doesn't know
what they're going to do or
how their going to interact
with each other.
It also doesn't presumably,
actually know what items are
coming out.
AUDIENCE: Oh, and then another
thing as players, you can
learn the patterns of some of
the hazards and be able to
predict which way to
go depending on
how you know a certain--
PROFESSOR: Just like
knowing the map.
Just like knowing the map.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
One of them are random,
actually.
AUDIENCE: Some of
them are random.
PROFESSOR: But one thing to keep
in mind about randomly
generated computers obviously,
well, maybe it's not obvious
but computers actually have a
real tough time generating
really random numbers.
AUDIENCE: It's starts
to assume.
PROFESSOR: That why they're
called pseudo-random.
So to some extent the computer
knows but it's trying really,
really hard not to know.
What's really, really useful
if you ever go into game
design for digital games, to
use that to your advantage.
Because you can use that to
reproduce problematic
situations.
It's like, yeah, write another
generator that we have
absolute control over and then
use that to your advantage
when you're trying
to find bugs.
Cool.
AUDIENCE: So just to remind
you, we did Go Fish.
So clearly every player knows
what's in his hand, knows what
pairs have been played thus
far, knows how many cards
people have, and stuff
like that.
AUDIENCE: Generally, people
should know what cards have
been given from one player
to another player.
Although, they may have
forgotten that.
Sometimes there's a situation
where most of the players
don't know which pairs
could be possibly
made at a given point.
Sometimes one player may know
that because he might have one
card and then somebody
else gave their
card to somebody else.
Something like this.
But the game definitely
knows this.
Also, the order of the deck
is randomly generated.
PROFESSOR: Yup.
And he's right at the beginning,
first turn.
AUDIENCE: So For Scrabble
all the players know the
pieces on the board.
They all know the letter
frequencies.
AUDIENCE: They don't know
what tiles they're
going to get next.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: That's randomly
generated.
AUDIENCE: What if someone knows
the dictionary, though?
Like your opponent could have
a dictionary, but not
everyone knows it.
PROFESSOR: That's the knowledge
that is both
available to one player
and to the game.
Technically the game has an
official Scrabble dictionary.
If you're playing a digital
version, they're
probably using it.
Your family, they probably
don't accept certain
two-letter words.
AUDIENCE: Until Pictionary.
AUDIENCE: They also don't know
what the other players have.
So one person only knows
what they have.
But then the other three
aren't really--
But then again, we discussed how
if you're playing with two
people you can probabilistically
figure out
what they've got.
Or, figure out what you're
going to get
next when you draw.
PROFESSOR: It's also more likely
for you to figure out
as the game goes on and tiles
get played what letters will
never come up again.
AUDIENCE: At pro levels of
Scrabble they do know exactly
what's the final set.
There's just a certain point
that you get to at which point
Scrabble players just know what
play and work out and all
the possible--
AUDIENCE: At that point do you
just keep letters that are
more likely to work with
what's in the bag.
How do you use that
to your advantage?
AUDIENCE: Well after all the
tiles are drawn you know what
your opponents have.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, you are trying
to prevent them from
using the letters that
they've got.
But most Scrabble boards,
although I don't know if all
Scrabble boards have this,
they actually show the
frequency in which the number
of tiles where I'd be given
that are in there.
So it's actually expected
that you're going to
take this into account.
It's like oh, there are only 4
h's or something like that,
and they're all out.
All right.
There's none coming
out of here.
AUDIENCE: Random other
Scrabble facts.
I found another one about
Scrabble when I was reading
about computational
Scrabble playing.
Apparently, in Scrabble
tournaments, they have a chess
court system, right, to making
sure it doesn't go over time.
And apparently, people set
aside half their time to
playing the end game
in Scrabble.
Which is the point at which
there's basically full
information.
And then, you're just sitting
there nodding out.
Like, what the best sequence
of play is to beat your
opponent so then, it
becomes like chess.
AUDIENCE: How much
time do you get?
AUDIENCE: I don't
even remember.
So, high level Scrabble is
completely different from the
Scrabble that you play.
It's crazy.
PROFESSOR: OK, all right.
We've still got some time.
Great.
Let's talk about cybernetics.
Cybernetics are, given that it
was kind of invented at MIT,
it's something that you probably
encountered there.
And we've mentioned this
a few times, the
whole idea of feedback.
I want to break this down a
little bit, though, because
feedback works.
The official sense of feedback,
and this theory of
cybernetic systems as written by
Norbert Wiener back in the
40's, I think, is that there is
a sensor, something which
measures what the
system is doing.
There is a comparative, which
was, in his era, was that
machine, and in our era is
probably a rule, a logic, a
statement, that compares this
against some sort of set value
or some sort of rule and decides
to take action--
an activator.
And you can think of this this
way, all as your sensor is the
variable that you're
looking at.
Or, a set of collection
of variables that
you're looking at.
So what are you looking at?
Your comparable is a rule that
you're comparing against.
I'm trying to pick a game that
no one has mentioned here, so
far, that has a good
few facts system.
Let's say I played a version of
Cops and Robbers as a kid
where every time the cop caught
a robber, the robber
would have to go into a jail
area and put him down until
someone tagged him.
Someone from the robber
team tagged him.
And the basic idea is that the
fewer people there are, and a
few of us humanly are playing
in a big space, the more
robbers there are in jail,
the easier it is
for a robber to run.
Actually, because they
have more freedom.
Sure, there are more cops to any
given robbers so that you
can do flagging [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
But one of the variables that
we're looking at are how many
people are trying to
be in the jail.
And an activator is basically
what's the rule or what's the
game dynamic that comes
with the play.
So that's a kind of interesting
things about the
Cops and Robbers situation.
One had more space to run when
all my buddies are in jail but
there are a lot more cops
going after me, and that
actually means that it's easier
for him to flag me even
though I had more
space to run.
So it goes up.
Both are negative and a positive
feedback system.
More space to run is actually
a negative feedback system.
And how you tell the
difference is is it
stabilizing to my state or is
it cumulative to my state.
And it's stabilizing, which
means I'm doing badly, my
team's doing badly but this
is now giving me an edge.
Or, I'm doing really well and
this is really crappy.
Mario Kart is a type of these.
Those are negative feedback.
Those are things that basically
reduce the gap
between the best and the people
who are doing well and
the people who aren't
doing well.
Positive feedback
is cumulative.
They're doing well, they're
going to do a bit better.
So the cops have got everybody
but one and now
it's a 5 to 1 game.
That's a positive feedback
system because now they can do
tactics as opposed to everyone
going after someone separate.
And you have these two feedback
views working together.
There are tons of
these in games.
Games aren't really the kind
of closed systems that
cybernetics were actually
originally designed to handle.
In fact, only a few systems are
digital systems in that
way and games are actually
better than most.
But let's talk about what's
in all the games
we're talking about.
What are some of the negative
feedback you experience, and
some of the positive feedback
you experienced.
Mario Kart team, you got way
too easy [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Think of some other game.
AUDIENCE: Wait, that's
what I didn't know.
The AI automatically
goes faster.
There's a huge gap.
PROFESSOR: That's more than just
a Mario Kart, actually.
That's a lot of racing games.
AUDIENCE: Also, when if you're
playing like the Grand Prix
there's always three computers
that are always better than
everyone else, then all
the rest of them.
So they will always be the ones
that are in the top four.
Like they're in the
top, always.
PROFESSOR: Mario Kart team,
pick a different game.
Go through all of the games.
Think about chess.
Actually, chess might actually
be an interesting one for you.
AUDIENCE: No, but shot
chess, where you
retake the shot after--
PROFESSOR: Shot chess?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, shot chess.
PROFESSOR: That gets too easy.
AUDIENCE: Well, it tends
to be negative.
It can be negative feedback but
there's also the method of
doing it where there's
positive feedback.
It depends on how you play.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Winner takes any drinking
game, pretty much.
PROFESSOR: It depends on what
your goals are, right?
AUDIENCE: Such that you'd have
it that whenever you take a
piece you have to drink
that piece.
But then there's also whenever
you take a piece you opponent
has to drink a piece.
So it can either be negative or
positive feedback depending
on how you play.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, but let's pick
a version of the game.
Ideally, pick the same game but
if it's too boring pick
something else.
OK, so let's start from
somewhere in the middle which
and I think is this
group right here.
AUDIENCE: So we took a pretty
easy one but it's pretty like
mathematical feedback.
We did War.
OK, statistically if you're
winning, every time you win
you're lowering the value
of your cards.
AUDIENCE: You had to average
the value to your deck.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So mathematically it's
negative feedback.
PROFESSOR: So, it's positive
feedback, right?
AUDIENCE: Negative.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] the negative
impact is you're lowering the
average value of what's
in your deck.
PROFESSOR: So which makes
it harder for
you to keep do winning.
AUDIENCE: Exactly.
PROFESSOR: So that's just
negative feedback.
Any positive feedback?
AUDIENCE: The small positive
feedback would be insofar as
you can't win unless you
get all the cards.
So that's winning hands gets
you more cards, gets you
closer to winning.
AUDIENCE: The more cards
you have the
closer you are to winning.
AUDIENCE: That's like saying,
and you get with points, the
more points you get, you're
closer to winning.
Therefore, positive feedback.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, I guess
it does count.
AUDIENCE: Logically it works,
but it's kind of a guess.
AUDIENCE: Well the only other
one is if you have a war then
you win those three extra cards
and depending on what
they are it could be positive
or negative.
PROFESSOR: OK.
All right.
Which way should we go?
This way.
AUDIENCE: We switched
to Settlers.
We got a bunch of
feedback loops.
Obviously, the more points you
get, as soon as the points are
cities and settlements, then
the more resources you're
going to get in the future and
the more points you can build.
So potentially one player just
has so much stuff that he can
just do whatever he wants to.
PROFESSOR: And that's
positive?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
There's also negative feedback
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
like it censors the relative
prices of resources.
The more one resource is worth
at the time, each person, the
other one's the more people try
to build on that resource
brick, then the less that
resource will be
worth in the future.
So, over the long term they tend
to balance out instead of
having one go rapidly
out of control.
PROFESSOR: Think
about that one.
That's interesting.
AUDIENCE: Also, the more, this
isn't exactly feedback, but
the more, the better you're
doing, the less likely people
are going to try to trick
you somewhere.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
That, in my opinion, is the
biggest negative feedback in
the entire game.
If you're in the lead,
everyone hates you.
And then you have eventually
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: There's also if he had
a bunch of resources, like
if you had a bunch of cities on
a resource and if someone
draws a six then you end up
getting six resources from a
tile then that's higher
probability that if someone
rolls a seven, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
So I guess that's negative
feedback, too.
PROFESSOR: Well your going to
seven and losing your cards
mechanic is very much
a negative feedback.
I'm so rich!
Now, I'm not so rich.
What kind of poor
is this, ha, ha.
I still could have seen
them [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
That's negative feedback.
A couple of things about
negative feedback to keep in
mind is that negative
feedback does tend
to make games longer.
It sort of staves off the ending
of the game because
obviously, the difference
between the people in the lead
and people not in the lead
narrow it to the point that
sometimes puts it back
in connection again.
And positive feedback tends
to make things end sooner.
OK, all right.
Now, next team.
AUDIENCE: So in Scrabble, the
main one we came up with was
that if you play a long word,
you get a lot of points and
you also get a lot of tiles
which gives you the
opportunity the next turn to
play more points and get more
tiles played.
PROFESSOR: Oh, yeah.
AUDIENCE: There's also that the
more tiles you play, the
less tiles there
are available.
So that's kind of negative.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
It's both positive
and negative.
That was proposed.
PROFESSOR: Near the end, yeah,
it becomes negative feedback.
You possibly end up with
just fewer tiles.
That's true.
Any other negative
loops in there?
AUDIENCE: Well we tried to
make it into a shot deal.
Yeah, every time you play a
bigger word it's easier for
someone else to play
a word off of that.
That's negative feedback.
PROFESSOR: That's an interesting
thing because
that's actually counter examples
to a point that was
made by Eric Zimmerman.
Because he argues that positive
feedback actually
magnifies early successes.
And negative feedback tends
to magnify big ones.
Just like in Mario Kart, it's
great to be the second place
because if you do a late game
success that propels you to
first place just as
the game ends.
Whereas, some of the examples
that we've been hearing on all
the feedback, if you manage to
be the first one to build a
city in Settlers, that tends to
perpetuate your success for
the rest of the game.
The game isn't quite as
predictable as that but it's
designed that way, at least.
But that's a very, very good
example of you've got this
negative feedback near the end
of the game where you have a
success by playing all
of your tiles but the
bag is almost empty.
So now, you are not getting,
not whether you are or not
getting an advantage, that
late game success isn't
translating into
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Still, it's as a general rule,
if you aren't dealing with a
limited resource, like tiles,
then we do this situation
where a positive feedback game,
a positive feedback loop
is going to have to find
early successes.
And negative feedback make
late successes more hard.
AUDIENCE: So we're basically,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
StarCraft.
But I think with StarCraft was
some of the obvious positive
feedback is that the more a
worker was built and then the
more mineral you can get.
The more mineral's gathered
you can get more troops.
PROFESSOR: The more workers
you build the
more cash you get.
The more cash you get the more
workers you can build.
That's [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Another positive
feedback loop is the more that
you conquer your opponents, the
harder it is for them to
build up and finance you
while the easier it is
for you to beat them.
On it the other hand-- do you
want do negative feedback?
AUDIENCE: I don't think
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: The only thing with
positive feedback is just like
emphasized a lot of the
earlier game strategy.
AUDIENCE: So a negative feedback
loop in StarCraft
would be the faster you, the
more you expand your
territories the harder it is for
you to defend because your
spraying half your resources,
and the more friends you have,
so the easier it is for your
opponents to attack you.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
We were having that little
discussion earlier and finding
other negative feedback
in this was
kind of tricky, actually.
AUDIENCE: Another one that
I thought of was the more
research that you do, the less
resources you have for
building units or workers
and such.
And so you have to decide.
I mean, your power will be units
but you may have less to
actually build those units.
And probably not really--
it's a very small
negative loop.
AUDIENCE: Another thing, too,
the more shoots you have, the
less attention you can give
to all the [? children. ?]
So it's harder to manage.
AUDIENCE: The less effectively
use them.
PROFESSOR: The more different
screens you've got to keep
your eye on makes it--
AUDIENCE: That's the great thing
about the control wand.
It's like one, go here.
Two, go here.
Three, go here.
One thing a team gives, though,
is there's a huge
positive feedback.
If you're doing 3D, if you take
out one of them and then
it's so much easier.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Then you have a bunch
of risk because what
happens if you try taking
out one person?
Then, you fail and now you're
weak but then they have a lot
more troops.
AUDIENCE: So in keeping in
comparison with Warcraft III
which didn't have built-in
negative feedback where if
your army gets past a certain
size and it costs more, at
least you can get
taxed income.
Yeah.
I don't know if you guys
know about this.
But basically, think like
StarCraft but then you have a
food count that once you get
past a certain food count,
each of your peons brings in
less gold from the farm.
I'm sorry, from the gold mine.
And it gets even worse the
more troops you get.
So you're kind of punished
for being too far ahead.
PROFESSOR: That's a very
key negative feedback.
AUDIENCE: This isn't a strict
thing to keep up with but it's
interesting to look at the
resource management.
Basically investing in units
that bring in more resources
or investing in other units that
you're fighting are all
different positive
feedback loops.
And you can view not investing
as negative feedback loops in
those areas.
Although, it's not really
completely true.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
are trying to think of
that as negative
feedback but you're right.
They are different positive
feedback groups.
They work very differently.
Winning a battle makes
it easier for you
to win later battles.
But building more workers makes
it easier for you to go
more units.
AUDIENCE: Kind of in a not
apparent positive feedback
issue with StarCraft upgrading
a Zealot's attack power by
just one greatly increases its
efficiency because now two
attacks will take
down a Zealot.
Where before it would
be three attacks--
PROFESSOR: I don't want to get
into that much detail.
Let's go onto the next game.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: So, let's just say,
Crunch we can have a bigger
workforce and they're returning
to pay for that.
So you get more money for your
workforce but you still have
to pay for that.
That's negative feedback.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
That's a killer.
AUDIENCE: It turns out in
Monopoly if you have a lot of
money, and a lot of stuff, which
people then land on,
which gives you more money.
AUDIENCE: With what?
AUDIENCE: That's top secret
secret strategy.
I mean, Monopoly is to buy lots
of stuff and then have
people land on it so you
can get more money.
AUDIENCE: So this one little
negative feedback into,
actually two, for the
income tax and--
AUDIENCE: --repairs on property
and the like.
AUDIENCE: So several thousand
dollars to build hotels.
AUDIENCE: Our actual government
is like that, too.
PROFESSOR: So it patterns out
to real life but then again,
so is the whole of the
Monopoly game.
The whole of the Monopoly game
is about real life land
ownership monopoly in Atlantic
City, I believe.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: It's Atlantic City.
PROFESSOR: So yeah.
And that gives us a good segue
into degenerate strategies.
OK.
All right.
So I'll go into that
a little bit.
But maybe I'll get at what
we did on Wednesday.
But Wednesday we're going to
focus that mostly on play
testing your game.
If we have no time for anything
else, we are play
testing your game.
And so bring in your games.
Bring in your cards.
Make sure your cards are
ready before class.
Don't be writing stuff.
Try not to be changing stuff
right up to another class.
Sometimes you might be feeling
the pressure to do that.
Try to be ready before
class starts.
And try to show up right at
the beginning of class.
Because it will really, really
suck if you finish play
testing, if you finish play
testing someone else's game
and that team doesn't
have enough time
to play test yours.
OK, and when it may happen
and that will suck.
So let's try to start that right
on time next Wednesday.
Thank you.