The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Welcome back.
Thanks for not dropping
the class yet.
AUDIENCE: I'm going to
do that right now.
PROFESSOR: Funny you
mention that.
Let's see, just a reminder.
Actually one big reminder for
folks who weren't here on
Friday is that we swapped around
Friday and Monday's--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I think
17th and the
20th have been swapped.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: In terms of reading
that we're going
to do in the class.
PROFESSOR: So, we're still
going to be playing
the games on Friday.
But the brainstorming activity
that we had scheduled for
Monday is going to be on
this Friday instead.
And then later on
in the course.
Anyone manage to get through
the reading?
Let's see, where should
we start.
So there was a Doug Church
article that was on Gamasutra.
And if you're familiar with
Gamasutra, or if you're not
actually, it's a fairly
well-read news and industry
news blog for the video
game industry.
That particular article, I
think, was originally written
not for the website but for
the magazine that the
associated company publishes,
the Game Developer magazine.
And Doug Church is actually
an MIT alum.
The other article that was
read, Mark [INAUDIBLE],
they're both MIT alums.
So that's one thing.
So Doug Church proposes
a set of tools.
And remember what
they're called?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So, and Mark's
framework which is--
AUDIENCE: M-A-D?
PROFESSOR: And we covered
mechanics
and dynamics on Friday.
And today we have a little
bit of time to talk about
aesthetics.
But the reason why these two
essays were put right next to
each other was MDA is an example
of what Doug Church
was describing as [INAUDIBLE].
In fact, at the time when MDA
came out it was pretty much
the only one that caught on.
Everybody, all of the problems
that Doug Church lays out in
his article about the problems
that we don't have a
vocabulary, a consistent
vocabulary, to talk about our
craft and thus we can't
actually deal with it.
And thus we need some formal
tools that everyone uses.
Unfortunately not much
has caught on.
MDA being one of the
few that has.
For a number of different
reasons.
First of all, it actually
is a useful framework.
You can think of many, many,
ways to properly look at games
but for a designer you need to
think of something where you
can actually apply it to help
improve your games.
And MDA actually gives you a
reason why design is hard.
So if nothing else, designers
like it a lot because it says
this is why their job is hard.
The reason being, you get to
control the mechanics.
But that's not what
you're going for.
You're not going for really
interesting mechanics.
They're going for really
interesting aesthetics.
They're going for a fun,
engaging, play experience.
There are mock--
in the MDA paper, this lists
eight kinds of fun.
And I've asked him about this
when we give this presentation
here in MIT.
Those eight were not meant
to be comprehensive.
They were meant to be, these
are the eight that I could
think of at the time.
After this I'm going
for [INAUDIBLE]
that's a bouquet of different
kinds of fun.
Different kinds of experiences
that people are trying to get
out of playing games.
That's what a game designer
is trying to get.
The only problem is that a game
designer doesn't actually
control that experience.
The game designer only gets
to upload mechanics.
Depending on what company you
are, maybe you have the title
of game designer but you're
also in charge of the art.
You're actually also the
lead programmer.
It's possible that you also have
more control over things
than just the mechanics.
But most designers, mechanics
is what the job still is.
So they write the rules, the
rules interact in some sort of
like ridiculously hard to
predict way, and then you get
the experience of playing
the game, the aesthetic.
And you hope that's what
you were going for.
It usually isn't.
And then you make a change to
the mechanics and try again.
The nice thing about that, is
that works really well with
the rate of design.
In fact, without a rate of
design it becomes really hard
to control this kind
of process.
Because basically, we are two
orders removed from the
experience that you're
trying to create.
It's like trying to draw on a
piece of paper where not only
can you not see the paper that
you're drawing on, you're also
controlling the brush or the
pencil tied to a stick, or
something like that,
blindfolded.
That's kind of what making
game designs are like.
So that's the experience of
the game design side.
You can control the mechanics,
and they're going towards some
sort of aesthetic.
And from the other side, the
player is experiencing some
kind of aesthetic and they can
sort of work their way back.
It's like, I'm getting this
kind of experience.
Why am I getting this
kind of experience?
If you've got a particularly
insightful game player, maybe
they're taking CMS.300
Introduction to Video Games,
and you're analyzing games.
And you're trying to say,
how did we get here?
If anything in this class,
you're going to be
doing that a lot.
This game, Heroes Might and
Magic 3 for instance, has--
give me a particularly--
a sensation.
Describe a sensation that you
got when you were playing that
game, that you recall.
AUDIENCE: Strategic.
Out-smarting.
To saying to friends.
Outsmart them.
Stump me.
PROFESSOR: Seem smart, make you
have to think really hard
and everything.
So then you think about
what dynamics might
have resulted in that.
AUDIENCE: Fog of War.
PROFESSOR: For you to figure
out is behind the
areas you can't see.
But it has some information
that you can see that will
give you clues.
And then, Fog of War might
already be a mechanic.
The idea of, there is
information that you can
deduce even though you can't
actually see it.
And there's some probability of
getting it right based on
their experience with games.
Fog of War being one game
that gets you there.
So you can analyze
it backwards.
And figure out, OK that's one
thing Fog of War gets you.
Sometimes Fog of War
just confuses you.
There could be anything
behind this corner.
I mean technically, Final
Fantasy random combat system
is like Fog of War.
I don't know if there is a
random encounter here, I will
walk into it.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: That's where Unix
merger is complete--
Plan to the classic Final
Fantasy one with slides and
the classic [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: But there is
actually a problem--
actually, I don't need
to write this down.
There is a problem with--
well, maybe it's
not a problem.
There is an issue that I
have with [INAUDIBLE].
Doug Church uses it specifically
to say, well it
should be sort of a serious
business right?
It's formal with a capital F.
We're not talking about how
cool this game is, we want
to be very precise in our
vocabulary.
We want to treat it like a
serious business with a
capital S, capital B.
However, the other assumption
with the word formal comes
from [INAUDIBLE].
You are thinking about
the form of the game.
In a way that if you were
trying to apply the same
technique to talk about art
you'd be talking about the
form of visual art.
The form of cinema.
And that is actually a very
narrow way to look at
something, at a topic, that
is as broad as a game.
It is as if we were trying
to analyze something like
[INAUDIBLE]
and completely ignoring the fact
that you were playing it
with friends from
French class.
That would be an example of,
well that had nothing to do
with the game.
Well actually, it probably had
a lot to do with how you
experienced the game.
Play, that's the
rules of chess.
And you could just look
at the game based on
the rules of chess.
You could also look at
the history of chess.
You could also look at who
you're playing it against.
Are you playing against
a random person or
against your dad?
Big difference, or in
my case my mom.
Are you playing it in a club?
Are you playing it against the
chess master in Harvard Square
or something like that?
What does this game mean?
Are you using the game
metaphorically in speech?
My opponent wasn't checking
his position.
Doesn't necessarily mean that
you were playing chess with
someone else in order to
get your point across.
There's a whole range of
different ways that you can
look at games, even as a game
designer, that isn't
specifically formalist.
That isn't specifically
just looking at
the form of the game.
Just understanding what context
people are going to be
playing the game in.
While a lot of the games that
you guys are going to be
designing this semester,
specifically in this class,
you have to think about the fact
that a lot of these games
are actually going to be played
by your instructors.
Are going to be played in a
setting very similar to this
by your colleagues.
Are probably going to end up
being tested by dorm mates,
fraternity friends, folks
around campus.
And all that is going to vividly
influence the kind of
game that you make.
For better or worse, you are
pretty much making a game for
an MIT audience.
I am trying to change that
a little bit for the last
assignment.
But keep in mind that's not
necessarily every single game
that you're going to
make in the future.
And that shouldn't be.
But, knowing that, you can try
to cater to the audience that
you've got.
That has very little, in some
ways, this is going to effect
the design decisions that
you make in your game.
What will be perfectly
acceptable to a competitive
MIT audience might not be
perfectly acceptable to your
average working buyer in Target
or something like that.
And so what may be a perfectly
engrossing game, mechanic,
dynamic, aesthetic experience,
that you will get.
But just like looking at the
formal aspects of one game,
this will be really cool if you
understood the mechanic,
played it out in the way the
creator designed the dynamic
to give you the aesthetic
experience.
But if you don't have the
standard context when you're
playing the game, as an example,
then your player may
not even get that far.
Your player may look at your
game and say this game is not
for me and just walk away.
It might mean that you might--
I'm thinking of things like we
just had this good discussion
over lunch about the sort of
games that you find on
Facebook for instance.
And a lot of social games--
I might have already made this
point, but it has been argued
that social games aren't
all that social.
All you do is really beg
and scam your friends.
That's the whole point--
In many ways, it's also the same
to your friends who are
doing the same thing.
And we may be separated by
time, and separated by
distance, we're all doing
the same thing.
And we could be playing this
game, we could be talking
about a show that we are
watching in our apartments and
get to discuss it, but in many
ways this is just me telling
you we're doing the same thing,
that we're part of the
same group.
And that serves a function that
has almost, that really
doesn't have anything to do with
the formal analysis of
how a game mechanic works, but
it's still incredibly crucial
to the popularity
of those games.
So keep that in mind,
that even though
Church makes his point--
I think a lot of designers
actually ignore that when you
read his essay--
that it's only one
set of tools.
The formal tools are only
one set of tools, even.
That our tools at looking at
games culturally, personally,
and other things that video
games cast into light--
that will effect how people
experience a game and how much
pleasure they're going
to get out of a game.
To understand video games doing
what it does right?
That aren't, that don't have
anything to do, necessarily,
with just by looking at
the self-contained
system of the game.
Just as a side note, how many of
you folks have heard of the
narrative versus ludology
debate?
How many of you are
sick of this?
I'm sick of it too.
But I bring it up for one
reason, there is an
interesting case that if you
actually look at narratology
as a study and ludology
as a study, they're
both formalist studies.
In fact, they're more accurate
more precisely, they're both
structuralist.
If you look at philosophies as a
sub-sect of formalism, or at
least a more recent version of
it, they're both basically
focused on these are the
elements of this art form.
And this is how they
interact to produce
some sort of effect.
And all that matters is what's
contained in this art form.
What's outside this art
form doesn't matter.
That's what narratology
does for stories.
That's what ludology
does for games.
That's, in fact, probably why
most people who study games
have walked away from ludology
because it's not that
interesting.
You just study what's
inside a system.
People want to see
what's outside.
And so when you compare
structuralistic and
structuralism wins
that's one case.
And you only have, you may not
realize that you're actually
looking at your game through
a very, very, narrow lens.
So I'm trying to broaden
the range of
tools that you've got.
This class is going to give
you a small set of them.
And it's not by any means the
be all and end all of every
single way and that you
can look at a game.
And again, you're not just
restricted to the tools that I
specifically teach you
in this class.
So keep looking out for
all the new ones.
Let's see.
Any questions so far?
That was my rant.
OK, no more ranting.
We have an activity.
Do you want to run through?
GUEST SPEAKER: OK I'm going to
pass around-- this is my
crappy race game.
So you're going to be getting
one copy per pair.
There's also some nifty
set of dice.
You'll need one copy
per, one die per.
And then, each person's
going to need three
of these poker chips.
It doesn't matter the color
so just grab three.
You're each going to need a
marker to indicate yourself.
And I recommend just grabbing
any given value--
There should be more
than enough copies.
So you only need one
board per group.
PROFESSOR: So one die for
every two people?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, one
of those six-sided
die for every two.
And then you need markers
for yourselves
and then bonus markers.
And that's what the poker
chips are for.
So keep the poker chips
circulating.
AUDIENCE: Three per person?
GUEST SPEAKER: Three
per person.
AUDIENCE: One playing
piece per person.
GUEST SPEAKER: You can use
coins, you can use die--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
paper, whatever you want.
PROFESSOR: So we have three
of the important questions
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: How many [INAUDIBLE]
take back?
GUEST SPEAKER: If you need
markers for yourself, you can
try one of the multi-sided
polyhedral dice over here.
I guess--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: OK, OK, what now?
GUEST SPEAKER: I'm more
well-versed in the--
GUEST SPEAKER: The
die is to roll
GUEST SPEAKER: OK, so can
everyone hold on for a second?
So what we're going to ask you
to do is just play through
this game a couple times?
Then we're going to come back
and apply the MDA framework to
the game itself.
And then if we have time, I
think we're going to spend
some time tweaking it?
OK, cool.
So we'll interrupt you guys--
actually, ten minutes
probably.
It's a pretty quick game.
This has sort of gone flat.
So what we'd kind of like
to do is hear about--
I guess we'll just go around
the room in pairs
and ask you to talk.
Or do you want a minute to talk,
to apply MDA to this and
focus on some things?
So I'm not like calling
anyone on the spot.
PROFESSOR: Anybody want to
volunteer what, how they felt?
What was the aesthetic
of this game?
AUDIENCE: There is none.
GUEST SPEAKER: There's
no emotional affect.
PROFESSOR: It felt
competitive.
AUDIENCE: The thing is, it's
a very simple aesthetic.
So in the paper they say you're
going to the pleasure
of using the aesthetic, but here
you go straight to the
mechanic and you're wondering
about it.
PROFESSOR: You, it definitely
is easy especially because
especially for board games the
mechanics are written down
right in front of you,
it's really easy
when you look at that.
But how did you feel while you
were playing this game?
AUDIENCE: There was a
sense of tension.
There was maybe a sense of
[INAUDIBLE] perhaps?
There was a sense of--
I mean there was the
intellectual challenge of
working out is there
really a meaningful
decision to be made here?
And if there is, what is
the correct decision?
PROFESSOR: So thinking
can I optimize this?
Especially with this crowd, I
think there was an immediate
try to figure out what
the right thing is.
And I know you were trying
to figure it out.
AUDIENCE: I think he correctly
figured it out.
PROFESSOR: So is there an
optimal way to play this game?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, OK, so
if you're losing--
If you keep putting
tokens down you're
going to lose anyway.
So you want to be rolling
in order to
increase the variance.
And if you're winning, you want
to be putting tokens down
in order to move the variance.
You can imagine if it's
like a distribution.
If you're below the winning line
you want to widen it out
as much as possible so as much
of that distribution is above
the winning line.
And if you're above the winning
line you want it to be
as narrow as possible so you
stay above the winning line.
PROFESSOR: So your strategy is
basically based on what's the
currency of the game.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, until the last
turn where obviously you don't
want to put a token down if
you're two from the end.
As long as no one can win on
this turn, if I'm behind him
I'm rolling the die.
And if I'm ahead of him I'm
putting down a token.
GUEST SPEAKER: Did anyone prefer
a strategy before you
started thinking about what
was the best one?
AUDIENCE: I'm too lazy
to use the tokens
so I just keep rolling.
GUEST SPEAKER: And that's
also part of the
aesthetic of it right?
You just happen to prefer
the die roll.
AUDIENCE: On the first three
spaces you should be getting
the average if you
roll [INAUDIBLE]
if you put a token down.
I personally like being
conservative.
PROFESSOR: You win
no matter what.
GUEST SPEAKER: I'm sorry what?
AUDIENCE: That's more
exciting because it
does different things.
AUDIENCE: The token gives you
the illusion that you're
actually playing.
PROFESSOR: Did anyone like get
in the situation where they
are really far behind in
a different color?
AUDIENCE: No.
PROFESSOR: The actual
difference--
one of the things that you do
get in this game is the
perceived distance
between players.
It's actually not that far.
If the one behind actually
has to still get in.
I think people refer
to this as the
American Gladiators effect.
You know how, American
Gladiators--
actually, is this your example
that I'm stealing?
GUEST SPEAKER: I don't
remember, honestly.
PROFESSOR: Someone I can't
help from stealing.
GUEST SPEAKER: I think it's in
the book at some point, but I
think we had applied
it to this.
AUDIENCE: Plagiarism!
PROFESSOR: Yes, yes,
well I'm crediting
someone for this question.
Citation needed.
The basic idea being--
who's seen American
Gladiators?
GUEST SPEAKER: They
might be too old.
AUDIENCE: No, no, we had
American Gladiators.
AUDIENCE: I've never--
I don't know what it is.
PROFESSOR: OK, there are also
a number of Japanese game
shows which are similar
to this.
The basic idea of American
Gladiators is that it's
basically an obstacle
course where the
obstacles are people.
Happen to be these athletic
dudes and women who are either
pummeling you with waffle sticks
or shooting tennis
balls at you out of a gun
and stuff like that.
And you basically have to get
from the beginning to the end
faster than the other team.
Actually, faster than
the other player.
So it's two regular dudes and a
whole bunch of athletes who
are throwing things at you.
Every time you get hit you have
to go back a little bit.
But the thing about American
Gladiators is that you have
this long obstacle course.
In fact, this was one
of the events.
This was always the final event
of the entire TV show.
Is that, you will have two
people doing the same course.
They will have to climb up a
wall and then they will have
to go down a zip line.
GUEST SPEAKER: But it was a
cargo net specifically.
So it was really difficult
to climb up it.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, the big
webbing kind of thing.
It was like climbing the
rigging off a ship.
It was really, really,
difficult.
So what happens is that if you
have two people who are
really, really, far apart--
one person is way ahead--
and that person starts climbing
the cargo net?
It takes that person forever to
get to the end of the cargo
net, because climbing up cargo
net is really, really, hard no
matter who you are.
That gives the person behind
plenty of time to catch up and
start climbing the cargo net.
But then, the person who was the
leader in the first place
hits the zip line.
And all of a sudden there's a
huge increase in distance.
So this whole idea that
they never really
were all that far--
they never really changed
their position.
For most Gladiators games the
winner has already been
decided by their points.
Because the first person who
reaches the cargo net tends to
win the match.
But it looks like the lead just
shrank because suddenly
you've got both of them
in one camera shot.
And then you've got
that cute--
mom likes to call that
dramatic tension.
Which I think is a better
description than it's other
term for the same thing
which is drama.
Because it's not drama.
It' s just tension really.
But that's an aesthetic.
You're going for the aesthetic
of tension and coming up with
a game that makes you feel like
the fight is closer than
it actually is.
Or allowing someone to close the
gap quickly because, many
of you have pointed about, these
things probabilistically
mean exactly the same
thing as a die roll.
Let's see.
But the ability to increase a
awkward gap to open up and
then to close, that's
actually a dynamic.
That's actually a result of a
number of different rules that
are in the particular
of the game.
It's not written down that
it's going to happen.
But it's pretty much going to
happen if you have two people
playing those particular
strategies, and one thing that
happens pretty often.
What are the constraints that
you're seeing in the design of
this game here?
What did this game have to do in
order for it to be a viable
in-class exercise?
AUDIENCE: Fit on a
sheet of paper.
PROFESSOR: Fit on a
That's a huge one actually.
Because first of all,
it limits how many
spaces you've got.
Assuming everyone's using
something like a die or a coin
or something.
GUEST SPEAKER: I mean, you can
laugh at that but it's
literally how it went.
I wanted it to fit on a sheet of
paper and the spaces had to
accommodate a die.
So the number of spaces
is a result of that.
AUDIENCE: It was almost
like an accident.
PROFESSOR: Well you probably
could have fit a few more
squares in there.
GUEST SPEAKER: Probably, but
you place some margins.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: The rules
have to fit on one
sheet of paper as well.
So the rules can't be
that complicated.
PROFESSOR: Most of these rules
are single sentences for the
most part, because we are
more than [INAUDIBLE].
It had to be quick.
It had to work within
10 minutes.
In fact, it had to work so you
get through a few games within
10 minutes.
Anyone only manage to
get through one?
AUDIENCE: That'd
be really hard.
PROFESSOR: So different
aesthetics.
So, this game tries to get
really, really, tense.
But obviously, the decisions
that you're actually making in
this game is minimal.
You get to say, well if you are
already losing, that has
[INAUDIBLE].
One rational thing to do.
But if you were playing this
game, as Jason recommended, if
I were playing this game against
myself there really is
no optimal strategy.
I could pick two different
strategies for each side.
AUDIENCE: It's whoever plays
first basically.
Whoever plays first is by
default going to win.
PROFESSOR: On average.
AUDIENCE: I won every
game but one.
I did bad rolling dice.
GUEST SPEAKER: Because if
you roll them now--
PROFESSOR: So I would like
actually, folks to try mixing
this up a little bit.
Pick a rule in here, any
rule, and alter it.
You can do things like
adding more squares.
You can change the
movement chart.
One idea that I had, and someone
was thinking probably
more recent than me, which is
what happens if you use the
higher of two dice rolls
instead of just one?
[INAUDIBLE] to the
probability.
Play around with that.
See what that feels like.
And if that feels just boring
try doing something else.
So we've got 15 minutes?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah,
that's reasonable.
PROFESSOR: And then, you'll tell
the class about what you
changed and how that changed
the feeling of the game.
Cool?
So, every two people,
work with a team.
Explain how your game, how your
version works, and have
the other group play
it and vice versa.
And what we're going to do once
everyone's done, you will
tell the class what
you felt the other
group's game felt like.
So let someone else figure out
what your game aesthetic is.
So, does any team want to just
go first in describing the
other team's game?
OK, starting with you.
AUDIENCE: Do you want
us to describe
the rules they changed?
PROFESSOR: Uh, sure.
AUDIENCE: Or just say--
the main change in this version
was that it's modular.
So you have to land exactly
on the end or
otherwise you wrap around.
It changed the aesthetic a lot
because it stopped being a
race against your opponent and
became more of trying to
figure out how you can use your
tokens to precision just
hit the end.
PROFESSOR: Oh, OK.
AUDIENCE: More methodical
and thoughtful.
You decide whether or not you're
going to stockpile
tokens to give you more winning
squares and then you
just waited until you landed
on a winning square.
PROFESSOR: So you get
a dis-computational
motive to the game?
AUDIENCE: It was not
as competitive.
AUDIENCE: So one of the
discussions we had was, what
if you had three tokens you
could just get to the end.
Because we made our tokens
move four spaces.
PROFESSOR: OK.
AUDIENCE: But I just realized,
you have to do the die roll
after that.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Oh, yeah.
AUDIENCE: They had a really
creative role where
they had a 10 here.
So it goes from 0 to 9.
And you roll under a cup and
that's the number of spaces
away from the end.
So from 0 to 9 that the
winning point is.
And at your turn you can either
play normally or you
can check to see where
the winning point is.
If you've won, that triggers
you winning.
But you cannot win unless you
physically check and confirm
that you've won.
So it eats up a turn, but it
could be that after two rolls
of two and this was
a nine you've won.
And it was a lot of fun
basically because we had to
figure out the optimal strategy
but it was just fun.
PROFESSOR: So what's it feel
like when you're trying to
figure out what you're
going to do?
AUDIENCE: He beat me by checking
when it was far away
and being lucky.
PROFESSOR: So if you don't check
you have to reach the
end to win.
So you have to check,
usually, anyway.
AUDIENCE: One thing Alecia had
in mind when we were thinking
about the rule was there ought
to be information that you can
get from how your opponent
reacts after they
look under the cup.
So if they then go and start
rolling again or what have
you, or they then
start options.
But there must be some way that
you can get a leak of
information from their behavior
which makes it
interesting in a
different way.
AUDIENCE: If you've have already
seen the cup, and you
get past the point, do you
have to check to win?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, we played
two different variants.
One where you did.
One where you didn't.
AUDIENCE: Oh, I see.
AUDIENCE: Well, you don't have
to check the second time.
If you check the first time and
then you pass it you win.
AUDIENCE: So that's why there's
one way of playing it.
PROFESSOR: So the person who
checks could win even they're
already passed the point?
Am I understanding this right?
AUDIENCE: Well, if he's the
first past the point.
If you don't have check to win,
so if you just need the
knowledge of what the endpoint
is, then if he
passes it first he wins.
If when he checks both
players are at that
spot then it's a tie.
PROFESSOR: Oh, ok.
AUDIENCE: But since it's
a sequential game it's
impossible.
Other than, at the moment of the
check if both players are
at the same spot is it possible
for them to win at
the same time.
So that's not really an issue.
AUDIENCE: What if I check, and
you're past me, and you have
passed the check spot?
AUDIENCE: I don't win.
AUDIENCE: OK.
AUDIENCE: Because
I never checked.
So as long as I don't
know I don't win.
PROFESSOR: Hey, he makes me
think of a different variant.
But OK.
AUDIENCE: So what they did
was they introduced
a couple new rules.
The first rule being that, the
person who rolls first on
their first turn they cannot
put down a token.
So they actually have to roll.
The second rule is, whenever you
roll if you have a bonus
token on the stockpile
you have two
options after you roll.
One is, you can take
it off and move
two spaces like normal.
The second is, you can choose to
make that block impassible.
So what this does is your
opponent cannot
land on that block.
If they are already on that
block they get pushed one
block back.
If they are behind it, and they
roll and they move to
that block, they get pushed
one block behind it.
PROFESSOR: So they're
changing the block
while you're playing.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR: And how did
that feel while you
were actually playing?
AUDIENCE: We didn't actually
use it that much.
AUDIENCE: I felt like the
penalty for the impassable
block should have been more.
Because if you land on the block
that they're on, and
make them move back one, that
token would otherwise have
made you move forward two.
So it doesn't really reward
you for that.
I felt it could have been really
awesome if the penalty
was significantly more severe.
Because it's hard to get in
front of them enough to
actually make a block impassable
and have them land
on it later.
AUDIENCE: Probably to all the
way back or something.
AUDIENCE: Yeah exactly.
PROFESSOR: So try multiplying
it by two
and see what happens.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, and then you
can always go land on it.
PROFESSOR: If you're like, hmm,
that should have changed
the game play but that didn't.
One of the tricks in chapter
one was just make it bigger
and see what happens.
If nothing else it will just
give you more information on
whether you should be
spending any more
time with this direction.
Or whether it really isn't going
to affect the way how
people play because people don't
end up caring about it.
So the rule of twos is just
multiply something by two, or
half it by two, and
see what happens.
Obviously halving by two
would not in this work.
Who else?
AUDIENCE: So actually they had
these tokens as power-ups.
And you would never actually
take them off
to move more spaces.
You would just keep adding
tokens and you could roll.
So you can spend one turn
to put a token on and in
consequent rolls you could
essentially say, I have N
tokens therefore I roll N plus
1 dice and subtract N.
PROFESSOR: I think
that's one dice.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: --and then you roll a
die for each token you have,
and then you move back one space
for each token you have.
PROFESSOR: Interesting.
AUDIENCE: So it moves your
average and your
maximum up each time.
AUDIENCE: So you could act it
as a power yourself up.
AUDIENCE: And you could also
remove tokens to take away
tokens from the other
guy, right?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Which we never
actually did.
AUDIENCE: I guess we forgot to
go into that, you don't take
out all the tokens when you
do your special move.
They stay in there.
Because, mathematically speaking
if you take them off
it makes it worse.
PROFESSOR: So, I mean, that's an
important object lesson in
how to explain the rules
to the people.
How'd it feel while you were
playing their version?
AUDIENCE: It made my mind tired,
being N plus 1 minus N.
But, it was interesting.
I actually used it.
Before I said I would only use
the die, but this time I
actually used tokens.
PROFESSOR: And what
happened when you
actually used the token?
Was it like yes!
AUDIENCE: Like I said, the
math made it too hard.
PROFESSOR: Well something
happened.
It made you use the tokens as
opposed to ignoring them.
AUDIENCE: It was interesting.
AUDIENCE: So, the rule that they
gave was that if you are
behind the player--
by behind, they mean if your
piece is behind the other one.
AUDIENCE: Losing,
in second place.
AUDIENCE: Right, but not
in the imaginary sense.
Well, whatever.
If you're physically behind them
then when you use a token
you get to use one extra
space ahead.
PROFESSOR: OK, if you use two
tokens do you end up getting?
AUDIENCE: It's still
one space.
PROFESSOR: So how
did that feel?
AUDIENCE: It actually changed
the strategy a little bit
because in the beginning you
basically don't want to be the
person that moves first.
Because then your opponent can
just use all their tokens and
get a lot better than you.
PROFESSOR: Oh, I see.
GUEST SPEAKER: You may want to
talk about tokens and what it
feels playing it ahead of
you so that you can
use them, you can--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Rather then
you just sit at the
start point every time.
AUDIENCE: So pretty much the
person who goes second?
AUDIENCE: Is at an advantage.
PROFESSOR: So that should be a
negative feedback loop, which
we'll we get to I guess in the
next class, but the whole idea
being there is a gap
between players.
And you have game mechanics
specifically designed to
narrow the gap.
Those are negative
feedback loops.
AUDIENCE: Mario Kart!
PROFESSOR: Mario Kart's blue
shell, it's the other
direction right?
To knock back the person who's
leading rather than helping
you catch up.
Actually, a lot of Mario Kart's
mechanics are basically
designed to help reduce
the lead.
All right, cool.
AUDIENCE: They add one rule in
keeping everything else equal.
They add a second die and then
the way it worked was you
arbitrarily assigned people
odd or even numbers.
And then you roll and would go
on that particular turn.
And then that person,
whoever it was
assigned to, would play.
And then you would roll again to
see who would went the next
turn and so on and so forth?
PROFESSOR: How'd that feel?
AUDIENCE: I got a tad memory
with Mario Kart.
PROFESSOR: It's like
what, again?
AUDIENCE: Many mechanics
describe as very Mario Kart.
PROFESSOR: Well, Mario Kart is
actually a collection of a lot
of fairly fundamental
mechanics.
AUDIENCE: I felt like just
rolling to see who'd win.
The sense that you were
just playing for luck.
PROFESSOR: So it amplified
the randomness basically?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, which I actually
detest personally.
AUDIENCE: That rule is like
initiative rule in Star Wars
Miniatures and Dungeons
and Dragons.
And like in that case where
there's actual strategic
decisions to be made
it's actually cool.
Because it means that you never
know whether you're
going to be able to capitalize
on the position that you're in
at the end of the turn.
AUDIENCE: But since we both know
optimal strategy for the
original game it was
just pure luck.
So there was no strategy.
PROFESSOR: So it almost becomes
like a gambling game
or a game of chance.
Cool.
AUDIENCE: They added different
dice you could roll for
different effects.
Such as, if you roll the D20
you can go 10 spaces.
If you need to go 17, 18--
AUDIENCE: Or 18, 19, 20.
AUDIENCE: --
Or 18, 19, 20.
So they added the D10
which also had
similar effects and deviate.
So Patrick and I pretty much
experimented with-- well, he
just rolled D20 the
entire time.
And I experimented with rolling
the D8 and the D10.
AUDIENCE: Why would you
not roll the D10?
AUDIENCE: I started
feeling impatient.
I would forget everything
about Alec and what
he wanted to do.
And every turn I would roll
the D20 hoping to
get 18, 19, or 20.
AUDIENCE: By the way, with the
D20 if you don't roll any of
those you go zero spaces.
So that's actually the risk.
PROFESSOR: So you could either
win the game or go nowhere.
AUDIENCE: So I roll the D20
wanting to get 18,19, or 20.
And not until I roll the 18, 19,
or 20 would I care where
he was on the board.
PROFESSOR: It's you
and the dice.
It's just you and
the randomness.
AUDIENCE: I rolled twice too.
PROFESSOR: Like what you
described earlier is that
whether you're behind or in
front of someone changed the
way that you would play in
the original version.
Now, no longer really matters
anymore, right?
It's just you and the dice.
And when the universe
loves you, you just
automatically win.
AUDIENCE: The intention was to
have the D20 for when you were
way behind and the other
one if you were
only slightly behind.
Apparently that's not
how it was used.
[INAUDIBLE] design, right?
PROFESSOR: Well, a good example
of the aesthetic you
were going for not being the
aesthetic that was actually
experienced.
So, it's still a powerful
aesthetic it's just a
different thing than
what you planned.
I think I might have
skipped you guys?
Sorry about that.
AUDIENCE: So their new rule
was, if you are physically
ahead and you roll a six instead
of only going three
you would go four.
PROFESSOR: If you're physically
ahead and you roll
a six you go?
Oh, OK.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: At first, we tried
playing it in a similar way of
how we did before.
And it really felt like the
person who was ahead
was ahead even more.
And now everyone's rolling,
because as soon as you roll
you get a higher expectation
value.
PROFESSOR: So you prefer the
low-ball luck rather than the?
AUDIENCE: So the problem is if
you put a token down and they
roll at least a one so you're
guaranteed you're
going to be the high.
And then they have a
higher expectation.
PROFESSOR: How does
it feel to play?
Mathematically that's
what it means, but--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Actually, in playing
the first game I don't think
it actually came up at all.
AUDIENCE: And then in the second
game, I believe it did?
And to me it didn't really
feel like it changed.
AUDIENCE: For me, the entire
time I felt like the person
who was ahead was more ahead.
AUDIENCE: It would come up more
if your board was longer.
It really encourages you
to stockpile for
the first few turns.
But if you're encouraged more
than you might want to search.
That's contrary to--
GUEST SPEAKER: When you guys
were going over mistakes did
you feel like it changed
your strategy?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
AUDIENCE: It made rolling
feel like a [INAUDIBLE].
Which was the point right?
That's what you guys
were aiming for?
AUDIENCE: The alternate rule
that we had toyed with was, if
you're ahead and you put down
a token you have to roll.
And if you get a six you have
to move one step back.
So there's a one in six chance
that there'll be a penalty for
[INAUDIBLE].
Because precisely what you
mentioned, which is that when
you're ahead the dominant
strategy is
to reduce the variance.
So we were just playing with
stuff to make you want to roll
more basically.
PROFESSOR: OK, so dynamically
that tells you to roll more.
I would say aesthetically you
have the whole Monopoly
situation where the
person who's
winning just keeps winning.
And there are times when you
actually want that feeling.
Especially when it came to the
game of Monopoly, the whole
point of the game was huge
financial embarrassments.
And it's like, wow I have no
money and I'm just going to
keep losing money.
That was the point of
the game actually.
That's why it's called
Monopoly.
AUDIENCE: The thing about
it is, the person who's
physically ahead may not
actually be ahead in terms of
absolute game play because
the other person
has stockpiled tokens.
And we weren't sure whether
determining who was ahead by
counting the tokens in the
equation or not was a better
game rule if we didn't have
that type of test.
PROFESSOR: Give it a
shot [INAUDIBLE].
The one thing we came
up with was--
at first we thought it wouldn't
change the game at
all I guess.
Which was basically, instead
of spending tokens to go
forward two steps you spend
tokens to knock your opponent
back two steps.
Completely changed
the game play.
AUDIENCE: We tried that.
It sucks.
AUDIENCE: Stock piled first and
then you knock people back
so you didn't go anywhere
for the first 10 turns.
And then you realize that
nothing is going to happen.
AUDIENCE: And then we
just kept rolling.
AUDIENCE: Rolled the
rest of the time.
PROFESSOR: Which is a completely
different way to
play the game.
That whole process of
stockpiling right at the
beginning is--
sure, we could have both started
with a stack of three
each because that's really what
happened three turns in.
But the whole act of--
that felt really like,
OK clearly you're
setting out to kill me.
AUDIENCE: Can you move?
PROFESSOR: No, we had it so it
wouldn't be a point spending
it when you're right
at the beginning.
But there was that whole arms
race feel that really didn't
happen the first game.
All it did really was make the
game longer, but it felt mean.
OK, that's pretty much
it for today I guess.
GUEST SPEAKER: And we need the
poker chips and all the dice
back but you can keep the
game boards if you're
really happy with them.
AUDIENCE: How long did this
game take you to make?
GUEST SPEAKER: It took longer
to make the board
than to make the rules.