PROFESSOR: So in this
recitation, we're going to
look at step and delta
functions, integration and
generalized derivatives.
So the first part, you're asked
to compute the integral
from zero minus to
infinity delta t
exponential t squared dt.
The second one is from zero
minus to infinity delta t
minus 2 exponential of t
squared sine t cos 2t.
The third one is zero plus to
infinity delta t exponential
of squared dt.
So know that it's the same as
a, except that the bounds of
integration changed.
The second part, we're asked
to define the generalized
derivatives of these two
functions, where u here is
just a step function that
you saw before.
So it's 3ut minus 2ut minus 1.
And the second one is t squared
for t is negative and
exponential of minus
t for t positive.
So why don't you pause the video
and work through this
example, and I'll
be right back.
Welcome back.
So let's compute
the first one.
Zero minus infinity delta t
exponential t squared dt.
So just to remind you, the delta
function is everywhere
zero except at the
value of zero.
And we represent it
with an arrow.
And the integral of the delta
would be 1 from minus infinity
to plus infinity.
In this integral, we're
integrating from zero minus to
infinity, which means that the
zero is included in our
interval from zero minus
to infinity.
Therefore, this integral is
basically assigning the value
to this function exponential
t squared.
And the value that it's
assigning to it is the value
it would take at t equals
to zero where
the delta is non-zero.
So really clearly, this is
just exponential of zero.
And it gives us 1.
For the second integral, it
goes from zero minus to
infinity, delta t minus
2 exponential, a more
complicated function, t
squared sine t cos 2t.
So now, let's represent this
delta function here.
So this is just our zero axis.
And the delta here is zero
everywhere except at 2 where
we would represent it,
again, with an arrow
at 2 amplitude 1.
So this delta is zero everywhere
except at 2 where
it would assign the value to the
function next do it at the
value t equals to 2.
So really this integration gives
us just the value of
this function at t equal
2, so 4 sine 2 cos 4.
And here, the key was that
again, this interval of
integration from zero minus to
infinity and clearly includes
the value at which delta
function is non-zero.
So for the last one, we return
to our first integral except
that now we are changing the
bounds of integration to zero
plus to infinity.
So now, if I do our presentation
of the delta
function that we're dealing
with, so delta centered at 1
and the interval of integration,
we have an open
interval now that does not
include the value at which
delta is non-equal to zero.
So everywhere this function
would just be assigned its
value at, it'd just be
multiplied by the function
that is zero.
And so basically, it's like
multiplying this function by
zero, and it just
gives us zero.
It's like the delta fell
off of our interval of
integration, so we're just left
with a zero function.
So let's move to the
second part.
The second part asked us to find
a generalized derivative
to f of t equals 3u of t
minus 2u of t minus 1.
So just to remind you here of
what u of t's are, just want
to sketch a few things.
So first, u of t is just the
step function that would be
zero everywhere and would
take the value 1 for
t larger than zero.
So this first part here would
just be non-zero for
t larger than zero.
Instead of being assigned
value 1, it's just the
assigned value 3 because we're
multiplying the u of t by 3.
So this first part would
look like this.
The second part here would be
u shifted by minus 1, which
means that u is zero everywhere
for t less than 1.
So we would have a zero
function here.
So let me just do that.
But it should be on the
same axis and 1 for
t larger than 1.
But here, we're multiplying
it by factor minus 2.
So really, what we have is
another u function that is
shifted down 2 minus 2.
So the sum of these two
contributions is zero for t
negative takes the value of 3
for t between zero and 1, and
the value 1, 3 minus 2,
for t larger than 1.
So clearly here, we have
discontinuities at t equals to
zero and t equals to 1.
So let's just write down
the derivative.
The generalized derivative here
would lead us first to
compute the derivatives where
the function is continuous.
So for minus infinity to zero,
it's a constant, derivative
would be zero.
Between zero and 1,
it's constant,
derivative would be zero.
And from 1 to infinity, it
would also give us zero.
So we would have a zero
contribution from the
continuous part of the function,
if you wish.
But we still need to account
for the discontinuities.
So at zero, we have a
jump from zero to 3.
And that we learned can be
written down as a delta
function of magnitude
3 centered at zero.
After that, we have
another jump.
Now, it's from 3 to 1.
So it's a jump of minus 2
amplitude centered at 1.
So here, we can also do that
with the delta, but we just
need also to shift it by minus
1 to show clearly that the
jump occurs at 1 and multiply
this by minus 2 to show the
amplitude of the jump down.
So if we were now to represent
this f prime, basically, the
regular part is zero.
So there's nothing
to write down
except just a zero function.
And these discontinuities that
I'm just going to represent on
the graph would be the delta
function centered at zero
magnitude 3 and delta function
centered around 1 of
magnitude minus 2.
And the rest would just
be the zero function.
So that would be f
prime, f of t.
So for the second one that we
were given, it's a function f
of t that takes the value t
squared for t negative and
exponential minus t
for t positive.
So a quick sketch here tells
that this function looks like
this, an exponential minus
t for t positive taking
a value here 1.
So clearly, there is a jump
here, discontinuity.
So how do we go about computing
this generalized
derivative?
So let's look again at
the continuous parts.
So from minus infinity to zero,
we're dealing with just
the t squared.
So the derivative is just 2t.
For t between zero and infinity,
we're just dealing
with exponential minus t.
So that's minus exponential
minus t.
But we need to account for the
discontinuity the jump of
amplitude, 1 at zero.
So as we saw before, this
can just be modeled
with a delta function.
And if we were to represent this
function, then we would
just need to add the delta
function of magnitude 1 here
and then just sketch 2t, for
example, and then minus
exponential of minus 2t.
That would give us something
like that.
And that ends the problem
for today.
And the key point here were
just to learn how to
manipulate the step function
and how to use the delta
function when you compute
your integrals.
And be careful with the
bounds of integration.