All right then.
Now we are coming again to an
example of Ampere's law.
I believe it's the last
one, I'm not sure.
We have here a very large sheet,
very wide, very long,
and it has uniform charge
density plus everywhere.
Charge density 'sigma'.
And it is moving in this
direction with a speed 'v'.
If I look from this direction
I would see here that width
'w' coming towards me, I would
see the velocity vector coming
towards me.
So this thing is coming
And it is uniformly charged with
charge density 'sigma'.
Now I have to choose cleverly
a closed loop in order to
apply Ampere's law.
This dotted line is
in the surface.
I go up by a certain
distance 'd'.
This here has a certain length
'l', which I can choose
arbitrarily.
This is 'd'.
I go down over the
distance 'd'.
I come below the surface,
again distance 'd'.
I return and I go up here.
This is 'd', this is 'l'.
It's really easy to
draw it here.
So this is 'd.' 'd.' 'l'.
'l'.
It shouldn't be hard for you to
convince yourself, which is
by convention, that the 'B'
field here must be in this
direction and that
the 'B' field
there is in this direction.
Now what I'm going to do, I'm
going to do the closed loop
integral of this loop.
I'm going to choose a flat
surface to calculate the
current going through
that flat surface.
That's this flat surface.
As the belt moves, charges
going through, you can
calculate how much charge
goes through per second.
I also I'm going to make
'd' very small.
I'm going to make
'd' going to 0.
So that means when I make this
integral 'B' dot 'dl' , I have
simply 'B' times 'l', because
they are in the same direction
so the dot product simply
gives me a cosine
of the angle 1.
0 here because I make 'd' 0.
Very small.
And then I have another
'Bl' here.
Because they again are in
the same direction.
And that now equals 'mu0'
times the current
through that surface.
'i thru' .
Well 'i thru' is the charge
that going through that
surface per second and
that equals 'l' times
'sigma' times 'v'.
You should be able to convince
yourself of this very easily.
That leads then to a magnetic
field which is 'mu0' times
'sigma' times 'v'
divided by 2.
Notice the faster the belt moves
the higher the current
is through the surface, the
higher the magnetic field.
The higher the surface charge
density, the higher the
magnetic field.
Notice also it's the
same on both sides.
There's no dependence on 'z.' If
I call this 'z', there's no
dependence on that.
This is slightly similar to
the case that we had early
whereby we had a very large
plane, uniformly charged with
a positive or negative charge.
We also there had that the
electric field, provided that
the sheet is large enough,
is independent of 'z'.
It's the same above the plane,
pointing upwards if it is
positive charge.
And down the plane it is
pointing downwards, but the
magnitudes are the same.
You see something very similar
here, this is that factor 2.
For an infinite charged plane,
the electric field, you may
recall, equals 'sigma' divided
by '2 epsilon 0'.
If you accept the fact that
the magnetic field is
independent of 'z', you could
also argue that if there is a
magnetic field here, and if the
sheet is very long, that
even if 'd' is not very small,
that 'B' would always be
perpendicular to 'd'
here and here.
Therefore the dot product
would disappear anyhow.
Even though I made 'd' going
to 0 to convince you that
there would be no contribution
here of integral 'B dot dl',
if you had accepted the fact
that the magnetic field here
is always in this direction,
and here is
always in this direction.
Not necessarily accepting the
fact that they have the same
magnitude independent of 'z',
you would still agreed that
'B' and 'dl' here would be
perpendicular to each other.
And therefore there would
be no contributions.
Now you have to finish
this problem.
You have two sheets.
I have here two sheets.
This has, again, sigma and I
have another one, also huge in
side, also '+ sigma'.
Uniformly charged.
But one is going in this
direction and the other one is
going in this direction.
We have a point 'A' here, we
have a point 'D' between the
plates, and we have a point
'C' below the plates.
I avoid the 'B' here, because
I don't like 'B's' when we
deal with magnetic fields.
Assume that these sheets
are infinitely large.
You can calculate what the
magnetic field above this one
is, and below this one.
You can do the same here.
And you obviously apply the
super position principle.
If you apply the super position
principal it's
immediately obvious that at 'A'
the magnetic field must
vanish, because the two plates
create a magnetic field which
is the same but in opposite
direction.
It will also vanished
at point 'C'.
But, of course, between the
plates the two fields will
enforce each other.
I don't think you're going
to have too much
trouble with this one.
I think it's about time
that we start
talking Faraday's law.
Not yet.
We're close but not yet.
Professor Becker invented acute
problem of a cylinder
which has a certain
length 'l'.
It's a hollow cylinder and it
is rotating with angular
velocity 'omega'.
Has radius 'a', and there is a
surface charges density '+
sigma', only on the surface of
the shell of the cylinder.
You are being asked what is the
magnetic field inside and
outside the cylinder.
Now first I would like you to
read up on page 920, because
it is very similar
to a solenoid.
A solenoid of winding, separate
windings, and
currents are going around
in a spiral.
Well here this drum
is going around.
So this is also currents
going around.
I'm going to solve this from
an over simplified case
whereby 'l', in my mind,
is going to infinity.
It's very, very long.
And I'm going to apply Ampere's
law and I have to
choose a very, very
clever loop.
Here is another view
of that cylinder.
Here is this radius 'A', it's
going around with angular
velocity 'omega'.
And the loop that I'm going
to choose is this loop.
The loop 'I' choose is at a
distance little 'r' from the
center line.
And this distance
'd' I'm going to
make very, very large.
Let this be 'b', this length,
and let this be 'b'.
I now have to apply Ampere's
law, closed loop integral, of
'B dot dl' equals 'mu0'
times 'i thru'.
It's clear that this is going
to be my surface, and I have
to calculate the current going
through that surface.
But that's only right here where
charge is moving through
this surface inside the plane.
The magnetic fields, by
convention, must be here in
this direction.
The magnetic field here, if I'm
very, very far away from
the cylinder, clearly
has to be 0.
And the magnetic field here,
well, if there is any, it
would have to be in
this direction
for reasons of symmetry.
Well here it is clearly
everywhere perpendicular to
the 'dl' if I go around
in this direction.
And it's everywhere
perpendicular to the 'dl' if I
go in this direction.
So there's no contribution to
this term of this part, of
this part, and of this part,
because 'B' is 0. so I only
have a contribution here.
What do I get?
'B' at that location 'r' times
'b' equals 'mu0' times 'i
thru' and 'i thru' equals
'sigma' times 'v' times 'b'.
If you want to write
down for this omega
'r', it that is fine.
Omega--
not 'r' but 'a'.
It's not 'r' but it is 'a',
because the current goes
through here.
So the velocity there is omega
'a' times 'b', 'Br' times 'b,'
and clearly you see you lose
your little 'b', of course.
Because Faraday's law doesn't
care about how long
you choose this loop.
Here you see that the magnetic
field increases when omega
goes up, that is intuitive.
And it also increases if you
had more surface charge on
your cylinder.
What happens now with the
magnetic field just outside
the cylinder?
In other words, if I don't
make 'd' very, very long.
What may not be so intuitive
that if indeed the cylinder
infinitely long, that only
then the magnetic field
outside the cylinder is to
a good approximation 0.
Here is now this closed loop.
I again have a certain distance
'r' here, but I have
already shown that 'B of r', for
'r' is smaller then 'a' is
independent of 'r'.
Notice when you look at my
previous results that there's
no little 'r' in here.
So it's constant inside this
cylinder just like it was
constant inside the solenoid.
To a reasonable approximation.
This is 'b' and this is 'b'.
I'm going around like this.
This is my surface.
And so I'm going to get that
'b', I call this magnetic
field here inside, times 'b'.
This part is 0 because
the dot product is 0.
Here I have a 'B' outside, but
since 'B' outside and my 'dl'
are in the same direction, I get
'B' outside times little
'b', that now equals 'mu0' times
'i thru', which we just
calculated.
But we already showed that this
is the same as that in
the previous calculation.
So there's only one possibility
that this is 0 and
so the magnetic field outside
the solenoid, independent or
how far you are away,
equals 0.
I really strongly advise you
to, again, read up on page
920, where we have cases where
the cylinder is not infinitely
long, the solenoid is not
infinitely long, and then you
do see magnetic fields here
leaking out, so to speak.
Very well.
There is a way, perhaps, that
I can make you see in an
intuitive way why the magnetic
field outside maybe zero if
the sheet is infinitely long.
It is just my attempt to give
you perhaps some insight so
that you don't feel that
you're sort of
being cheated, perhaps.
Would you agree that right here
at the edge the cylinder
into the paper?
So there is a current going
into the paper.
Would you agree that here at
this edge where the cylinder
is coming towards you,
there is a current
coming out of the paper?
By convention, if there's a
current going into the paper
the magnetic field
is down here.
The magnetic field is
up here, and the
magnetic field is up here.
Now imagine that this
was an infinite
sheet, which it's not.
Then 'B' and 'B' and 'B' would
have the same magnitude,
except that the directions
are different.
I can do the same for
this current.
The 'B' would now be
pointing upwards.
The 'B' here would also
be pointing upwards.
But on the left side the 'B'
would be pointing downwards.
And you see that you get outside
0, and that inside the
two magnetic fields, due to do
this current going into the
paper and this current coming
out of the paper,
support each other.
Very similar to what we had
earlier when we had very large
capacitor plates, very large in
size, linear size 'l' here
much larger than the
distance 'd'.
We had positive charge here,
negative charge here.
Remember, for the same
reason 'E' was 0
here, 'E' was 0 there.
And the electric field inside of
the two plates support each
other and was 'sigma' divided
by 'epsilon 0'.
Superposition principle
again, in case of
very, very large plates.