Here we have a long wire with
a circular cross section.
It has a radius 'R'.
There is a current going into
the wire in this direction,
but the current density
is not uniform.
In other words, per square
centimeter more current flows
here then what flows there.
It is a linear relationship.
'J', which is the current
density, is some constant
alpha times the radius
'r', if this is 'r'.
So you see current density
here is higher than here.
Let's make a large cross section
and we have therefore
here the radius 'R' and I have
here a concentric circle with
radius little 'r'.
And one that is slightly
larger, so that this
thickness is 'dr'.
And I would like to calculate
now with you what is the
current going through this
ring, so to speak?
Well, that current 'di' at that
location 'r' must be 'J'
at that location 'r' times the
surface area of the ring which
is '2 pi r dr'.
So if I want to know to the
total current that flows is
this whole surface area, in
other words up to radius 'r',
so 'i' up to radius 'r',
including this whole area,
then I have to do it an
integral, 'r' has to
go from 0 to 'r'.
And I find '2 pi alpha' times
the integral from 0.
Let me first do the integral all
the way from here to here.
Let me first do 'i total', which
is this total value.
That would be then from 0 to
'R', '2 pi alpha' and then you
get 'r squared dr'.
That tells you then that this
equals '2 pi' divided by 3
times alpha times 'R cubed'.
You can write that differently
if you want to.
You can say that alpha therefor
is '3i', this is 'i
total' now.
Total current through
the cross section
divided by '2 pi R cubed'.
This it's not too difficult.
To get the current the relation
between the current
and alpha, current
going through
this whole cross section.
And now, as you see, I
was getting a little
bit ahead of myself.
Now we want to know what the
magnetic field is at all
values of 'r'.
We have two domains.
We have the domain whereby 'r'
is smaller than capital 'R'
and we have the domain where it
is larger than capital 'R'.
I suggested you do this one
and I will do this one.
Here is the cross section,
radius 'R'.
And I'm now going to
apply Ampere's law.
So I have here a closed loop.
Remember Ampere's law that
connects a closed looped, this
is a closed loop that
you must choose.
Equals 'mu0' times 'i thru' And
that 'i thru' is through a
surface, which is an open
surface attached
to the closed loop.
And this is that closed loop.
Whether it's a floppy
surface, bulged or
flat, doesn't matter.
That's the amazing thing
about this law.
I will choose a flat
surface, not making
our lives too difficult.
And so the current 'i' that goes
through this area, that's
why I put an 'r' in here, that's
through the area up to
radius little 'r' immediately
follows from what we just did.
Alpha 'r cubed',
this is alpha.
This is also the same as 'i',
the total 'i' 'r cubed'
divided by capital 'R cubed'.
Now if we apply Ampere's law,
and we go around in this a
circle the magnetic fields by
convention is in this direction.
It's everywhere the same because
the radius 'r', little
'r', doesn't change and so we
get that 'B' at the distance
'r' times '2 pi r' equals 'mu
0' times the current going
through that flat surface,
uniquely determined and that
equals 'i r cubed' divided
'R cubed'.
And out pops immediately 'Br'.
And what you see is that 'Br'
proportional to 'r squared'.
If the current density had been
the same throughout the
whole surface, not linearly
growing with 'r', but the
same, then you would have found
that the magnetic field
inside the wire would
have grown linearly.
0 at the center and growing
linearly to the outer radius.
No it's grows in a
quadratic way.
In a parabolic fashion.
It think you should try to
convince yourself that it's
linear if the current density
had been constant throughout.
Now when you are going to do
your part to calculate 'B of
r' for 'r' larger than 'R',
there is one thing--
it's really not so difficult.
I really get the part I believe
that is more difficult
than what you have to do.
But I want you to check that
your result is exactly
identical to my result when
you substitute little 'r'
equals capital 'R'.
The two must be the same.
So please check that.
Those consistency checks
are important, they
don't cost very much.
They give you some confidence
in your results.