PROFESSOR: We have a cylindrical
conductor, with an
inner core which is metal.
Radius 'a'.
And we have an outer cylinder,
which has a certain thickness,
which is not 0.
This radius is 'b', and
this radius is 'c'.
And this is metal.
And there's a current going
into the direction of the
paper, in here, in this inner
core, which call 'i1'.
And for now there is also a
current flowing in the outer
shell, which is 'i2', and they
are in the same direction.
You're being asked now what
is the magnetic field
everywhere in space.
Well thank goodness that we
don't have to use Biot and
Savart, because we have a very
long, infinitely long wire.
So we're going to use
Ampere's law.
But I want to talk a little
bit about Ampere's law.
Ampere's law says that the
closed loop integral 'b dot
dl' over a close loop equals
'mu 0' times 'i' and 'i' is
through an open surface
attached to that loop.
I cannot stress this enough,
because almost all books,
really explain this
incorrectly.
The correct way of thinking
about it is the following: you
draw a closed loop in space.
I don't care how crooked
that loop is.
It doesn't have to be
a perfect circle.
You attach to that loop
an open surface.
It could be flat, it could be
so bubbled that you blow out
so that b gets to the
form of a hat.
There is a surface
which is open.
You can stick your hand in
through the loop, and you get
into this blown up surface.
But it is open.
You don't have to break
through the
surface to get inside.
Once you have done that, it
is immediately clear which
current cuts through
that surface
that is uniquely defined.
Anything else about currents
going through
a loop is ill defined.
I don't like it.
I really don't like it.
So if I had a particular
situation whereby I would
choose this to be my closed
loop, and you are perfectly
free to choose the surface.
Flat.
Then it's very easy to determine
whether there is
something poking through
that flat surface.
But here you see a bag.
And I have here a closed
loop at the end.
I hope you can see that.
This is a closed loop.
It's a wire here,
it's a string.
I have attached to it
an open surface.
This whole bag is
And I can stick my
hand in here.
And even if I make it much
smaller, and it's still open
here, I can still stick
my hand in here.
This could be now my loop,
and this crazy
thing could be my surface.
It's an open surface.
And if there is a current going
through here this is the
wire, then it's very clear that
this current is going
through loop.
Here look.
It's very clear.
There's no doubt.
There is a wire going
through here.
It's coming in here and
it's coming out here.
It's uniquely determined.
And I'm not talking about a
current going through a loop.
it stinks, I don't like it.
It has to go through
a surface.
Perhaps some of you have seen
these wonderful Japanese
papers balloons.
They have a little opening here,
no larger than a dime.
I can blow it up.
OK.
This little opening, that
you can see here.
This little opening here think
of this as a little loop.
It's very small, but
it's still a loop.
And the surface attached to
it is an open surface.
When there's a current going
through that open
surface I will know.
If the current flows in and
flows out again, of course,
then one is positive and
the other is negative.
I'm not going to poke a hole
through this beautiful
balloon, by the way.
I'm going to leave it as that.
You get the picture about the
meaning of Ampere's law.
And now we have to calculate
what the magnetic field is
everywhere in space.
That's not so difficult.
I will make a loop, a concentric
loop, concentric
circle, with radius 'r'.
The magnetic fields I know
by convention is in this
direction and it's tangentially
going around.
I know it's everywhere the same
because the distance 'r'
is the same to this circle.
So I can write down immediately
that 'B' times '2
pi r', I don't have to worry
about the dot product because
'B' and 'dl' are in the same
direction 'dl' is not in the
direction of the current,
by the way.
'dl' is along this line
in Ampere's law.
So they are in the same
direction, so the cosine
between the angle is 1.
This now equals 'mu 0' times the
current that cuts through
an open surface that I attached
to this line.
Why not just making
a flat one?
I don't have to get myself
a hard time.
Making a flat one.
Then the current that goes
through here is 'i1'.
And there it is.
And so out pops immediately that
in the case that 'r' is
smaller than 'b' and larger than
'c', that the magnetic
fields falls off again as '1/r',
which is no surprise '2
pi' over 'r'.
If, however, I have also a
current 'i2' flowing also in
the same direction as 'i1', and
I want to know now what
the magnetic field is larger
than 'c', outside here.
Again I make a circular loop and
I go through exactly the
same exercise of Ampere's law
and now, no surprise, I will
find that 'B' equals 'mu
0' divided by '2 pi r'.
But now I have here
'i1' plus 'i2'.
If 'i1' and 'i2' are the same
in magnitude but in opposite
directions, then obviously
the net result will be 0.
I'd like to make a drawing, a
graph, which is always nice.
'B' versus 'r'.
Here is 'r'.
Here is 'B'.
Let this be 'a', let this
be 'b', and this be 'c'.
What happens from 0 to 'a',
it's a big question mark.
We have not discussed that.
But you will see that
in the future.
Right here at this point 'a' the
magnetic field equals 'mu
0' times 'i1' divided
by '2 pi a'.
It will fall as '1/r', there it
goes, proportional to '1/r'
and right here at this location
it will have the
value 'mu 0' times 'i1'
divided by '2 pi b'.
'1/r'.
What happens here in this
metal we don't know yet.
But you will learn
about that later.
I know that the magnetic
field here--
well I know it mathematically
this 'mu 0' times 'i1' plus
'i2', assuming that they run in
the same direction, divided
by '2 pi c'.
Remember '1/r'.
Now whether this is larger than
this number or smaller,
or larger than this number or
smaller, I do not know.
That depends on 'c' and
'b' and on 'i2'.
So what I'm going to draw
now is rather arbitrary.
Let's say it's this high and
it falls off as '1/r'.
it's interesting for you to
think about now already what
it is doing in here and
what it's doing here.