PROFESSOR: And problem
number 1 is 29-55.
I will be very brief about
this one, because I don't
think you will have too much
problems with this.
There is a current flowing in
this wire and at 90 degree
angles the wire continues,
same current 'i'.
At a distance 'd', in the
extension of this wire there
is a point 'P', and you are
being asked what is the
magnetic field in strength and
direction at that point 'P'?
It's clear that it is the
superposition, factorial
superposition, of the one
due to wire 1 and the
one due to wire 2.
The contribution, due to wire
1 is 0, you can figure that
out for yourself.
As far as the contribution from
number 2 is concerned you
could, but I don't think you
should, you could use Biot and
Savart and do the integration
over all these pieces, all the
way from here to infinity.
But that would not be a very
smart thing to do.
What I would do is the
following: I would pretend
that the wire is infinitely
long, even though it isn't,
and then I would calculate the
magnetic field at 'P' using
Ampere's law and divide
the number by 2.
The answer by 2.
Because let's face it, if I
extend this wire and pretend
that there is an infinitely long
wire with a current 'i',
it is trivial the calculate
the magnetic field here.
For reasons of symmetry,
obviously if this piece is
missing it has to be
1/2 that value.