PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video what we'd like
to do is to solve a certain
differential equation.
And I'm not even giving
you initial condition.
So we just want to find a y,
such that x times dy dx is
equal to x squared plus x
times y squared plus 1.
So I'll give you a minute
to think about it and
then I'll be back.
Welcome back.
I'm going to use the technique
of separation of variables to
solve this differential
equation problem.
Hopefully you thought about
doing that as well.
Because it's really
set up nicely for
separation of variables.
So let me let me first get all
of the values, or terms that
involve y on the
left-hand side.
And then I'm going to move the
dx to the right-hand side and
get all the terms that involve
x to the right-hand side.
So I'm going to write dy
divided by y squared
plus 1 is equal to--
so I'm going to multiply through
by dx divided by x.
So I'm going to get x squared
plus x over x dx.
Now if x is 0, I have a little
problem but we're going to
ignore that for the moment.
So I can rewrite this
as x plus 1 dx.
And now I'm totally set up
with my next step in
separation of variables and so
I can integrate both sides.
So let's see what happens
when I integrate
the left-hand side.
OK?
What is an antiderivative to
1 over y squared plus 1?
Well that's arctangent, that's
arctangent of y.
So the derivative of arctangent
of y is 1 over y
squared plus 1.
And so on the left-hand
side I get arctan y.
If you wrote tangent to the
minus 1 y, that's the same
thing, the inverse tangent of
y, that's the same thing.
And on the right-hand
side what do I get?
Well this is a nice easy
thing to integrate.
When I integrate x, I get
x squared over 2.
And here I just get an x.
And then I should add
in my constants.
So x squared over 2 plus
x plus a constant.
So this is, so far I'm
doing everything OK.
Now I need to figure out
how to isolate the y.
Well arctan y is the inverse
of the tangent function.
So if I want to isolate y I have
to take the tangent of
both sides.
So when I take tangent of
arctangent of y I just get y.
Then over your I get tangent
of x squared over 2 plus x
plus C.
And now because I didn't give
you any initial conditions, we
can't say anything about C. But
if I gave you some initial
conditions then we could
evaluate and solve for C. Now
how do I go about checking to
make sure that this works?
Well, what I do is actually
take the derivative.
So you may want to take the
derivative of the right-hand
side, take dy dx.
Evaluate what that is when you
have y equals tangent of x
squared over 2 plus x plus C and
see if you in fact get the
relationship you're
supposed to get.
But I'll stop there.