PROFESSOR: Hi guys, today we are
going to play around with
the basics of eigenvalues
and eigenvectors.
We're going to do the following
problem, we're given
this invertible matrix, a, and
we'll find the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors not of a, but of a
squared and a inverse minus
the identity.
So, this problem might seem
daunting at first, squaring a
3 by 3 matrix, or taking an
inverse of a 3 by 3 matrix is
a fairly computationally
intensive task, but if you've
seen Professor Strang's lecture
on eigenvalues and
eigenvectors you shouldn't
be all too worried.
So I'll give you a few moments
to think of your own line of
attack and then you'll
see mine.
Hi again, OK, so the observation
that makes our
life really easy is
the following one.
So say v is an eigenvector with
associated eigenvalue to
the matrix a, then if we hit v
with a squared well, this we
can write it as a times a v,
but a v is lambda v, right?
So we have a lambda v.
Lambda is a scalar, so we can
move it in front and get
lambda a v, and lambda a v is,
when we plug in a v lambda v,
is lambda squared v. So, what
we've find out is that if v is
an eigenvector for a
then it's also an
eigenvector for a squared.
Just the eigenvalue is the
eigenvalue squared.
Similarly, if we had
a inverse, if you
hit v with a inverse.
So in this case we can write v
as av over lambda, given that
of course, lambda is non-zero.
But the eigenvalues of an
invertible matrix are always
non-zero, which is an exercise
you should do yourselves.
So if we just then take out the
a and combine it with a
inverse, this is the identity,
and so we get 1 over lambda v.
So v is also an eigenvector for
a inverse, with eigenvalue
there is a reciprocal
of lambda.
OK, and from here of course, A
inverse minus the identity is
lambda inverse minus 1 v, so
the eigenvalue of A inverse
minus the identities, 1
over lambda minus 1.
OK, so, what we've figured out
is we just need to find the
eigenvalues and eigenvectors of
A and then we have a way of
finding what the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors of A squared
and A inverse minus the
identity will be.
OK so, how do we find
the eigenvalues?
Well what does it mean
for lambda to be an
eigenvalue of A?
It means that the matrix A minus
lambda, the identity is
singular, which is precisely
the case when its
determinant is 0, OK?
So we need to solve the
following equation 1 minus
lambda, 2, 3, 0, 1 minus lambda,
2, -2, and 0, 1, 4
minus lambda.
OK, it's fairly obvious which
column we should use to expand
this determinant.
We should use the first column,
because we have only
one 0 entry, and so this is
equal to 1 minus lambda times
the determinant of the
two by two matrix.
1 minus lambda, -2, 1, 4 minus
lambda, which is, I'm going to
do the computation up here.
1 minus lambda, lambda squared
minus 5 lambda plus six.
Which is a fairly familiar
quadratic, and we can write it
as the product of
linear factors.
Lambda minus 2, lambda minus
three, so the three
eigenvalues of A are
1, 2, and 3.
OK so, first half of our problem
is done, now we just
need to find what the
eigenvectors associated with
each of these eigenvalues are.
How we do that, well
let's see.
Let's figure out what the
eigenvector associated with
lambda equals 1 is.
So, we know that the vector
needs to be in the null space
of A minus lambda, the identity,
so A minus the
identity, v, so--
write this out--
it's, 0, 0, 3, 2,
3, 0, -2, 0, 1.
And we see that the first column
is 0, so the first
variable will be our free
variable if we want to solve
this linear system
of equations.
And you can just set it to 1 and
it's not hard to see that
the other two entries
should be zero.
So we can do the same procedure
with the other two
eigenvalues and yeah will get
you an eigenvector for each
eigenvalue.
And in the end you
go back here.
So I'm going to put our results
in a little table.
So A squared inverse equals the
identity, so the first row
will be eigenvalues.
So it's going to be lambda is
an eigenvalue for A, and we
saw that lambda squared will
be the eigenvalue for A
squared and lambda inverse
minus 1 will be the value
inverse minus the identity,
and the
eigenvectors will be the same.
OK, we're done.