The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
OCW.MIT.edu.
PROFESSOR: Today is pretty
much just set aside for
brainstorming.
So we're probably going to
do about an hour of that.
Just to throw the ideas that
people already have in their
heads about what could be with
the problem space that we're
working on.
This whole preparing people to
deal with violence and folks
suffering from an illness.
And there's a whole bunch of
different things that people
may be working on.
And the idea is that hopefully
we can get this all out and
then we can spend the next
half-hour, and frankly the
rest of this week, trying
to figure out
who's in which team.
Who's collaborating on a
similar topic and who's
interested in what.
And then, anyone actually get
through any of the readings?
OK, great.
So there's a few things
up there.
I realize that we don't have
a lot of time to read.
And there's probably more stuff
up there to read that
needs to be read necessarily.
But it's all there
as resources.
Any ideas that people
thought might be
interesting to work on?
Andrew?
AUDIENCE: So one of the basic
issues I heard from the
presentation, and the papers,
was communication.
So this may work as a
simulation, but the real world
system would be communication
between the psychiatrist and
the patient.
Along with the psychiatrist with
the person above them.
PROFESSOR: Psychiatrist,
patient, communication?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
What do they call them?
Not the patient.
Patient, psychiatrist?
AUDIENCE: Orderly?
AUDIENCE: Nurse?
AUDIENCE: What function
do they have?
AUDIENCE: Give us more
information.
AUDIENCE: Psychiatrist-Patient
for now that's fine.
PROFESSOR: You know how talking
about psychiatrists
there is patient.
Psychiatrist, resident?
AUDIENCE: Maybe like nurse,
patient, and then nurse
reporting incidents
to supervisors?
PROFESSOR:Three levels?
AUDIENCE: Yes, that's the one.
PROFESSOR: So it would go
supervisor, nurse--
AUDIENCE: I'm sorry, guys.
PROFESSOR: --and you
have the patient.
Those kinds of reporting
up and reporting down.
All right, yeah?
AUDIENCE: So I had
a couple ideas.
One of them was, every idea you
have a patient and there's
two doctors or psychiatrists.
And so one psychiatrist is
trying to calm the patient
while the other is doing the
opposite and trying to make
this patient as angry
as possible.
So the way I was thinking was,
the psychiatrist that's trying
to enrage the patient?
That's training in
what not to say.
While the doctor who is trying
to calm them down is--
PROFESSOR: So by showing what's
the worst possible way?
OK, I'm going to call that
good cop, bad cop.
AUDIENCE: --Yeah, and then
another idea I had which I
thought of with [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
yesterday was
have a team of psychiatrists
working with one patient.
But interlaced in one of the
psychiatrists is a saboteur
trying to enrage the
patient as well.
PROFESSOR: And what are the
target audiences going to be
like actual residents.
I'm just going to say a
saboteur in a group of
psychiatrists.
Because maybe there's an
idea under that dynamic
that we can play with.
OK?
AUDIENCE: OK, so a
few quick things.
One would be, I'm not
exactly sure how
this fits into a game.
But simulating people who are
delusional schizophrenic by
either having every player have
a separate audio track
playing in their ear
as they play?
So there's voices speaking to
them and they have different
audio experiences.
Or having just one speaker that
everyone can hear that's
playing audio.
So incorporating audio into the
experience to simulate in
some way the internal thought
processes and perhaps these
delusional thoughts.
The voice that tells you to go
kill your mother and what not.
Which is a documented issue.
PROFESSOR: This particular
game doesn't have to be a
board game, doesn't have to be
a card game, you have a lot
more flexibility in what
you want to do.
I would suggest steering away
from doing anything that
requires digital logic.
But MP3 players would
be perfect.
AUDIENCE: Exactly, something
like that.
So the second thing would be a
board game where you're in
charge of managing a ward.
It's just a logistical game.
Making sure that you don't
leave anyone neglected or
forget anyone.
So your patients have their
favorite nurse, and they have
issues that you have to
uncover and deal with.
And if you leave somebody
unattended and someone goes
over they may become violent.
So you've got to try
and make sure.
And then the third idea would be
to have one player play as
the patient and to simulate
their inability to communicate
properly for whatever reason.
The information of their
condition is
hidden from the player.
And so try to create a game
experience that is genuinely
frustrating because the player
doesn't quite know what's
wrong with them and can't
articulate it properly.
And the other players are in
charge of finding it out.
And putting some kind of
time-constraint things where
it gets heated.
PROFESSOR: There are a bunch
of improv games that are
exactly that.
I have something about me but
can't tell you what it is.
AUDIENCE: But the players know
that it can get really, yeah.
AUDIENCE: That's like the game
where you have, I can't
remember what it's called, but
the one where you have to try
to make the other person
say a word.
But you can't use a certain
series of key words.
AUDIENCE: I'm simulating
schizophrenia with audio tape.
Being part of RPG's which
have done that well.
So like live-action role
playing stuff.
Which did it really well.
It actually works.
So I recommend that.
It's been tried in a setting
which I've seen before and
worked really well.
So I think it could work out.
PROFESSOR: You could do a
refinement on that idea.
AUDIENCE: So I know one of the
main things that he was
talking about was knowing what
to do and just going through
the process of what happens when
somebody does something.
And so that brought to mind
D & D, and how you have to
prepare for the encounter and
then in the encounter you have
certain actions that
you can do.
Calm through speech, calm
through presenting some
object, or some idea
or whatever.
Which I think would map pretty
easily into the D & D space.
And then you could also have
certain abilities which are
natural to your character like
you're very charismatic which
makes some things
easier and such.
So simplify D & D to handle
interactions with patients.
PROFESSOR: So table-top
RPG style.
And the kind of things you want
to emphasize are things
like preparation and playing
up your actual skills?
AUDIENCE: Right.
PROFESSOR: Things that
you're good at.
So natural skills
and preparation.
AUDIENCE: So I had an idea for
a game that could potentially
be a card game.
Where the player who's playing
as the patient and the player
who's playing as the doctor
are operating
under different rules.
And one of the main points of
the game is they're not
actually aware of the other
player's rules.
So, for instance the patient
could have certain goals which
he is trying to achieve.
But he is unaware which of
these goals is completely
unreasonable to the doctor.
And the doctor has certain
actions he can take and is
unaware which of these
are going to be
threatening to the patient.
And so, then there could be an
instance where the patient
actually believes the only way
he is capable of winning the
game is by using violence.
And so that could be one
of the end conditions.
PROFESSOR: So, sure.
And you have to deduce
that out?
Moving on to Michelle?
AUDIENCE: I like the idea that
a psychiatrist has to really
keep their composure when
dealing with a violent person.
They can't raise their voice.
They have to keep at
a certain distance.
And they can't seem upset
for whatever reason.
Sort of a party game idea, you
could have two people.
Basically, one person would
just have to be throwing
insults at the other person.
And the person who's receiving
the insults would just have to
stay calm the whole time and
continue to talking.
Which is really hard to do even
if you know it's coming.
PROFESSOR: So keep your cool.
I mean, that could be a game
where you're literally
insulting someone or it could
be a thing where you're
playing a character with a
certain amount of composure
points or something and you're
planning actions and
maintaining notes.
And different tactics to be
able to increase those or
decrease those.
AUDIENCE: A co-op type of game
where you are a bunch of
nurses trying to take
care of the ward.
This is a lot like Jeremy's
Diner Dash style game.
Except, you have a limitation
to how you can
actually do it once.
So you will be forced to
neglect one often.
PROFESSOR: A patient, one?
Neglect one patient?
AUDIENCE: So nurses
will get sick and
they'll have to leave.
PROFESSOR: So, rather you
have limited resources.
Not quite nearly enough to deal
with every single crisis
that's going to happen.
AUDIENCE: So the one thing I
found interesting in reading
this stuff is statistically the
amount of violence that
happens with mental patients is
not actually that different
from the amount of violence that
happens in the general
population.
And it talks about how people
going through this, and
deciding to go into the
profession, might actually
second guess themselves
because they have this
perception of there's
more violence.
So I think incorporating
something where you have life
in the ward and life
outside of it.
So you incorporate both the
things where you're trying to
deal with patients but you're
also reinforcing this idea
that it's not significantly
more dangerous
than real life is.
AUDIENCE: None of your patients
stab you but you get
mugged on the way home.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, something
like that.
It's just life.
PROFESSOR: One thing that could
be really attractive is
that now broadens your audience
to people who aren't
just psychiatric residents.
AUDIENCE: So, I like the idea
of the patient and doctor
having different roles, rules,
goals, views, et cetera.
But I also like the idea of
incorporating an escalation
and de-escalation into
the conflict
between the two of them.
So I feel like part of the
thing which was really
compelling about the
role-playing scenario which
they showed was there was then
sense in which the doctor can
say things which can escalate or
de-escalate the situation.
Make it more or less likely that
things will go a bad way.
And one way which that could
be done partially through
roles would be to have hidden
keywords which the patient
responds to or what have you
and that moves them into a
different state.
And then transitioning between
these two states changes the
goals which the patient has so
maybe the intent on trying to
get Nurse-- what was
the nurse's name?
Dave?
AUDIENCE: John.
AUDIENCE: Nurse John.
But as they get de-escalated
then they just want to change
their meds.
But then as they get
de-escalated from that then
they just want to
go run back out.
PROFESSOR: Just coming up with
the rules that model what an
unreasonable patient would
do or what are you
willing to give up.
And actually putting somebody
in the shoes of that, is
essentially something
to think about what
I can do as a doctor.
AUDIENCE: So, there was this
guy we used to play in my
family where you're given a
scenario and certain number of
words you can't use.
Essentially, you choose random
words and you have a scenario.
Basically what you were saying
where certain keywords do
certain things.
But you have to somehow create
the best story or the best
calm-down passage to read
to the patient.
And then there's some
arbitrator, the GM of the
game, that decides which of
the three people that were
playing which one had the
best story out of those.
To get you to have to come up
with something to deal with,
You need Nurse John
right away.
PROFESSOR: You could do a thing
where you had to create
a story about a random
explanation
of elements or cards.
But then some number of those
cards, specifically the other
player or maybe the game of
other players specifically
just saying.
Those internally are supposed
to be our keywords.
And there's some 20 questions
type of way to try and figure
out what those cards are.
So that would be like a doctor
trying to figure out what
they're dealing with while
they're [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: You can make that
game like Guess Who.
Where each person draws a card
and you have to give a
statement to the other person
or ask them something.
And then you see whether they
escalate or de-escalate and
each individual card
has a trade story.
If you talk about
this that's bad.
If you talk about this
that's good.
PROFESSOR: I'm not familiar
with Guess Who.
AUDIENCE: OK, so it's
not really that
much like Guess Who.
AUDIENCE: 20 questions?
AUDIENCE: What I can think of
is everyone just has a whole
bunch of character cards and
each of them have traits.
Like, watch this.
If you you say this
they'll get upset.
If you say this, it's not
very fully fleshed out.
But everyone just randomly
draws traits.
And you just take turns speaking
to each other.
And then the patients
either will
respond or get more angry.
PROFESSOR: So it's almost like
your role is a collection of
randomized traits or randomized
behavioral rules.
So, rules determined by
randomized rules.
For those people in the
Assassin's Guild, or are
familiar with the Assassin's
Guild, there's the concept of
assignments.
Things that you as an individual
player are given at
the beginning of the game as
things that you can do and
have to do.
Or if you do something you
have to do it in these
specific conditions.
Psychological limitations
is what they're called.
It could be something as simple
as you have to speak in
an accent all the time
or you have to limp.
It could be something more like
every time you see blood
you have to run away because
there's a [INAUDIBLE].
It might be interesting to think
of a collection of those
things and that crafts
how we play.
So this makes me think I
should probably do the
live-action class at some point
and talk about party
games and role-playing games.
I think you had your hands up?
AUDIENCE: No, my hands
are in my pocket.
PROFESSOR: Your hands are
just up, correct?
AUDIENCE: Another thing that
psychiatrists do when they're
talking to a patient is to try
and get the story out of them
as to why they're upset.
So you could have a game where
the patient has some set of
cards that has some set of story
with some keywords and
the doctor has to try and get
these words out of him.
But the patient, himself,
doesn't fully know his story
so it keeps on changing.
You can keep modifying your
story as you go by drawing
cards and putting them away.
And you can only really get the
full picture once you get
all the cards from the
patient that you can.
PROFESSOR: So, does the patient
have all the cards?
AUDIENCE: The patient
has his full story
but it keeps changing.
PROFESSOR: So, ever-changing
story and you want to stay on
top of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Yes.
AUDIENCE: This isn't really
a fleshed out idea.
But as a mechanic?
Say there's a doctor and
a patient and the only
communication is
through cards.
So the doctor will give the
patient two cards, and then
the third card is randomly
inserted off of a deck and
shuffled in.
The patient receives
all three.
So the patient might
be schizophrenic
and imagining things.
And they get what the doctor
is saying but they also get
other random things as points.
PROFESSOR: So as a mechanic
that would be--
man, that's hard to describe.
The idea that you will be adding
the randomized element.
AUDIENCE: So you get information
that is both what
the other person played, and
something random, and you
can't distinguish
which is which.
AUDIENCE: You have a
communication channel and
you're adding random noise.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
Is that a question
[INAUDIBLE]?
I am running out of space,
so that's a good thing.
Any other ideas?
That's creepy.
Anyone else?
AUDIENCE: One concept I thought
was interesting,
though I'm not really sure how
to turn it into a game
immediately, is the idea of the
patient and specifically
the doctor or the rest of the
world having at the moment
irreconcilable narratives.
And the goal of bringing those
into some type of medium in
which the patient can
comfortably exist with this
narrative that's in line with
the rest of the world.
PROFESSOR: So the idea, again,
of narrative disruption is why
people get violent in
the first place.
So maybe even taking out the
question entirely of is this
person going to act violently,
but can you even work together
with somebody to change how they
see the world until it
makes sense on both sides.
AUDIENCE: So with that,
something I can't actually
think of a game for it right
now, be something like you
have the patient and doctor.
One person trying to figure
out the other person, the
other person trying to
trigger the other.
But there's something in the
middle that's changing
everything.
So it's just trying to reconcile
the difference.
Figuring out the connection and
communication between the two.
PROFESSOR: So you have a
situation where you actually
have three people playing.
And there's one person who's
changing information on some
predictable or unpredictable
way.
AUDIENCE: Maybe they have their
own objective in mind.
The two people on the ends are
trying to figure out what the
other one's saying and then one
person in the middle has
their own agenda, representing
schizophrenia.
PROFESSOR: So there's a noisy
communication channel with an
agenda --I like that.
That could be an algorithm or
that could be a person.
It could be a person running
an algorithm in their head.
AUDIENCE: I mean the noisy
communication channel, or the
actual state of mind of
the patient, that
is the point right?
And then depending on their
level of arousal, that could
change how everything
gets screened
into being very combative.
And so everything the doctor
says is taken as being.
PROFESSOR: Some sort of parable
that's actually going
to affect how they were
able to [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
AUDIENCE: This would probably
only work once, the first time
you play through, but again
you've concealed from the
players, or certain players,
themselves
what their goals are.
Or what they believe think
about the game.
Say, it is in fact a delusion
or not true.
So you might tell them that it's
about a game set in 2100
when you've been wrongly
imprisoned in a psychiatric
ward and you must fight
your way out or
something like that.
And there's a voice that will
guide you, or whatever.
And then you don't tell that
player that they're in fact
playing a schizophrenic player
who will [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
these things.
And then you use some sort of
live-action role playing or
not, I'm not exactly sure, but
this other guy is convinced
that this is what the
game is about.
PROFESSOR: I could write
a [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
rivals scenario.
The player's don't know that
going in, but folks have seen
the film The Cabinet
of Dr. Caligari.
It's an old German expressionist
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
film.
I could spoil it?
Does anyone care?
It's an old 1920s.
AUDIENCE: I think you're fine.
PROFESSOR: But the basic idea
comes down to the hero of the
horror story is actually
just a patient in
a psychiatric ward.
And everybody who he believes
is part of the story he's
conquering is somebody else
in the psychiatric ward.
The big villain is actually the
person running the ward.
AUDIENCE: That's like
Shutter Island.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, it's
like Shutter Island
PROFESSOR: Not entirely unlike
a lot of different stories.
But similar idea of the
information being given is not
to be trusted.
AUDIENCE: Something to go
along like that, a game
mechanic for that would be
everyone's assigned a
different role.
And one of those roles
is patient.
So you don't know if you're
the patient or not.
And so in time as you do your
objectives, and as you play
along you may start to
realize things aren't
actually as they seem.
So eventually you may
figure out I'm
actually the patient here.
PROFESSOR: Right, almost
like primeval
authority in that sense.
AUDIENCE: Going along with that,
I think an interesting
mechanic would be like the
Battlestar Gallactica.
The person knows that they're
a Cylon but they can
infiltrate by doing that voting
system at the end.
What is that?
The [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So you know that someone's
trying to sabotage you but you
don't know who.
PROFESSOR: So that's who's
the patient from a
different way, right?
One is, player knows who--
at least one person knows and
the other one is trying to
figure out whether
they are it.
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: This is just an
interesting mechanic.
There was this RPG called,
Great [INAUDIBLE]
Game that had this really
interesting mechanic for
handling the dark side
that each player had.
Which might be relevant
in this situation.
Essentially you had a different
person who's also
playing another protagonist
also play your antagonist.
And so, they would either talk
to you and tell you things or
they would just directly control
your character like if
you fail at the composure
role.
And taking the adversarial side
of your character away
from your control, it means that
your character is more
likely to behave in a really
disruptive way.
Rather than just a controllably
disruptive way
would be if you had a vested
interest in your character.
PROFESSOR: So, open end case
control of your character.
And that might work really well
with some of the ideas of
the good cop bad cop idea that
someone thought of already.
AUDIENCE: So, actually going
off of the audio idea of
someone is actually
hearing voices?
If it was the patient thing.
You could actually have things
where you have one player is
actually playing a patient who
is schizophrenic and another
player is playing the
voices in his head.
But they don't really
know that.
They are playing the scenario
where they have some delusion
that they're trapped
in whatever.
So having a person actually
being the--
as you're saying-- having an
actual person be the dark side
of the patient.
PROFESSOR: But neither of them
know who's the dark side?
AUDIENCE: The patient, yeah,
you could have it.
AUDIENCE: One way you could
arbitrate it is you could say,
the patient player is
just basically able
to do as they please.
But there are rules which govern
whether the dark side
character can take over.
And that means that the patient
is genuinely driven by
trying to reach a compromise but
they can just be overruled
by the dark side.
AUDIENCE: There could also be
things where it could be more
like a strong role-playing
thing?
Where the voice is actually just
trying to convince them
that yes, this delusion
is real.
PROFESSOR: So, do you
still think you
have a recorded thing?
Or two different?
AUDIENCE: You could actually
have two people just actually
standing there talking.
PROFESSOR: So two people playing
one character at once.
AUDIENCE: It would potentially
require a lot of suspension of
disbelief on the part of
the person playing the
psychiatrist.
PROFESSOR: It might be one of
those things that's easier to
mediate by having people
talk on screen or
something like that?
Or a microphone in a
speaker type thing?
[INAUDIBLE PHRASE]
I've not seen many games that
are designed specifically to
be played on the [INAUDIBLE]
function.
AUDIENCE: I definitely like
that idea, and I think it
could work well in a
card game as well.
If you have two players sharing
the same hand, and the
player who actually gets to play
the cards from the hand
is whoever's in control
of the patient.
And so the state basically
changes depending on what the
doctor does.
Different players come in
control of the patient's hand.
PROFESSOR: So it seems like
we actually have a lot of
different options on how we
could mechanic someone who's
going to be unstable.
And also, a bunch of ideas on
how that state switch could
happen or what makes
it take over.
So that's pretty cool.
And that's not mutually
exclusive from any other ideas
that are specifically
about the patient
and the doctor, right?
So we're talking about what
happens to the patient.
These are the rules a patient
could be operating under.
The doctor could have a
different set of rules.
AUDIENCE: I was reading about
this, and I think that it
turns out most violence in
psychiatric wards happens to
the patients themselves or to
other patients by patients.
Much more than it actually
happens towards practitioners.
And I'm just noticing that I
don't think any of our ideas
address any of those issues.
PROFESSOR: Ward management maybe
gets a little closer.
AUDIENCE: People start turning
on themselves.
And I was just thinking another
possible way you could
apply a lot of these
role-playing multiple role
auditory mechanics is
to a situation.
We should probably do research
in what situations lead to
patients coming in contact
with each other and the
encounter turning violent.
And all players be patients that
have various different
mental disorders, and just to
help you understand as a
patient what kinds of behaviors
and situations would
lead you to going violent
on someone else.
Just like one of those, be in
someone else's shoes helps you
understand the situation
better.
PROFESSOR: So we're just putting
them in an environment
where everything that is
necessary for a different
character to become upset and
violent and just see how it
naturally occurs.
[INAUDIBLE].
OK.
AUDIENCE: They gave a persuasion
that's a cross
between BS and Uno.
So you have two doctors who are
trying to get rid of cards
in their hand, and the patient
wants a certain set of cards.
And he's saying, I'm
looking for John.
And the two doctors pull out a
hard and say, oh this is John.
Or they can be like, oh this
isn't John but I can
help you out later.
PROFESSOR: That almost seems
like it's intended to teach
people about lying.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR: So, I'm going
to say it's almost
like BS and Go Fish.
So we have a pretty
good pile here.
A lot of these can obviously
be combined.
And there's no reason why
multiple groups couldn't
attempt to do similar topics.
In fact, you could take exactly
the same set and I'm
pretty sure you're going
to [INAUDIBLE].
So that's fine.
Again, a lot of things that
could probably be easier done
live-action.
Or easier to do a prototype
The folks who were here on
Monday, they are actually
focused mostly on trying to see
what could be moved out to
more resonant things
in the future.
Your games don't necessarily
need to do that.
But you might want to
keep that in mind.
Because this assignment is a
game for a client after all.
And if you manage to
address that need--
here's something that doesn't
require one person from the
original GM team.
You can imagine the acting
exercise that we ran through,
beyond talented improvising
on their feet.
Requires people and requires
responses that may not
necessarily every gaming
environment's going to have.
Something that can be turned
into a very understandable set
of rules or using technologies
that are very accessible.
They're going to play your voice
and its going to be a
lot easier than something like
formulas or something like a
phone as opposed
to [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: It was a phone
conversation actually going?
So if it's live, and people are
in different rooms, and
actually talking to each other
over the phone or Skype or
something like that.
But you're talking to someone?
You have the phone-ups and then
that other person can
hear what you're saying
and be the evil voice?
PROFESSOR: That's the thing,
you don't even
need to do it on Skype.
You just get two cell phones
with [INTERPOSING VOICES]
Now, the technology just becomes
that much easier for
games [INAUDIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: Or you could make it
like if there's some game that
two people are playing.
The two groups that are playing
the same game but they
both hear the other group.
Like this group would
hear the other
group's playing the game.
So it's not even just a
random conversation.
They're playing the same game
you're playing but you're
hearing them play games.
PROFESSOR: Wow.
Wow.
AUDIENCE: That's deep.
PROFESSOR: I could
say two groups
eavesdropping same game.
AUDIENCE: I just wanted to say
that I think the thing which
is really hard if you're working
with people who like
don't really want to do a
role-playing thing is building
a level of emotional intensity
and the fear of violence.
Which is the point
of the training.
They want them to be able to
deal with that kind of
emotional stress on your feet.
So I was just wondering.
Because I don't have
any good ideas.
Can anyone think of something
which works out?
AUDIENCE: Which could genuinely
create a situation
where one could be afraid
of violence?
AUDIENCE: Without actually
having to
threaten another person.
AUDIENCE: I don't think you're
going to be able to do that.
AUDIENCE: Well, if one player's
role is actually not
to understand but to provide the
experience for the other?
And they are hearing the
recording that's giving them
cues as to what to do?
And the other player's not
agreed to this, and one of
their cues is like and now, grab
the other player by the
shoulders and shake them
violently and say something.
You could possibly create
a situation where
you're like, whoa.
AUDIENCE: The problem is you
have to be able to get
somebody who can do that without
cracking up in the
middle of it.
Because people do that when
they're nervous and
uncomfortable.
So you'd pretty much be
reduced to finding
professional actors.
And that's a limited resource
that puts a limitation on how
widespread your game is.
PROFESSOR: Even people
who are [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I had a thought where
you have a patient to
patient interaction.
So you have two people in
different rooms on the phone
with each other trying to
negotiate something.
I don't know what it would be.
AUDIENCE: And some other people
in each of their rooms
that are talking in their ear
and trying to distract them
from the conversation.
PROFESSOR: OK, so patient
talks to patient.
AUDIENCE: Maybe it could be
something like they're trying
to negotiate [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: With voices
in-person?
There is a specific article on
schizophrenia that I uploaded
in your resources.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Patrick first, then Michelle?
AUDIENCE: So I was thinking
something along the lines of
Battleship?
If you have a doctor player
and a patient player and
they're both looking at their
own version of the same board.
And if the patient wants to get
from one end to the other
and the doctor has to allow
whether or not they can make
their move.
But on the doctor's board they
have different obstacles.
And so the patient will
say, I want to move
from here to here.
And the doctor says, I can't
let you do that.
I can let you go from
here to here.
It'd be a game about
compromise.
PROFESSOR: OK, so sort
of a doctor mediated
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
And the Battleship analogy is
good to help us remember where
the idea came from.
Michelle?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so just
something that Owen said about
trying to simulate fear.
I mean, if you can add time
pressure to any game then I
think that strong of a stress
situation can almost be fear.
It can get [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Because what you're
really going for is stress in
making decisions.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
created stress without the
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So, an idea of how
to take the doctor mediated
board movement into
the real world?
We're talking about these phone
to phone conversations.
You could have the patient in
a room but he's blindfolded.
And he's trying to move through
the room towards an
exit in the room or something.
And the doctor has some limited
information about the
room and has to help him
navigate through the room.
And he'll say, I want
to move forward.
And he'll say, well I can't
really let you do that because
there's a pit fill of spikes
in front of you.
And you wouldn't necessarily
actually have a real pit full
of spikes in front of them.
But that kind of thing where
you're trying to gather
information and help
them through this.
And you could put time pressure
on it and say, well I
have to make a decision now
because he wants to move now.
But I might accidentally move
him into an obstacle and have
to deal with that.
PROFESSOR: You could have a
thing where there are some
things that the patient needs
to do that the patient can't
talk about.
And it might be something like
the patient has to move every
10 minutes.
And only the patient
knows this.
The doctor doesn't.
AUDIENCE: The patient has a fear
of moving to the left.
PROFESSOR: Or something
like that.
AUDIENCE: Things like that.
PROFESSOR: Patient has
to move left, right.
AUDIENCE: I think it also
emphasizes the thing they were
talking about on Monday
in that you are
both trying to not--
if it escalates to the point
where violence happens--
you're both trying to not let
yourself get hurt but you're
also trying to not hurt them.
And I think incorporating that
in some way might be cool.
PROFESSOR: Definitely a lot
of these ideas are sort of
mechanicing the patient's
limitations are really,
really, cool.
But again, remember the audience
is the residents.
So understanding what
a patient is
going through is useful.
But also thinking of rules
that help a resident
understand what they can do
is also really important.
So don't just think about
throwing a ton of limitations
on them without also given
them a release.
Things that they can
actively do.
Words that they can carry out.
AUDIENCE: So, working off the
time pressure thing, I think
that it might make sense for
these kinds of escalation,
negotiation type, situations
for the person who's
controlling the patient to know
what their triggers are.
And every time a bad thing is
said, they just reduce the
amount of time that the doctor
has to deal with them.
And they say that, they just
say minus 10 seconds.
And they have a timer and it
ticks down to reach the
conclusion of the doctor getting
them to where they
want to be.
And rather than like raising
their voice, or being
physically in some way, they
just adjust a timer.
And when it gets down
to zero it's over.
PROFESSOR: I can see that.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: I'd just like to say,
one way you could make
your players feel pressure is
to give them a really flat
goal hierarchy.
Right?
So a good example is
Missile Command.
Does everyone know that game?
Missile Command is
just six cities.
And there's missiles coming
in and you have to
shoot them all down.
And each city is equally
valuable.
So if you lose one you're in a
drastically reduced position.
Whereas games that tend to have
a more structured goal
hierarchy basically means
you can afford a loss.
Right?
So like chess is
a good example.
Where you can say, OK I can
afford to lose this.
Whereas in Missile Command you
can't afford to lose anything.
So by really capping what the
player has, what they can
afford to lose, and then making
sure that all of their
goals have equal value, that
means that every loss and
every failure is felt
much more strongly.
And I felt like, Dion when you
were doing your role play,
there was this sense, especially
coming from Caesar,
that any one thing that goes
wrong is really bad.
There's a really thin
line there.
PROFESSOR: That's especially
applicable when talking about
the doctor's goals,
not necessarily
the patient's goals.
AUDIENCE: I mean, from the
doctors' position right?
You can't really afford a
lot of mistakes in these
situations.
AUDIENCE: I'm kind of aghast,
but I was listening to what
you were saying and I have a
thought on how to combine lots
of these different ideas.
I'm envisioning a game where
there'd be two types of
players, like you were
mentioning, doctors and patients.
And there'd be one doctor
and multiple patients.
It would be a turn based game
where you go around and give
each person a turn.
The doctor would always be
in relationship to each
individual one.
And limited vocabulary I thought
was important, taking
that from a couple
of the ideas.
The patient and the doctor each
have their own set of
vocabularies and the
clash of that would
introduce mechanic there.
Where the patient has their own
vocabulary describing to
the doctor what they like,
what they don't like.
They know what they like.
You could extract it to describe
anything the doctor
would have in their
vocabulary.
So, as one example the doctor
could give the patient a card
with a shape or some
item on it.
And the item has attributes like
color, shape, something
that somebody could
like or dislike.
In their list they could look
at this and see one of these
things clashes with something
in my list of dislikes.
I don't like that card.
I'm going to escalate my anger,
my displeasure, with
the situation.
And so, the doctor has a limited
amount of time to deal
with each patient.
As the patient's escalation
increases, they have less and
less time to be dealt with.
After a certain point the doctor
loses that patient, so
you have that loss brought in.
And then after all the patients
have been lost the
game is over.
The way that it would be won
is that the doctor is
discovering the profile
of each patient.
Because they are trying to, like
in a normal setting or a
real world setting, you're
trying to discover the profile
that allows the doctor to deal
with the patient in the best
possible way so that they
aren't violent.
PROFESSOR: So that seems to
play off the patient and
doctor have different
rules and triggers.
You've got a situation where, in
what you're suggesting, you
have one doctor and
multiple patients.
Which is accurate.
I'm not quite sure that they'd
be dealing with them
simultaneously but it might
not matter for the
purposes of the game.
It might be like those improv
games where you manage to
figure out before time
runs out what a
person's profile is.
That could be the
win condition.
So it's equal win
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and equal loss if you don't
actually get it incorporated
with something like you give a
trigger and reduce the amount
of time you have available, the
number of turns available.
It doesn't have to
be real time.
So you can use it with
multiple patients.
So that doesn't even necessarily
have to deal with
talking about actual psychiatric
ward situations.
That could be something like
objects and colors.
It's more of a guessing game.
That might be too abstract,
possibly, because in the end
you want people to be able to
tie it back to the experience.
To be able to make an easy
connection to what it's like
to be a resident or what
it's going to be
like to be a resident.
So this is where the theme
needs to be pretty clear.
But in [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
talked, fear is not meaning.
Meaning is also tied pretty
well with your mechanics.
So that's just something
to keep in mind.
OK?
PROFESSOR: We probably have
another half-an-hour class.
I think the plan was just to let
everyone figure out teams
you wanted to be in.
This is going to be class time
to talk to each other and see
if there's stuff in here
that people are
really psyched about.
Is there anyone in this class
that's already like, this is
something I really want to do?
AUDIENCE: Well, my preference is
towards the ward advantage.
To ward advantage?
PROFESSOR: I don't really
have a plan [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I'd be interested in
voices and hidden information.
So fooling players and that
result in them behaving in
erratic ways.
And as from the point of view of
other players, and then the
point of view of player's
behaving erratically, other
players are behaving erratically
because it's not
in line with what they think
is actually going on.
Or voices, or both, or
something like that.
PROFESSOR: So that's the general
territory you're
interested in going into?
Who wants to?
AUDIENCE: I'm very interested
in the escalation and
de-escalation by hidden
keywords.
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I like basically
hidden rules, goals, and
keywords, and two different
players
playing the same character.
Those are two mechanics
I really like.
PROFESSOR: We have a couple
of seats out there.
Caffeine helps, there's
a bunch.
What do we have on Friday?
GUEST SPEAKER: On Friday we
mostly just have brainstorming
and team-building scheduled?
That time is pretty flexible.
PROFESSOR: S0 what I can do
maybe, if folks can plan to
come into Wednesday with a team,
what I'm going to do is
I might move my--
AUDIENCE: You mean Friday?
PROFESSOR: --Sorry,
Friday, yeah.
Then I will move my
live-action talk
up to Friday instead.
So Wednesday we can just-- since
it seems like a lot of
people are going in
that direction.
You don't have to do a
live-action game, but it's one
of my favorite games.