PROFESSOR: And now we're going
to problem number four.
Now we have a capacitor
with a dialectric.
And that is always a
little bit harder.
Here is the capacitor.
The area is 1 square meter.
It has a distance 'd' between
the plates, and what we are
being told is that the net 'E'
field in the capacitor is 1.4
times '10 to the 6' 'newtons
per coulombs' or 'volts per
meter', which ever you prefer.
And there is here a dialectric
inside with a dialectric
constant of 4 and 1/2.
We're being asked what the free
surface charges density
is on the plate, that we call
that for definition free, and
what induced surface charge
densities on the dialectric.
And for that I'm going to make
an enlarged picture.
Here, the top plate, I make,
artificially, a gap, but the
gap is not there.
Here is the dialectric, and
again, I make here,
artificially, a gap.
Let's assume that the top plate
is positively charged,
then there will be free charge
here on this plate.
Let's call it 'sigma free'.
And there will be an equal
amount of negative charge.
Again, 'sigma free'.
In the absence of a dialectric
there would
be an electric field.
I call that the 'E free'.
And that free field is
easily calculable.
That would be 'sigma free'
divided by 'epsilon 0'.
In the absence of
this dialectric.
However, the dialectric is going
to be charged, itself.
We get negative induced
charge here.
I call it 'sigma-induced'.
It has the opposite sign, and
we got positive induced
charge, here.
'Sigma- induced' positive.
And this positive and this
negative charge will produce
an electric field--
I call it 'E-incuded'-- and do
which is opposing the electric
field without the dialectric.
And what you have in here is,
of course, the net electric
field, 'E net', which is the
vectorial sum of 'E free' plus
'E-induced'.
All right.
Let's now apply Gauss's Law to
a little bill box like so.
Within an area 'E' here, the
electric field outside the
plane capacitor equals 0.
Inside here I have an
electric field,
which is this net field.
It's pointing perpendicular
to the surface.
There's is no flux leaking
out through the sides.
And I want to write down,
now, Gauss's Law in
two different ways.
First, I'm going to say that 'E
net' times that area 'A' is
the total charge inside that
box divided by 'epsilon 0'.
What is the total charge
inside that box?
That is, 'sigma free' minus
'sigma-induced'--
the minus sign because the
induced charge here is
negative, and I assume
that this metal
plate here is positive--
times 'A'--
this is the total charge
inside my pill box--
divided by 'epsilon 0'.
But--
and this is the definition
for dialectric--
it is also equal to 'sigma free'
times 'A' divided by
that dialectric constant
'K' 'epsilon 0'.
This is all the same.
And if you never want to bother
with induced charges,
you can just forget about this
and immediately write
down the 'K', here.
And what you see, here, that the
effect of the dialectric
is, if the dialectric constant
is 4.5 , that the 'E' field,
because of the dialectric, is
4.5 times the smaller that
what it would have been if the
dialectric hadn't been there.
You can just see this.
If a dialectric hadn't been
there, this would have been
the answer.
That would've been
the 'E free'--
that's this field.
But since the dialectric is
there, that's not the case.
Now, we lose the 'A's.
And now it's a little
bit up to you.
Let us combine first this
one with this one.
I have one equation with
'sigma free' as--
no, no, no.
I'm going to do it slightly
differently.
I first take this.
And gives me one equation with
'sigma free' as unknown.
So you solve immediately
for 'sigma free'.
Now I take this equation, but
I know 'sigma free', and so
this equation now is, again,
one equation with
'sigma-induced' as unknown.
So now you can solve for
'sigma-induced'.
If you want to combine them in
a clever way, if you like
that, it's easy to prove that
'sigma free' equals '1 minus
'1 over 'K''' times
'sigma-induced'.
Don't try to remember that, but
that's what will follow
from these results.
So due to the dialectric the net
electric field is reduced.
And so if I summarize the
situation, the 'E' field--
this is my short
hand notation--
because of the dialectric is 4.5
times lower than what it
would have been if the
dialectric hadn't been here.
Therefore, the potential
difference over the plates is
4.5 times lower.
Because remember, the potential
difference is simply
'E' times 'd', and 'd'
is not changing.
'C' equals 'Q free' divided by
the potential difference.
'Q free' is not changing, the
potential difference goes
down, and so the capacitance
goes up by a factor 'K'.
So with the dialectric, the
capacitance has a 4.5 times
larger capacitance.
The little 'u', which is energy
density, how many
joules per cubic meter equals
1/2 times the dialectric
constant times 'epsilon
0' times 'E squared'?
This would be in joules
per cubic meter.
It's easy to calculate
how much this is.
I found it to be 39.0.
Because I think you know 'E',
you know 'K', so that is
rather easy.
Since you know, if you want to
know the total 'U', you have
to take the little 'u' times
the volume, and that is the
little 'u' times the area 'A'
times the separation 'd'.
This was 1 meter.
You are given 'd', so you can
calculate what the total
electric energy is
in this system.