WALTER LEWIN: We go
to number six.
Again, a classic.
Because it's a cylinder
in a cylinder.
And that means you smell
Gauss's Law.
Both metallic surfaces.
It has length 'l'.
The radius here is a, the
radius here is b.
That is '+q' charge.
Only on the outer surface of
this metal, but there is no
charge here.
At least that was the situation
when Professor
Becker gave me the problem.
He may change his mind between
now and when you see him.
But that's the case, that's
the situation
the way I saw it.
Now clearly, as a result of this
'+q' charge, there will
be a '-q' charge induced on the
inside of this cylinder
and a '+q' induced on the
outside of that cylinder, but
the net charge on that
cylinder is 0.
And you're being asked now
what the E field is
everywhere in space.
Well, 'r' less than a inside
this metal, 'E' is 0.
That is easy.
'r' less than 'b' and larger
than 'a', which
means in this opening--
we've done that before,
I think you
should do that yourself--
we get 'E' equals 'q' divided
by '2 pi r l 'epsilon 0'' if
'r' is this distance.
And it is pointing outwards,
so I give it a 'r roof'.
We've seen this before in our
previous assignment when we
called 'q' divided
by 'l' as lambda.
So you may want to
revisit this.
It's a famous result
for a cylinder.
But now, since there is no net
charge on the outside, this is
also true for 'r'
larger than 'b'.
Because if you make yourself
a Gaussian cylinder with a
radius larger than 'b', then the
charge inside remains '+
q' because this '-q' and '+q'
here cancel each other out.
There is no net charge, so you
find exactly the same answer.
What is now the potential
difference between this point
and this point between
the two cylinders?
And I will just write that
down-- shorthand notation--
as 'Va' minus 'Vb', which is the
integral in going from 'r'
equals 'a' to 'r' equals 'b' of
'E' in the cavity dot 'dr'.
That equals 'q' divided by '2
pi l 'epsilon 0'' times the
integral going from 'a'
to 'b', 'r roof' dot
'dr' divided by 'r'.
Remember, the field pulse is
'1 over r' because we're
dealing with cylinders.
This here, this dot product, is
scalar, which is the same
as 'dr' and this integral equals
the logarithm of 'b'
divided by 'a'.
And so since this is positive,
since 'b' is larger than 'a',
you see that 'a' has a larger
potential than 'b'.
if you want to know what the
capacitance is of the cable,
well, then I have to scratch
my beard a little bit.
Well, I don't have one.
Because whenever I have to
calculate capacitors, I've
always been taught to put the
same positive charge on one
metal surface, and the same
negative charge on the other.
Then calculate the E fields,
calculate the potential
difference, and then simply
say, 'C' equals
'Q' divided by 'V'.
But they don't have the same.
There's no positive charge
here and the
same negative charge.
So let me, for now, for the sake
of the argument, put '-q'
charge on the insides of the
cylinder and forget the '+q'
on the outside.
So this outer cylinder
is now charged with
a net charge '-q'.
Since, because of induction,
all the charge goes on the
insides, the location that
I had is still correct.
But there's no '+q'
on the outside.
What now is the electric
field in this cavity?
It hasn't changed.
It's exactly the same
that it was before.
It's this.
So what is the potential
difference over this gap?
It's exactly the same
that it was before.
It hasn't changed.
In other words, the capacitance
'C' equals that
charge 'q' that I have here
divided by the potential
difference that I calculated,
which is the 'Va' minus 'Vb',
and that we calculated here.
You could read it here.
And so it's done.
And notice, by the way, that it
is proportional with 'l',
as it should be, because
clearly, the larger, the
longer the cylinder is, you
expect intuitively that the
larger the capacitance is.
But I hope you understand
the subtleness of why
I somehow, to be--
maybe I was too much
of a purist--
but to be absolutely on the
safe side, why I gave the
outer cylinder a '-q' charge
instead off it making neutral.
And that the '-q' charge
all goes to the
insides, well, so be it.
And that it turns out now that
I find it the same answer for
the electric field in the cavity
and therefore the same
answer for the potential
difference between 'a' and
'b', well, maybe I
was just lucky.
I don't know.
But I still think I did
it the safest way.
OK.
Now we fill the capacitor
with oil.
And the dialectric
constant is 2.2.
And we do that in the area where
there was vacuum before.
Now, 'E' remains 0 for
'r' less than 'a'.
That's not going to change.
The new 'E' in going to be the
old 'E', which we calculated,
divided by 'K'.
Remember, 'E' goes down.
That is for 'r' between
'b' and 'a'.
But for larger than 'b', now
the old 'E' does not change
because there is dialectric
outside the cylinder.
So now, the old 'E' that we
calculated, which falls off as
one of our remains.
So the only 'E' that changes,
that goes down by a factor of
'K', it in between
the two shells.
The induced charge, or maybe
the induced charge density,
which you want on the
dialectric, well, I would say
you do that.
And you may want to go back to
somewhere earlier in the
assignment where I did
that for you on
the parallel plates.
I don't think you are going to
find this so different .
So no we have, what happens with
'Va' minus 'Vb' when the
oil is in place?
Well, with the oil in place the
E field in that gap goes
down by a factor, 'K'.
And since the potential
difference is simply 'E' times
'd', and since 'd' is not
changing, the potential
difference goes down
by that factor 'K'.
And therefore, 'C' goes
up by that factor 'K'.
Think about that.
'C' equals 'q' divided by 'V'.
If 'V' goes down by a factor
of 'K', 'C' goes up by a
factor of 'K'.
Now comes a very
cute question.
Let's first assumed that
the cavity is open.
And now I, Walter Lewin,
bring in this oil.
And the question now is, when I
bring in this oil, will this
oil be sucked into this opening
or will this oil be
pushed out?
That means, do I have to do
work to keep it in there?
Well, it's a very
good question.
The way I would deal with it
is to calculate the total
electric energy in the case that
the oil is in there and
that the oil is not in there.
So now, let's write
down what 'U' is.
'U' equals '1/2 C V squared'.
Of course, you could always
use '1/2 QV' if
you like that better.
Or if you want to, you can write
down '1/2 Q squared'
divided by 'C'.
It doesn't matter which
one you pick.
I prefer to pick this one.
'Q' is now changing and since
the capacitance went up when I
bring in the oil by a factor
Kappa, it is clear that 'U'
goes down by a factor, Kappa.
Or, I call it 'K'.
Whatever.
So what does that mean?
Again, when I bring
in the oil, the
potential energy goes down.
It's like potential falling.
The system likes to do that.
Nature wants to go from high
potential energy to low
potential energy?
So what does that mean when
I bring in the oil?
That the oil is being suck in.
That's what it means.