PROFESSOR: Problem number 6.
29-49.
I have here infinity long wire,
which is, of course,
always very unpractical, and it
is drawing a current 'i1'.
And here I have a loop, a
rectangular loop, and this
distance equals 'r1', and this
distance equals 'r2'.
This loop itself has a current
going through it, 'i2'.
And the length of this arm
equals 'l', and the length of
this part of course is
'r2' minus 'r1'.
There is a magnetic field and
that magnetic field is
perpendicular to the
paper, it's in the
paper and it's uniform.
As a result of that each
one of these four--
this magnetic field, by the way,
I was a bit misleading,
is the magnetic field that
results from this current.
So I put a 1 there.
This is 'B1'.
So I only am considering the
magnetic field as a result of
the current in this wire.
So it'll be strong here, and it
will fall off as '1/r' when
I go further out.
Now I want to know what
the forces are
on these four sides.
Well, the force here, and you
should convince yourself of
that, because you're--
just the simple fact that you
know that the force equals 'i'
times 'l cross B', you can
convince yourself that the
force here will be down, the
force here will be up, and
these two forces will exactly
cancel each other.
There will be a force here,
outwards, I call it 'F2'.
And they will be a force here,
inwards, I call it 'F1'.
And these two are not the same,
because they are at
different distance:
'r2' and 'r1'.
So this force is clearly smaller
than this force.
This force is winning.
Because 'F1' must
be larger than
'F2' in terms of magnitude.
I now want to calculate what
the magnetic field is as a
function of distance
from this wire.
I use Ampere's Law.
And I will get back to Ampere's
Law later, so even if
you can't follow this answer
right away then you'll see
later how it evolves
using Ampere's Law.
I assume that by now you may
know that the magnetic fields
outside a straight wire
pulls off as '1/r'.
So the force 'F1' minus 'F2'
is the force in this
direction, will therefore
be 'mu 0' times 'i1'
divided by '2 pi'.
And I have '1 over r1'
minus '1 over r2'.
And that is the force, and there
isn't really much more
that I can add to this.
Wasn't all that difficult.
So the loop wants to move
in this direction.