We are going to problem
number 4.
Notice, we are going
quite slowly.
We have plenty of time today.
I have a wire which has a
certain length, 'l' which is
0.15 meters.
And I have a current
in that wire.
That's a little bit funny,
because you can't have a
current in a wire with a certain
lenght, because then
you get pile up of charge.
Let's assume that the wire
continues here and continues
there, but we are only
considering this portion.
We have an 'x y z' coordinate
system.
Let this be 'y', this 'z' and
this 'x', convince yourself
that it is a right-handed
coordinate system.
There is 'B' field in space and
you're being given what
'Bx' is, what 'By' is and you
are being given what 'Bz' is.
And you are being asked what
is the force on the wire.
The force on a very small
element, 'dl' of the wire,
that force would be 'df' which
equals 'I' times 'dl cross B'.
That's an immediate consequence
of the 'v cross B'
force that we just discussed.
But since here 'dl' and 'v'
always make the same angle
with each other, the wire is not
snaking through space, and
'B' is uniform, there is a sign
theta which is a constant.
It's not 1, it's not minus
1, but it is a constant.
Therefore, if I do the
integrations I could say that
the force on that whole
wire 'l' equals 'i'
times 'l' cross 'B'.
So I can take the wire as a
whole, I don't have to worry
about that the angle here is
different from the angle here
between 'dl' and between 'B'.
That's why this simple
result holds.
'l' itself equals 'lx' times
the unit vector the 'i'
direction plus 'ly' unit vector
in the 'y' direction
plus 'lz' unit vector in
the 'z' direction.
This is 0.
This is 0 because we only have
'l' in the 'y' direction.
Now we have to do the
cross product.
The cross product 'F' becomes
'i', 'j', 'k'; 0, 0.15 times
'i', 0, 'Bx,' 'By', and 'Bz'.
And this, I'm sure you will be
able to work that out for
yourself, is 0.15, this was the
length 'I' think of the
wire, times 'B of z' in the 'x'
direction minus 'B of x'
in the 'z' direction.
So this is the 'x' component,
and this
is is the 'z' component.
And there is no 'y' component
of the force.
If you want to know the
total force, well,
you can do that one.
I leave you with that.