PROFESSOR: So let's now go
to problem number 2.
And that is 28-23.
It's very clever.
A very clever idea.
We have aluminum ions,
negativity charged.
I presume they're negatively
charged.
So they have an extra
electron.
They could have been positively
charged if you
strip an electron off, but
this is my assumption.
I have here an oven in which I
heat the aluminum and out of
this oven, there's an opening
here, come aluminum ions in
various directions with
various velocities.
Large velocities and
small velocities.
And right here there's
also a small opening.
There is a condensator, here, a
plate which provides me with
a more or less constant
electric
field, in this direction.
In addition, I have a magnetic
field 'B', which is pointing
in the paper and I assume it
is uniform everywhere.
And now there is a remarkable
consequence of this set up.
By adjusting 'E' and 'B', I can
select here aluminum ions
which have a specific
velocity, speed.
I call it 'v' selected.
How does it work?
The force on these ions equals
'q' times 'E' plus 'q' times
'v cross B'.
If I make the force on these
ions 0, then obviously they
will not be deflected.
If the force is not 0, but
constant then they will
probably, if they come in like
this and the force is like
this, they will make a parabola
or they will be
accelerated in one direction.
But if this is exactly 0, so
that the net force is 0, then
they will go through
undisturbed.
The direction of this force on
a negative charge is upwards.
And the direction of this
force is downwards.
You can easily convince yourself
of that. 'v cross B'.
For this to be 0, 'q' cancels.
I have that 'v', which is the
selected 'v', equals 'E'
divided by 'B'.
If I change 'E', if I increase
'E', then I will
get a higher velocity.
If I decrease 'E', then I
get a lower velocity.
So this is a very clever way
of selecting the speed.
I should perhaps put the
magnitude here, the speed that
comes out here.
These selected aluminum ions
come out in a uniform magnetic
field, 'B'.
By the way, the reason why I
ignored this cross is that 'v'
and 'B' are perpendicular to
each other, and so I get a
plus or a minus sign due to the
sign of the angle theta.
And I have ignored that.
So I get here that the speed at
which they come out is 'E'
divided by 'B'.
And as I said, by adjusting
'E' and 'B', you can get
various velocities.
So now, let's call this point
'A', where they come out.
Now we look at them
more closely.
This is 'A'.
So here come out these selected
velocity aluminum ions.
With a certain velocity 'v'
select, and what do I see?
I see that they go around in a
perfect circle, in this case
half a circle.
And the circle has
a radius 'R'.
You're being told that the
magnetic field is everywhere
the same as it was before.
Perpendicular to the paper
and in the paper.
In order to make this
trajectory, I need a force,
centripetal force.
Here is that centripetal
force, here is that
centripetal force.
And so I simply get
that 'm v squared'
over 'R' must be 'qvB'.
Again I leave the cross out,
because the sign of theta is
either plus or minus 1.
I lose 'v' and what do I find?
That the mass equals 'q' times
'v' times 'R' divided by that
selected velocity, which itself
was 'E' divided by 'B'.
So I get this simple
relationship.
I know 'q', I know 'B', I
know 'R', I know 'E'.
And so I can calculate the mass
of the aluminum ions.
And this is what we call
a mass spectrometer.
A very clever instrument.