PROFESSOR: So let's start
with problem number
one, which is 28-15.
An electron is going around in
half a circle, this is the
center of the circle.
I call this point 'A' and I call
this point 'D', to avoid
confusion with 'B', and the
electron right here has a
velocity 'v'.
We know that the electron
follow this trajectory,
therefore there must be the
centripetal force acting on
the electron everywhere
in orbit,
pointing towards the center.
The direction changes but the
magnitude does not change.
What should be the direction
of the magnetic field to
accomplish this arc?
Well, the force equals 'q'
times ''v' cross 'B''.
'v' is the velocity of the
electron, 'B' is that magnetic
field that we're interested in,
and 'q' is the charge of
the electron.
Keep in mind that this
is negative.
When you take that into account
it will not be too
difficult to convince you that
the only way that this could
happen is if the magnetic field,
which you are being
told is uniform everywhere
otherwise it wouldn't go
through a perfect circle, by the
way, is perpendicular to
the paper and it's
in the paper.
So we already the direction.
So we're not concerned
about that.
Now we want to know
the magnitude.
'q' times ''v' cross 'B'', but
I can really write 'vB',
because the cross product
implies the sine of theta,
theta being the angle between
the velocity and the magnetic
field, but that is 90 degrees,
so that is 1, so I don't have
to worry about that.
This is the force, this is the
magnitude of the force that
you see here, and that is also
mv squared divided by 'R'.
If 'R' is the radius
off the circle.
Notice that is 'v' does not
change during this trajectory,
for the simple reason that
the force is always
perpendicular to 'v'.
Because notice this is a cross
product, so the force is both
perpendicular to 'v' and
perpendicular to 'B'.
It's also perpendicular
to 'v'.
Since the work that you do on
this electron is the integral
of 'F' dot 'ds', and since these
two are perpendicular to
each other, if I move a little
bit here, over a certain
element ds, the force is always
perpendicular, the work
done is zero.
The speed cannot change.
The velocity changes, because
velocity is a vector.
But the speed, there's no
change, so this 'v' is the
same as this 'v'.
And soI lose one 'v', and I find
that 'B' equals the mass
of the electron times that
velocity times the charge of
the electron divided
by the radius.
Since I know the mass of the
electron, I know the velocity,
I know the charge, and I believe
I know the radius, you
can calculate the
magnetic fields.
We already argued that
it is pointing down
perpendicular to the paper.
The time for half a circle,
the time to go from 'A' to
'D', is obviously 'pi r' divided
by that velocity.
So I don't think that that
could be a problem.
At all.