CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
work on the following problem:
So given the region r shown
below, which I'll mention more
of in a moment, compute the
integral double integral over
r of the quantity 4x squared
minus y squared to the fourth
dx dy, and I want you to do it
by changing variables to u is
equal 2x minus y and v is
equal to 2x plus y.
And the region defined down here
is just these three line
segments and the intersection of
the region bounded by these
three line segments.
So one of them is a portion of
the y-axis, one of the them is
a portion of the line defined
by 2x minus y equals 0, and
one of them is a portion of
the line defined by 2x
plus y equals 2.
So why don't you do this, make
sure you use this change of
variables, and then I'll come
back, and I'll draw the
accompanying region in the u,
v plane, and then we'll see
how I set it up.
OK, welcome back.
Well, the first thing I'm going
to do is I'm going to
draw the region in the u, v
plane that is determined by
this region in the x, y plane
and the change of variables.
Now, as was mentioned in the
lecture, all of the changes
are linear, and so I'm going to
be taking lines to lines.
So what I'm going to do is
determine at each endpoint
here where that endpoint goes
under the transformation, and
then I will connect the dots.
So what do I get?
Well, this first one is 0, 0
for x and y, and so that
corresponds to x and y are 0
here, so u is 0, and x and y
are 0 here, so it would be a 0,
so that's the point 0, 0 on
the u, v plane.
Now, I want to mention something
here is that based
on how these lines were defined,
this is telling you
that all along this line 2x
minus y equals 0, that means u
is equal to 0 all along
that segment.
And if you'll notice also, 2x
plus y is equal to 2 here, so
v is equal to 2 all along
this segment.
So we should expect whatever u
is, v's going to be 2 here,
and whatever v is here,
u is going to be 0.
OK, so I'm going to have
something with u, 0 initially,
and then v, 2, I can already
expect, it's going to come up
here and move over that way.
But let's just check.
So this is the point 0, 2,
0 for x and 2 for y.
Let's see what it is in
the u, v variables.
So u in that case is negative 2
and v in that case is 2, and
so I'm going to go
left 2 and up 2.
This might not be drawn to
scale, but this is negative 2,
and this is up 2 here, and so
that's where this point goes
in the transformation.
This point is 1/2 comma 1.
You can actually check
what it is.
But actually, as I mentioned,
you already know what has to
happen, because this segment is
connected right here, and
then we said all along this
line, v is 2, and all along
this line, u is 0, and
so that actually
carves out that rectangle.
So if you were worried and you
weren't able to do it that
way, what you could actually
do is say, well, where does
the point 1/2, 1 go?
If I plug in 1/2 for x and 1 for
y, I notice that I get u
equals 0 and v equals 2,
and that's this point.
And so now, I'm looking
at this region.
Now, these two things are not
drawn to the scale, because
what I want to point out is
they're both triangles.
It's easy to find the area based
on how they're sitting
in two-dimensional space.
So what we see here is if I
wanted to find the area of
this triangle, let's
make this the base.
The base is 2 and the height is
1/2, so 1/2 of base times
height is--
that area is equal to 1/2.
So the area of r is 1/2, and
what's the area of this one?
The area this one is-- well,
I've got base 2 and height 2,
and so it's 1/2 of 2 times
2, and so that
gives me area as 2.
So here the area is 1/2, here
the area is 2, and so notice
that I've multiplied by 4 to
get from here to here.
So I can anticipate that I
should have-- based on the
principle you saw in lecture,
I should have something like
du dv is going to be equal
to 4 times dx dy.
That is what I expect to get.
Now let's see if when we
do the Jacobian, we
get the same thing.
Let me double check, right?
This is area 2, this is area
1/2, so I have 1/2 times 4 is
going to give me 2.
Yeah, that's what
I should get.
Oops!
That sticks out a little.
So now let's just check our
Jacobian and see if that is
indeed what we get.
So I'm going to look at
u sub x, u sub y, v
sub x, v sub y, right?
So u sub x is 2, u sub y is
negative 1, so I get 2,
negative 1.
v sub x is 2, v sub y
is 1, so I get 2, 1.
2 times 1 is 2 minus negative
2 gives me, indeed, 4.
So I do get, in fact, du
dv is equal to 4 dx dy.
So I know that I'm going to have
to-- because I'm changing
variables, though, from dx dy to
du dv, I'm going to divide
by 4, obviously, when I
do the substitution.
The substitution will be
replacing just dx dy.
So I just mention that, but
notice: Again, we get what we
expect to get.
We got a 4 based on the picture
and we got a 4 based
on the Jacobian.
And so now, we need to finish
up the process.
We need to figure out how to
write this in terms of u and v
and then figure out our bounds
in terms of u and v, and then
we're done.
So let me mention, one thing
you should notice is that u
times v is equal to exactly--
this is going to be a difference
of two squares, and
it is precisely 4x squared
minus y squared.
If you need to multiply it out
to check, you can check it,
but that's indeed what it is,
which is why this particular
substitution is quite nice,
because that means this
function I'm supposed to be
integrating is just uv raised
to the fourth.
So I'm almost done.
So let me write in the pieces I
know, and then we'll fill in
the last two spots, or four
spots, which will be all the
bounds on the integral.
So I'm going to write it here,
give myself some space to
write the bounds.
So I'm replacing the 4x squared
minus y squared by a
uv, so I'm going to get u
times v, and then the
function, that is raised to
the fourth in the initial
problem, so I raise that
to the fourth.
Then dx dy, as I mentioned, will
be replaced by a du dv
divided by 4.
And so I can just put this
over 4 and write du dv. I
should be careful which
order I want to do.
It doesn't really matter.
I can do either one.
du dv, OK?
And so now I want to know what
u goes from and to and then
what v has to go from and to.
So if I come over here, you'll
see it didn't matter, because
I could have picked either
direction to go.
But if I'm going to go with u,
I'm coming from whatever this
function is over
to here, right?
And this value here is easy.
That's u equals 0.
So the top bound for u is 0,
and the bottom bound for u,
this is v is equal to minus u,
so the bottom bound for u is
when u is equal to negative
v. So I'm running from--
because I put the du on the
inside, my first one is
running from minus v to--
what did I say--
0, and then the v values from
there go between 0 and 2.
You can see this easily
from the picture.
So they go between zero and 2.
And I am not going to finish it
off from here, because it
would require not
too much work.
It's actually quite simple,
because it's just a polynomial
and u and a polynomial and v,
but there are a lot of powers
and there will be
big powers of 2.
So suffice it to say, at this
point, we can evaluate this
integral and it's quite
easy to evaluate.
And the main point I think we
should make is how did it make
it simpler?
I mean, the initial problem, if
we come over here, this is
annoying to find an
anti-derivative, but not
impossible.
But the really annoying part is
I would have to take this
region and split it into a bunch
of pieces, or at least
two pieces, to evaluate the
integral in a reasonable way
or my y-values would go
from this line here up
to this line here.
It could be complicated.
So what we've really done is
we've simplified the region.
That's the easiest thing.
I mean, we also simplified the
function, but we've really
simplified the region we're
integrating over.
And so we only have one is
a function and one is a
constant, and that's quite nice
to have on the inside.
So I think that's
where I'll stop.