DAVID SHIROKOFF: Hi, everyone.
So today I'd like to take a
look at linear equations,
linear first order differential
equations.
And specifically, we're going to
look at just exactly, what
is a linear equation?
So for example, which of these
equations are linear?
And then second of all, we're
going to take a look at
superposition.
And we ask to consider the
differential equation y dot
plus y squared equals some
function q of t.
And just to demonstrate that
this equation does not satisfy
the superposition principle.
So I'll let you take a look at
this problem, and try and work
it out for yourself.
And I'll be back in a minute.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
All right.
So we're asked to figure
out which of these
equations are linear.
So just to recap, what
does it mean for an
equation to be linear?
What does it mean for a first
order equation to be linear?
Well, it means that we can write
it in the general form.
So if it's a function
of dy dx plus some
general function of x.
And this could be anything.
But the point is that it's
multiplied just by y.
And then it can equal some
arbitrary function q of x on
the right-hand side.
So every first order linear
equation can be
rewritten in this form.
So let's tackle part A. All
right, y dot plus ky equals--
or y dot equals ky.
We can just rewrite it as y
dot equals negative ky.
Note that just some constant
k is a function of time.
It's a constant function of
time, but it can just be
thought of as a function
of time.
Same with the right-hand
side, it's 0.
And so this equation has the
same form as our general first
order linear equation.
So this is a linear equation.
Let's take a look at
question 2, part 2.
We have y dot plus
y squared t.
I'll bring the y to the
left-hand side.
If we do that, we get this.
And just by comparing this to
our generic first order linear
ODE, we note that it's
not of this form.
So specifically, this is the
bad term in question.
We see that it's y
squared times t.
Notice how we're not allowed
to have any term that's y
squared in our first order
linear equation.
Now I will say this
just as an aside.
This equation's also known
as a Bernoulli equation.
And as an aside, if you were
to make a substitution u
equals 1/y, and rewrote this
equation in terms of u as the
independent variable.
You'd find out that this
equation would be linear in
terms of u.
But as it's written now in terms
of y, it's not linear.
So this is a kind of an
interesting point.
That sometimes we can get
lucky and do a nonlinear
transformation and convert a
nonlinear equation into a
linear one.
So for part 3 we have y prime
plus cos x y equals x cubed.
So again, we see that this is
a linear equation because we
can identify p of x with cosine
x, q of x with x cubed.
So this equation has the general
form of a linear ODE.
For part 4, well if we take a
look at it right away, y dot
divided by y is equal
to t squared.
It doesn't appear
to be linear.
But of course, we can
multiply through by
y and rewrite things.
And of course, this equation is
equivalent to y dot minus t
squared y equals 0.
Which again, is linear because
p of t can be identified with
negative t squared and q of t
can be identified with 0.
And then lastly, for part 5,
we have x squared y y prime
plus 4x equals x cubed.
And again, if we were to try
to write it in the general
form of a linear ODE, which we
have here, it would look like
4x divided by x squared y minus
x cubed divided by x
squared y equals 0.
And because there's a y on the
denominator here, this
equation doesn't have the
general form of a first order
linear equation.
Now again, I note that if you
were to make a substitution, u
equal to y squared, that
substitution would make this
equation linear.
So this concludes part a.
So for part b, we're given a
differential equation y dot
plus y squared is
equal to q of t.
And we want to show that this
equation doesn't satisfy the
superposition principle.
Now, you might note that this
equation is not linear.
And second of all, we know that
linear equations satisfy
the superposition principle.
So we need to exploit the fact
that it's a nonlinear equation
to make it fail the
superposition principle.
And just as an example, what we
can do is I can just pick a
couple right-hand side's q
as examples of this ODE.
So we can imagine we have a
solution y1 which solves the
ODE y 1 dot plus y1
squared equals--
I'm just going to say 1 on
the right-hand side.
And I can also take another
function y2, which say
satisfies this differential
equation, say t.
So all I've done is I've just
picked one q1 on the
right-hand side and another
function q2.
And I imagined that I have a
solution y1 which satisfies
this differential equation and
y2 which satisfies this
differential equation.
So what does the superposition
principle say?
Well, superposition says that if
y1 solves this equation and
y2 solves this equation, then
the function y equals y1 plus
y2 must solve the equation y dot
plus y squared equals the
sum of the right-hand
side, 1 plus t.
So if we try and substitute in
y1 plus y2 into this equation,
we're going to come to
a contradiction.
So let's do that now.
So we take d by dt of y1 plus
y2, and I'm going to add it to
y1 plus y2 quantity squared.
And now what I can do is I
can just simplify this.
So I get y1 dot plus y2 dot.
And I can expand out
this square.
So I get y1 squared plus y2
squared plus 2 y1 y2.
And now what I'm going to do
is I'm going to combine the
term y1 with y1 squared.
And by construction, y1 dot plus
y1 squared is equal to 1,
because I assumed that
it satisfied this
differential equation.
And then in addition by
construction, y2 dot plus y2
squared satisfies the right-hand
side of the second
equation with t.
So I get 1 plus t, but I'm
left over with this other
piece 2 y1 y2.
So in general, if I take a
function which solves this
differential equation and
another function which solves
this differential equation, and
I add them together, and
plug it into the left-hand
side of this differential
equation, I get something which
is 1 plus t plus some
other stuff.
And if it did satisfy the
principle of superposition, it
must equal 1 plus t.
So we arrive at a contradiction
because it
doesn't equal 1 plus t.
In fact, it fails to equal 1
plus t by this term 2 y1 y2.
And this term comes directly
from the fact that we had a
nonlinearity in the equation.
So this is just one illustration
of the fact that
a nonlinear equation doesn't
necessarily satisfy the
superposition principle.
Whereas, every linear equation
satisfies the
superposition principle.
This is one reason we love
linear equations and we study
them extensively.
OK, so I'd just like
to conclude here.
And I'll see you next time.