CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
see how geometric methods can
help us understand the flux of a
vector field across a curve.
So in particular, what we're
going to do is try and use
geometric methods to compute
the flux of four different
vector fields F across curve
C. So I've labeled them for
later purposes.
I've labeled them F1,
F2, F3, and F4,
and they are as follows.
F sub 1 is the vector field that
is a scalar function of
only the radius times the
vector x comma y.
And the curve I'm interested
in in this
part is the unit circle.
The second one, part b, is the
vector field that is g of r.
Again, where g is a scalar
function and r is the radius--
so it depends only
on the radius--
times the vector minus y, x.
And again the C will
be the unit circle.
The third and fourth ones, we
use a different C, but they
will be the same there.
I'll point that out.
So in the third one, the vector
field is 3 times the
vector (1, 1).
And C in this case will be
the segment connecting
(0, 0) to (1, 1).
So it's a piece of the
line y equals x.
And then in part d, F will be
3 times the vector (-1, 1).
And C is, again, this segment
from (0, 0) to (1, 1).
So again, what I'd like you to
do is rather than trying to
parametrize the curve and do
the entire calculation, I'd
like to see you try and
understand the relationship
between each of these factor
fields F and the normal to the
curve that they're on.
And see if you can figure out
the flux based on that
relationship.
So why don't you pause the
video, give that a shot, and
then when you're ready to see
how I did it, you can bring
the video back up.
OK, welcome back.
Again, I'm going to try and use
my geometric intuition to
understand what the flux is for
each of these four vector
fields along these
four curves.
So what I'd like to do is
if I'm going to try and
understand geometrically what's
happening, it's always
good to draw a picture.
So I'm going to draw a picture
that I'll use for a and b, and
then I'll draw another picture
later that I'll
use for c and d.
So notice again in a, my curve
is the unit circle.
And I have a somewhat explicit
understanding of what the
vector fields are.
So I'm going to draw the unit
circle and see if I can figure
out where F1 and F2 are.
It's not a perfect unit circle,
but it looks sort of
like the unit circle.
So this is going to
be my unit circle.
And what I want to point out
first is that I was not trying
to trick you, but just to help
you notice, that in a and b,
they both depended on this
radial function.
But the radius on the unit
circle is fixed at 1.
So in both of these vector
fields, it will
simply be g of 1.
So that will be a
constant value.
So all that's giving me is
some scalar multiple of
whatever the length
of this one is.
So it's this direction times
this scalar g of 1.
One other thing I want to point
out is that both of
these vectors, F1 and F2, if I
ignore the g part, and I look
at just the x comma y and the
minus y comma x, is these
parts have unit length.
And you should be able to see
that right away, because x and
y are on the unit circle.
And so the length of the vector
whose tail is at the
origin and head is on
the edge of the unit
circle has length 1.
And then you can easily see
that this vector and this
vector have the same length,
because their individual
components are the same
absolute value.
We already understand a
few things about F1
and F2 right away.
That all the length is coming
from this g, and g is fixed
all the way around the unit
circle at g of 1.
Now let's figure out what the
flux is for these two things.
So if you notice first, F sub
1 is the vector (x, y) times
the scalar g of 1.
So if I come over here,
I want to point out--
I'll do this part in
white first-- that
if I'm at this point--
this is the point (x, y)--
the vector (x, y) is equal
to this vector.
So if I think about putting
that at this point--
I'm going to draw it here--
I get something that
looks like this.
So this is F sub 1, probably.
I'm going to have to make
one comment about that.
But notice, this should
look like
it's all in one direction.
So this is the vector (x, y).
If I slide it so its tail is
here, it's again in the same
direction, and now I've just
scaled it by g of 1.
Now, this is assuming,
obviously,
that g of 1 is positive.
So we're going to assume that
throughout this problem.
I'll mention what happens when
g is negative at the end.
So this is my vector F sub 1.
Let's think about what is the
normal to this curve.
The normal to this curve,
actually at each point on the
circle, points in exactly the
same direction as F sub 1.
Because if I'm parametrizing
in this direction--
I'll draw one down here so we
can see what it looks like--
the normal-- actually, let
me come from there--
the normal is going to look
something like this.
OK.
So it would be connecting from
the origin to that point on
the circle, and keep going
out in that direction.
That's the normal direction.
So F sub 1, if g is a positive
function, it points in exactly
the same direction
as the normal.
If g is a negative function,
it points in exactly the
opposite direction.
So F1 would be flipped
exactly around if g
was a negative function.
So if I want to compute
the flux for part a--
I'll do it down here--
if I want to compute the flux,
remember, I'm taking the
integral along the curve
of F dotted with n ds.
Well, F dotted with
n is constant.
And that's the main
point that's going
to make this easier.
At each point--
I guess I should say F1--
F1 dotted with n is always
equal to the length of F1
times the length of n
times cosine of the
angle between them.
With a very quick calculation,
you can see that winds up
being g of 1.
So the only reason I don't have
to worry about absolute
value, is if g is positive, I'm
pointing in the same direction.
If g is negative, I'm pointing
in the opposite direction.
And so the cosine theta is minus
1 instead of plus 1.
You might want to check that
for yourself, but this
is just g of one.
So that's a constant.
So this is actually equal
to g of 1 times the
integral over C of ds.
Now, what is this?
If I integrate this, I should
pick up exactly the
length of the curve.
OK.
Because this is the derivative
of arc length, so when I
integrate this, I
get arc length.
But it's a unit circle, so the
arc length is just the
circumference of the
unit circle.
So that's 2 pi times g of 1.
OK.
And that's all you get.
That's it.
So we didn't actually have
to parametrize anything.
We just had to understand F1
relating to the normal.
So I didn't draw the normal
here, but if I take this
normal and I spin around to
here, the normal is in the
same direction as F sub 1.
So now let's look at F sub 2.
And let's do this first by
pointing something out about
the relationship between
F sub 2 and F sub 1.
Notice that if I take F sub
1 and I dot it with F
sub 2, I get 0.
Right?
Because ignoring even the scalar
part, I get x times
minus y, plus y times
x, which gives me 0.
If the scalars come along for
the ride, I still get 0.
So F sub 1 and F sub
2 are orthogonal.
And in fact--
you can do this for yourself--
but if I come over and draw
the picture, F sub 2 is
going to be F sub 1
rotated by 90 degrees.
Something like this.
This is my F sub 2.
Again, if g of 1 was negative,
F sub 1 would be this
direction, and F sub 2 would
then be around here.
But ultimately, it's not going
to matter in this case whether
g is positive or negative,
because notice what happens.
If I want to integrate F sub 2
dotted with the normal, notice
the normal is in the same
direction as F sub 1, so F sub
2 dotted with the normal is 0.
So if I'm going to integrate the
function 0 all along the
curve, I shouldn't be surprised
that my answer to
part b is 0.
So there was even less
work in part b.
Because I immediately had that
F sub 2 is really in the
direction of the tangent
to the curve.
And so I have something in the
direction of the tangent
dotted with something in the
direction of the normal-- in
fact, the normal--
so I get 0.
All right.
So now I'm going to draw a
picture for c and d, and then
we're going to use that one.
And I have to make sure
I come on this side.
Sorry about that.
So here is (0, 0).
And here is (1, 1).
Actually, you know what?
I'm going to make it
a little longer.
I might need more room.
So (1, 1) I'll make a
little further up.
OK?
(0, 0) and (1, 1) and
that's my curve.
There's (1, 1).
OK.
Now, if I parametrize it in
this direction, then I can
draw my normal.
Because it's a line segment, my
normal is constant in its
length and direction.
So at any given point, it's
exactly equal to this vector,
up to the right scaling.
And it should be something
like (1, -1) divided
by square root 2.
That's my normal.
If you want it precisely,
that's what it is.
You don't actually need it to
solve this problem, though.
But that's what it is if
you want it precisely.
Now let's look at what F3 is,
and then we'll look at what F4
actually is.
So let's look at F sub 3.
F sub 3 was the vector
3 times (1, 1).
So if we come back to our
picture, at any point on this
curve, if I go in the (1, 1)
direction, I stay parallel to
this curve.
I don't want to draw the whole
thing, because it would take
up the entire curve.
It's longer than the
curve itself.
But F sub 3, at any
given point,
points in this direction.
So this is F sub 3, but not
as long as it actually is.
But only the direction is going
to matter in this case.
So F sub 3 is pointing
in this direction.
So if I want to compute
the flux, I
dot it with the normal.
But look at what happens.
The normal is orthogonal to
F sub 3 at every point.
And so F sub 3 dotted with
the normal is 0.
And so again, for exactly the
same reason as part b, in part
c, the flux is 0.
So again, it's exactly the same
that the vector field I
was looking at and I wanted to
compute the flux for, is
actually tangent to the
curve at every point.
And so when I dot it to the
normal to the curve at every
point, I get 0.
And so computing
the flux is 0.
So now, I have one more to do,
and that one is part d.
And in this case, F sub 4--
let me just remind you--
is 3 times the vector (-1, 1).
And so if we go back to our
picture here, F sub 4, if I
compare it to the normal, in
fact, what I get is very long.
This is probably not
quite long enough.
But that's at least the
direction of F sub 4.
And so F sub 4 is exactly
the opposite
direction to the normal.
So if I want to compute the
flux of F sub 4 along this
curve, all I have to understand
is F sub 4 dotted
with the normal and the
length of the curve.
This is exactly the same type
of solution as part a.
So let's notice this.
First, F sub 4, the length
is 3 root 2.
You can compute that
pretty quickly.
The length of n is just 1.
It's a normal.
That's why this stuff
didn't really matter
what exactly it was.
It's good to know what direction
it points in.
So F sub 4 dotted with n is
exactly 3 root 2 times cosine
of the angle between
n and F sub 4.
The angle is pi.
You notice they differ by
180 degrees, right?
So it's cosine pi,
which is minus 1.
So what I do in part d, is I'm
integrating along the curve
the constant negative
3 square root 2 ds.
This is exactly F sub 4 dotted
with the normal.
And so as before, this is going
to equal to negative 3
root 2 times the arc length.
Because the integral over the
curve ds is going to be the
arc length.
And the arc length is
very easy to see.
You've gone over 1 and up 1.
Right?
So Pythagorean theorem,
understanding right triangles,
however you want to do it,
the length of this
curve is root 2.
So this works out to be negative
3 root 2 root 2,
which is just negative 6.
So let me just remind you, there
were four problems here.
There are two sets of problems,
where in each case,
you have one similar
to the other.
So let me point this out
one more time, and just
sort of step back.
We had a circle, and then
in the next part
we had a line segment.
But in the circle, one of the
problems had the vector in the
direction of the normal, and
you wanted to compute
the flux for that.
And in the other, the vector was
tangent to the curve, and
so it was orthogonal
to the normal.
And you wanted to compute
the flux for that.
Obviously, when you're tangent
to the curve and then
orthogonal to the normal,
you get 0.
And that was the case
for b and for c.
When you're normal to the curve
and of constant length--
which was the case actually
for both a and d--
then all you have to do is find
F dotted with the normal,
and then find the arc length,
and multiply them together.
So that was the real strategy we
had to use for a and for d.
So hopefully, this helps you
see how the geometric
quantities are interacting to
understand the flux of a
vector field across a curve.
And that's where I'll stop.