JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about how to solve
multivariable optimization
problems using the method of
Lagrange multipliers, and I have
a nice problem here for
you that can be solved
that way.
So in this problem, we've got
an ellipse, the ellipse with
equation x squared plus for
4y squared equals 4.
So that's this ellipse, and we
want to inscribe a rectangle
in it, so here I mean actually
a rectangle whose edges are
parallel to the axes.
So I want to inscribe a
rectangle in this ellipse, and
among all such rectangles, I
want to find the one with the
largest perimeter.
So I want to find the maximal
perimeter of a rectangle that
can be inscribed in
this ellipse.
So why don't you have a go at
solving this problem, pause
the video, work it out,
come back, and we
can work it out together.
So hopefully, you've had some
luck working on this problem.
Let's get started on it.
So one thing we need to start is
we need to figure out a way
to sort of describe these
rectangles in a way that will
let us describe their perimeter,
write down what
their perimeter is.
So a natural way to do that is
to call this upper right-hand
corner of the rectangle, to
call it the point x, y.
So x, y is going to be that
upper right-hand corner of the
rectangle, and it's going to
be ranging over the region
from this topmost point on the
ellipse down to this rightmost
point on the ellipse, on this
quarter arc of the ellipse.
So if that point is x, y, we
need to figure out what is the
perimeter that we're
trying to optimize.
So the perimeter here, P, which
is a function of x and
y-- well, so x is this distance,
so the length of the
horizontal edge of the rectangle
is 2x, and we've got
two of those, so that's 4x from
the horizontal sides.
And then this height is y, so
the length of the vertical
side of the rectangle is 2y, so
the perimeter is going to
be 4x plus 4y.
So that's our objective function
that we're trying to
optimize, that we're trying
to find the maximum of.
And we also have the constraint
function g, which
is x squared plus 4y squared,
and the constraint is that g
is equal to 4.
So we have the objective
function P--
P of x, y-- and we have this
constraint function g, and so
we want to write down some
equations using Lagrange
multipliers whose solutions
will correspond to the
possible maximum points of P.
So what are those equations?
Well, we need that the gradient
of P is parallel to
the gradient g.
So that means that we need Px
is equal to lambda times gx
and Py is equal to lambda
times gy for
some value of lambda.
We need to find a value of
lambda that makes this true.
And then also, our third
equation is the constraint
equation, that g
is equal to 4.
So what is Px equal lambda gx
translate to in our case?
Let's just draw a line here.
So in our case, Px is the x
partial derivative of 4x plus
4y, so that's just 4, and gx, we
take the partial derivative
with respect to x of x squared
plus 4y squared, and that's
equal to 2x, so 4 is equal
to lambda times 2x.
And from taking the y partial
derivatives, we have that the
y partial derivative a P is 4,
Py is 4, and gy is going to be
the y partial derivative of x
squared plus 4y squared, so
that's 8y, so 4 equals lambda
times 8y, and we also have the
constraint equation x squared
plus 4y squared equals 4.
So we need to solve these three
equations, and we need
to figure out which values of
x and y are the solutions.
So I think the simplest way to
proceed here is to note that
from the first equation and the
second equation, we can
eliminate lambda between them,
and what we'll see is that x
has to be exactly four times as
large as y for this to be
true, for both of these
equations to be
true at the same time.
So we need x to be
equal to 4y.
So from the first two equations,
we have that x is
equal to 4y, and now we can
substitute that in to the
constraint equation.
So if x is 4y, then x squared
is 16y squared, so x squared
plus 4y squared is
20y squared.
So we have 20y squared
is equal to 4.
And OK, so we can solve
this for y.
We can divide by 20 and
take a square root,
so we get that y--
well, so y squared is equal to
1/5, so y is equal to plus or
minus 1 over the square
root of 5.
But remember, come back over
here, we've taken x, y to be
the upper right-hand corner,
this first quadrant corner of
our rectangle, so y is
always positive.
So we had that y squared equals
1/5 and y is positive,
so there's actually
only one root.
We don't need to consider
the negative root.
So over here, we know that
y is 1 divided by the
square root of 5.
OK, so that's y.
Now what's x?
Well, OK, so we solve for x in
terms of y, so x is equal to 4
over the square root of 5.
So Lagrange multipliers, when we
use the method of Lagrange
multipliers, we get this one
possible point at which we
have to check to
be the maximum.
But remember that when you're
using Lagrange multipliers,
you also have to worry about
the boundary of the region
that you're interested in.
So let's go look at
our picture again.
So over on our picture, this
point x, y moved along the arc
connecting the topmost point
of the ellipse to the
rightmost point of
the ellipse.
So we also have to look at the
perimeters when the point is
the topmost point and when the
point is the rightmost point.
Now, in those two cases, the
rectangle is a sort of
degenerate rectangle, and when
x, y is this point 0, 1, it's
sort of two copies of this
vertical line, this minor
axis, and when x, y is the point
2, 0, then our rectangle
just looks like the major
axis, which is
that horizontal line.
But we still have to check those
cases to see whether our
function has a maximum
and what it is.
So we need to compute the
objective function value at
this point and we need to
compute it at those endpoints.
So we need to look at P of--
so this is our point 4 over the
square root of 5 comma 1
over the square root of 5, and
we know that P of x, y is 4x
plus 4y, so that's equal to 20
over the square root of 5,
which we can also write as 4
times the square root of 5.
And we also need to check those
two endpoints, so we
need to check the point P of 0,
1, so that's 4, and we need
to check the point P of
2, 0, so that's 8.
So in order to find out what the
maximum value of P is, we
need to compare the value of P
at the points given to us by
Lagrange multipliers and at
the boundary points of the
region, which in this case are
the endpoints of the arc.
So we need to compare the
numbers 4 square root of 5, 4
and 8, and indeed, 4
square root of 5 is
the largest of these.
So this is the largest, so
this is actually the
maximum value, OK?
So the maximum perimeter is
4 square root of 5 when
rectangle has its upper
rightmost vertex at this
point: 4 over square root of 5
comma 1 over square root of 5.
So our rectangle's maximal
perimeter is 4 root 5, and
that occurs when the upper
right-hand vertex is at the
point 4 over root 5,
1 over root 5.
So to quickly recap, we wanted
to apply the method of
Lagrange multipliers
to this problem.
So we chose to keep track of our
rectangles by their upper
right-hand corner.
And then that gave us-- the
perimeter was 4x plus 4y.
That was our objective
function.
And the constraint was that that
upper right-hand corner
actually had to lie
on the ellipse.
So then we set the gradients of
the two functions equal and
solved the system of equations
that we get by having those--
sorry, the gradients not to be
equal, but to be parallel.
There's some constant multiple
lambda that appears.
So we set the gradients to be
parallel to each other and the
constraint equation to hold,
and we solved those three
equation simultaneously
for x and y.
And those equations gave us one
point that we had to check
to be the maximum, and we also
needed to check points on the
boundary of the region
in question.
So here, those were just the
two points 0, 1 and 2, 0.
So I'll end there.