Very well.
So let's now go to problem
number one.
Problem number one is 26-4.
It's In a silver wire and you're
being asked, what is
the current through the wire?
Well, the current through the
wire is the charge through the
wire divided by the time
that it takes for
that charge to flow.
You know the charge is given,
you know the time is given, so
clearly you can calculate
the current.
The current density 'J' if that
current divided by the
cross sectional area.
Which in the case of the silver
thread, the silver wire
is just the 'pi r squared'
of the cross section.
But if you look in section 26-7,
where the idea of drift
velocities are discussed, you
will see that it is also equal
to 'n', which is the number of
free electrons per cubic meter
in the metal.
'q' is the charge
of the electron
times that drift velocity.
Average drift velocity,
I should say.
And if you want to be really
cute, complete should say
there has to be here--
a vector then there has
to be a vector here.
So since you know the number
of free charges per cubic
meter, you know the charge
of an electron.
You know the 'J' because you
just calculated I, and so
obviously you'll find
the drift velocity.
And the drift velocity is of
the order of microns per
second, which is exceedingly
low.
I mean, it is so low you cannot
even imagine that these
electrons would drift
so slowly.
And this comes down to a major
misconception that most
physicists have. Most physicists
think that the
energy that is transported by
the silver wire, in this case,
is in the form of kinetic
energy of the electron.
But that's not the case.
If I would here have the silver
wire and a certain
current, 'I', would come in.
And I had here a resistor, and
say resistor 'R' for something
like 100 ohms. And we both know,
or should know, that the
power dissipated by this
resistor equals 'I squared R'.
And the energy dissipated is the
power times the time that
you let the energy come
out every second.
Now, the drift velocity, as
you will see, can be made
arbitrarily small by making that
cross sectional area of
the wire very, very,
very large.
You will see that immediately.
Because notice that if you make
this cross sectional area
very large and you keep the
current the same, then 'J'
would come down.
So the drift velocity
will come down.
And so you can come down to a
negligibly small drift velocity.
And if the energy that is going
into this resistor 'R',
if that were really the sum of
all the kinetic energies of
the electrons with the mean
drift velocity, 'Vd', that was
the sum of all these
electrons, then
obviously that cannot be.
Because this one, this drift
velocity we can make
arbitrarily small.
Whereas this number
is now changing.
It's independent of this
drift velocity.
But there are very difficult
concepts and I want you to
think about that.
It's not so obvious.
And to be frank with you,
it's not something
you can easily see.
But what I want you to remember
is that the energy
that is transported through a
wire to a resistor and the
energy comes out in the form of
heat, that that energy is
not going through the wire
in terms of kinetic
energy of the electrons.