We are going now to problem
number two.
Here I have a wire with a
certain cross section.
Cross sectional area.
Here is point 'a' on the wire,
here is point 'b'.
The length of the wire is 'L'.
I believe it's 8 meters--
it's not so important now.
And there is a current going
through the wire 'i'.
And as a result of that, if
the wire has a finite
resistance then there is an
electric field in the wire.
Now 'Va' minus 'Vb'-- there
is the potential
difference over the wire--
is given.
I should say, is given.
And also, what you're being told
is the current density.
It is also given.
So those are the two things
that you know.
And the question now is,
what is the electric
field in that wire?
And what is the resistivity
of the wire?
Well, let's first write
down what it
means, 'Va' minus 'Vb'.
That's the integral of going
from 'a' to 'b' of 'E' dot
'dl' dot product.
'E' and 'dl' are in the
same direction if I go
from here to there.
And since 'E' presumably is
constant throughout the wire,
this is simply equals 'El'.
Well, since you knew 'Va' minus
'Vb' and you know what
'l' is, out pops 'E'.
But that's an easy one.
As far as the resistivity is
concerned, the current density
'J' equals the electric field
vector divided by the
resistivity.
Check equation 26-21.
Well, we know 'J' we just
calculated 'E', out pops rho
So again, that is not a very
difficult problem.