JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about using gradients
to compute tangent planes
to surfaces.
So I have an example of a
practice problem here for you.
So what I'd like you to do in
part a is to use gradients to
find the tangent plane to the
surface z equals x cubed plus
3xy squared at the
point 1, 2, 13.
And in part b, I'd like you to
do something similar, which is
to use gradients to find the
tangent line to the curve x
cubed plus 2xy plus y squared
equals 9 at the point 1, 2.
So why don't you pause
the video, have a
couple goes at those.
Come back and we can work
on them together.
So hopefully, you had some good
luck working on these
problems. Let's just take
a look at them.
So for part a, you're given a
function in the sort of usual
form that we use to graph it,
which is you're given z equals
a function of x and y.
But in order to apply this
gradient method, what we
really want is we want to look
at this surface as if it were
a level surface of some function
of three variables.
So in order to do that, what
we want to do always is to
bring the x, y and z all
together on the same side with
just a zero or a constant
on the other side.
So let me do that.
So I'm going to rewrite the
defining equation of this
surface as 0 equals x cubed plus
3xy squared minus z, and
I'm going to define this
right-hand side to be a new
function w of x, y, z.
All right?
So if I call this thing w, then
our surface in question
is just a level surface of w.
It's the level surface
w equals 0.
And so we know in that situation
that the gradient of
w is perpendicular to
its level surfaces.
It's orthogonal to its
level surfaces.
So the normal to our surface is
exactly the gradient of w.
All right?
So gradient of w is the normal
to our surface, and a normal
is what we use to write down
the equation for a tangent
line-- oh, tangent
plane, excuse me.
So, OK, so let's compute
the gradient of w.
Well, that's not hard to do.
We just take the partial
derivatives with
respect to x, y and z.
So the partial derivative of
w with respect to x is 3x
squared plus 3y squared.
The partial derivative with
respect to y is 6xy, and the
partial derivative with respect
to z is minus 1.
So one thing to notice is that
when you do this method, when
you have the function given at
z, when you have the surface
given in the form z as a
function of x and y, you're
going to bring the z over, and
you always have a minus 1
there when you set the
problem up this way.
Because you'll have a minus z,
and then you'll just take the
partial with respect to z, and
the other terms will only
involve x and y, so they'll
be killed by the partial
derivative.
So in any case, this is our
gradient, so we want the
normal vector.
We were asked for the
tangent plane at a
particular point, I believe.
Yes, at the point 1, 2, 13.
So we need to compute the
gradient at that particular
point and that will be
our normal vector.
So the gradient at
this point is--
well, we just plug in, so the
gradient at 1, 2, 13.
So x is 1.
So this is 3 times 1 plus 3
times 4, so that's going to be
15, and 6xy is 12, and minus
1 is just minus 1.
So this is the gradient vector
at our point 1, 2, 13.
So now we have a point, the
point 1, 2, 13, and we have
the normal vector 15, 12, minus
1, so that gives us the
equation for the tangent
plane right off.
So the equation for the tangent
plane, I just dot the
normal vector with the vector
connecting our point to the
point x, y, z, so that gives us
15 times-- well, our point
is 1, 2, 3-- so it's 15 times
x minus 1 plus 12 times y
minus 2 minus 1 times
z minus 13 equals 0.
So in point-normal
form, this is the
equation for that plane.
Great.
And if you wanted, you could
rewrite this a whole bunch of
different ways, but I'll
just leave it there.
So let's do part b.
I guess I'll just start
it right below here.
So for part b, we have a curve
x cubed plus 2xy plus y
squared equals 9.
So this is a curve that is
defined by this implicit
relationship between x and y.
All right?
And so what I want
to do is I can do
exactly the same process.
We're going to do exactly
the same thing.
We're going to find the
normal-point form for the
tangent line, and so we're going
to do that by defining a
function f of x, y.
In this case, it's a function of
just two variables, because
we're only working with a
curve in two dimensions.
Before, we had a surface in
three dimensions so we had a
function of three variables.
So f of x, y, and so then our
curve is exactly a level curve
of the graph of f, right?
It's the level curve
f equals 9.
So in order to find the tangent
line, I can do exactly
the same thing.
I can find the gradient.
The gradient is normal to the
tangent line and then I can
use normal-point form.
So the gradient of f is-- again,
f is just a polynomial
function so its gradient
is easy to compute.
It's 3x squared plus 2y
comma 2x plus 2y.
And so we're interested in
this tangent line at a
particular point so we're
interested at the point 1, 2.
So the gradient of f at 1, 2,
well, I just plug in again, so
I get 3 plus 4.
That's 7.
And 2 plus 4 is 6.
And so again, the same analysis
as we used in the
tangent plane case works in
the tangent line case.
Let's come over here.
So xy is on the tangent line
if and only if we have that
the gradient dot, so that's
the gradient 7, 6 dot the
vector x minus 1, y minus 2--
this is the vector connecting
the point x, y to
our point 1, 2--
is equal to 0, if and only
if those two things are
orthogonal.
So this is i.e., 7 times x minus
1 plus 6 times y minus 2
is equal to 0.
So this is the point-normal
form for the
equation of that line.
And again, you could, you know,
expand out and rewrite
this in whichever forms you
happen to like to see your
equations of lines.
So there you go.
Using the gradient,
we can compute
tangent planes to surfaces.
Similarly, we can use the
same idea to compute
tangent lines to curves.
The point is that the gradient
vector of a function is
orthogonal to the level curves
of that function.
And so we use that to get the
normal vectors to our curves
or our surfaces, and with the
normal vector, we can then
easily compute the tangent plane
or the tangent line.
So I'll stop there.