LINAN CHEN: Hello.
Welcome back to recitation.
I'm sure you are becoming more
and more familiar with the
determinants of matrices.
In the lecture, we also
learned the geometric
interpretation of
the determinant.
The absolute value of the
determinant of a matrix is
simply equal to the volume of
the parallelepiped spanned by
the row vectors of
that matrix.
So today, we're going to apply
this fact to solve the
following problem.
I have a tetrahedron,
T, in this 3D space.
And the vertices of T are
given by O, which is the
origin, A1, A2, and A3.
So I have highlighted
this tetrahedron
using the blue chalk.
So this is T.
And our first goal is to compute
the volume of T using
the determinant.
And the second part is if I fix
A1 and A2, but move A3 to
another point, A3 prime, which
is given by this coordinate, I
ask you to compute
the volume again.
OK.
So since we want to use the fact
that the determinant is
related to the volume, we have
to figure out which volume we
should be looking at.
We know that the determinant is
related to the volume of a
parallelepiped.
But here, we only have
a tetrahedron.
So the first goal should be to
find out which parallelepiped
you should be working with.
OK, why don't you hit
pause and try
to work it out yourself.
You can sketch the
parallelepiped on this picture.
And I will return in a while and
continue working with you.
All right.
How did your computation go?
Now let's complete this
picture together.
As we were saying, we need a
parallelepiped so that we can
use the fact that the
determinant is
related to the volume.
Here, I have a tetrahedron.
And let's look at these three
edges, OA1, OA2, and OA3.
All of them meet
at the origin.
So why don't we just consider
the parallelepiped spanned by
those same three edges?
It's a natural choice because at
least it shares three edges
with T.
OK, now let's move on to
this picture here.
As you can see, I
have drawn this
parallelepiped in red chalk.
So the blue part is
my original T.
And the red part, let me call it
P. It's the parallelepiped
spanned by edges OA1,
OA2, and OA3.
So that's the parallelepiped
that I'm going to work with.
Now the next step is to relate
the volume of T to the volume
of P. OK, let's recall together
what is the volume of
a tetrahedron.
We note that the volume of a
tetrahedron is going to be
equal to 1/3 of the
area of the base
times the height, right?
Of course, you can choose any
side, any face to be the base.
But for convenience, we're going
to choose the triangle
OA1A2 to be the base of T. So
the volume of T is going to be
equal to 1/3 times the area
of triangle OA1A2.
So I use this A to indicate
the area.
Then times the height.
Well, if I choose this to
be my base, then this
A3 becomes the apex.
Then the height is simply equal
to the distance from A3
to the triangle OA1A2.
Let me use letter h to
denote this quantity.
So that's the height.
And the volume of T is equal to
1/3 of the product of the
area of the base times
the height.
OK, this is the volume of
T. Now let's see what
the volume of P is.
So P is a parallelepiped.
The volume of a parallelepiped
is simply equal to the area of
the base times its height.
This time, which face would
you choose to be the base?
Well, of course, you would
like to choose this
parallelogram to be the base
because it contains the base
of T.
If we do so, so we want to
choose this parallelogram to
be the base, then what
is the area of this?
Well, it clearly contains two
copies of the triangle OA1A2.
So the area of the parallelogram
is simply equal
to twice the area of
the triangle OA1A2.
Then what is the height of P?
Again, if you choose this face
to be the base, then A3
becomes the apex again.
Then the height of the
parallelepiped is equal to the
distance from A3 to the base,
which is the same as the
distance from A3 to
triangle OA1A2.
So here, the height is
also equal to h.
Now you can compare these
two formulae.
You see that volume of T is
simply equal to 1/6 of volume
of P. That's the connection
between the volume of the
tetrahedron with the volume
of the parallelepiped.
In order to compute the volume
of T, we only need to compute
the volume of P.
Now let's compute the volume
of this parallelepiped.
We know that it's related to the
determinant of a matrix.
And the row vectors of that
matrix are given by these
three edges.
So because all of them start
from 0, we only need the
coordinate of A1, A2, and A3.
So here, volume of P is equal
to the absolute value.
So don't forget the absolute
value sign.
Absolute value of the
determinant of a three by
three matrix.
So we just need to copy
the coordinates of the
vertices down here.
The first one is 2, 2, -1.
These two are too close.
-1.
And A2 is 1, 3, 0.
A3 is -1, 1, 4.
The absolute value of
this determinant.
And if you compute this, this
is a three by three matrix.
The determinant should
be easy to compute.
And the result should be 12.
So that's the volume of P, which
means the volume of the
tetrahedron, T, is equal
to 12/6, which is 2.
Did you get the correct
answer?
OK, so in order to compute the
volume of T, we have related
to a parallelepiped, P, which
contains T. All right.
Now let's look at
the second part.
The second part says that if I
keep A1 and A2 unchanged, but
I move A3 a new point.
So A3 is going to be moved to
a point given by A3 prime.
And the coordinate is
-201, -199, and 104.
And I'm asking you to compute
the volume of the new
tetrahedron.
Well as you can see, this point
seems to be far away
from the origin.
I'm not even able to draw
this point here.
But you can imagine as this
point goes far away from the
origin, this spike is going to
become more and more pointy.
In other words, the entire
tetrahedron looks more and
more like a needle.
But nonetheless, we can
use the same method
to compute the volume.
So we follow the same idea, the
volume of T is going to be
equal to 1/6 of the volume of
P. And in this case, that's
going to become the absolute
value of the determinant of a
three by three matrix whose row
vectors are given by these
three edges.
So in this case, we again
copy down the
coordinates of three vertices.
The first one is 2, 2, -1.
The second one is 1, 3, 0.
The third one should become
this, so -201, 199, 104.
OK.
That should give me the volume
of the new tetrahedron.
Let me call it T prime just to
differentiate it from the
previous tetrahedron.
And of course, you can compute
this determinant explicitly.
If you do so, you will see the
answer should be 2 again.
But in fact, there is a way that
you can just read out the
answer directly without
any real computation.
Let's pay attention
to the last row.
In other words, let's pay
attention to this new A3,
well, A3 prime.
What do you observe here?
A3 prime, if you consider the
difference between A3 and A3
prime, in other words, if you
consider how much you have
moved your apex, you will see
that's equal to -181.
Right?
So A3 is -1, 1, 4.
A3 prime is this.
That's exactly equal
to -100 times A1.
What does that mean?
Well from the point of view
of the matrix, you are
subtracting from the original
third row 100
times the first row.
But this row operation does not
change the determinant.
In other words, you know that
this determinant should be the
same as the previous one.
So you can write
out 2 directly.
From this picture, we can
also see that fact.
So from this picture, we know
that this section is saying
that I need to move A3 in the
inverse direction of A1
by 100 times A1.
So you're moving A3
parallel to A1.
But it doesn't matter how far
you've moved your apex.
You're moving in a way that
remains parallel to the base,
which is saying that
this movement does
not change the height.
Since A1 and A2 are fixed, your
base is fixed, and you're
not changing the height.
So of course, the volume
is not changing.
That's also a reason, another
way to see that the volume of
T prime is simply equal
to the volume of T.
OK, this completes
this problem.
I hope this example was
helpful to you.
And we should keep in mind
that the fact that the
determinant is related to volume
sometimes can become
very handy in computing
the volume of
certain geometric objects.
Thank you for watching, and
I'm looking forward
to seeing you soon.