The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Hi, and welcome
back to the 14.01 problem
solving videos.
Today, we're going to work on
Fall 2010, problem set one,
problem number four.
And in this problem, we're
going to be working with
elasticities.
But instead of starting with a
demand function, and starting
with a supply function, and
calculating the elasticity
given those functions, we're
going to be given the
elasticity of demand and the
elasticity of supply.
And we're going to have to
back out what the demand
functions and the
supply functions
should have looked like.
So we're basically just working
in reverse from what
we did in lecture.
Let's go ahead and read the full
problem up through part
A. You have been asked to
analyze the market for steel.
From public sources, you are
able to find that last year's
price for steel was
$20 per ton.
At this price, 100 million
tons were sold
on the world market.
From trade association data,
you are able to obtain
estimates for their own price
elasticities of demand and
supply on the world markets as
negative 0.25 for demand and
0.5 for supply.
Assume the steel has linear
demand and supply curves
throughout.
Part A asks us to solve for the
equations of demand and
supply in this market,
and to sketch the
demand and supply curves.
So looking at the formal
definition of elasticity of
demand and elasticity of supply,
we basically are going
to have three different
parts to it.
We have the derivative of
either demand or supply
function with respect to P, in
this case the own price of P,
or the price of steel.
And we also have the equilibrium
price, or any
price at the point on the
curve, and a quantity.
In this case, it's going to be
the equilibrium quantity.
So basically, what we have
now is we are given--
for the elasticity of demand,
we're given three variables.
We're given the price,
the quantity, and the
elasticity of demand.
And that means the only thing
that we don't know is the
derivative of the demand curve
with respect to P.
So if we can isolate this
derivative, then we can
integrate the number
that we're able to
solve through for.
And then we can solve out for
what our demand curve is going
to look like.
So let's go ahead and walk
through that process together.
Substituting in for the
elasticity of demand P and Q,
we're gonna have
this equation.
And the one thing that I want
you to notice is since the
derivative of the demand curve
with respect to P is negative
0.25, in this case, we know
that it's linear.
But just because it's linear at
the point where price is 20
and quantity is 100, that
doesn't necessarily mean it's
gonna be linear throughout.
So it's useful to know that at
any point on this line, it's
always going to have
the derivative
equal to negative 0.25.
So that's useful.
We know we can integrate and
have the correct answer.
Solving for dQD dP, we're gonna
have negative 1.25.
And we're just going to
integrate this with respect to
P. And after we integrate,
we're going to
be left with a constant.
In this case, we're going
to call the constant a.
This is how much the demand
curve has actually shifted up
to begin with, shifted
up or down.
And to solve for a, all we have
to do is we can just plug
back in for the $20 and the 100
quantity, and we can solve
through for what a is
going to be equal.
When you solve through plugging
in Q and P, you're
going to find that a
is equal to 125.
So we're gonna have that our
final demand function is gonna
be negative 1.25P plus 125.
Now we can go through this exact
same process with the
elasticity of supply now.
And all we have to do now is
use the number 0.5 instead,
and we can solve through.
We can integrate.
And then we're going to solve
for the other constant to,
again, get our supply curve.
Substituting in the information
we have, we're
going to be left with
this equation.
And we're gonna go ahead and
isolate the derivative that we
have. And when we integrate
again, we have to remember
that we are going to have a
constant that we're gonna have
to solve for.
And I'm gonna just call
this constant c.
Again, plug in the price of 20
and the quantity equal to 100
and you're gonna find that the
supply curve is gonna be equal
to 2.5P plus 50.
And we can do a quick sketch
of this on our axes here.
We're just gonna go ahead and
draw our upward-sloping supply
curve, our downward-sloping
demand curve.
And we're gonna mark the
equilibrium point and label
the equilibrium quantities
and the
equilibrium prices, as well.
And before we move on to the
second part of this problem,
we can pause here.
And we can think about what did
the elasticities that we
started with actually mean.
Well, if we were to look at this
point of intersection at
the equilibrium of the demand
curve, we're looking at the
percentage change at this
point in quantity per
percentage change in price.
So we're basically just saying,
for that tiny change,
an infinitesimally small change
at this point for the
demand curve, how much
does quantity change,
percentage-wise, relative
to price?
And that's also what
we're looking at
with the supply curve.
So when you're given a
elasticity, if you have an
elasticity of supply, it makes
sense that it's gonna be
positive, in this case 0.5,
because when price increases,
suppliers are willing
to supply more.
And it makes sense that the
demand elasticity that we're
given is negative, or negative
0.25, because when price
begins to increase, the
consumers are gonna want less
of the product.
Now, the second part of this
problem is going to give us
new elasticities of
demand and supply.
And I'm gonna just quickly
run through the actual
calculation, because it's
gonna be the same as our
calculation that we just did.
And instead, we're gonna think
about possible causes for the
shifts that we see in the supply
and the demand curve.
Part B says, suppose that you
discover that the current
price of steel is $15 per ton
and the current level of
worldwide sales of steel
is 150 million tons.
The most recent elasticity
estimates from the trade
association this year are
negative 0.125 for demand and
0.25 for supply.
Describe the change in the
supply and the demand curves
over the past year using your
diagram from part A. What sort
of events might explain
the change?
Now, I've given us the
information for this part of
the problem on this board.
And you'll notice that our
inputs, or our variables, have
changed now.
The price has dropped
from $20.
Now it's gonna be down to $15.
You're gonna notice that the
quantity has actually
increased from 100 up to 150.
And our elasticities of demand
and elasticities of supply
have changed, because the price
and the quantity are
different, and we're at a
different point on our graph.
The process we're gonna do to
solve for our demand curves
and our supply curves are going
to be exactly identical.
And when you follow
the same process--
I'll just do the first
step up here--
you're gonna substitute in for
the information that's given
in the problem.
And all you're going to do is
you're, again, gonna solve
through for the derivative.
You're gonna integrate.
And you're gonna find
the constants.
After you do that entire
process, you're gonna find
that the demand curve is
given by this equation.
And you're gonna find that the
supply curve is given by this
new equation.
Now, if we look at this new
demand curve and this new
supply curve, we'll actually
notice that the slope, with
respect to P, is going to be
identical in both of the cases
that we solved for, both the
beginning case and the case in
the end of the problem.
The only thing that's shifted
between our quantities
demanded and our quantities
supplied, or the curves, is
there's been a shift.
And the shift for the
demand curve--
it went from an intercept
of 125 now to an
intercept of 168.75.
So our demand curve is
shifting up and out.
So we can represent this shift
in demand like this.
Notice that the slope is going
to be exactly identical.
I'm going to write a small
db for part B.
And then we can do the same sort
of interpretation for our
supply curve.
Looking at our supply curve, the
intercepts, now, is 112.5.
But before, it was only at 50.
And what this means, this means
that the supply curve is
going to shift in and down.
And so my graph with the
equilibrium price that I've
drawn-- it's a little bit off,
but what you should see--
you should see that the new
equilibrium price has fallen.
In this case, it's
fallen to 15.
And the equilibrium quantity has
increased from 100 to 150.
So since we had both a shift
in supply and a shift in
demand, necessarily we see that
quantity is going to increase.
But if the demand curve had
shifted way up here, we could
see that price could
have increased.
So the effect on the price in
this market is ambiguous.
We can say that, necessarily,
the effect on quantity is
going to be clearly towards
an increase.
So to wrap up this problem,
we saw that changes in
elasticities can also represent
changes in the
underlying demand and
supply functions.
Let's wrap up by just thinking
about what could have caused
the demand shift that
we've seen.
And what could have caused the
supply shift that we saw?
Now, there are a couple
of ideas that we
can have for demand.
The first idea that we could
have is we could just have had
an increase in the income
of a consumer.
If a consumer has more income,
then they might be willing to
spend more on steel.
A second idea that we have, we
could have that the price of a
substitute--
perhaps you're considering
building a bridge out of iron
instead of steel--
if the price of the substitute
has increased, then perhaps
the consumers are going to be
willing to pay more to get the
steel since the iron
is more expensive.
A third possible idea is that
the number of goods that you
need to make from steel
is increasing.
So if you suddenly find new uses
for steel, then the price
that you're willing to pay
at any given point
is going to be higher.
Basically, to affect the demand
curve, you have to
think about why would people
be more willing to pay more
for a fixed quantity.
And I just listed off a
couple of ideas there.
We can also think about reasons
about why the supply
curve could be shifting in.
In this case, why is it--
why are sellers willing to offer
a cheaper price at any
fixed quantity?
And one idea that we could have
for this is just that
there are more firms
in this market.
If this market isn't perfectly
competitive to start off with,
then increasing the number of
firms is gonna increase
competition, and the producers
are gonna have
to drop their prices.
A second idea for why we've seen
the supply curve shift
out and down could be the
fact that input price
for steel has dropped.
Perhaps the way of manufacturing
or getting the
raw material is cheaper because
the machine they're
using to get the steel
is cheaper.
Basically, when you're thinking
about the shift
that's making it cheaper for
suppliers to produce the good,
all you need to think about is
what could make it so that
they're more willing to produce
at a lower price.
So again, with this problem, we
went through working with
elasticities and demands.
We've seen that we can go from a
demand curve or supply curve
to elasticities, or we can go
from elasticities to demands.
And then, once we've had the
supply and the demand curves,
we looked at how
do we interpret
the shifts and shocks?
And we looked at possible
explanations for those shift
and shocks.
I hope you found this
problem helpful.