CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
Today we're going to talk about
some rules of logarithms
that you're going to
need to remember.
We're going to prove why one of
them is true, and then I'm
going to ask you to use these
rules to take a derivative of
a function.
So let's just look at these
rules first. So I want to
point out as I'm talking about
these rules, the first three
are written with natural log.
But one can also write them in
any base as long as the base
is the same all the
way across.
So in any legitimate base that
one is allowed to use, so with
a positive base, one can use it
all the way across instead
of the natural log.
So the first one says that the
natural log of a product is
equal to the sum of
the natural logs.
So natural log M times N is
equal to the natural log of M
plus natural log of N.
The second one says the natural
log of a quotient is
equal to the difference
of the natural logs.
So natural log of M divided by N
is equal to natural log of M
minus natural log of N.
This third one says that the
natural log of something
raised to a power is that power
as a coefficient times
the natural log of
the something.
So natural log of M to the
k is equal to k times the
natural log of M.
And what I want to point out
is that there's a distinct
difference where the power is.
So if the power is inside the
argument then this rule holds,
but if the power is outside
the argument--
so if it's natural log
of M, the whole
thing raised to a power--
this does not work.
This is not equal to what's
written above.
And then the third-- the
fourth one-- sorry.
The fourth one is a change
of base formula.
So if I have, if I have log base
something b, that maybe I
want to change the base
of M, I can rewrite
that in the base e.
I can write that as natural
log of M divided by
natural log of b.
And I want to point out a common
mistake people make is
sometimes they confuse the
second and the fourth because
they both have quotients.
But notice that the second one
is the natural log of a
quotient, and the fourth one
is about the quotient of
natural logs.
So that's a distinct difference,
and hopefully then
you see that they are not, these
two statements are not,
in fact, the same statement.
So now what I'd like to do is,
using what we know about
exponential and log
functions--
I want to prove number one.
So let's set out to do that.
Well, in order to make this top
line make sense we know
that M and N have
to be positive.
And so I can find--
actually, let me write first
what we're doing.
We're going to prove one.
So with M and N both positive I
can find values a and b such
that e to the a equals M and e
to the b is equal to N. And
let me just write out also
what that means, because
exponential and log functions
are inverses of one another.
This means that a is equal to
natural log of M and b is
equal to natural log of N.
So these are equivalent
statements.
This statement and this
statement are equivalent.
So now let's use that
information to try and solve
the problem.
To try and prove number one.
So the natural a log of M times
N, well, what is that?
M is e to the a, N
is e to the b.
So I can write this as natural
log of e to the a
times e to the b.
What's e to the a times
e to the b?
This is where we use our
rules of exponents.
e to the a times e to the
b is e to the a plus b.
So this is natural log
of e to the a plus b.
And now, what's the point?
The point is that natural log
in exponential functions are
inverses of one another,
or natural log of
e to the x is x.
So natural log of e to the a
plus b is just a plus b.
And I've already recorded
for you what those are--
it's natural log of M plus
natural log of N. So notice
we've done when we
set out to do--
natural log of the quantity M
times N is equal to natural
log of M plus natural
log of N.
And in a similar flavor one
could immediately do number
two, and number three follows
quite similarly, as well.
It uses, obviously, these are
going to use different rules
for exponents besides the
product of two exponential
functions is equal to the
sum of the powers.
It's going to use some
of those other rules.
And I believe that some of
these other things might
actually also be proven
in a later lecture
in the actual course.
So you'll see these.
But I would say, you might want
to try and prove two and
three, at least, on your own--
might be helpful to look at
how those work using the same
kind of rules here.
So now what I'd like us to do is
using these rules, I'd like
us to take a derivative.
So what I want us to look at is
y equals the square root of
x times x plus 4.
And we'll just assume that
x is bigger than 0.
And I want you to
find y prime.
Now you could do this just brute
force, cranking it out.
But I'd like you to try and use
the log differentiation
technique in order to find
this derivative.
I'll give you a moment to do it
and then I'll come back and
I'll show you how I do it.
OK.
Welcome back.
So I'm going to use the log
differentiation and the rules
I have on the side of the
board there to take a
derivative to find y prime.
So first what we do is we take
the log of both sides and then
we use some of the rules of
logarithms to simplify the
expression on the
right hand side.
So I will take natural log y is
equal to natural log of the
square root of x
times x plus 4.
Now square root--
wow, sorry--
square root is the power of
something raised to the 1/2.
Right?
That's what it means to
take a square root.
You can take this whole
product and
raise it to the 1/2.
So I'm going to use rule number
three and I'm going to
bring that 1/2 that is a power
out in front of the log.
So I can rewrite this
expression as
1/2 log of this product.
That's one too many parentheses,
but that's OK.
OK.
So I have 1/2 the natural log of
the product x and x plus 4.
So now I'm going to use rule
number one which changes the
product, the natural log of a
product into the sum of the
natural logs.
And I can rewrite this as 1/2
natural log x plus 1/2 natural
log, its quantity x plus 4.
Essentially what I'm doing here
is I have to distribute
this 1/2 because I had one term,
and then I'm going to
have two terms that are added
together, but the 1/2 applies
to both of them.
So now I have this nice setup.
I have natural log
of y is equal to
something in terms of x.
And now I can take the
derivative of a both sides.
Now remember, I want to find
y prime, so there's some
implicit differentiation
going on.
So let's just be careful
when we do that.
If I take the derivative of this
side I don't just get y
prime, I get y prime over y.
Where does that come from?
Well, d dx of this expression
is the derivative of the
natural log evaluated
at y then times the
derivative of y.
You've seen this, I think, a lot
by now, but just to make
sure you understand where
both of those come from.
So when I take the derivative
here I get y prime over y.
When I take the derivative here
with respect to x, well,
derivative of natural log
of x is just 1 over x.
So I get 1 over 2x.
And then the derivative of
natural log of x plus 4, if I
use the chain rule I get 1
over x plus 4 times the
derivative of x plus 4, which
is still just 1--
so I get 1 over 2
times x plus 4.
So now I wanted us
to find y prime.
So to find y prime I'm
going to move over
a little bit more.
And just notice that y prime
is going to equal y
times all of that.
Well, I know y.
So I'm going to write
what y is.
y is the square root
of x times x plus
4 times this quantity.
1 over 2x plus 1 over
2 times x plus 4.
So that's actually one way to
write the derivative of y
prime now--
or sorry-- the derivative
of y.
Now I could combine these two
fractions into a single
fraction and try and make it
look a little bit nicer, or I
could just leave it this way.
This is technically
a derivative.
So if I started trying to
combine things I might find
out that I could have
just taken the
derivative the long way.
So this is a nice short way to
just get to a place where I
can start to find out
something about the
derivative of y.
So I guess I'll stop there.