JOE LEWIS: Hi.
My name is Joe Lewis.
At the time of this filming in
2010 I'm a graduate student
in the Math Department at MIT,
and I'm also a TA for OCW
Scholar 1801 and 1802.
CHRISTINE BREINER: Hi.
I'm Christine Breiner.
I'm a Moore Instructor here at
MIT and for OCW Scholar, I'll
be a teaching assistant
for 1801 and for 1802.
DAVID JORDAN: My name is David
Jordan and I'm a graduate
student here at MIT.
And I'm a TA for OpenCourseWare
Scholar 1802.
So I thought I would say a
little bit about what we do
with recitations here at MIT.
So, the purpose of the
recitations is for you to
apply what you've learned in
lecture towards solving
specific concrete problems and
then for you to compare your
solutions to those problems
with those of your TA.
CHRISTINE BREINER: The purpose
of the recitations on OCW
Scholar is really the same
purpose that David described
for recitations here at MIT.
What we want you to do is have
an opportunity to work varying
levels of problems and then see
us give detailed solutions
to those problems so that you
can see how we think about
mathematics.
JOE LEWIS: Almost all of our
videos have a natural moment
where you can pause after the
problem's been stated.
And we really strongly suggest
you work out the problem on a
piece of paper before going back
to the video and seeing
our solutions.
This will help you do
mathematics rather than be
able just to see mathematics.
Hope you enjoy the course.