JOEL LEWIS: Hi, welcome
back to recitation.
In lecture, Professor Jerison
was teaching about
L'Hospital's Rule, and one
thing that he mentioned
several times was that when you
apply L'Hospital's Rule,
it's really important that the
second limit exists in order
for L'Hospital's Rule to be
true, in order for the first
limit to equal the
second limit.
So I have a--
but he didn't give you any
examples of what can go wrong.
So I have here a limit
for you to work on.
So what I'd like you to do is
try L'Hospital's Rule, see
what happens, and then try to
solve it a different way not
using L'Hospital's Rule.
So why don't you pause the
video, spend a couple minutes
working on that, come
back, and we
can work on it together.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you've have some fun
working on this limit.
Let's go through it and see what
happens when we try to
apply L'Hospital's Rule to it.
So the first thing to notice is
that as x goes to infinity,
x plus cosine x-- well, cosine
x is small, and you know,
between minus 1 and 1, x
is going to infinity.
So the top is going to infinity
and the bottom is
going to infinity.
So this is an infinity over
infinity indeterminate form.
So it is a context in which we
can try to apply L'Hospital's
Rule, so that's fine.
So it's an indeterminate ratio,
we can look at applying
L'Hospital's Rule.
So let's try to do that.
So L'Hospital's Rule says that
the limit as x goes to
infinity of our expression x
plus cosine x divided by x is
equal-- and I'm going to put
a little question mark here
because what L'Hospital's Rule
says is that it's equal
provided, it's equal to what I'm
going to write over here
provided that the second
limit exists.
So what goes over here?
Well it's the limit as x goes to
the same place as x goes to
infinity of the ratio of the
derivative, so the derivative
of the top divided by the
derivative of the bottom.
So in this case that's 1 minus
sine x is the derivative of
the top and 1 is the derivative
of the bottom.
OK, now let's look
at this limit.
What happens?
Well, OK the over 1 part
is irrelevant.
The 1 minus part,
OK, who cares?
The only thing that's changing
in this limit is the sine x.
So as x goes to infinity what
this does is it oscillates,
just like sine x does.
I mean, it's offset and flipped
upside down because of
this 1 minus.
So, in particular, you know,
sometimes it's near 1,
sometimes it's near negative 1,
sometimes it's near 0, and
it oscillates back and
forth in between.
So in particular, because it's
oscillating, it's not
approaching any value.
So this limit doesn't
exist. It's not
equal to any real number.
It's not equal to infinity.
It's not equal to
minus infinity.
It does not exist.
OK, so the statement of
L'Hospital's theorem says that
this equality is really wrong.
OK?
What it means is that
L'Hospital's
Rule tells you nothing.
You don't learn anything here.
So if we want to compute this
first limit, we can't use
L'Hospital's Rule.
We have to come up with some
better way to do it, OK.
So that's what's going wrong.
Now let's see about doing
this even though we
don't have this tool.
So if we try and solve this
limit without L'Hospital's
Rule, so we want to look at
the limit as x goes to
infinity of x plus cosine
x divided by x.
Well, think about what's
important in this limit.
As x is getting big, well x is
getting big and x is getting
big and what's cosine x doing?
Well cosine x is behaving like a
constant but wigglier right,
we could say.
So cosine x is always between
minus 1 and 1, but, you know,
it's oscillating, but it's in
some bounded interval there,
whereas x and x are both going
to infinity at exactly the
same speed, so this suggests
a manipulation that sort of
allows us to quantify
that explicitly.
And so one thing that we can
do is we can divide top and
bottom of this limit by x.
So if we do that, or
equivalently we can just
divide this x into the fraction
above, split it into
two fractions.
So we have--
I'm just going to re-write it
one more time --the limit of x
goes to infinity of x plus
cosine x divided by x is equal
to the limit as x goes
to infinity of 1 plus
cosine x over x.
All right, so what's
happening here?
Well all I've done is I've
divided that x in-- and now
you see that this 1, that was
from the x over x, so that's a
constant that's going to 1 --and
as x goes to infinity,
cosine x again we can think
of it like a constant but
wigglier, x is going to
infinity, so cosine x over x
is going to 0 as x
goes to infinity.
So I guess I wouldn't call this
plugging in, but it's,
you know, sort of just
like plugging in.
So this part is going to 0,
so we're left with just 1.
OK, so we can evaluate this
limit fairly easily.
It just took a couple steps.
But we can't evaluate it
with L'Hospital's Rule.
So this is why you have that
extra thing in the statement
of the theorem that Professor
Jerison kept saying, and that
I'll say every time I use it,
which is L'Hospital's Rule
says that the limit of the ratio
is equal to the limit of
the ratio of the derivative
provided the
second limit exists.
OK, so here's an example where
the second limit didn't exist
and so we can't say that the two
are actually equal to each
other, and we need some other
tools to evaluate
the limit in question.
So I'll end there.