PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
You've been talking about
computing limits of some
indeterminate forms. In
particular, you used
l'Hopital's rule to help you
out with some limits in the
form 0 over 0 or infinity
over infinity.
So these are the two
indeterminate ratios.
And you also, so OK, so when
you have a limit that is in
the form of an indeterminate
ratio, you've seen that one
tool that you can use to help
compute the limit is
l'Hopital's rule.
There are other indeterminate
forms for limits as well.
So you actually saw, in lecture,
another one of these,
which was you saw a limit
of the form 0 to the 0.
So that was the limit you saw,
was the limit as x goes to 0
from the right to x to the x.
So that was going to 0 over 0.
And the two competing forces
are that as the base of the
limit goes to 0.
That wants to make the whole
thing get closer to 0.
And when the exponent is going
to 0, that makes the whole
thing want to get closer to 1.
So you have those two
competing forces.
That's why it is an
indeterminate form.
When you were solving this
limit, you, first thing you
did was you wrote it as an
exponential in base e.
So you wrote x to the
x as e to the xlnx.
So xlnx is also an indeterminate
form
as x goes to 0.
It's an indeterminate form of
the form 0 times infinity.
Here I'm writing infinity to
mean either positive infinity
or negative infinity.
So in this case, this is an
indeterminate form because
when you have one factor going
to 0, that makes the whole
product want to get
closer to 0.
Whereas when you have one factor
going to infinity,
either positive or negative,
that makes the whole product
want to get big.
So that's why it becomes
indeterminate.
And you were able to evaluate
the limit xlnx, in that case,
by rewriting it as a quotient.
There are a few other
indeterminate forms that I'd
like to mention.
So in particular, there are
three other indeterminate
forms not, different
from these.
And then I'll give you an
example of one of them to
solve a problem.
so the three other indeterminate
forms, there are
two more that are an exponential
indeterminate
form, and there's one
sort of outlier.
So one of the other
indeterminate forms is
infinity to the 0.
So when you have an exponential
expression where
the base is getting very very
large, and the exponent is
going to 0, well the base
getting large makes the whole
fraction want to be-- sorry--
the whole expression want to
be large, whereas the exponent
going to 0 makes the whole
expression want to
get closer to 1.
And so those two forces are in
tension, and you can end up
with limits that equal any value
when you have a limit
like this, infinity to the 0.
Another similar one is
1 to the infinity.
And this is the one
I'll give you an
exercise on in a minute.
So when you have a limit of the
form 1 to the infinity, so
something to the something where
the base is going to 1
and the exponent is going to
infinity, the base going to 1
makes this whole thing
want to go to 1.
The exponent to infinity makes
this whole thing want to
either blow up if it's a little
bigger than 1, or get
really small if it's a little
smaller than 1.
So you have, again, a tension
there, and the result is
indeterminate.
The one sort of unusual one
that you have is also--
which I'm not going to talk much
more about-- is infinity
minus infinity.
So when you have two very large
things, so here I mean
either positive infinity minus
positive infinity, or negative
infinity minus negative
infinity.
When you have two things that
are both getting very large,
their difference could also be
getting very large, or it
could be getting very
small, or could be
doing anything in between.
So that's also an indeterminate
form.
So these are the seven
indeterminate forms. When you
have a quotient, you can always
apply l'Hopital's rule.
When you have a product, you
can always rewrite it as a
quotient, by writing for
example, x squared plus 1
times-- well, let's see--
e to the minus x.
That's a product.
And you could always rewrite it
as a quotient, for example,
e to the minus x over 1
over x squared plus 1.
There might even be a smarter
way to rewrite this product as
a quotient.
But, OK.
And so when you have an
exponential, as in this case,
you can use this rewriting in
base e trick to turn it into a
product, which you can then
turn into a quotient.
For the difference case, the
reason I say it's unusual, is
just that there's not a good,
general method for working
with these.
There are a lot of
special cases.
And you sort of have to-- or
what I mean is you have to
analyze them on a case
by case basis.
There are different sort of
techniques that will work.
So let me give you an example
of one of these 1 to the
infinity kinds.
So why don't we come
over here.
So compute the limit as x goes
to 0 from the right of 1 plus
3x to the 10 divided by x.
So we see as x is going to 0,
this base is going to 1.
And so that makes this whole
expression want to be close to
1, whereas this exponent is
going to infinity, since this
is just a little bit bigger than
1, that makes the whole
expression want to be big when
the exponent is big.
So you have a tension here
between the base going to 1
and the exponent going
to infinity.
So the question is, try and
actually compute this limit.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a couple of
minutes to work on this
question, come back, and we
can work on it together.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you had some luck
working on this problem.
As we said, this is a limit of
an indeterminate form of the 1
to infinity type.
As one of the three exponential
types of
indeterminate forms, a really
promising first step almost
every time is to rewrite this
as a exponential expression
with the base e.
So we just do, so first we
just do an algebraic
manipulation on the thing we're
taking the limit of, and
then often, very often, that
simplifies it into something
that we can actually compute
the limit of.
So in particular, we have that 1
plus 3x, if we want to write
this in exponential form.
This is equal to e to
the ln of 1 plus 3x.
This is true of any
positive number.
Any positive number is e to the
ln of it, because e and
log are inverse functions.
So OK, so we right
it like this.
And so that means that 1 plus
3x to the 10 over x is equal
to e to the ln of 1 plus
3x to the 10 over x.
And now you can use your
exponent rules.
So this is equal to e to
the ln of 1 plus 3x
times 10 over x.
So our original expression is
equal to this down here.
So the limit of our original
expression is equal to the
limit of this one.
The other thing to notice is
that because exponentiation is
a nice, continuous function,
in order to compute this
limit, or the limit of this
expression, it suffices--
just with base a constant, e--
it suffices to compute the
limit of the exponent.
All right, so let's do that.
Let's compute the limit
of the exponent.
So we have the limit, so it has
to be x going to the same
place, which in this case is to
0 from the right of ln of 1
plus 3x times 10 over x.
Well, this is a product.
It came to us as a product.
But there's an obvious way to
rewrite this as a quotient.
I should say it's an
indeterminate product.
As x goes to 0, this goes
to ln of 1, which is 0.
Whereas this goes to infinity,
positive infinity since we're
coming from the right.
So this is a 0 times positive
infinity form.
So it is an indeterminate
limit-- or sorry-- an
indeterminate product.
And, right, and there's an
obvious way to rewrite this as
an indeterminate quotient, which
is to rewrite it as the
limit as x goes 0 plus of ten
ln of 1 plus 3x divided by x
as x goes 0.
So now, this is a limit where
a it's an infinity-- sorry--
a 0 over 0.
So OK, so good.
So now we can apply
l'Hopital's rule.
So by l'Hopital's rule, this
is equal to the limit as x
goes to 0 on the right.
Of, well we apply l'Hopital's
rule on the top, we get 10
over 1 plus 3x, by the
chain rule, times 3.
And on the bottom,
we just get one.
So now, OK, so this is
true provided this
second limit exists.
And the second limit is no
longer indeterminate.
It's easy to see what it is.
You just plug in x equals
0, and we get that
this is equal to 30.
OK so this limit is equal to 30,
but this isn't the limit
that we started out wanting
to compute.
The limit we started out wanting
to compute is e to the
ln of 1 plus 3x times
10 over x.
So it's e to the this.
So our original limit as x goes
to 0 from the right of 1
plus 3x to the 10 over x is
equal to e to the thirtieth
power, which is pretty huge.
OK, So that's how we-- right--
and OK, so that's the answer
to our question.
So we took our original limit,
it was this indeterminate
exponential form.
So what we do to it is, when
you have an indeterminate
exponential form, you do this
rewriting as an exponential in
the base of e trick, and
then you pass the
limit into the exponent.
Because e is now a nice
constant, life is simple--
life is simpler I should say--
you pass the limit into the
constant, then you have an
indeterminate ratio,
indeterminate product, which
you rewrite as an indeterminate
ratio on which
you can then apply
l'Hopital's rule.
Or possibly, you know, you
rewrite it as a product.
Then it's easy to see
what the value is.
So, all right, so that's how
we deal with limits of
indeterminate exponential forms.
And I'll end there.