Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
We've been talking about Taylor
series for a number of
functions and rules by which you
can compute Taylor series.
I have here an example that I
don't think we did in lecture.
So this is the function f
of x equals secant of x.
Now, unlike some of the other
ones you've seen, there's not
a really simple formula
for the whole Taylor
series of secant x.
So what I'd like you to do is
not to find, you know, a
formula for the general term,
but rather, just to use some
of the tools that we've learned
to compute the first
few terms of the Taylor series
for f of x equals secant x.
Say, up through the x to the
fourth term, if you wanted, or
even a little further if you
were feeling ambitious.
So why don't you pause the
video, have a go at that, come
back, and we can
do it together.
So welcome back.
I asked you to compute
the first few
terms of a Taylor series.
One thing you can always do in
this case, is you can go and
you can apply the general
formula that we have for
Taylor series, and use it to
compute the series that way.
So in order to do that, you
just need to compute a few
derivatives of your function.
So remember that the general
formula for a Taylor series is
the Taylor series for f of x
is equal to the sum from n
equals 0 to infinity of the nth
derivative of f taken at
zero divided by n factorial
times x to the n.
And since we're only interested
in the first few
terms, this is f of 0 plus f
prime of 0 x plus f double
prime of 0 over 2x squared,
plus dot dot dot.
I'm not going to write out
the next few terms.
And if you want to apply this
formula to secant of x, what
you would have to do, is you
would have to compute these
derivatives.
And so we could try
doing that.
So in our case, f of x is
equal to secant of x.
So f of 0 is secant of
0, which is just 1.
So then we need to know f prime
of x, so that's the
derivative of secant of x.
So this is one you
should remember.
This is equal to secant
x times 10x.
And when you plug in x equal
to 0, well, the tan x is 0.
So f prime of 0 is equal to 0.
And then you could keep going.
So you could compute f
double prime of x.
So we would have to compute
the derivative of
secant x tan x.
And you would do that
by the product rule.
You know, you take derivative of
secant of x, and that gives
you secant x tan x
times 10x plus--
and then you, OK.
So you leave secant of x, and
you multiply it by the
derivative of tangent, which
is secant squared x.
And now when you put in
0 here, you get f
double prime of 0.
Well, OK.
So this has a tan x in
it, so that part's
going to give you 0.
And here we end up with secant
of 0 times secant squared of
0, so that's 1 times
1 times 1.
So that's just 1.
So f double prime of 0 is 1, and
you could keep doing this.
Now one thing you'll notice is
that this is getting more and
more complicated.
I mean, we can simplify this
expression a little bit.
We could write it as secant x
tan squared x plus secant
cubed x, and there are, you
know, all sorts of trig
manipulations you could do, if
you wanted to try and rewrite
that in some simpler form.
But fundamentally, it's more
complicated than the first
derivative was, and that's more
complicated in the function.
And it will keep getting more
complicated as you compute
more derivatives.
So we can do this.
So so far this shows us, by the
way, that this is equal to
1 plus 0x plus x squared over
2 plus dot dot dot.
And if you wanted to compute,
you know, up through the
fourth degree term or something
like this, that's
something that's manageable.
But I want to suggest that there
are maybe some nicer
ways to do it.
So one thing to notice is that
secant of x is closely related
to the function cosine of x.
And you know the Taylor series
for cosine of x.
So one thing you could think
to do, is to leverage the
information that you have about
cosine of x in order to
use it to get some information
about secant of x.
So one simple way to do that,
is that you know that cosine
of x is even.
It's an even function.
Cosine of minus x is equal
to cosine of x.
So that means secant
of x is also even.
Secant of x is an
even function.
And you've seen that even
functions, their Taylor
series, all the odd powers
have coefficient 0.
So what that means is without
ever computing the third
derivative, we can know already
that the next term in
this Taylor series is going
to be 0x cubed over 6.
OK?
So that's nice.
So the odd terms of the Taylor
series for secant of x are 0.
OK.
So that's one thing you
can get right away.
So that gives you, if you like,
that gives you half of
the terms of the
Taylor series.
It's a little bit
of a joke, but.
OK, so then you only need to
figure out the even terms.
That's one way we can leverage
the relationship between
secant and cosine.
The other way is that we can
remember that Taylor series
multiply just like
polynomials do.
So if secant is 1 over cosine,
that means secant times cosine
is equal to 1.
OK?
So idea, secant of x times
cosine of x is equal to 1.
Now, that means that the Taylor
series for secant of x
times the Taylor series
for cosine of x has to
simplify just to 1.
So we can write down that
product as a product of two
infinite polynomials,
and we can start
multiplying term by term.
And that'll allow us to solve
for a bunch of terms, just by
solving some simple
linear equations.
So let me show you
what I mean.
So we know--
let me write it as cosine
times secant.
So we know that cosine of x is
1 minus x squared over 2 plus
x to the fourth over 24.
That's 4 factorial.
Minus x to the sixth over 720,
which is 6 factorial
plus dot dot dot.
And so we know that if we
multiply this by the series
for secant of x--
well, what is the series
for secant of x?
Well, we've already computed a
few terms. We know that it's 1
plus x squared over 2, we
computed that already.
And we know that the third
degree term is 0.
So there's some fourth degree
coefficient a4 x to the
fourth, or 4 factorial.
And there's some--
well, we know, we said it's
even, so we know the fifth
degree coefficient is 0.
So then the sixth degree
coefficient we don't know yet.
So this is plus a sub six times
x to the sixth over six
factorial, plus dot dot dot.
So we know that when we multiply
these two things
together, it has to
give us just 1.
All the higher order terms have
to cancel, because over
here we have a 1.
So what you can do, is you can
actually try multiplying these
things out.
So it's easy to see, for
example, that the constant
term of this product is just
1 times 1, which is 1.
Which is good.
So that's a check on what
we've done so far.
And there is no x-term, because
there are no x's.
The x squared term here is 1
times x squared over 2 minus x
squared over 2 times 1.
Well, that gives us
0, so that's good.
So this product is equal to--
well, it's 1, plus we saw 0x,
plus 0x squared.
How about the x cubed term?
Well, there are no odd terms
in this product, so
there's no x cubed.
How about the x to
the fourth term?
Well, OK.
So how do we get an
x to the fourth?
We could have an x to the fourth
here times a constant.
So that's x to the
fourth over 24.
Or, we could have an x squared
times an x squared.
So in this case, that gives us
minus x squared over 2 times x
squared over 2, which is minus
x to the fourth over 4.
Or we could have a constant
times an x to the fourth.
So this is plus a4 x to
the fourth over 24.
And then we'll have a sixth
degree term, and so on.
Notice that there's never any
involvement from the higher
order terms in the fourth
power here.
Right?
If you ever took an x to the
sixth here, well then
everything you multiply it
by has at least an x
to the sixth power.
So we don't have to worry about
that showing up in the x
to the fourth term.
Well, OK.
We know this is actually equal
to 1, so we know that this
thing has to be 0.
This is x to the fourth term.
It has to be 0.
So that means that 1/24
minus 1/4 for plus a4
over 24 equals 0.
So OK.
So now you can multiply
everything through by 24, and
rearrange to figure out
that a4 is equal to 5.
So I've done that correctly.
And then if you wanted, it would
be fairly easy to go
back up and then you look at
the x to the sixth term.
And from there, you could figure
out that a6 was equal
to, say, 61 or something
like that.
I think 61.
And you could keep doing this.
So this is one way to compute
more terms of the series for
secant of x.
Another thing you could do--
which I'll just mention very
briefly, I'm not going to show
you how to do it-- is that you
can do long division
on power series.
So it actually works out very,
it works out just like this.
It's mathematically
equivalent.
The way you actually do
it looks different.
It looks like long division.
When you do long division with
polynomials, you start with
the highest order term.
Of course, power series don't
have highest order terms. What
you actually do with a power
series, is you start with the
lowest order term.
So to divide this into 1, you'd
say, oh, you mean the
factor of 1, and then you'll
have a, you know, you subtract
off 1 times this, and that gives
you an x squared plus 2.
And so, OK, so you say, I
need a plus an x squared
plus 2, and so on.
So that was too brief for you to
understand it properly, but
you can go and look up somewhere
the method of long
division on power series.
So just to recap, we talked
about three methods for
computing the coefficients
of a power series.
There's the formula that you
were given, which works, and
which you could use.
In this case, it's a
little complicated.
Then there's the method of using
a relationship between
your power series and other
known power series.
In this case, we can use the
relationship that we know our
power series satisfies
a certain product.
We know that our power series
times cosine of x equals to 1,
and we can use that to solve for
some of the coefficients.
Or you can also, similarly, when
you have that situation,
you can also use long division
to compute the coefficients.
I'll end there.