Welcome back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
do the following problem,
which is going to be relating
polar and Cartesian
coordinates.
So I want you to write each of
the following in Cartesian
coordinates, and that means our
x y coordinates, and then
describe the curve.
So the first one is r squared
equals 4r cosine theta, and
the second one is r equals 9
tangent theta secant theta.
So again, what I'd like you to
do is convert each of these to
something in the Cartesian
coordinates, in the x y
coordinates, and then I want you
to describe what the curve
actually looks like.
So I'll give you a little while
to work on it, and then
when I come back, I'll
show you how I do it.
OK, welcome back.
Well, hopefully you were able
to get pretty far in
describing these two curves
in x y coordinates.
And I will show you how I
attacked these problems. So
we'll start with a.
So for A--
I'm going to rewrite the problem
up here, so we can
just be focused on
what's up here.
So we had r squared equals
4r cosine theta.
Well, we know what
r squared is.
That's nice in terms of
x and y coordinates.
That's just x squared
plus y squared.
So we know that, so we'll
replace that.
And then we can actually replace
all the r's and thetas
over here pretty easily,
as well.
Because we know r cosine
theta describes x.
So the cartesian coordinate x
is the polar coordinate--
or described in polar
coordinates as r cosine theta.
So we can just write
that as 4x.
And the reason I asked you to
describe the curve is because
from here, you could say, oh,
well I wrote it in the
Cartesian coordinates.
I wrote it in x y, and
so now I'm done.
But the point is that you can
actually work on this equation
right here and get into a form
that you can recognize.
That it'll be a recognizable
curve.
So let's see if we can sort of
play around with this, and
come up with something
that looks familiar.
And what you might think to do,
would be, say, you know,
subtract off the x squared, or
subtract off the y squared.
Try and solve for x
or solve for y.
But that can be a little bit
dangerous in this situation,
because in fact, y might
not be a function of x.
So we might run into
some trouble there.
But if you'll notice, there's
something kind of, a glaring
way we should go.
And that's because we have this
x squared plus y squared
together-- this maybe could look
something like a circle
or an ellipse or something like
that, if we could figure
out a way to put this part
in with the x squared.
So this is kind of--
it's a good way to think
about what direction to
head in this problem.
In particular, it would be a bad
idea for this problem for
you to subtract x squared
and take the square
root of both sides.
Because you would lose some
information about
what this curve was.
OK?
Because when you take the square
root, you would have to
say, well, do I want the
positive square root, or do I
want the negative square root?
We'd lose a little bit
of information.
So we do not want
to solve for y.
So let's do what I said.
Let's try and figure out a way
to get this 4x into something
to do with this x
squared term.
So I'm going to subtract 4x and
rewrite the equation here.
And so you might say, well,
Christine, this doesn't really
seem that helpful.
It's just the same thing
moved around.
But we're going to use one of
our favorite techniques from
integration, which is completing
the square.
So we can actually complete the
square on this guy right
here, and turn it into
a perfect square.
We'll have to add an extra term,
but once we do that,
we'll have a perfect
square, an extra
term, and a y squared.
And we're getting more into
the form of something that
actually looks like a circle.
So let's see.
Completing the square on this,
it's going to be x squared
minus 4x plus 4.
How did I know that?
Well, if I want to complete
the square on this, I need
something that, multiplied by
2, gives me negative 4.
That's 2.
And then 2 squared is 4.
So that's where the
4 comes in.
To keep this equal, I'll add 4
to the other side, as well.
So if I add 4 to both sides, I
haven't changed the equality,
and I keep my y squared
along for the ride.
So now I have a perfect
square.
What does this give me?
This gives me x minus 2 quantity
squared plus 4-- plus
four squared-- plus y squared.
So x minus 2 quantity squared.
That came from these
three terms. Plus y
squared equals four.
And now it's a curve we
can describe, clearly.
What curve is this?
Well, it's obviously a circle.
It's centered at the point 2
comma 0, and it has radius 2.
We've talked, or you've seen
this in the lecture videos.
I believe what the form for a
circle is, x minus a quality
squared plus y minus b quantity
squared equals r squared.
So this is, a is 2, b is 0, and
r is 2. so it's a circle
of radius 2, centered
at 2 comma 0.
So we have a good way to
describe what started off in
polar coordinates.
We can now describe it
in x y coordinates.
OK.
So now let's move on to B. And
I'm going to rewrite B over
here as well, so we don't
have to worry
about it, looking back.
r equals 9 tan theta
secant theta.
OK.
So let's look at this.
Now, there's some information
buried in here, in terms of x
y coordinates.
And one thing that should stand
out to you is, what is
secant theta?
Secant theta is 1 over
cosine theta.
Right?
And if we have 1 over cosine
theta over here, we can
multiply both sides by cosine
theta, and we get an r cosine
theta over here.
So I'm going to write
that down.
That this actually
is in the same--
this is the same as r cosine
theta equals 9 tan theta.
Right?
I mean, you could get mad at me
about where this is defined
in terms of theta, but I'm not
worrying about that in this
situation, just right now.
We're just trying to figure
out how we could write
this in x and y.
We know what our cosine
theta is.
Again, it's x, as
it was before.
What about tan theta?
Tangent theta, remember, if you
recall, this tangent theta
is opposite over adjacent,
right?
And in this case, opposite is
the y, and adjacent is the x.
This is something you saw a
picture of, you can see a
picture of pretty easily.
So this is x is equal
to 9 times y over x.
Right?
Which is x squared
is equal 9y.
So this is in fact how you could
write this expression
that's in r and theta
in terms of x and y.
And so this, if you look at
it, is actually a parabola
that goes through the point 0,
0, and is stretched by a
factor of 9, or 1/9.
Well, I guess you can say,
there's a vertical stretch or
horizontal stretch, you can
pick which one it is.
And in one case, it's going
to be by 3 or 1/3.
I always mix those up.
I'd have to check.
Or by 9 or 1/9.
So essentially, it's going to
be a parabola with some
stretching on it.
Now, the problem is that you
might say, well, it's not
really all of that.
Because secant theta is not
going to be defined for all
theta the way cosine is.
So you do potentially run into
some problems. You might have
to worry about what part of
the domain makes sense for
theta, so that this
is well-defined.
And so that this is
well-defined, what part of the
curve is carved out.
That's a little more technical
than I want
to go in this video.
But some of you might look
at it and say, oh,
she's missing something.
Yeah, you caught something
that I'm
intentionally ignoring.
So the main point of this was
just so that you could see how
you can take these functions of
r and theta and turn them
into functions of x and y, and
then figure out kind of what
the curves might look like.
So I'm going to stop there.
Hopefully this was a good
exercise to get you
understanding how these
different coordinates relate
to one another.
And yeah, that's where
we'll leave it.