JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
Today I wanted to talk about
something that's mentioned in
the notes but wasn't
covered in lecture
because of the exam review.
So this is, the subject is
hyperbolic trig functions.
So first I just wanted to define
them for you and graph
them so we can get a little
bit of a feeling for what
these functions are like, and
then I'm going to explain to
you why they have the
words hyperbolic and
trig in their names.
So these are some interesting
functions.
They're not, they don't, aren't
quite as important as
your usual, sort of circular
trig functions.
But yeah, so let me introduce
them and let me jump in just
with their definition.
So there are two most
important ones.
Just like a regular
trigonometric functions
there's the sine and the cosine
and then you can write
the other four trigonometric
functions in terms of them.
So for hyperbolic trig
functions we have the
hyperbolic scoine and
the hyperbolic sine.
So the notation here,
we write c o s h.
So the h for hyperbolic.
So hyperbolic cosine.
And usually we pronounce this
"cosh." And similarly, for the
hyperbolic sine we write s i n
h, for hyperbolic sine, except
in the reverse order.
And we usually pronounce this
"sinch," so in American
English as if there were
an extra c in there.
Sinch.
OK.
So these functions have fairly
simple definitions in terms of
the exponential function--
e to the x.
So cosh of x is defined to be e
to the x plus e to the minus
x divided by 2.
And sinh of x is defined to be
e to x minus e to the minus x
divided by 2.
So if you remember what your
graph of e to the x looks
like, and your graph of e to the
minus x, it's not hard to
see that the graphs of cosh x
and sinh x, should look sort
of like this.
So for cosh x, so we see as x
gets big, so e to the minus x
is going to 0.
It's not very important.
So it mostly is driven by
this e to the x part.
And as x gets negative and big,
then this is going to 0
and this is getting
larger and larger.
So we got something that
looks like this.
So it looks a little bit, in
this picture it looks a little
bit like a parabola, but the
growth here is exponential at
both sides.
So in fact, this is growing
much, much, much faster than,
say 1 plus x squared.
So it's a much steeper curve.
OK.
And it reaches its minimum here
at x equals 0-- it has
the value 1 plus 1 over 2.
So its minimum there is
x equals 0 as its
minimum value 1.
For sinh, OK, so we're taking
the difference of them.
So it's similar when x is
positive and large, e to the x
is big, and e to the minus
x is pretty small, almost
negligible.
So we got exponential growth
off that side.
When x becomes negative and
large, e to the x is going to
0, e to the minus x is becoming
large, but it's,
we've got a minus sign here.
So as x goes to minus infinity,
this curve goes also
to minus infinity.
And again, the growth here is
exponential in both cases.
And if you were curious, say
about what the slope there at
the origin is, you could quickly
take a derivative and
check that that's passing
through the origin
with slope 1 there.
OK.
So this is a sort of basic
picture of what
these curves look like.
They have some nice properties,
and let me talk
about them.
So for example, one nice thing
you might notice about these
functions is that it's easy to
compute their derivatives.
Right?
So if we look at d dx of cosh
x in order to compute that,
well, just look at the
definition of cosh.
So it's really just a sum of
two exponential functions.
Exponential functions are easy
to take the derivatives.
Take the derivative of e to
the x, you get e to the x.
Take the derivative of e to the
minus x, well, OK, so it's
a little chain rule so you
get a minus 1 in front.
So the derivative of cosh x is
e to the x minus e to the
minus x over 2.
But we have a name for this.
This is actually just sinh x.
So the derivative of cosh is
sinh, and the derivative of
sinh, well, OK.
You look at the same thing, take
this formula, take its
derivative, well, e to the x.
Take its derivative,
you get e to the x.
e to the minus x.
Take its derivative, you get
minus e to the minus x, so
those two minus signs cancel
out and become a plus.
So this is e to the x plus
e to the minus x over 2,
which is cosh x.
So here you have some behavior
that's a little bit
reminiscent of the behavior
of trig functions.
Right?
For trig functions, if you take
the derivative of sine
you get cosine.
And if you take the derivative
of cosine you almost get back
sine, but you get minus sine.
So here you don't have
that extra negative
sign floating around.
Right?
So you, when you take the
derivative of cosh you get
sinh on the nose.
No minus sign needed.
So that's interesting.
But the real reason that these
have the words trig in their
name is actually a little
bit deeper.
So let me come over here and
draw a couple pictures.
So the normal trig functions--
what sometimes we call the
circular trig functions if we
want to distinguish them from
the hyperbolic trig
functions--
they're closely, so circular
trig functions, they're
closely related to
the unit circle.
So the unit circle has equation
x squared plus y
squared equals 1.
It's a circle.
Well, close enough, right?
And what is the nice
relationship between this
circle and the trig functions?
Well, if you choose any point
on this circle, then there
exists some value of t such
that this point has
coordinates cosine
t comma sine t.
Now it happens that the value
of t is actually the angle
that that radius makes with
the positive axis.
But not going to worry
about that right now.
It's not the key
idea of import.
So as t varies through the real
numbers, the point cosine
t, sine t, that varies and it
just goes around this curve.
So it traces out this
circle exactly.
So the hyperbolic trig functions
show up in a very
similar situation.
But instead of looking at the
unit circle, what we want to
look at is the unit rectangular
hyperbola.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, so instead of taking the
equation x squared plus y
squared equals 1, which gives a
circle, I'm going to look at
a very similar equation that
gives a hyperbola.
So this is the equation,
x squared minus y
squared equals 1.
So if you if you graph this
equation, what you'll see is
that, well, it passes through
the point 1, 0.
And then we've got one branch
here, we've got a little out
asymptote there.
So it's got a right branch
like that, and also it's
symmetric across the y-axis.
So there's a symmetric
left branch here.
So this is the graph of the
equation, x squared minus y
squared equals 1.
So it's this hyperbola.
Now what I claim is that cosh
and sinh have the same
relationship to this hyperbola
as cosine and
sine have to the circle.
Well, so I'm fudging
a little bit.
So it turns out it's only the
right half of the hyperbola.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, here's what
I'd like to do.
Set x equals--
so we're going to introduce
a new variable, u--
I'm going to set x equal cosh
u and y equals sinh u.
And I'm going to look
at the quantity x
squared minus y squared.
So x squared minus y squared.
So this is, so we use most
of the same notations for
hyperbolic trig functions
that we do for
regular trig functions.
So this is cosh squared u
minus sinh squared u.
And now we can plug in the
formulas for cosh and sinh
that we have. So this is equal
to e to the u plus e to the
minus u over 2 quantity squared
minus e to the u minus
e to the minus u over
2 quantity squared--
and now we can expand out both
of these factors and, both of
these squares, rather, and
put them together.
So over 2 squared is over 4 and
we square this and we get
e to the 2u.
OK, so then we get 2 times e to
the u times e to the minus
u-- but e to the u times e to
the minus u is just 1--
so plus 2 plus e to the minus
2u minus e to the 2u minus 2
plus e to the minus 2u-- so
same thing over here--
over 4.
OK, so the e to the 2u's cancel
and the e to the minus
2u's cancel and we're left
with 2 minus minus 2.
That's 4.
So this is 4 over 4, so
this is equal to 1.
OK.
So if x is equal to cosh u and
y is equal to sinh u, then x
squared minus y squared
is equal to 1.
So if we choose a point cosh
u, sinh u for sum u, that
point lies on this hyperbola.
That's what this says.
That this point, OK so the
point cosh u, sinh u is
somewhere on this hyperbola.
And what's also true is the
sort of reverse statement.
If you look at all such points,
if you let u vary and
look through the real numbers
and you ask what happens to
this point cosh u, sinh u, the
answers is that it traces out
the right half of
this hyperbola.
If you go back to the graph of
y equals cosh x, you'll see
that the hyperbolic cosine
function is always positive.
So we can't--
over here-- we can't
trace out this left
branch where x is negative.
Although it's easy enough to say
what does trace out this
left branch.
Since it's just the mirror
image, this is traced out by
minus cosh u comma sinh u.
So there's a, so the hyperbolic
trig functions have
the same relationship to this
branch of this hyperbola that
the regular trig functions
have to the circle.
So there's where the words
hyperbolic and trig
functions come from.
So let me say one more thing
about them, which is that we
saw that they have
this analogy with
regular trig functions.
Right?
So instead of satisfying cosine
squared plus sine
squared equals 1, they satisfy
cosh squared minus sinh
squared equals 1.
And instead of satisfying the
derivative of sine equals
cosine and the derivative of
cosine equals minus sine, they
satisfy derivative of cosh
equals sinh and derivative of
sinh equals cosh.
So similar relationships.
Not exactly the same,
but similar.
So this is true of a lot of
trig relationships that
there's a corresponding formula
for the hyperbolic
trig functions.
So one example of such a formula
is your, for example,
your angle addition formulas.
So I'm going to just leave this
is an exercise for you.
So let me, I guess I'll just
stick it in this funny little
piece of board right here.
So, exercise.
Find sinh of x plus y and cosh
of x plus y in terms of sinh
x, cosh x, sinh y, and cosh y.
So in other words, find the
corresponding formula to the
angle addition formula
in that case of the
hyperbolic trig functions.
So I'll leave you with that.