Now I'll go to problem
number six.
Problem number six is 23-14.
I have a sphere, which is
a solid metal sphere.
It is solid.
It's not hollow,
and it's metal.
There is a charge plus
Q on this sphere.
You're being asked: If the
sphere has a radius capital R,
what the electric field inside
the sphere is, what is radius
little r, and what it is
outside the sphere.
I will not assume, which is
something we already know,
that all the charge will
have to be at the
surface of this sphere.
The reason is that it's a
conductor, it's a metal, and
there cannot be any charge
inside the sphere.
That's not the case if the
sphere were made of glass.
Then you could have uniformly
distributed charge throughout
the glass, but not
for a metal.
But now I will first show you
why that is the case, so I
will distribute artificially
the charge uniformly
throughout this volume.
I'm now going to calculate what
to the E field is at the
location r from the center.
I introduce a Gaussian surface,
which is a sphere.
It has a radius r, and
obviously, there would be an
E-field which is pointing
radially outwards, and the
elements ds are exactly in
the same direction as E--
this is ds--
everywhere on this sphere, which
is a concentric sphere.
I apply Gauss' Law with
4 pi r squared--
that's the surface area--
times E. Forget the dot, because
the cosine of the
angle is plus 1, but that now
must be the charge inside this
sphere divided by epsilon 0.
This charge inside the sphere
is not zero, and therefore,
what's going to happen is there
is going to be a force
on the electrons.
If I have an electric field, and
there are electrons, they
will experience a force, but the
electrons in a conductor,
in a metal, are free to move, so
they're going to move under
the inference of the force
imposed on them by the
electric field.
They will not stop moving until
that force is zero, and
that force will only become zero
when the electric field
has vanished.
So there is no electric
field inside a
conductor that can be possible.
The electrons would
simply kill it.
What is the conclusion?
That the charge must all
be at the surface.
I conclude that the E field for
r less than R must be 0.
Now, we will calculate
the electric
fields outside the sphere.
I think we should make a
new drawing for that.
Radius R, and now I have a
Gaussian surface, which has
radius little r, and the E
fields will be pointing out
radially everywhere, and the
ds's will be pointing out
radially everywhere, and so it's
is very easy now to write
down Gauss' Law.
4 pi r squared E of r equals all
the charge, which we know
now is the surface.
It's uniformly distributed at
the surface Q divided by
epsilon 0, and so we find that
E equals Q divided by 4 pi
epsilon 0 r squared.
Famous result, inversely
proportional to r squared, and
this holds as long as r is
larger or equal to R. Of
course, you can put in some
numbers, and then you'll get
some answers.
This is always true.
This is even true if this were
not a metal and if the charges
were uniformly distributed
throughout, then the answer
outside the radius capital
R would still be correct,
because I have still
applied Gauss' Law.
Of course,
if this were glass, and if the
charges were uniformly
distributed throughout, then the
electric field inside the
sphere would not be zero.
Maybe you would want to
calculate what it would be as
a function of little r.
Maybe that's a nice
exercise for you.