PROFESSOR: Hi.
Today we'll explore the complex
numbers and Euler formula.
So the first part of the problem
is to write this
complex number minus 2 plus
3i in polar form.
And at this point, it's
written in rectangular
coordinate form.
The second question asks you
to do the reverse, to write
three exponential to the i
pi over 6 in rectangular
coordinate form.
Question c asks you to draw
and label the triangle
relating the rectangular
coordinates to the polar
coordinate form.
D asks you to compute 1 over
this reverse complex number
that we already saw
in question a.
And e asks you to find
the cube root of 1.
And in all these questions,
you'll be using Euler formula.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a few minutes to
work out the problem,
and we'll come back.
Welcome back.
So we're asked throughout the
problem to go back and forth
between coordinates in polar
form and in rectangular form.
So a key thing to remember is
Euler formula from the start.
So we're just going to
write it up here.
It allows us to express a
complex exponential into the
sum of its cosine plus
i sine theta.
So how do we tactical
question a?
Question a gives us a complex
number in rectangular form.
So in this form, a plus i b.
And we're asked to write it in
polar form, which introduces
the modulus of the complex
number r and its phase theta.
So r, modulus of the complex
number that we can compute
when we know its rectangular
form, with its real form
squared plus imaginary part
squared, the whole
thing under the root.
So in this case, we
have four plus 9.
So we end up with root of 13
for the modulus of the
complex number z.
So now for the phase.
Using Euler formula, we can
see that we can relate the
rectangular form to the polar
form by just introducing--
I'm going to keep r.
And you can see now that we can
extract the sine and the
cosine of the angle theta and
relate that to a ratio of a.
And the modulus r that we just
found, b modulus r that we
just found.
Or in one move, just express it
as the tangent of the angle
theta, just sine over the
cosine, just becomes basically
b over a, which we have here.
So we have the modulus r, which
is now root of 13, and
the angle theta that we can
now extract by using the
reverse of the function 10.
So just before we move to the
next question, this is not one
of the classical angles
that you learned.
So just to have an idea of where
this angle lies on the
trigonometric unit circle, just
recall here that the sine
is positive and the cosine of
this angle is negative.
So we're bound to be in this
region, where basically theta
is between pi and pi over 2.
And that's the answer
to question a.
So now for question b, we're
asked to do the reverse,
expressing the polar number 3i
pi over 6 in rectangular
coordinates.
So now this is just a
straightforward application of
the Euler formula that
we just saw.
By just expanding the
exponential, as I already
wrote there.
Plus i3 sine pi over 6.
And on the same trigonometric
circle here, that's roughly
where pi over 6 lie.
And you can just re-express this
as 3, root of 3 over 2,
plus i, 3 over 2.
So that answers the solution
for question b.
So now question c.
Let me just add a line here.
Question c we're asked to draw
and label the triangle
relating rectangular to
polar coordinates.
So that's what we already had
a sense with when we wrote
this formula going from
a plus i b to r
exponential of i theta.
So in the complex plane, we
have the real axis, an
imaginary axis, and a complex
number lying on this plane
written in this form in a
rectangular coordinate.
You'd have a projection of a in
the real axis, projection
of value b on the
imaginary axis.
And in polar form this would
be its modulus or distance
from the origin, and its phase
theta that would come in the
polar form.
So that's the triangle that
allows us to go back and forth
between the rectangular
and polar coordinates.
So to almost finish, question
d now asks us to compute the
reverse of the original complex
number that we used.
So 1 over minus 2 plus 3i.
So to do this, we can stay in
rectangular form and basically
multiply the numerator and
denominator by the complex
conjugate of the number.
But clearly now that we learned
how to use polar
coordinate expressions of this
number, it's much easier to
just write it directly
in this form.
In one step we basically arrived
to the results, where
we express that the angle
was the reverse 10 of
minus 3 over 2.
And that's done.
So now are for the last
question, we were asked to
compute the one third
root of 1.
So basically, 1 to one third.
So here, obviously,
we're treating 1
as a complex number.
And if we go in the complex
plane and I just introduce
here the number 1, we see that
in polar form 1 is just
basically a complex number with
modulus 1, and angle 0
modulus 2pi.
So we can write 1 as exponential
2 n pi, because
it's basically angle
0 modulus 2pi.
And from here we know that we're
looking at third roots,
so we're going to have
three roots.
And these roots are going to be
expressed by changing the
value of n.
First one, n equals to 0 is
just going to give us back
root of 1, because we're going
to have exponential
to 0 is just 1.
Power of one third is just 1.
n equals to 1.
We are going to have exponential
of 2pi over 3,
which we can express again using
the Euler formula, also
in coordinate form.
And then just write
down the values.
And for the third root we take
the value n equals to 2, so we
have i 4 pi over 3, which again
we can express as the
cosine plus the sine
of 4pi over 3.
So where do these roots lie?
So we have root 1 for
n equals to 0.
The second root exponential 2pi
over 3, basically in polar
form would be here, where
we would have the
angle 2pi over 3.
So 1pi over 2 would here.
2pi over 3 would be here.
3pi over 3 would be here.
And 4pi over 3 is our third
root, it would be here.
So then we can just write
down the values.
And you can do that when you
know the angles, or just keep
it in either form when you
don't know their overall
expression for the angles.
So this completes the problems
in all of these problems what
we kept using is Euler formula
to go back and forth between
coordinate in rectangular form
to expression of complex
number in polar form.
And that's the key formula
that we kept using.
And you'll be using this
repeatedly when we will be
solving other ODEs for which we
can use complex number as a
trick for solutions.
And this ends this session.