CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like to do
two problems that ask us to
determine the flux of a vector
field along a surface.
So the first one is I'd like you
to find the outward flux
of the vector z comma x comma
y through the piece of the
cylinder that's shown.
So it's just shading the
cylindrical part.
So it's a cylinder of radius a,
and you're taking the piece
in the first octant
up to height h.
So that's the first question
I'd like you to answer.
Is the flux of this vector field
through that piece of
the cylinder the outward flux?
And then I'd also like you to
find the outward flux of this
vector field xz comma yz comma z
squared through the piece of
the sphere of radius a
in the first octant.
So again, it will be in the
first octant like this one is
in the first octant.
It'll be the piece of the sphere
that sits in the same
part of three-dimensional space
as the piece of the
cylinder we're looking
at here.
So what I'd like you to do,
again, is just find the flux--
in both cases, the outward
flux-- of the vector listed
through the surface
that is listed.
And then when you feel
comfortable and confident with
your answer, you can bring the
video back up and I'll show
you how I did it.
OK, welcome back.
So again, what we're trying to
do is determine flux of a
vector field through
a surface.
So I am going to determine first
what the normal is here,
and then what F dot n is here,
and then using the fact that I
know F dot n and I know dS in
a good parametrization, I'm
going to be able to calculate
the integral quite simply.
So let's point out first, that
the normal at any point on the
surface is going to be equal to
x comma y comma 0 divided
by a, where a is, again,
the radius.
Because in the normal, I know
there's no z component.
And I actually know it's the
same as the normal would be on
a circle of radius a.
And so this vector x comma y
has length a obviously, so
that's why I'm dividing by a.
So when I look at the normal and
I dot it with F, let's see
what I get.
F dotted with the normal is
going to be xz plus xy divided
by a, right?
So I just took x dotted with
x times z, y times z, and 0
times y, I add those up, and I
still have to divide by my a.
So that's actually the vector
dotted with the normal.
Now, what a natural
parametrization to use here is
obviously the cylindrical
coordinates
because I'm on a cylinder.
The radius is fixed.
But what I'm interested in is
changes in theta and changes
in the height.
So I'm going to be interested in
d theta and dz, and I need
to understand what dS
in this case is.
And it's just a d theta dz.
So let me write down what I'm
going to need to completely
determine the rest
of number one.
I'm integrating over
the surface.
And I'll put the bounds
momentarily.
Actually, I should also point
out, I'm going to write x and
y in terms of theta, because
now I know what they are.
x in terms of theta is a cosine
theta, and y in terms
of theta is a sine theta.
So when I simplify the
expression F dot n, I get z
times cosine theta for
my first component.
And I get a times cosine
theta sine theta
for my second component.
So let me maybe point out
again how I got that.
Let me come over here.
x is a cosine theta.
So I get z times a cosine
theta divided by a.
So I get z times cosine theta.
x again is a cosine theta.
y is a sine theta.
So I get a squared cosine
theta sine theta.
And I divide by a, so
I get a single a
cosine theta sine theta.
And then my dS, as I mentioned
before, is
a d theta dz, right?
And so now I just have to figure
out the bounds in theta
and the bounds in z.
Well, the bounds in
z are very easy.
The bounds in z are simply 0 to
h, and so I'm going to put
those here on the outside.
And then the bounds in theta.
Maybe it's helpful to come over
and look at my picture.
This direction, in the
x-direction, is
theta equals 0.
When I swing around to the
y-direction, I'm at theta
equals pi over 2.
So I need to go from 0
to pi over 2, right?
So let me come back over here.
OK, so now, really, I have a
couple of constants that are
letters, but everything now,
I'm ready to integrate.
So a is just a constant, and h
is a constant, and z and theta
are my variables, and I can
actually do this integration
quite simply.
I'm not going to do it because
I know this is at this point
something we already know
how to do, but I'll
give you the answer.
So let me write down
the answer.
You get ah squared over 2,
plus a squared h over 2.
So that's the solution
you actually get.
So again, I mean you have to
integrate in d theta first. So
you have to deal with this, you
have to deal with this,
and this uses a good
trig identity.
You can use the fact that 2
sine theta cosine theta is
sine 2 theta.
I'll give you that little hint,
and then you can figure
it out from there.
And then you integrate in z, and
you evaluate from 0 to h.
So that's the solution
to number one.
So now, let's look
at number two.
Number two we have to
again figure out.
We have our vector field and we
know our surface is a piece
of a sphere.
And so if we're going to
parametrize the surface of a
sphere, we know we want to use
d theta and d phi, OK?
And let me point out first,
that again, the normal is
going to be in some ways similar
to what we saw on the
cylinder, but now instead of x
comma y comma 0, because it's
a sphere, it's going to be x
comma y comma z divided by a.
So again, as before, let me just
point out the normal that
I'm going to be using is
x comma y comma z,
all divided by a.
So I'm going to dot F with
n and look at the surface
integral with respect to dS--
d capital S there--
and I'll see what I get.
So again, I know how I'm going
to parametrize this sphere.
I already mentioned it, but
let me say it again.
It's going to be in theta
and phi, right?
Because we have a
constant radius.
We're on a sphere of radius a.
So I don't need to change rho.
It's a two-dimensional thing.
So theta is varying and
phi is varying.
So let's see what we get first.
Let me do a little work
and see what we get when we
look at F dotted with n.
So let me first point out that
F dotted with n looks like
it's x squared z plus y squared
z plus-- just to make
this obvious--
z squared z, all divided by a.
x squared plus y squared plus z
squared is a squared, right?
So it's actually a squared
times z divided by a.
So it's just a times z, right?
So far, all I've done was I
dotted F with the normal, and
I knew the fact that x squared
plus y squared plus z squared
was a squared, because I was
on a sphere of radius a.
So a squared times z divided
by a is a times z.
And now if I want to use the
right coordinates, think about
theta and phi.
z is a cosine phi.
So F dot n in the coordinates
I'm interested in is going to
be a squared cosine phi.
So let me get out of the way
so you can see that.
So that's what our
F dot n will be.
And now, if we're going to
figure out the flux, of
course, it's the integral
of F dot n dS.
And let's remind ourselves
what dS is.
dS is going to be a squared
sine phi d theta d phi.
You saw this in lecture,
actually, also.
So this should look familiar.
And so now I just have to
integrate F dot n dS over the
right bounds for
theta and phi.
So let's determine
what those are.
I'll put everything together,
and we'll
determine what those are.
So I've got F dot n dS.
That's going to be a to the
fourth sine phi cosine phi d
theta d phi.
And let's think about what is
the picture that I need in
terms of the first octant
of a sphere.
Maybe I should draw a quick
picture over here so we can
remember what that looks like.
So it's going to be--
this is not going to be the
greatest drawing ever-- but
it's something like this.
And so I've got pieces of
a circle at each level.
I've got a piece of
a circle, right?
If this is the x-direction, this
is the y-direction, and
this is the z-direction,
theta is going from 0--
again--
to pi over 2, and phi is going
from 0 to pi over 2, right?
So they're both going
from 0 to pi over 2.
So hopefully, you were able to
get this far at least, in
terms of figuring out the
flux of F through that
piece of the sphere.
And I'm, again, just going to
write down the solution, and
then you can check your answer
against the solution.
And I got a to the fourth
over 4 times pi.
So this whole solution
is a to the fourth
divided by 4 times pi.
So you can check your
solution there.
Again, I want to point out, what
we did in both of these
problems is we were trying to
compute the flux of a certain
vector field through
a surface.
And if you'll notice, what I
actually did in this case is I
kept the parametrization in
terms of the x, y, z variables
first, and then I put it in the
parametrization of theta
and phi after.
And that made it a little
easier to hang on to and
figure out what it was.
Because notice, that x, y, and
z become very complicated in
theta and phi.
I have to write a lot
more down, I guess.
And then simplify things
more carefully.
This way, it was very obvious
that I got an a squared times
z in the numerator.
So sometimes it's a little
easier to compute the F dot n
in the initial x, y, z
variables, and then change it
to the appropriate
parametrization for the
surface you're looking at.
So that's what we
did, actually.
In both cases we computed F dot
n, we put it in the right
parametrization, and then we had
to figure out what dS was.
We had to make sure we knew dS,
and then we just had to
integrate over the appropriate
bounds for our parameters.
And that's giving us the flux
across the surface.
So I think that's
where I'll stop.