Welcome back to recitation.
In this video I would like us
to do the following problem.
We're going to let z equal x
squared plus y and we want S
to be the graph of z above the
unit square in the x-y plane.
And what we'd like to do is
for F equal to zi plus xk,
find the upward flux of F
through S. So S is our surface
that's a graph over the x-y
plane and the unit square of z
equal to x squared plus y.
And we want to compute
the upward flux of F
through that surface.
So why don't you work on this
problem, pause the video, and
then when you're ready to
see my solution, bring
the video back up.
OK, welcome back.
So again what we want to do is
we want to find the upward
flux of F through this surface
S. And let's think about
first, how do we describe
the surface S?
S is the graph of z equal
x squared plus y.
So we can think of it as, z is
really a function of x and y
over the unit square.
So we can say F of x, y is equal
to z which is equal to x
squared plus y.
And then we know how to
compute the normal--
well, we know how to compute n
dS, which also in class is
sometimes written notationally
as dS with the vector dS.
So we know how to compute
this form right here.
And it is-- you were shown
in class that if F is--
or sorry.
If you have a graph, if your
surface is a graph, then this
is exactly equal to the vector
minus f sub x comma minus f
sub y comma 1 dx dy.
So that's exactly
what this n dS--
so n is the vector, and dS is
the surface form we have here.
So n dS is exactly equal to
the vector minus f sub x,
minus f sub y, 1, dx dy.
So what do we have here with
f sub x? f sub x--
because f is equal to z-- f sub
x is 2x and f sub y is 1.
So in our case we get exactly
minus 2x, comma minus
1, comma 1, dx dy.
And now to compute the surface
integral what we do--
or sorry, to compute the flux
along the surface--
what we do is we integrate
over the surface--
which I guess we should remember
that's a double
integral, because it's
over a surface--
of F dotted with dS.
But that's the same as
integrating over the region.
So we have this surface, we
know the region below that
defines the surface in
the x-y coordinates.
So it's integrating over the
region of F dotted with this
vector here.
Because n dS, dS is n dS and
in the x-y components it's
exactly equal to this.
Minus 2x, minus 1, 1, dx dy.
So now we're integrating.
We've gone from looking
at a surface integral.
Now we're integrating--
we were integrating F dot dS on
the surface, to now taking
F dotted with this vector on
the region in the x-y plane
over which we can define S.
So the region we're
interested in,
remember, is the unit square.
So we have the unit square which
is x goes from 0 to 1
and y goes from 0 to 1.
And then what we're doing is
we're looking at F as a
function of x, y, and z.
And we want to dot that
with this vector.
And it's all being done in
the variables x and y.
So we should be able to change
everything to x and y
ultimately.
So let's look at what we
get when we do that.
So F--
I'm going to remind myself--
F was equal to zi plus xk.
Which, if I write that in the
component form, it's z comma,
0 comma, x.
So F dotted with our minus
f sub x minus f sub y 1--
which was minus 2x,
minus 1, 1--
we see we get--
minus 2x dotted with z-- we get
minus 2xz and then we get
0 and then we get x.
So we get minus 2xz plus x.
That's exactly what f dotted
with the vector we have is.
So now also we know that z was
equal to x squared plus y.
So we actually get negative
2x times x squared
plus y plus x again.
So I'm going to just
expand that so it's
easier to deal with.
So we get negative 2x cubed
minus 2xy plus x.
And now we have exactly what--
if we look over here-- we have
exactly this entire part here
written as a function
of x and y.
Which is good.
Why is that good?
Because everything we're
integrating is in x and y.
We're doing dx and dy so we just
need to figure out the
bounds and compute
the integral.
So let's come over here.
So the flux then is going to
be equal to-- well, we know
the region.
We know the region is y and x
are both going from 0 to 1.
So the order doesn't matter
because nothing depends on
another function.
And then we're integrating
exactly this function.
Negative 2x to the third
minus 2xy plus x dy dx.
So when we integrate
in y, we should be
careful what we get here.
We're going to have the integral
from 0 to 1, and then
we're going to have--
this we get a negative 2x
cubed times y, and then
evaluate it at 0 and 1.
So we just get a negative
2x cubed again.
We integrate this we have a
negative 2xy squared over 2.
So at 0 we get nothing
and at 1 we get 1/2.
And so we get minus 2x.
And then here when we integrate
in y, we get x times
y and we evaluate that at 1 and
0, and we got just plus x.
So let me just make
sure I didn't make
any mistakes there.
So this one, I'm integrating
it in y and so I get a
negative 2x cubed y, evaluated
at 0 and 1.
So at 1 I just get a negative
2x cubed, at 0 I get 0.
In this one, I have
a negative 2xy.
When I integrate that I get
a y squared over 2.
The 2s kill off.
So I'm left with a negative
of xy squared.
Evaluating that at 0 and 1, at
0 I get 0 and at 1 I get
negative x.
Oh, there.
So there shouldn't
be a 2 there.
And then here when I integrate
that I get xy evaluated at y
equals 0 and y equals 1, and
take that difference.
And at 1 I get just x and
at 0 I get nothing.
Hopefully that one
is correct now.
Because I forgot to kill off
the 2 there first. So those
subtract off and I'm left with
minus the integral from 0 to 1
of 2x cubed dx.
Well, that's going to be minus
of x cubed, it's going to be x
to the fourth over 4.
And then I have the
2 still here.
So that will divide out.
Evaluate at 0 and 1.
At 0 I obviously get nothing.
At 1 I get negative 1/2.
And so the flux of F across
the surface is equal to
negative 1/2.
And that's the upward flux.
So obviously if I wanted to know
the downward flux, that
would be positive 1/2.
It doesn't have anything
to do with what F is.
It has to do with the direction
of the normal that
I'm dotting F with.
So since I was dotting F with
the upward normal--
which is the ndS that I showed
you was the upward normal--
then I know that this
is the upward flux.
So let me just remind you
what we did here.
Let's come back to the
very beginning.
So the object was that we had
z as a function of x and y.
So we knew we had a surface
sitting over some region in
the x-y plane.
And we wanted to compute
the flux of a
certain vector field--
the upward flux of a certain
vector field--
across that surface.
And so all we had to do to
solve this problem was
ultimately understand what n
dS was-- which you actually
did in class.
You saw what n dS is,
this is the upward
normal through the surface.
And then recognize
that the flux--
again, we saw this from class--
that the flux is equal
to the double integral over the
surface of F dot dS, which
is the same as the double
integral over the region of F
dotted with n dS.
Where ndS now I'm referring to
as n is the vector and dS is--
this whole component is ndS--
that's what we found.
And so then we know F. It's
in terms of z, x, and y.
But then we can find it
in terms of x and y.
When we take that dot product we
end up with exactly just a
function of x and y, when we
replace z by what it actually
is equal to.
And then we just compute
the integral.
And this is just a regular
old double integral.
And we get the flux was
equal to minus 1/2.
And again, I want to point out
that if we wanted instead of
the upward flux the downward
flux, it would be the same
with the opposite sign.
OK.
That is where I think
I'll stop.