The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Before we move on
to the rest of the topics,
maybe just some administrative
stuff about the next
assignment.
So the idea is to model
a system, right?
So the idea is to pick some
sort of dual system.
In the past people have picked
stuff like applying for
college because they knew
all about that.
People have talked about any
type of idea, you know,
running a nuclear reactor
or something.
Specifically there's a--
but hey, any of you nuclear
science majors?--
oh, perfect.
One of my favorite Apple II
games was actually nuclear
reactor simulation, and
it always melted down.
That's why it was fun.
But pick a real world system
to start modeling.
Obviously, you're trying
to find the fun.
Obviously, you're trying to make
something that people are
going to enjoy playing.
But the idea is to start from
a slightly different place
from where we had in the
first assignment.
Now a couple of you guys already
did that for the first
assignment, though.
I mean things like picking
up girls at a party.
You know, modeling real
systems and things.
Still haven't played yet,
a genealogy game yet.
So, we're going to
play next March.
So [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
The survival horror game, I
would say it's not a real
world system.
It was a system.
Horror, wizards, trolls.
So, yeah, pick something within
games negotiating around--
like negotiating greenhouse gas
emissions, that was one
which was really, really
cutthroat.
That's what probably
you imagine.
Actually I'll try to get
that team to come in
later in the semester.
They did this and like talk
about their card game.
It was a freshman team
on Terrascope.
Let's see, On Wednesday, we're
going to do the usual
brainstorming inside of
the second half of the
upper-class.
You know, everybody throw
out your ideas.
Come in with a bunch of ideas,
we'll try to build on that.
But this time around you're
allowed to actually
pre-build your team.
You're allowed to ask people,
hey, you guys
want to work together?
You don't actually have to
figure it out on the spot if
you don't want to.
I don't really care how you do
it, as long as by Friday you
know who your team is.
And who's on your team.
Team sizes are the same.
So, any questions?
AUDIENCE: Are we allowed to
simulate things that aren't
from this era?
PROFESSOR: Yeah, like
normal history?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: OK, not from
like the future.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Yeah, I'm serious.
This is how I think
[INAUDIBLE].
OK, yes, absolutely there are
no historical stuff--
but you do have some
liberties.
I'm not saying that your game
has to be a faithful
simulation.
You can even build your model
simulation [INAUDIBLE].
But it doesn't have to be a
faithful simulation, that's
certainly a poor design.
But, you know, in a sense you're
trying to capture the
spirit of it.
If the point is, I'm running
a nuclear reactor.
And you can sort of capture
the, oh my God, it's so
dangerous , or the, oh my God,
it's so boring aspect of it.
Have you actually put the
nuclear reactor--
AUDIENCE:: Well, like,
what's there.
And I know the mechanics of
it, I think, were there.
PROFESSOR: I have been told it's
not necessarily the most
exciting job in the world.
AUDIENCE: No, you just sit there
and do your homework.
And every once in a
while you look up.
Very reasonable.
And you get paid for it.
Like $12 or $13 an hour.
PROFESSOR: So if your whole idea
of the game is let's try
to get as much homework done
without letting [INAUDIBLE].
That might be more entertaining
than just looking
[INAUDIBLE].
But I got my problems in then.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
You have to do [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: And besides, I think
we still have a time
limit, like half an hour.
It's not [INAUDIBLE]
homework, it's really
easy homework.
Really not homework.
Let's see, just a reminder for
everyone who has been falling
off on the foreign posts, please
make sure that you keep
up on your foreign posts.
Those things actually do
affect your grade.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
one person, not one team.
If you have any--
since we're in between reading
assignments right now, you can
write about the assignment.
But if you wrote up something,
let's say a reflection on how
the class assignment
went, that's fine.
We're not expecting more than
one foreign post a week.
Of course, feel free to comment
on other people's
foreign posts as well.
If a discussion or a point has
been raised that's kind of
interesting, you want to kind
of develop on that.
Put some thought into it.
Write something interesting
you're going to keep on the
compilation, that counts too.
And that's fine.
OK, so puzzles.
So Brenda's, before we start
with Brenda's, let's start
with Scott's.
What were some of the
definitions, or some of the
things that Scott's game was
mentioning, that were good for
puzzle design
AUDIENCE: The book or
not in the book?
PROFESSOR: This was
on the web page.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: --and had
the right answer.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: He didn't really
differentiate between puzzles
that could be generated like a
pseudo-GUI or something, where
you kind of have an algorithm
that lets you
create multiple puzzles.
But as long as that particular
iteration had one answer.
So that was really there.
Anything else you remember?
AUDIENCE: Tactical difficulty.
Make it accessible but
not super easy.
I think targeting a
specific audience.
It was also the ability to
change difficulty, it was
dynamic difficulty.
So some areas may actually be
easier settings, and then
actually what they want to
be is harder settings.
PROFESSOR: I think that
was Brenda's.
But, yeah, am I wrong?
AUDIENCE: There's also the
distinction between types of
difficulty.
Things where, you know, the
letter puzzle you had at the
beginning where it requires
thinking about
it, figuring it out.
It was patients versus
something else.
I can't remember what
the editor used.
But then you have things like
mazes and locations where you
have to be very careful, and
separate your way through.
PROFESSOR: And sometimes they
bring in information from
other domains.
From outside the puzzle, it's
not just like all the
information that you currently
need in the puzzle.
But the interesting thing
about the puzzle that he
particularly shows, is that he
shows a range of different
ways to actually solve it.
None of which are actually
satisfying except for the
final answer.
Which irritated me,
I'm telling you.
I'm not giving you
another puzzle.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
But it's kind of interesting to
think about, actually, what
audience it's for those kinds
of specific puzzles.
I mean, there are magazines
out of there like Games
magazine in particular, but
sometimes you see stuff
nestled into magazines that
are not just about games.
You see stuff like crossword
puzzles in newspapers and
things like that.
And now things like Sudoku and
all that are way more popular
that are meant to be really
in mass audience.
Whereas a magazine that is
specifically targeted at
puzzle enthusiasts can
be super hardcore.
With puzzles through the whole
magazine then you can have a
whole range of different
difficulties in there.
The assumption that you can
solve something not so hard.
AUDIENCE: I'm kind of
interested, does anybody know
how people in newspapers
generate crossword puzzles and
Sudoku puzzles?
Does anybody know what the
actual process behind that is?
I mean, I can imagine
how you might do it.
You might start with the filled
out thing and then
remove bits to get
your Sudoku.
Or you might brute force,
dictionary search to come up
with words which fit together in
order to form a crossword.
AUDIENCE: What they do with
Sudoku now is, they have some
computer algorithm--
and it has scales
of difficulty--
and it generates a random Sudoku
puzzle from your input.
AUDIENCE: Sudoku is solved
enough that you can actually
just algorithmically generate
[INAUDIBLE].
An actual numerical
difficulty.
You scale it from 1 to 10, 10
being where where there's like
literally only one step
to take in each point.
AUDIENCE: The one that took them
three months to solve.
AUDIENCE: But like crosswords,
there's people who actually
just get paid to sit down
and generate those.
AUDIENCE: I know that Premiere
takes submissions from other
people and they're edited
by [INAUDIBLE].
And then people submit
that and he kind of
like steps it up.
AUDIENCE: So he kind of
crowdsources crossword puzzles.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: But the difficulty
in a crossword puzzles isn't
just in the geometrically
how the words go.
The specific clues that they
give you can be more or less
obfuscated in some ways.
And New York Times, in
particular, is super
irritating with this.
They'll give you two words with
no grammatical context
about how they're supposed
to fit in.
So you can actually compare it
to see how they're difficulty
scaling just by looking
at the clues.
Not even looking at
the puzzle itself.
And I thought the other thing
about crosswords is, just to
bring up a point that we talked
about in the earlier
class, the crosswords,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
that these are dependent
upon the redundancy
of the English language.
You don't see every single
letter of a word in order to
figure out what the word is.
So that if it's a word that you
couldn't otherwise have
gotten from a clue, you can
still get just by seeing the
letters that are available.
Because the English language is
kind of about [INAUDIBLE],
redundant information.
If you dropped every single
vowel in a sentence, you could
probably still make out
what that sentence is.
And you don't necessarily
get that with Chinese.
How many folks here
have, [INAUDIBLE].
There are probably other
languages here where like
every single character means a
word or something like that.
AUDIENCE: Hebrew has
no vowels, right?
AUDIENCE: Well, they do up until
third grade and we start
dropping them after that.
So it's basically, because it
is understandable without
vowels, you eventually
just stop using them.
PROFESSOR: So that's
interesting.
If you had a crossword in
Hebrew, where you were
expected to write in the words
with vowels, you probably
could actually do one very
similar to an English one.
AUDIENCE: It's difficult because
the vowels in Hebrew
are attached to a letter, not
a separate character.
They're just down at the bottom
of the lower letter.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Another thing, in a
crossword the letter can make
a different sound in both.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Because a "v"
could be vo, or va, or
ve, you don't know.
You only know by context.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
like "c" could be sss or ca.
Like a hard or soft c.
Or "g" could be ga or ja.
PROFESSOR: That is true, but
although in English in
particular the phonetic meaning,
the way how a certain
word is pronounced isn't
necessarily essential for
solving a crossword puzzle.
Unless the clues happen
to be phonetic clues.
You know, sounds like a fish.
So that may not come in so much
to play when it comes to
finishing a part of it.
Jason, you had your hand up
earlier about Sudoku.
JASON: It was a comment about
the algorithmic [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Also, one thing
about algorithmic, about
Sudoku difficulty, a lot of
it comes from the selected
removal of numbers.
There's not what is the final
pattern going to look like
that's actually the
difficulty.
It's how do we remove the
numbers in a way that gives
multiple possible answers or
multiple possible dead ends,
because really there's
only one solution.
I'm not actually familiar
with the algorithm with
which it does so.
But it seems to be very clear
that there are at least two
algorithms.
One of which is very easy,
which is just provide a
legitimate Sudoku solution.
And then the one that is
slightly harder is now which
number is to be removed so
that's it's still solvable.
PROFESSOR:: Have you
all played Picross?
Someone want to describe it
for the folks who aren't
familiar with it?
We can use the white
board if--
sure.
AUDIENCE: I think the green
one works better.
I remember green is
better than black.
NICK: I'm really only familiar
with the [INAUDIBLE]
3D [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE:: Sorry to put you on
the spot Nick, as always.
NICK: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Here you'll have
written poems.
And then they all have something
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Oh, this.
This one where you spell
in the blocks.
NICK: And then given bits of
information, we have to work
out which of these blocks
is built and
which can be removed.
So the idea is the number tells
you the number of blocks
in that row or column which
has a filled block in it.
So in this case, nothing
is in it's column.
This column and that column
have nothing in it.
And this is probably not
actually a very good example
because I just pulled the
numbers out of my head.
AUDIENCE: Then you have the
sums are not the same.
NICK: So it's not going to work,
but you get the idea.
And things can get more
complicated, traditionally
there's just, I think,
three that are names.
That's there a connected
block of three.
So, for instance, this,
that, and that.
And I thought it had
to be broken.
But if there's a three which,
I think, is in a square or
something along these lines,
that means there are three in
that column.
But there's a gap in
there somewhere.
And then if it's like a three
inch circle or something else
complicated like that.
Then that means that there are
three but they all have gaps
between them.
AUDIENCE: But I've also seen
versions where they have just
a list of numbers.
And those are the--
there are [INAUDIBLE] blocks
of that length.
PROFESSOR: So if there's four in
a column you might say two,
three, five.
Which means there is a block of
two, followed by a block of
three, followed by
a block of five.
AUDIENCE: And they have to
have a gap between them.
PROFESSOR: And they will have to
have a gap in between them.
So it's not like you can
actually get a block of eight
in there somewhere.
But the whole idea is that
you've got this information
that is actually redundant.
You've got more information in
there than you necessarily
need to be able to figure out
which box and the situation to
be filled in.
Whether this should be empty.
But it's presented to you
in this obfuscated way.
The evidence, the clues that are
given to you in a way that
requires you to perform these
algorithms in order to figure
out which ones should
be changed.
And usually that's an algorithm
you can use to solve.
Although, I think Kim was the
one that was talking about
pattern matching.
But eventually as you get good
at these things, you start to
recognize patterns
right of the bat.
Like, that's a zero.
So that entire row is empty.
That's the sort of thing
that I do that becomes
automatic for you.
AUDIENCE: So, let's see.
I don't have much left more to
talk about Scott [INAUDIBLE].
Now these are, these are
more generated stuff.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So this basically is along the
lines of what Scott [? Pim ?]
is talking about.
But obviously this is more
physical not the pen and paper
kind of thing.
AUDIENCE: Will you
print up a copy?
PROFESSOR: Oh, you
want the copy?
No, because I just want
you to look at this.
Look at this first, don't
look at that.
Don't look at that.
So the basic idea is, let me
just start with one, you get a
card that is actually
a puzzle.
I wish we were doing these
outside now, because we're
going to zoom this out.
But the puzzle basically just
tells you how you are supposed
to set up your board
initially.
So, there's a-- oops
wrong [INAUDIBLE].
There's a green guy there.
This is supposed to be an easy
puzzle, I hope it is.
Because I'm getting
bad at this.
Red guy go to [INAUDIBLE]
I think.
Yeah, and that's the puzzle.
And there's one little
square on it, and
that you have to check.
So the basic idea is you
tip over the pieces so
that the guy moves.
And you don't want to be tipping
over the pieces in a
way where the white guy
can't move anymore.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so you're
tipping over things to make a
path that he can walk
along, right.
AUDIENCE: If I make a
closed loop, he has
to touch every piece?
AUDIENCE: I think he just
has to get to this one.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, you have
to get to the red one.
AUDIENCE: There's a plus mark.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: I'm not exactly sure
how to solve this one.
AUDIENCE: Yellow that way,
green, yellow that way.
AUDIENCE: Wait, you're allowed
to tip him over?
How do you die?
PROFESSOR: My understanding is
that he needs to fall onto
another piece, actually.
So let me just confirm I set
this up right, actually.
Yeah, I did.
AUDIENCE: No, so you push
the yellow that way.
And then the green that way.
And the other green that way.
AUDIENCE: So put the
yellow ones first?
AUDIENCE: So do the
green ones first.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I don't
actually have the
rules for the guy.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: How does he fall?
PROFESSOR: He's actually allowed
to move on anything
that's contiguously connected.
So, as long as you can
continuously connect up to
this, you're fine.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: 10: So tip
that first green.
No, other one.
And then form a path, right
now, if you tip that.
Oh, there's a hole.
AUDIENCE: 11: Are you sure tip
them over means more brown
spot and not--
AUDIENCE: 12: Well, if doesn't
then you can't reach
the red after it.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, I am absolutely
sure it means that
you're supposed to tip it
over in a way that--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: 13: Tip the
yellow one first.
Then move the guy out
to the green.
Then tip over the green.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: That is why it's
supposed to begin a
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
You can actually do it.
This is why this
is puzzle one.
AUDIENCE: 14: You can even
fall on top of anything?
That's bizarre.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: But, you know, this
is not entirely unlike the
kind of puzzle that
Scott does.
I mean, sure, this is one
particular piece of plastic
that the game is designed
to work with.
But basically it's just
like a book, right?
It's like a book of puzzles.
So there are also solutions in
here, but I find the solutions
harder to read.
AUDIENCE: The [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
was in the book.
PROFESSOR: It was in
Brenda's book?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: So, actually, that's
probably a good excuse
to switch over to Brenda's.
Well, actually, before
that I want to take
a look at the tangrams.
Everyone play the tangrams?
So, the basic idea is you've
got these shapes.
Does this one get
in, like this?
You've got these shapes, and if
you assemble them right as
is usually described on the
side of the box somewhere.
Where the heck?
AUDIENCE: It's on the inside.
PROFESSOR: I've got a big
picture on the side.
Is that you can actually fit
all of these shapes inside
that square.
So these are basically just a
square that's been divided in
a specific way.
So once I've got this assembled
everyone can just
pass this around.
Anyone who has already seen
it can pass it on.
That one doesn't fit very
well, but it works.
Hey, that's, ta da.
OK, so this is the basic side.
Now this is how it's been sold,
at least, is that this
is actually a calendar.
So every day you get
a different shape.
It's a cute little thing.
It's a pretty rudimentary
geometrical shape.
Some of them have, I think
this is supposed to be a
sphynx or something.
It looks like a frog.
This looks like a
Pac Man thing.
So the idea is that you
rearrange those particular
shapes into all of these
different shapes.
And you could play the game
without getting these puzzle
solutions, right?
And it talks a lot about, if
you've got a toy that's worth
playing with, you've got the
beginning of something that
might make a good game.
The nice thing about tipover
is that it's kind of fun to
tip over things.
And the thing about tangrams
is that I actually had more
fun playing with tangrams than
trying to solve specific
problems just by just trying
to rearrange these.
Who hasn't seen these before?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Kind of
embarrassing.
AUDIENCE: You should be
ashamed of yourself.
And all the work that
you did is gone.
PROFESSOR: But the thing is,
as a toy it doesn't really
matter, right?
Because it's just a certain
piece of anything.
And you kind of want to take it
apart and make new shapes
with it, like a little house.
So if you've got something
that's kind of fun to fiddle
with to begin with, you've got
possibly the beginning of a
game in general.
But the way how Scott was
talking about it, there's this
intermediate step where
it's a puzzle.
It's a toy with a specific
solution that you're
trying to get to.
And a game is kind of one step
beyond that where now there is
multiple solutions
and competitive.
At least, that's how
he's describing it.
He's not really a
game theorist.
He just works with puzzles.
AUDIENCE: He talks about it
in terms of a goal, right?
So then with a toy that you
don't have a goal with them.
With a puzzle, you have one
goal with no interaction.
And then a game is
with interaction.
PROFESSOR: And possibly multiple
goals as well.
But again it becomes more and
more directed as toys
are very free form.
So there are people who describe
games, like the Sims
for instance, as
actually toys.
In the same way that you
describe a doll house as a
toy, they're saying it's kind of
like a digital doll house.
But later versions of the
Sims added more and
more specific goals.
Like now you have to throw a
party with at least five
people in it.
Or you have to attain
career level five or
something like that.
I can't remember exactly
how they measured it.
But that kind of has a goal.
We are going to give more and
more specific things for you
to work towards.
But the Sims is very careful
not to lose it's toy sense.
This adds up.
If you really want to just dick
around with these guys,
go right ahead.
Just play around with them
and see what happens.
AUDIENCE: Why is there a
distinction for physical
objects between toys and games,
but for like video
games-- like Mindcraft it is
technically still a game but--
PROFESSOR: It kind of
has different modes.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: I guess it has
different modes, but it's more
of a toy, I think.
PROFESSOR: I would say that's
entirely marketing.
The only reason is people
haven't figured out how to
sell digital toys.
And there are games aisles in
like Best Buy and so, well,
this is a fun thing we're
going to put it
into the game section.
Everyone starts calling
it games.
And that's kind of the same
thing with the Sims.
It's that really the Sims should
be it's own genre, but
you can't sell it's own
genre that well.
[INAUDIBLE]
Was there a hand over here?
OK, so let's start
with Brenda's--
if it stops reading, so let's
just move on to Brenda's.
And she's very specific about
the kinds of puzzles that
she's talking about.
Is that these things that get in
the way of a very specific
narrative experience
that a game wants
to guide you through.
She describes them more as
roadblocks than anything else.
But, you know, things to make
the challenge higher, but
possibly so high that no
one is going to be
able to get past them.
Some of her examples are things
that come up as, sort
of, intermittent but optional
mechanics like
hacking in Bio Shop.
And sometimes there are things
that you have to solve,
especially in adventure games.
There's this, you have to
combine this object with that
object and bring it to
a specific location.
And then now you can proceed
with whatever narrative
they've got.
AUDIENCE: She had this specific
axe to grind against
puzzles having meaningful
rewards or not being
completely bought in.
So, for instance, she says you
should never have a puzzle
being required to open a door.
She said, solve a puzzle and
then get some kind of tangible
reward like loot or something.
This is after I just spent the
bus ride to New York City
playing Professor Layton's.
Which was nonstop, with on the
door, it's got a lock on it,
looks like a puzzle.
So I wasn't entirely to sure
what to make of that.
I thought that my Professor
Layton experience was fine,
and I didn't need to get fat
Layton loot from some
[INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: That's actually
something, and there's a
really good article actually
written by
Clara over in our lab.
Actually, it wasn't an article,
it was the transcript
of a talk that she gave
at Austin University--
I'll send on the link
to everyone--
about how you can integrate, and
why you should integrate,
puzzles really, really well
into the narrative.
It's like really why is there
a puzzle in your game at all
unless it's been integrated
into the narrative?
And Brenda seems to be, sort
of, providing a cautionary
tale of the--
But if you do it badly, no one
can get on with the story.
No one can enjoy the
rest of the game.
It becomes this one thing that
prevents you from proceeding?
Is there anyone who
had that moment?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: About five
minutes into Mist.
I don't know.
It had some sort of cool live
action video and stuff.
And it looked like it could
be an interesting story.
That's kind using technological
prowess of
integrating video into 3D.
And then suddenly I looked
in to the picture
and I was on an island.
And then there was nothing
happening and I had to turn
things to face each other.
And I couldn't figure it out.
AUDIENCE: When I originally
played The Legend of Zelda.
The original one.
So they don't tell you
anything pretty much.
And so the temples, you just
walk around the sun, then it's
like, OK, there's a
tree and a forest.
You're supposed to
burn [INAUDIBLE]
and there's the entrance to
this temple that you can't
proceed until you
do this thing.
And so, it's just like, how am
I supposed to know that I'm
supposed to burn this particular
tree in the middle
of this huge map?
PROFESSOR: Did you beat
any of the other--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, and they
didn't say anything.
PROFESSOR: No, I mean
the other Zeldas?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, actually
yesterday we [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I was just saying,
so the interesting thing is
most people nowadays they end
up playing, like the Ocarina
of Time, Majora's Mask, they
are moving backwards.
So they end up playing the
first Zelda after having
played these old ones.
So you sort of know that you're
expected to do these
random things to get
like across.
So I feel like it's easier
for people, but then--
AUDIENCE: But with the
original Zelda--
you know how in new ones they
have, let's say, a wall that
you can blow up.
It's discolored or something.
In this one every tree looks
exactly the same.
They use the same stripes.
AUDIENCE: If I remember
correctly, though, it's placed
such that it's in the center
of your screen, right?
So it does look a little
bit different.
AUDIENCE: No, it was
just a random tree.
It was just a whole
bunch of trees.
And so you just really have to
get, whatever a type of thing
to burn it-- a specific one--
and burn it.
AUDIENCE: I remember it was
a little suspicious.
Because I think there was a one
tile column, you kind of
navigate around just
this loop.
You just entered and--
AUDIENCE: That's suspicious.
AUDIENCE: And I'll feel very
frustrated by games that
require walk-throughs in
order to play them.
PROFESSOR: Sure, and that was
the other thing that she
suggested some game
designers do.
They put the solution
in the Prima Guide.
So that you have to buy the
Prima Guide in order to
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Does Prima have
a deal with the--
PROFESSOR: Oh, they must have.
AUDIENCE: They say "official"
on the top for a reason.
AUDIENCE: It's also ironic,
because modern Zelda games,
it's very obvious that you have
to use this or that item.
AUDIENCE: You've got a key.
Use this key to open.
AUDIENCE: Oh, you got this
item in the dungeon.
You have to use this item
to kill the boss.
That sort of thing.
It's blatant.
AUDIENCE: Well, for people who
are really, really hopeless,
there's that little fairy.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: They're usually less
useful than you think.
So one big difference between
the old Zelda games and the
new Zelda games is just this
continual refinement in their
user interface.
And it goes all the way from
little things like the notes
that you hear when you
find a new dungeon.
And exactly when, precisely,
you hear the sound of, you
know, too da loo--
at least I think that's
how it sounds.
You know, as a clue that now
you have opened a door.
That's one of those things
that, if you look at post
[INAUDIBLE]
Ocarina of Time.
I think there's a couple on
Gamasutra, exactly when that
sounds plays is a decision
that was
very carefully designed.
And it seems to me that in
digital puzzles those kinds
of, especially in some sort of
narrative structure like in
Ocarina, that's the big problem
that you have to solve.
You have to give enough clues.
You have to give enough
UI feedback.
And you have to think about your
UI so hard in a way that
is going to make it possible
so that we get all the
information [INAUDIBLE].
So, say that burning fire tree
situation, if there is nowhere
else in the world where you can
get that information, then
it's back inside puzzle.
If there is a guy in--
I can't remember Zelda I--
but there is a guy who actually
tells you that that's
the tree that you
need to burn.
But if it's not obvious,
especially for someone who
hasn't encountered that guy,
that that's where you get that
information it's still a
bad designed puzzle.
Even though now there's
a solution.
But thinking about, and some
examples will be in a lot of
tech space adventures as well
as text heavy graphical
adventures.
You have a, I can't solve this
puzzle, but what my character
says to the player about why you
can't solve the puzzle is
itself a clue.
It's like, hm, I must not
have the right item.
Maybe there's something
else I can use.
That's a huge clue.
AUDIENCE: I feel like digital
popular games have gotten
really good at integrating hint
systems in recent years.
But I can't think of any
physical puzzles that I've
come across that may just not
have quite been up to speed
with crossword puzzles.
That have that kind of not
totally revealing the solution
but giving you a gradual
hint which can help
you figure it out.
AUDIENCE: Well, mystery puzzles
kind of do that.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Describe the mystery
puzzle for folks who
don't have--
AUDIENCE: It's basically, it's
a competition run by MIT over
IAP where teams of people
compete to solve a bunch of
puzzles, like 70 puzzles, that
kind of build on each other.
So you have, say,
20 base puzzles.
And if you solve those
20 puzzles you
get 20 words as solutions.
And then those 20 words become
a new puzzle, and that's the
meta-puzzle.
And it kind of keeps them like
that for a couple layers.
But the point is the winning
team from the previous year
writes the next year's
mystery hunt.
So you get all kinds of varying
puzzles of varying
difficulties and styles.
A very well-designed puzzle
actually does that, because
you have this thing
called, flavor--
Oh, I guess I should say that
the puzzles aren't like Sudoku
or crosswords.
You literally just get something
on a screen or
something on a piece of paper,
and you have to figure out
what to do with it.
You're not given any
instructions for how to solve
it whatsoever.
And the only clues you get are
either by the title of the
puzzle, by the group of puzzles
that it's in, or by
this thing called flavor text.
Which is like, they say some
kind of random phrase that
seems to not have anything
to do with anything.
But that kind of gives you a
clue about what to do in the
thick of this puzzle.
So that's kind of like what
you were describing.
AUDIENCE: That's interesting,
because it's really
challenging when you don't have
any mechanism for giving
feedback to the person who
is working a puzzle.
In Zelda, or what have you, you
can see that they've spent
a long time dicking around.
PROFESSOR: It's kind of a
double-edged sword, in that
particular case, because you
have so many mechanisms and
now you're expected to use all
of them in a game like that.
You use sound, you have to use
contextual buttons, you have
to use the inventory.
The position of the player
matters or something.
I've seen games where the main
clues is what is the character
looking at, for instance.
And you walk around, why does my
character keep looking that
way every time something
happens?
Oh, that's because--
you know.
So, yeah, as far as of a lot of
physical stuff, I would say
that one of the reasons is
they're just starting to build
these physical games
from toys.
A lot of the importance is,
a lot of things you could
possibly do, are kind of built
into the physical object.
And if you're building a puzzle
based on what you could
do with these things as a toy,
then you're necessarily
already using the constraints of
what you can do with it as
a toy in order to create
the puzzle.
This might be a good exercise
actually, if time--
we could take a shot at this.
And just by, you know, trying
to come up with
a puzzle and see.
But instead of imagining one
in a digital space, try to
imagine one in a
physical space.
Because I suspect what you
actually get is, you get a
free language with
physical puzzles.
Because things physically have
interactions that we
[INAUDIBLE] from a
digital puzzle.
ADAM: I feel like Coral Reef
or something, and that's a
game where like the puzzle--
I mean obviously it's still a
digital game-- but the puzzles
are very much physical
puzzles.
Like you kind of have
an idea about what--
has Patrick played Portal,
of course?
Or know the idea?
I mean, you have these two
portals and you understand
what the physics is
going to be like.
So the puzzles aren't
frustrating in the sense that
it's like, oh, you realize
there's this
random statue here.
And if you pull the lever it
raises the water level or
something like that.
But it's very intuitive.
It feels like a physical puzzle
in a sense that I know
what will happen if I do this.
And I just figure out how to
put the pieces together.
And also Portal what I think it
does a really good job of,
as well as some physical
puzzles do, is having a
learning curve.
Like Tangram will have some
basic puzzles, or I'm sure the
falling thing, a lot
of them do it.
Physical puzzle things where you
like, I don't know, how to
jump over pieces or whatever,
have basic levels--
basic boards--
where they show you various
techniques.
And you only have to figure out
one technique, and it's
very obvious what
you have to do.
And later on you have to
use those techniques.
PROFESSOR: Well in Tickle Her,
this particular example does
something that multiple portals
does really well.
Is that the very first puzzle
that we did earlier only has
one solution.
And you do not get that solution
unless you understand
all the mechanics of the game.
But we tried to solve
it a whole bunch
of different times.
And it's like because we didn't
quite understand the
rules, we couldn't get it
until we understood the
mechanics of the game.
Now we can suddenly solve it.
So from puzzle number two
onwards, we can't be confident
unless you know it.
Portal, and even--
actually just about any
well-designed game-- but I
would say Portal is a fine
example-- if you've beaten a
game, you can play through the
game again with developer
commentary.
And when you show that, you
actually realize that every
single fairly intuitive physical
thing that you pick
up in the game had to
be taught to you.
And they've designed the
level very clearly.
So right in the beginning of
the game, if folks can't
remember, you're trapped
in the middle cell.
And the GlaDOS talk to you, and
a portal opens and you can
walk through it.
What do you see out of the
first portal that opens?
AUDIENCE: You see yourself
going into the other one.
PROFESSOR: You see
yourself going
through the other portal.
And it's like, they force you
to have to look at what the
basic game mechanic is going
to be before you can do
anything else that's productive
in the game.
You know, you can pick
up the radio, but--
So that was a design decision.
They could have decided
not to make it.
They could have just made you
go through that into a
different room, and the learning
opportunity would
have dissolved right there.
So if you've got a copy of
Portal, I would suggest go
back and page through
the commentaries
because they are hilarious.
And you're also rereading good
form, demonstrating in this
room, this is what we had
to do in order to
make people get it.
I'm also thinking of games like
Mario World I where you
don't get very far on
this kind of basic
game mechanics now.
But they make it really gentle
in that I don't think there
are any hits that instantly
kill you.
AUDIENCE: That's exactly what
I was thinking in Mario.
In the first Gamasutra article
we read on late-game
abstractions, we read
about a Mario world.
He's like, we expect the same
kind of actions, key the
system, all the time-jumping.
And I guess you can kind of
look at different things
there, like double-jumping.
And things like that in
a specific puzzle.
And the physical [INAUDIBLE]
also.
PROFESSOR: I mean a lot of
Mario's worlds are laid out
basically as spatial
puzzles, right?
It's like you know you have to
get there, but you don't know
exactly how you're going to use
all of the mechanics that
you've got.
AUDIENCE: In Mario 64, I think
their way of solving the
impasse problem of not locking
up all the content in the game
because of the one puzzle you
can't get, they're giving you
so much to do that even if they
don't really tell you--
even if a good 30%, 40% are
going to remain mysterious to
you, you're not really going
to figure them out--
there's so much [INAUDIBLE]
between, you never walked off
with a significant amount
of content.
PROFESSOR: So if you've got a
hub-like structure you can do
any one of five different things
at any given time.
Plus you have some secondary
solutions, like you can always
go back to a world that you've
been to before and try to
collect all the stars,
for instance.
I think that's kind of what
Brenda was kind of indicating.
You don't necessarily want, if
you're putting puzzles in your
game, she was advocating for--
Brenda and Ian were
advocating for--
something that wouldn't
necessarily progress
on to the next one.
But I think that's not
a requirement.
I think that's a, if you want to
make your life easier, this
is what you do.
If you decide that you're up to
the task, you can achieve
some really amazing effects
by having your puzzles
narratively incorporate it.
Has anyone heard of the game
called Eternal Darkness?
It's a sort of Lovecraftian
horror game on the GameCube.
I'll sort of describe it, but
basically the whole basic idea
is that you have four gods all
warring against each other.
Three of them hate one of them,
but then those three
also hate each other.
And most of the puzzles are
just sort of understanding
that there is this
mystical object.
One god defeats another god
defeats another god in a rock,
paper, scissors circle.
And all of them hate this
one other [INAUDIBLE].
So early on in the game there
is actually a puzzle, there
are actually a number of
different puzzles, where you
see the symbols of these gods.
And you have to kind
of rearrange them
in the correct order.
And the rest of the game is all
going to be variations of
understanding what these
gods do to each other.
So those are all puzzles
that inform you of
how the world works.
And that kind of works
in two ways.
One, information that you've
already gathered about the
world-- about how this
world works--
gives you clues on how
to beat the puzzles.
Beating the puzzles, finding the
solutions for the clues,
gives you information about
how the world works.
And that's kind of like the
holy grail for a puzzle
designer in a digital game, is
that you're going to design a
puzzle that's going to reinforce
how the world works.
There's a chap--
who gave a talk, and I believe
his name is Jeff Howard.
He came to Camp [INAUDIBLE]
and gave a talk last year.
And he makes this case that
games, and the logic that you
present in games, do basically
the equivalent of what magic
systems actually do
in the real world.
What people like cultists or
astrologers do is they
basically give you logics
that explain how the
world is going to work.
And while that may not
necessarily be obvious, but if
it is viewed as a whole
knowledge you'll be able to
understand how it's [INAUDIBLE]
in you.
But more importantly you'd be
able to do things in the world
that allow you to accomplish
things that you wouldn't
otherwise do.
Learning a game is very much
like that, it's like I don't
know how this world works but
if I understood these
particular rules I
could be able to
accomplish greater things.
And puzzles can be one
of those things where
it becomes a test.
And it becomes a test of, just
exactly how well do you
understand this?
Even if it is like in a combat
game like Quake or God of War
or something.
I can understand how the combat
system basically works
if I just keep mashing the
x button or something.
Or just shoot everything
with rockets.
But if I really, really
understand the combat system,
I might be able to hit something
that I wouldn't
necessarily be able to hit.
I might be able to take down a
horde of enemies instead of
hitting them down
one at a time.
I might be able to
beat a boss.
And actually a lot of boss
battles in digital games are
actually puzzles.
There's not, how well do you
generally react, it's can you
figure out the pattern.
But that pattern doesn't mean
anything unless [INAUDIBLE]
how all your other combat
skills work.
So a boss battle in Zelda only
makes sense if you figured out
how that one item that you
picked up in that dungeon
works really, really well.
OK, it shoots fire.
That means that not only does it
hurt them from distance, it
also lights some of the
things on fire.
And that's what I'll tell the
boss, basically, is combining
this leaders ability
to hook up.
Like everything else that
you've done before
into taking it out.
That's why boss battles, that
always kind of puzzled me.
AUDIENCE: One thing I wanted
to say, before I get going,
you were asking about hints
and a physical puzzle.
The one thing that jumped to my
mind was a couple years ago
the weekly Day--
I don't know if anyone
reads it, it's like
a free Boston newspaper.
And they always have
crossword puzzles.
For the longest time they were
thematic, and so you would
have a guest crossword.
The first one I ever
did was Hulk Hogan.
So all of the hints in the
crossword puzzles are related
to Hulk Hogan.
So it's a question of, not what
does this mean to me but
what would it mean
to Hulk Hogan?
And they don't do it anymore,
which is really depressing,
because every week it was
something different and it was
like a built-in hand
write as you went.
You didn't just pick them out
literally, you have to kind of
contextualize it.
PROFESSOR: You can think about
all the things that come with
the puzzle, that potential
hook, [INAUDIBLE].
Like a title, like a data
text-- as you were
describing-- the fact that you
get in puzzle and mystery
crimes, they may be
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] and they may
be disillusioned but it lies
on a different puzzle.
Not the one I'm currently
looking at right now, because
that's how [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Metal Gear Solid has a really,
really bizarre one where--
AUDIENCE: Look in
the back case.
PROFESSOR: Where they tell you,
oh, there's a specific
radio frequency that you need.
It's written in the
back of box.
And it's like, the
back of the box?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
Anti-piracy.
PROFESSOR: Yes, but it's
still a puzzle.
And I was like, I know
how to solve that.
I mean, it was pretty obvious,
because maybe it's just me,
because it about half an hour
to figure that one out.
It took me some effort.
AUDIENCE: I mean Metal
Gear Solid a lot of
meta-puzzles like that.
Like when you fought Psycho
Mantis for the first time.
Well, so the scene you had to do
is you went to unplug your
controller and plug it into
the second port because he
would read your movements.
And it was this cool, physical
layer of it where you're
playing the game.
Then you realize I have to
interact with the physical
world so that he can't
see what I'm doing.
PROFESSOR: But that one
[? cannot do, ?]
because in that particular
example that one gave you a
very big clue because right at
the beginning of that match
that boss tells you to put your
control on the ground.
And he says, I'm going
to control this
controller with my mind.
And actually, just
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: That's only if
you have dualtech.
So, because on PlayStation,
if you didn't he just
ignored that part.
And you didn't get
that clue at all.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, and
that's a problem.
But it's still very cool.
AUDIENCE: There were other
clues, like you would talk
about how you had been playing
certain games by reading saves
on your [INAUDIBLE].
At least not in Castlevania.
I just remember being like--
[INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So basically it's
giving you a clue that there's
got to be something better
about the way that you're
currently playing.
The funny thing about the radio
channel is that one
really did not give you
any clue that there
was something better.
It just told you about
the back of the box.
It was like, it didn't tell you
the back of the video game
case, right.
It's not going to be
that specific.
AUDIENCE: It said CD
case, specifically.
I was really confused, because I
think mine came in a slip of
paper or something.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, if you buy
it used or something.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, so it's
anti-used game
protection, as well.
But yeah, mine was I think I
actually said on the back of
the CD case, but I was playing
like a [INAUDIBLE] or
something and that came
in the DVD case.
So I didn't make a connection.
But if you look at the back of
it, you see what the radio
frequency is in the
screenshot.
One of the eight screenshots
that they show to demonstrate
this is what the game is all
about, there's the number and
it's just right in there.
And then key it in.
AUDIENCE: Has anyone played any
of those breakout games?
Where it's lock you in a
room and you have to--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you find the
thing, you find a slip of
paper and escape [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So, actually
who doesn't know
what these are about?
Escape the room.
OK, so escape the room--
actually, could we bring up
something on your computer?
AUDIENCE: I have to go
grab the video thing.
PROFESSOR: Oh, the
video cable.
AUDIENCE: It's back there
in my office.
PROFESSOR: Oh, OK cool.
Call [? Becky ?] to send it.
Escape the room games are
typically flash games.
And they're kind of like
adventure games because
there's usually only one room,
although sometimes you have
multiple rooms.
It's a much smaller world
in most adventure games.
But the basic idea
is the same.
You pick up objects, you use
objects in a room, and you try
to make things happen.
You know, if you haven't made
anything, you are not
progressing in the game.
If you made something happen,
you are almost always making
forward progress in the game.
And there is, actually, a guide
for playing adventure
games written by Roberta
Williams, who did the Original
King's Quest series.
And her guide is like, pick-up
everything, go everywhere, use
everything on everything.
That's actually what escape
the room really is.
But there's a little bit more to
escape the room games, but
there's just not that many
things that you can explore.
That's the idea is that you're
stuck in a room.
And basically it comes down
to just use everything on
everything until you figure
out what comes up.
Rarely is it logical, often
pretty entertaining, because
they're animation heavy.
So every time you do something
right, you
get some crazy animation.
I put the fish into
the mail slot and
out appears an octopus.
It's fun to watch.
For us, the kind of
comparatively opposite of
those are the Grow games.
And they're a series of
games called Grow.
I think the guy who does them
is called Eyezmaze.
And the whole basic idea is that
imagine that you have a
flower pot.
And every time you
add something to
it something happens.
But the order in which you are
adding things to it makes
different things happen.
And there are solutions,
basically, in making the
optimal number of things happen
if you do it right.
So what you can do is not
a mystery at all.
You have these six things that
I could add to my pot.
And I know those are the only
six things I could add.
The question is what
order do I do them?
And doing them in different
orders give
you different results.
And I feel that these two genres
are kind of linked, but
they're playing off very
different things.
One of them is, I don't know
what I'm going to do.
But I know that whatever I do
has got to leave this space.
And the other one is very much,
I know exactly what I
can possibly do, I just don't
know what order to do them in.
So a couple of puzzles
that you see online.
These are fairly encapsulated
things.
One game is one series
of puzzles.
There's not like a
professor-made encyclopedia
puzzle kind of thing.
What time is it?
OK, I think I'm actually going
to grab a few more puzzles and
bring them in.
But I do actually want to try
to see whether we can put
together a list of the kinds
of puzzles that we haven't
talked about today.
These could be physical puzzles,
these could be
puzzles that you've seen in
a book by their genre.
Logic puzzles, you know, of a
certain kind that you either
really, really like or you
really, really loathe.
And just break up
in groups of--
three, six, nine, Heather
[INAUDIBLE], ten, eleven,
twelve, seventeen people.
Seventeen people?
That doesn't divide at all.
OK, two or three.
Groups of two or three
and just like--
AUDIENCE: Jason should
be back.
PROFESSOR: OK, all right,
then groups of three.
How about we--
just like--
you know, just a couple of
puzzles that we haven't
discussed and a description
about what they're like.
And we'll quickly run through
the class to sort of give
everyone an idea of what--
As a toy, playing with a Rubik's
Cube is more fun than
the algorithm to solve it.
That's not fun at all,
in my opinion.
AUDIENCE: It's fascinating,
you can also solve it.
But it's [INAUDIBLE],
very tempting when
you look at it also.
AUDIENCE: So, one of the things
you were talking about
was interactive fiction.
Text adventures.
And how sometimes they could
be considered just like if
you're playing a regular
adventure game but just with
text instead.
And so the puzzle could be how
you interact with the world,
or it could be trying to figure
out what actions are
available to the user.
Like sometimes not all
actions are there.
But also in some games the
nature of text gives you
different ways to
have a puzzle.
Like in Lost Pig, because
you're playing an orc he
doesn't know English
very well.
Or doesn't have full control of
language, so you're trying
to decipher his words
to figure out what
he's actually seeing.
PROFESSOR: Do you have an
example you can do?
To give with that to
make it clearer?
Because I haven't played it.
AUDIENCE: In that game, there
is one part where he's
describing a box and
it has a slot.
And you put something in it
and then it gives you
something out.
But the way he's describing it,
you don't really know what
he's describing until you
realize he's talking about a
vending machine.
He describes it as a tall
box with a slot in it.
And another example we were
talking about was the game
Aisle, which is you're this
guy in a grocery store.
And it gives you this
big prologue.
And you have one action
that you can do.
So after you type in your one
action, it tells you what
happens and gives
you an epilogue.
And then the game starts over.
But then using the information
from that epilogue, you have a
different choice of actions
that you can take and
different key words to use.
And so by playing it over and
over you're uncovering more of
the story until you
get somewhere.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Aisle.
A-I-S-L-E.
AUDIENCE: We also thought about
puzzles that were games
put into a very contrived
scenario.
Like bridge puzzles, or chess
puzzles, or back when the
Duelist magazine still existed
they had Magic
the Gathering puzzles.
PROFESSOR: So like
chess puzzles are
like, here's this board.
What was the move that
led to this board.
AUDIENCE: Or like, black
to win in three moves.
Something like that.
PROFESSOR: So that's like, you
are now placing additional
constraints on the game.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, exactly.
It already puts you in a
situation like, pretend you're
in this game.
Now, we promise you there's a
way you can automatically win,
you have to find it.
PROFESSOR: There's a number of
computer games like ChuChu
Rocket and everything
where it does like
completely separate modes.
ChuChu Rocket is a frenetic
both player--
AUDIENCE: It's a mice-herding
game.
You have to get them
into rocket ships,
so they go in space.
It was for the Dreamcast.
It's so good.
The idea's really simple.
A bunch of mice wander around
the streets, and each player
gets to place three arrows.
And when the mice run
under the arrow
they follow the arrow.
So you want to get all your mice
on your ship, and want to
get the cats on the other ship
so that they eat their mice.
PROFESSOR: In puzzle-mode, you
have three arrows in these
particular directions.
But the way you place them, you
have as much time as you
want, but there's only
one right answer.
And that immediately shows you
the difference between a game
and puzzle.
Right there.
Even though they are all
in the same package.
AUDIENCE: So, first off I don't
like jigsaw puzzles, but
Michelle loves them.
And then we also talked
about whodunit's.
And I really love whodunit's
because you have to pay
attention to the detail
in the stories.
Like the one thing that--
I guess the example that we
were talking about is, if
there's a mailman and it happens
to be on a Sunday, he
probably committed the crime.
Because they don't have
mail on Sundays.
And it's like small
details like that.
PROFESSOR: Are you talking about
mystery books or just
like little paragraphs?
AUDIENCE: Well, it's usually
like a story.
And they say, oh, here's the
scenario, here's the
background story, who
is the murderer?
PROFESSOR: They compare it
though, [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: People have parties
like that, like full-on
whodunit parties.
AUDIENCE: That's very true.
I didn't see who was talking
for a second.
Who's talking?
AUDIENCE: Another puzzle we
came up with, was the ones
that you did in elementary
school with like the big grid.
And you would have someone's
name, and maybe their favorite
food, that you would give them
a bunch of clues and you have
to match them.
Yes, with something like the
checks and the xs and stuff.
PROFESSOR: So, that's just
generally called logic
puzzles, I believe.
It's just you are given the
incomplete set of information
but enough constraints that you
can figure out the rest of
the information.
And really the way to solve it
is just write everybody's
name, all the characters that
you're given in the prose.
Write down all the characters
on one column.
Write down all the things you're
trying to figure out,
like who's wearing what colored
shirt, for instance,
so just write out all the colors
on the other column.
And just by the process of
elimination, just figuring
out, usually the answers
are mutually exclusive.
So if somebody is wearing a red
shirt, can not be wearing
a green shirt.
AUDIENCE: So part of the much
harder ones are every fourth
statement is false.
Like you don't know if one
statement is definitely false.
And I've seen one where
every statement is
false except for one.
And I can bring in my book and
there's like [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: The worst version
of it is figuring out how
puzzles see people
in the world.
AUDIENCE: They wouldn't fix it
before because he pushed it
out last week.
PROFESSOR: You guys want
to throw in any?
AUDIENCE: Sure, we started by
trying to think of all the
puzzles that we really
dislike.
And we came up with
a couple here.
The sliding square puzzles, you
know where you have like--
Basically just a variation on
a jigsaw puzzle where the
rules are more constrained.
I don't like jigsaw
puzzles either.
So we're like-minded there.
And then John had a couple.
I guess there's a Light's
Out puzzle.
Inside the image you touch
certain areas and [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So you've got like
a grid of buttons and every
button you push will invert all
those neighboring buttons.
Like implanting the top button,
left and right, will--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: And then I guess
I already described the
concentric circle thing.
Yeah, their puzzles are similar
that we're taking an
action on one item
in the scene.
These are incredibly difficult,
the concentric
circle ones, will have
an effect on other
things in the system.
And typically these are used in
games where there will be a
center podium with a pathway
leading off.
On one side of the podium,
then there will be a
concentric circle around the
concentric ring with a pathway
off of that ring and
another interval.
Then more and more circles to
each side and you get to
rotate individual circles and
that will rotate the other
circles different ways.
And you need to create
a pathway.
AUDIENCE: Every time I
rotate one, something
else is going to rotate.
AUDIENCE: Then it's always
going right before you're
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I guess three of those
are examples of games
where you have to take action
on an environment, but your
action has direct effects
throughout the environment.
And it's just really annoying
figuring out
how to optimize that.
PROFESSOR: But they are
predictable effects.
It's like every time I rotate
this one left, that one's
going to rotate right.
AUDIENCE: I think it's kind of
funny how the context has a
lot to do with whether these
puzzles are annoying or not.
Because I do enjoy Professor
Layton quite a bit.
And it's the most, through an
arbitrary character in order
to justifying that you're
trying [INAUDIBLE].
It's just fun.
Your intention on even playing
the game is that you're going
to be solving puzzles.
Not as [INAUDIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Also, the way that is
presented makes it funny in
that as well, right.
So the mafia goons come up to
you and say, we're going to
stop you from coming in here
unless you solve this puzzle.
Shouldn't you just shoot me?
It would solve all
your problems.
No, no, solve this puzzle.
PROFESSOR: It's like they're
making fun of themselves even.
All right, cool.
AUDIENCE: I'm not sure if we
really commented on what we
liked or didn't like.
But some things that we came
up with that haven't been
brought up yet are cryptics,
which are kind of a
combination between crosswords
and riddles, riddles,
combinatory games as
a puzzle apparatus.
Logic puzzles in general, not
just like typical logic
puzzles like that.
You can have state machines,
or Sudoku, or any type of
numerical puzzle.
We also want to differentiate
that a lot of those games, or
some of those games,
are spatially
oriented and some aren't.
Which we thought was an
important aspect, but not
necessarily definitive of a
completely different genre.
PROFESSOR: I'm not sure I've
seen a state machine puzzle,
actually, outside of a computer
science textbook.
AUDIENCE: I know some.
PROFESSOR: I'll never ask you.
I expect it's going to
be more involved than
we have time for.
By combinatory puzzles
you mean stuff like--
AUDIENCE: Combinatory games.
All the games that fall under
combinatory game theory.
AUDIENCE: Like Nim's.
[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: These are sort of
exploration, so games where
you have to see everything
around you to know what is
available for use.
On the [INAUDIBLE]
so in the book they
talked about
actually Zelda, and just--
So a situation in a game that
I didn't like is, you're
playing a game and something
happens you don't step too
fast or something.
And because of that,
you get too inert.
You're in a spot where you don't
have the tools necessary
to beat the enemy right
in front of you.
But you also are trapped
and can't go back.
It happened to me one time.
It was the Star Wars: Knights
of the Old Republic.
There's an enemy, you couldn't
go forward, and there was a
cliff so you couldn't
get back up.
And so, since I couldn't do
anything I was forced to
completely go back
to the last save.
PROFESSOR: But is that a puzzle,
or is that just a bug?
AUDIENCE: I mean, it's time
worth expiration and
it's an item use.
So you need to get an
item to go ahead.
If you have this item, then
the enemy that you--
I think it was like a Rancor
or something--
you could beat the Rancor or at
least put it to sleep and
walk by it.
But without it, you had
to try and beat it or
it would kill you.
PROFESSOR: OK, so it was a
item that would have made
combat easier, basically.
But they kind of made it
this one way with--
yeah.
So you see a lot of puzzle games
where they have easy
reset, right.
And it's like you can stop
trying to solve it and you
really screw up something along
the way You hit reset
and go right back to
the beginning.
Nice that the Republic
has no easy reset.
You live with the consequences,
I guess that's
what they were trying
to go for.
AUDIENCE: All right,
so we've also had a
loathing sliding puzzles--
AUDIENCE: Either with numbers or
pictures, both of them are
equally annoying.
But, on the other hand,
Alec loves Rush Hour.
AUDIENCE: It's the traffic red
light game where you have to
fly cars out of the way
to form a path.
AUDIENCE: In Professor Layton
there are an awful lot of
sliding puzzles that have
differently shaped pieces, or
oddly shaped pieces.
Which is slightly more
interesting, or less annoying
than regular sliding puzzles
but it's still incredibly
frustrating.
AUDIENCE: Well, I think the
difference there is that when
you have differently
sized pieces--
When you're doing just like a
sliding puzzle where you're
trying to recreate an image
there's definite patterns that
you keep using over and over
again, because you're just
like a rotating spaces.
So it's not actually
interesting.
Whereas Rush Hour you actually
have to think
about things fit together.
So one other puzzle type that
we haven't really mentioned,
that I actually really enjoy,
is pictographic puzzles.
Where it relies on sort of your
association with visual
images and wordplay and stuff.
Like, for example, you'll have
a puzzle that's just an image
of an eyeball, a bumblebee,
and a screen shot of Judi
Dench in a James Bond movie.
And the idea is it's IBM.
So I love puzzles like that.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so stuff like
that where it relies on
someone, like a human being,
actually associating
information with something
visual.
Rather than it being just a
straight modern puzzle where
you have this information and
you use this to derive the
rest of the information.
PROFESSOR: There's R-E-B-U-S,
and of course those are very
language focused even though
they're image-based.
AUDIENCE: What one has the two
lines and then [INAUDIBLE] in
the middle?
AUDIENCE: Well, things
like that, yeah.
PROFESSOR: You had Rebus where
you are trying to basically
reconstruct a sentence.
And then I forget what's the
classification of puzzles
where you're given a certain
lead of images and you're
trying to write enough.
But if I wrote it in--
this is not a good puzzle but
just to give an example-- if I
put [INAUDIBLE].
I think there is a specific word
for these kind of things.
But the whole idea is you're
trying to reconstruct these
sayings or these [INAUDIBLE]
from individual theories.
So I mean, these are usually
spatial to begin with.
I think there was a whole
game show in the '80s
that was just all--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Australia had
a show called Catch
Phrase which was--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I think Catch
Phrase was the show.
AUDIENCE: So we wrote a B-list
of different types of puzzles,
so let's just run
through them.
All right, we've got
lots of different
sliding puzzle variants.
We've got hidden object finding,
the variance on
Where's Waldo and then it's
kind of [INAUDIBLE].
We have riddles, various kinds
of logic puzzles, particularly
two of which we've
mentioned before.
Several people, witnesses,
give statements.
One of them is a liar,
which one's the liar.
So find the hidden
sinister person.
And then there's the figment
property x is next to figment
property y, what order
are they sitting in?
That kind of puzzle.
There's a million of them
in Professor Layton.
There's these kinds
of unraveling, or
reverse-engineering
type, puzzles.
Where some system has been
permuted and you have to
restore it to its
original state.
Which Rubik's Cube is like the
canonical example, I guess.
But then there's a bunch of
other different good ones.
PROFESSOR: I mean that chess
games is kind of in that
category too.
AUDIENCE: There's tile rotation
and swapping puzzles.
One example of this is Bioshock
hacking, but then
there are 1 million other
variations on exchanging tiles
or swapping them around
or this kind of thing.
Lots of different kinds
of math puzzles.
This particular word
transformation puzzle type
that I used to see all the time
when I was a kid, where
by changing one letter or word
per step, you had to transform
one word into another.
Mazes, jigsaw puzzles, code
breaking nobody mentioned yet.
And then also, these kind of
full experiment type puzzles.
I don't know how else
you categorize them.
PROFESSOR: Give us an example.
AUDIENCE: All right, so I'm
trying to remember how this
works but I think it is--
this one popped up on Day(9)s
podcast the other day.
I only give it because otherwise
if I get it wrong
then people will go oh my God,
and try and puzzle it out.
So it has to do with the piece
of string and burning.
AUDIENCE: Oh, the 13 minutes?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, do you remember
exactly how it goes?
AUDIENCE: OK, you have
two pieces of string.
You know that the whole string
takes an hour to burn but it's
not linear.
You have an infinite supply of
matches, how can you measure
15 minutes with this string?
AUDIENCE: One of those lateral
thinking puzzles.
AUDIENCE: I would classify
this under riddles, but--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Let them go, but
they both take an hour--
[INAUDIBLE]
but they both take an hour
to burn, non-linearly.
AUDIENCE: Couldn't you just be
lighting matches the entire
time, and see how many matches
you can burn an hour.
After that, just take four
to that number--
AUDIENCE: Then how are
you going to measure
that original hour?
[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: But you know that
the thing takes an hour to
burn, yeah?
AUDIENCE: The whole thing.
PROFESSOR: It will take slightly
longer than the
amount of time it takes
to get to class.
We close by then.
It would be nice to give
people time to
think about it too.
So answer on Wednesday.