All right, you did well on the
exam.
Class average was sixty-two.
I always aim for sixty-five,
so I was very happy.
Eleven students scored a
hundred.
I believe that my exam review
was extremely fair.
According to some instructors,
perhaps even too close for
comfort.
I did a problem with parallel
resistors and a battery.
I applied Gauss's Law for
cylindrical symmetry.
I spent quite a bit of time
discussing  where charge
occurs and where charge  can not
be located on conductors  and I
hit the idea of capacitors and
dielectrics also quite hard.
I prefer not to think about a
rigid division between pass and
fail, but I'd rather tell you
that all of you who scored less
than forty-seven,
in my book, are sort of in the
danger zone.
Now, that doesn't mean that
you're going to fail the course,
nor does it mean that you will
pass the course if you scored
seventy.
But those people are in the
danger zone.
I think you should talk to your
instructor, and I would advise
those people also to make
frequent use  of our tutors.
Two exams to go,
plus the final.
Today I'm going to uncover a
whole new world for you  and you
will see how eight oh two comes
in there in a very natural way.
The Lawrence force F is the
charge  times the cross product
of the velocity of that charge
and the B field that the charge
experiences.
If I have here  a positive
charge plus Q  and it has a
velocity V in this direction,
and the magnetic fields would
be uniform and coming out of the
blackboards, there's going to be
a force on this charge according
to this relationship  and the
force
is then  like so.
Perpendicular to V,
perpendicular to B.
In this case  the charged
particle is going to go around
in a circle .
The Lawrence force can not
change the speed,
can not change the kinetic
energy, because the force is
always perpendicular to the
velocity but it can change the
direction of the velocity.
And so, what you're going to
see is
that the charged particle will
go around into a perfect circle
if  the magnetic field is
constant throughout.
And the radius of this circle
can very easily be calculated
using some of our knowledge of
eight oh two.
The force is QVB  because I
chose B also perpendicular to V,
and so there is no sign of the
angle between them.
This one, and this now has to
be the
centripetal force that we
encountered in eight oh one,
which is MV squared divided by
R, M now being the mass of this
particle.
And so you'll find now that R
equals MV divided by QB.
And this, by the way,
I want to remind you,
is the momentum of that
particle.
If you look at this equation,
it's sort of pleasing.
If the
charge is high then the
Lawrence force is high so the
radius is small.
If the magnetic field is high
then the Lawrence force is high
so the radius is small.
If the mass of the particle is
high, there is a lot of inertia
and so it is very difficult to
make it go around,
so to speak,
so a very high mass,
you expect a very high radius.
And so that looks all
intuitively quite pleasing.
Let's do a numerical example.
I take a proton,
P stands for proton,
and I take a one MEV proton.
It's the same I took during my
test review.
One MEV means that the kinetic
energy is one MEV is the charge
times the potential difference
over which this proton was
accelerated, in this case,
delta V would be one million
volts.
And this now equals one-half
times
the mass of that proton times
the velocity squared.
In this case,
if I have the one MEV,
so it is a million volts,
you will find that this is one
point six times ten to the minus
thirteen joules.
I gave you there the charge of
the proton, you multiplied it by
a million, and this is the
energy.
And so now you can calculate
the velocity because you know
the mass of the proton.
I gave
you that too,
there.
And so you will find exactly
what you found during my test
review, one point four times ten
to the seventh meters per
second, which is five percent of
the speed of light,
comfortably low so we don't
have to make any relativistic
corrections.
If this proton now enters a
magnetic field B,
which is one Tesla,
then  by using the equation I
have up there,
you know the mass of the
proton,
we just calculated the
velocity.
You know the charge of the
proton and you know the B field.
You will find that R is oh
point one five meters,
which is fifteen centimeters,
just a numerical example.
It is more common,
or at least often done,
to eliminate out of that
equation there the velocity and
replace it by the potential
difference,
capital V, over which we
accelerate these particles.
And so, what you can do,
you can replace this V by using
the equation I have there,
the one half MV squared,
so we have that one-half MV
squared equals Q times delta V,
but I will write for that just
a capital V, and I substitute
this V now in here,
and so I now longer see the
velocity
but I now see this potential
difference.
In the case of that proton,
this V would be a million and
you will find then that R is
then the square root of two M
times that capital V divided by
Q B squared.
And so the two equations are of
course the same physics,
but it's different
representation.
If you put in for V now ten to
the sixth mass of the proton,
charge of the proton,
and one Tesla field,
of course you find exactly the
same point one five meters.
Now this is all nice and dandy,
but this works as long as the
speed is much smaller than the
speed of light.
If that's no longer the case,
then we have to apply special
relativity and that is not part
of this course but I would like
to briefly touch upon that
today.
I can show you how things go
sour because suppose we have a
five hundred kilo electric volt
electron.
So that means that in this
equation here,
the V is five hundred thousand,
the Q is the charge of the
electron, M is now the mass of
the electron,
and if I apply that equation I
find that V is four point two
times ten to the eighth meters
per second and that is larger
than the speed of light,
so that's clearly not possible.
The actual speed,
if you make relativistic
corrections, is two point six
times ten to the eighth meters
per second.
And although I don't expect you
to be able to make those
relativistic corrections,
I will make them today and you
will
see why I have to,
and I want to show you that in
fact this is not all that
difficult even though I will not
hold you responsible for these
equations.
So what I have here is now
kinetic energy,
is again QV,
that's not changing,
but is no longer one-half MV
squared but it is gamma minus
one times MC squared,
and gamma is defined there --
it's called the Lorenz Factor,
and so if you know now for the
electron that capital V is five
hundred thousand,
you can calculate what gamma is
from the first equation and then
you go to the second equation
and you find what the speed is,
and you will see then that you
never find a speed larger than
the speed of light.
And so we now have to make the
correction also for the radii
and those corrections become
again relatively easy.
This now requires a factor
gamma and you see that on the
upper blackboard there,
and this too now has to be
replaced by this gamma plus one
and then everything is OK.
So I don't expect you to know
this, but I don't want you to
think that all these
relativistic corrections come
out of the blue,
nor do I want you think that it
is very difficult.
It really isn't.
The equations are extremely
straightforward.
So I want to show you now some
of the results that we just
discussed.
The one MEV proton and the five
hundred KEV electron,
this is on the Web.
You can click on Lecture
Supplements and you can make
yourself a hard copy.
So here you see the kinetic
energy, one MEV proton.
Notice the speed that we
calculated there is
non-relativistic,
gamma is very close to one.
You don't have to make a
correction.
And in a one Tesla field you
get a radius of fifteen
centimeters, which we just
calculated.
If you go to a fifty MEV
proton, it's sort of in the
borderline between relativistic
and non-relativistic.
It's still non-relativistic
enough, and if it is
non-relativistic you can clearly
see here that the radius goes
with the square root of capital
V.
And for fifty MEV,
capital V is fifty million,
and for one MEV,
capital V is one million.
And since it goes with the
square root of V,
you expect roughly the radius
to be the square root of fifty
times larger which is seven,
and indeed, you see that.
So you see, from fifteen
centimeters the radius goes to
about one meter.
Um, here is our five hundred
KEV electron,
and notice that I did the
calculation correctly.
This is relativistically
corrected now.
You get your two point six
times ten to the eighth meters
per second  by applying the
formalism that you see there.
I will leave this here
throughout this lecture,
because I will return to this
several times.
I want to show you a  a cute
demonstration.
I have an, er,
electron gun here  and the
electron gun  comes like
so.
This is the velocity of the
electrons.
I put a minus sign there to
remind you that they are
electrons.
If electrons go in this
direction, the current goes in
that direction.
And so if now I have a magnetic
field which, let's assume the
magnetic field is in the
blackboard.
This is B.
Then I cross B is the direction
of the force.
I is in this direction,
B is in the blackboard.
So if I'm not mistaken,
I think the force is in this
direction and so you will see
that it starts to bend in this
direction.
If you change the direction of
the magnetic field,
the magnetic field is coming
out of the blackboard,
then the electron will go in
this direction,
and I can show you that here.
It is not too different from
the distortion experiment I did
when I had the  television
program there and I had the
strong magnet
and we distorted the image,
but this of course is a little
bit more controlled.
So, we're going to see the
image there and we want to make
it quite dark in the room.
Mmm.
And turn on the  electron gun.
So you see, the electron gun it
strikes a fluorescent screen and
that's how you can see it,
and I have here a bar magnet
and if I hold the bar magnet
behind it then I can create more
or less situations like this.
I can flip over the magnet and
then the direction of bending
should change,
so here I come with the magnet,
and you see,
curve up the electrons.
I turn the magnet over and I
come in again and they curve
down.
Very straightforward,
very simple.
OK.
There is a fantastic way in
physics that we can separate
isotopes from one and the same
element.
If we, for instance,
take uranium,
now uranium,
when you find it,
is for ninety-nine point three
percent uranium two
thirty-eight.
That means it had ninety-two
protons, otherwise it wouldn't
be uranium,
and it has hundred and
forty-six neutrons,
ninety-nine point three
percent.
Point seven percent is uranium
two thirty-five.
Again, ninety-two protons,
otherwise it wouldn't be
uranium, but only a hundred and
forty-three neutrons,
and that you'll find in nature
for oh point seven percent.
So you go to a chemist and you
give a chemist a little bit of
uranium and you say would you
please separate these two
isotopes for me,
and he of course would laugh at
you and he would say go fly a
kite because the chemical
properties are exactly the same
for the two because uranium is
uranium.
Neutral uranium here has
ninety-two electrons and neutral
uranium here has ninety-two
electrons, so there's no way
that they could separate those.
And I will show you now how
they can be separated with what
we call a mass spectrometer.
You heat the uranium so that it
ionizes.
Let's assume it's ionized once
so it
loses one electron,
so it's positively charged with
one unit charge,
one of those charges that you
see here.
And we now accelerate it over
certain potential difference so
these uranium atoms,
two thirty-five and the two
thirty-eight get a certain speed
and they come in here with this
speed V, so they're positively
charged and let's assume that we
have a magnetic
field that is uniform and that
is in this direction,
comes out of the blackboard.
So what will happen is that
these  charged particles which
are positively charged now,
one unit charge,
are going to go around a circle
and hit here.
It is the radius.
But if you look here at these
equations  so you will see that
the radius is proportional with
the square root of the mass of
the particle and the mass of two
thirty-eight is one point two
percent larger than the mass of
two thirty-five.
And so with one point two
percent larger,
since we have the square root
there, we see here the square
root, we accelerate them over
the same potential difference,
so this one doesn't change.
This is the only thing that
changes.
So then you expect an oh point
six percent change in radius and
so the
two thirty-eight will end up
here.
I exaggerate that very highly.
And the two thirty-five will
end up here.
The two thirty-eight has a
larger radius because it has a
larger mass, and you see that
here.
There's no change in B,
there's no change in Q,
and there's no change in
capital V.
We accelerate them over the
same potential difference.
And so if the radius,
for instance,
were one meter of this mass
spectrometer then the difference
here -- remember this is two R
-- the difference would come out
to be
about one point two
centimeters, and so you have a
collector here where you collect
your two thirty-eight nuclei
atoms and here you collect your
two thirty-five and that is the
idea behind a mass spectrometer.
Why did I choose this
particular example?
Well, this example changed our
world and it made history.
Uranium two thirty-five was
needed by the Americans to build
an atomic bomb to end the Second
World War.
This is- this was done under
the famous Manhattan Project.
And Ernest Lawrence of Berkeley
built mass spectrometers  which
were able to separate uranium
two thirty-five from two
thirty-eight.
In the beginning,
it went very slowly,
about one hundred micrograms
per day.
But a few kilograms was
required for an atomic bomb.
They finally managed to get up
to one gram per day  and in
combination with other
separation
techniques such as the gas
diffusion techniques which I
will not discuss here now  they
managed to get a few kilograms
and they dropped a bomb on
Hiroshima on August sixth
nineteen forty-five and three
days later a bomb was dropped on
Nagasaki.
The Japanese surrendered and it
was the end of World War Two.
It's a good thing that there
are many peaceful applications
nowadays of mass spectrometers,
particularly in the medical
area.
People sometimes require
radiation and they need
radiation from a particular
radioactive isotopes,
but you don't want the other
isotopes from the same element
and so you separate them then
with a mass spectrometer.
It's a whole industry,
very important industry.
And I would like to address
the issue how you accelerate
protons to extremely high
speeds, almost approaching the
speed of light.
And that is also something for
which Ernest Lawrence is
credited.
In the early days it was done
in a cyclotron,
which I will describe to you
now.
The cyclotron consists of a
chamber which is called a D.
This is one D and here's
another D.
These are conducting chambers.
If you look from the side it
would look like so.
This is the left chamber and
this is the right chamber and
all of this is in vacuum and
let's assume that we have a
magnetic field coming out of the
board like so.
Let's revisit our one MEV
proton.
Suppose I release in this
chamber
here a one MEV proton and I
know the speed with which it
comes out, because the one MEV
proton had a speed -- Oh,
you still see it there,
one point four times ten to the
seven meters per second.
We also know that in a one
Tesla field, let's make this one
Tesla, that the radius is going
to be fifteen centimeters.
You see it up there.
So what is this proton going to
do?
It's going to do this.
But when it gets there,
the potential difference is
introduced between these two
D's, so that this is low pot-
high potential and this is a low
potential.
And so you're going to get an
electric field now in this gap
in this direction and so this
proton is being accelerated.
And let's suppose that the
difference in potential is
twenty kilovolts.
Then this proton will gain in
electric- in kinetic energy,
it will gain kinetic energy,
twenty
kilo electron volts.
That's the way electron volt is
defined.
And so you start off with one
MEV, so when it has  crossed
this gap it is now one point oh
two MEV.
Twenty KEV more.
The radius, now,
is larger.
If capital V is two percent
higher, and I go to this
equation,
then the radius is one percent
higher and so when it comes out
here and it makes a circle,
the radius now is one percent
higher than fifteen centimeters.
But when it gets to this  part
of the D, this potential
difference is reversed and so
the electric field is again in
this direction,
in the direction of the proton
and so it is accelerated again
by twenty kilo electron volts.
Now the radius,
of course, is even larger and
so very gradually every time
that it reaches the gap the
potential difference is changed
in direction to accelerate the
proton and so it gradually
spirals out, then,
to the largest radius that you
have.
So during one full rotation it
gains twenty kilo electron volts
once, and twenty kilo electron
volts twice, so it gains forty
kilo electron volts.
And so the electric fields are
doing the work.
They accelerate the particles.
Magnetic fields can not
accelerate.
Magnetic fields can change the
direction but they can do no
work on the particles.
So the magnetic fields confine
the particles.
So let's assume we go twelve
hundred and twenty-five full
rotations.
During each rotation the
kinetic energy increased by
forty KEV.
And so if you multiply the two
then
you see now that the kinetic
energy of this proton increased
by forty-nine million electron
volts, because it went
twelve-hundred and twenty-five
times all the way around,
and so now you have forty-nine
MEV plus the one MEV that you
started with,
so now you have a fifty MEV
proton.
You see the second line there?
There we have that fifty MEV
proton
that I discussed with you
earlier.
In a one Tesla field now the
radius is one meter,
so if this unit had a radius of
one meter that would be fine.
By that time it would be all
the way near the circumference
of this unit.
What is remarkable and not
intuitive, that the time to go
around as long as we don't have
to make relativistic
corrections,
that the time for a proton to
go around is independent of its
speed.
Not so intuitive,
and you can see this very
easily because the time to go
around  is two pi R divided by
its speed.
You see, the radius is
proportional to V.
And so the time itself is
independent of V,
because R itself is linearly
proportional with the speed and
so that cancels and so you'll
find now that the time to go
around is simply two pi times
the mass of that particle
divided by QB.
And if you correct
relativistically,
then you have to multiply by
gamma, but if you stay
non-relativistic,
then it's independent of the
speed of the protons.
So if we stick to this
particular case of our one MEV
proton that became a fifty MEV
proton going around twelve
hundred and twenty-five times,
this time to go around once is
only sixty-six nanoseconds,
so this is six point six times
ten to the minus eight seconds.
Give you some feeling of how
fast all this is going.
So if you go around twelve
hundred
and twenty-five times,
that would take only eighty
microseconds so in eighty
microseconds does all of this
occur and that means you have to
switch this field twice before
rotation, make sure that the
e-field is in this direction,
but when the proton comes here
the e-field has to be in that
direction.
And so the switching frequency
which easily be calculated
becomes about thirty million
times per second,
about thirty megahertz.
And all of that takes place in
eighty microseconds and you
create one MEV protons,
you turn them into fifty MEV
protons.
A mind-boggling concept,
but it works.
Quite remarkable.
Now because of the relativistic
corrections that you see here
with gamma, if you go to very
high energies then the time  is
not constant for a full
rotation,
so you have to adjust now the
frequency with which you switch
the potential between these
gaps.
So if the time increases then
this switching frequency has to
go down and we call those
instruments synchrotrons,
or synchrocyclotrons.
They have names.
So you synchronize now and
correct for relativistic
effects.
Modern accelerators have
constant radii.
They are rings.
And so if you have a ring with
constant radius,
the only way that you can keep
the particles in the ring when
they have a low energy and when
they have the high energy is by
gradually increasing the
magnetic field.
So you start off with a weak
magnetic field,
you go around huge circle,
very large radius,
and you gradually increase the
magnetic fields as you keep
accelerating them and by making
the magnetic field go up just in
the right way,
maybe all the way up to two
Tesla,
you can keep them in that ring.
The first slide that I'd like
to show you is the slide of an
ancient cyclotron that is
actually a synchrocyclotron,
was built by Lawrence in
Berkeley, and this was capable
of accelerating protons to seven
hundred thirty MEV.
You see here a person to give
you feeling for the size  of
this instrument.
Lawrence received the Nobel
Prize for Physics in 1939 for
his
invention of the cyclotron.
The next slide is Fermilab near
Chicago.
This is one of these modern
accelerators also called
sometimes colliders,
and this has a diameter of two
point two kilometers,
and this instrument,
this here, plans to accelerate
protons up to thousand GEV,
G stands for giga,
giga is the same as billion.
A thousand giga electron volts
would
be ten to the twelfth electron
volts.
The beams of high energy
protons are made to collide with
other nuclei to uncover the
inner workings of nuclear
physics.
The higher the energy of the
protons, the larger is the
impact when the protons collide
and the more one expects to
learn.
By using ever-increasing
energies of the protons,
which are nuclear bullets,
one explores unknown territory.
In the news,
these colliders are often
called
atom smashers.
That is a flashier name which
appeals more to the general
public who pays for all this
with their tax money.
This research is a multibillion
dollar industry.
The words atom smasher are
actually a misnomer.
The colliders smash nuclei
which are ten thousand times
smaller than atoms.
And the next slide shows you
the tunnel of the largest ring
in the world which is in Geneva,
at CERN which is a European
collaboration.
This tunnel which already
exists for many years has a
confluence of seventeen miles,
has a radius of four point
three kilometers,
and in here are these protons
being accelerated [inaudible] on
the high vacuum.
And with very modern techniques
of superconducting magnets they
can even go up now to about five
Tesla.
And in this tunnel right now a
whole
new experiment is under
development which is called the
Large Hadron Collider which is
considered the Holy Grail for
particle physicists and it's
hoped that that will go on the
air in the year Two Thousand
Seven or so and it will
accelerate protons to an
unprecedented energy that will
give them kinetic energies of
seven thousand GEV,
seven times ten to the twelfth
electron volts.
So I would like to return to my
overhead there,
so that you can see some of
that what we just discussed
right there, thank you Tom.
So here we have Fermilab.
You see a radius of one point
one kilometers.
I showed you a picture from the
air and so they went up to one
point five Tesla,
so that's the maximum magnetic
field strength.
Get very close to the speed of
light
by the way [laughter] and you
see five hundred GEV protons.
And here you see the holy
grail, the large hadron
collider, European collaboration
in Geneva at CERN,
whereby you have the
circumference of seventeen miles
and the magnetic fields that
they hope to achieve going up to
five and a half Tesla using
modern techniques of
superconductors.
So if you want to go around in
those tunnels by the way,
by the way, you need a
motorcycle, [inaudible] go
seventeen miles around.
The goal of all this physics,
of all these experiments,
is to enter new territory,
to learn about these mysterious
nuclear forces and to see what
is insi- inside protons and to
see what is inside neutrons.
And with these experiments many
nuclear particles were
discovered
whose existence was completely
unknown previously.
Now comes the issue how can
you see the results of these
collisions of these particles
with very high energies.
Well, you can make the tracks
of these particles visible.
In fact, today you will see
them with your own eyes.
And in the old days this was
done with cloud chambers and
that's the
demonstration I will do today
for you.
But nowadays they do them with
bubble chambers.
Let's first understand the
principle.
If you had a charged particle,
whether it is an electron or a
proton or an alpha particle --
alpha particle is the nucleus of
helium, it's two protons,
two neutrons.
If it goes through the air it
makes ions and as it goes
through the air and it makes
ions it slowly loses its kinetic
energy and it finally
comes to a halt.
If we take a ten MEV electron
and one atmosphere air it could
go forty meters.
If you take a proton of ten MEV
it would only go one meter
because the density of ions is
higher because it has a higher
mass and if you take an alpha
particle which has a higher mass
than a proton and it has a
double charge of a proton,
then it would only go ten
centimeters.
It's a very high density track
that
you would get from an alpha
particle.
And so one way you could see
these tracks is using cloud
chambers, and a cloud chamber
works in principle as follows.
You can just have a chamber in
air, one atmosphere air,
which you put liquid alcohol in
there, that's the way we will do
it, and you cool the bottom.
You see one there,
which you will see a little
later, and you cool the bottom
with solid CO two and then you
get inside this chamber,
you get a temperature gradient
and there's a layer there where
the
alcohol should really condense
into little drops because it's
that cold, but for reasons that
are complicated it doesn't do it
quite yet.
We call that undercooled
alcohol.
Even rain can be undercooled.
Just below freezing point,
still liquid.
When the moment it hits the
ground it will immediately
become solid,
by the way.
That's also undercooled liquid.
Now, here we deal with an
undercooled vapor and so when
these
ions are made by these charged
particles, these ions act as
seeds for the drops,
in this case the alcohol drops,
and you can literally with your
eyes, visually see these drops
being formed.
I'd like to go through one
numerical example and I want to
go to a five hundred KEV
electron which you see there.
Um, notice that I have
corrected the speed
relativistically,
otherwise you would get this
ridiculous number that we
calculated
earlier which is larger than
the speed of light.
And suppose we have a
one-tenths Tesla field.
Then the radius would be two
point nine centimeters.
But after a while this electron
will lose its energy and then
there comes a time that it has
only hundred kilo electron volts
left.
By that time,
the radius in a one-tenths
Tesla field would now be one
point one centimeters and so
when you look at cloud chambers
at the tracks of electrons and
you have
magnets there,
you will see the tracks being
curled up which of course is the
result of the fact that the
radius gets smaller in time and
since the magnetic field is
constant you can see then large
radius here and as the kinetic
energy slowly decreases the
radius gets smaller and smaller
and smaller.
So let's look at  a few more
slides.
In 1932, Anderson noticed a
track in a cloud chamber which
had the appearance of an
electron.
It had the right mass,
it had the right charge,
but the curve- the direction of
curvature was wrong.
And so he concluded that it was
an electron which was positively
charged, which is now called a
positron.
And these positrons had been
predicted on purely theoretical
grounds by Dirac,
and Anderson receives a Nobel
Pri- [break in file] discovery
in Nineteen Thirty-Six,
only four years after he
discovered the positron and
Dirac had already received his
Nobel Prize in Nineteen Thirty
Three for his theoretical work.
The bubble chamber is an
advanced form of the cloud
chamber.
In the bubble chamber,
liquid hydrogen is used and if
now
the ions go through  the ions
become the seeds now for little
gas bubbles.
So you have liquids which
really should have been gas but,
uh, not quite and so now it
forms gas bubbles.
So in a cloud chamber,
you're going to see the drops.
In a bubble chamber,
you see gas bubbles but the
idea is the same,
and Glaser who invented these
chambers, is also from Berkeley
by the way,
he got a Nobel Prize for that
in Nineteen Sixty.
So let's look at the discovery
by Anderson.
Here you see a positron coming
from above,  and this positron
has sixty-three MEV  kinetic
energy and Anderson put some
half a centimeter of lead in
there which was very clever,
think about that.
When it comes out,
the energy now is less,
because in the lead it produces
a lot of ions and so it loses a
lot of kinetic energy and it
comes out with roughly
twenty-three MEV.
And why did he do that?
Because now he knows for sure
that this particle came from
above, because when it loses
energy the radius is smaller.
That's why he was sure that it
was curved in the wrong
direction.
If he didn't have the lead,
you never know whether the
electron
came this way,
in which case the curvature
would be perfect.
But now he knows it comes from
above and if this had been an
electron it would've curved this
way.
So this is one of the early
discovery, cloud chamber
photographed by Anderson.
And the next slide is a bubble
chamber and we see here both
positron and an electron in a
constant magnetic field and it
speaks for itself,
notice that the curvatures are
exactly in opposite directions
and you see this spiral
structure that I discussed with
you as the electrons lose their
energy and since this is a
bubble chamber,
which has an enormous density a
thousand times higher density,
say, than air,
these electrons don't travel
forty meters in these chambers.
In air they would,
but in this case it is
substantially less and so you
can roll them up nicely.
And you can study them,
their momentum and their
charge.
Using  uh, accelerators and
cloud chambers and bubble
chambers, a whole new world  of
nuclear physics emerged.
Wow.
And between Nineteen
Fifty-Eight and Sixty-Eight
thirty new nuclear particles
were discovered.
And MIT has always been on the
forefront of this research.
Professor Sam King,
who is still at MIT,
got the Nobel Prize in Nineteen
Seventy-Six.
Steven Weinberg,
a theoretician who did his work
while he was at MIT got his
Nobel Prize in Nineteen
Seventy-Nine.
Jerry Friedman,
still at MIT,
and Henry Kendall,
got the Nobel Prize for their
work in Nineteen Ninety.
And Clifford Shull got his
Nobel Prize in Nineteen
Ninety-Four.
If I summarize the basic idea
behind it, it is very relevant
to eight oh two,
you accelerate these particles
using electric fields.
That's the only way you can
accelerate them.
Magnetic fields can only be
used to confine them.
It can not change their kinetic
energy but kinetic electr-
magnetic fields are crucial,
because that allows you as you
gradually increase their speed
to confine them,
either by a ring,
which is done nowadays,
or in the old days in these
chambers of the cyclotrons and
the synchrotrons.
And then we have the bubble
chambers, in the old days the
cloud chambers,
whereby you use magnetic fields
to get information on the radius
of these particles as they are
being detected.
And out of all these emerged a
whole new way of looking at our
world and completely new ideas
about what makes the world tick.
This is nothing short of a
revolution.
And so now I want to enjoy with
you the last five minutes of
this lecture by looking at a
cloud chamber and by looking at
some of these tracks.
You're going to see a lot of
electrons in there.
The walls of the cloud chamber
are radioactive just like you
are radioactive.
Your bones are radioactive,
your windows are radioactive.
They emit electrons.
No protons, but they certainly
emit electrons.
And we have in there a
radioactive isotope,
a rod, which has thorium in it
which
produces alpha particles.
And so you're going to see
electrons which make beautiful
spider web structures.
Please don't clean up yet,
we have plenty of time.
To be precise,
we have five minutes and
eighteen seconds left.
So these electrons,
you will see them going like
spiders through this chamber and
sometimes they change abrupt
direction because they can
collide, particularly when they
have low energy and then they
[break in file]
so to speak,
and then occasionally we may
see an alpha particle coming
from our radioactive thorium and
that makes a very thick track.
And so let's try this.
We have an expert here which is
Marcos who has not only borrowed
these instruments,
and if you like it we may
actually buy it,
it's not cheap,
we may buy it,
but he borrowed it specially
for you, for which I'm very
grateful, Marcos,
and he also did quite a bit of
work to get the light just
right.
It's not too easy to
see those tracks.
So Marcos, you will get a
chance to adjust the lights if
you want that.
Um.
We're going to make it very
dark  and let's enjoy them,
this wonderful world,
invisible world,
of nuclear physics.
So here you see this  th- the
rod with thorium  so Marcos feel
free to adjust the light if you
feel the need.
I will go into the audience as
well
and see whether  we can
identify the electrons.
Oh, there was an alpha
particle.
So this is this rod and so the
bottom of this chamber is cooled
with solid CO two.
Ah, there was an electron,
very nice.
As I said, you know,
they almost look like spider
webs.
There was an electron here.
Also keep an eye on this rod
and occasionally you will see a
very dense track which then
indicates -- there was one,
that's an alpha
particle.
There's a beautiful alpha
Just enjoy this.
You know, you're looking at a
world which is completely new.
Think about it.
You're looking at the world of
nuclear physics.
You're seeing individual
electrons and occasionally you
see alpha particles.
Here, there's one coming out.
And think about the physics
what's going on here,
this alcohol which refuses to
become drops and then these ions
say we force you to become uh --
here's an alpha particle,
I don't know what it's doing
there.
So these, these,
um, these ions force these,
um, these, this,
this alcohol vapor to become
drops.
That's an incredible,
complex picture that you're
looking at.
It is amazing every time I see
this.
It's absolutely fabulous.
And all through these very
simple rules,
now think about it,
we have the Lawrence force,
that  makes these particles go
around, electric fields that you
can use them to  accelerate
them, and then this subtle way
that you can actually make them
visible, individual particles
visible.
It is a new world.
And the goal of my lecture was
to make you peek into this world
which has revolutionized our
whole way of thinking.
Thank you.