JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about two-dimensional
flux and the normal form of
Green's theorem, so normal
here meaning perpendicular.
So I want to give you a
problem about that.
So what I'd like you to do is
to verify Green's theorem in
normal form for this particular
field, the field F
equals xi hat plus yj hat and
the curve C that consists of
the upper half of the unit
circle and the x-axis
interval (-1, 1).
So first of all, let me say what
I mean by this C. So C,
it's the usual unit circle,
circle of radius 1 centered at
the origin, so just its top
half, And the x-axis interval
(-1, 1), I mean, the line
segment that connects the
points (-1, 0) and (1, 0),
so the diameter of that
semicircle.
So that's the curve
C and the field F.
What I mean by verify Green's
theorem is I'd like you to
compute both the double integral
that appears in
Green's theorem and the line
integral that appears in
Green's theorem and check
that they're really
equal to each other.
So that'll confirm Green's
theorem in this particular
instance and hopefully help
give us a feel for how it
works a little bit.
So why don't you pause the
video, have a go, compute both
of those integrals, come
back and we can
work them out together.
Hopefully you had some
luck with this.
Let's have a go at it.
So what Green's theorem tells
you is that the flux across a
curve, which we usually compute
as a line integral, is
also equal to an integral of the
divergence over the region
bounded by that curve.
So here the curve has to be a
closed curve so that it bounds
a region of the plane.
So in particular, let's draw
the picture here so we know
what we're talking about.
So the curve C, so we've got the
segment from -1 to 1 along
the x-axis, and then
we have the top
half of the unit circle.
That's the curve C. And I didn't
specify an orientation
but in any context like this,
when you don't specify an
orientation, what you mean
is positively oriented.
So it's a positively
oriented curve.
So that's our curve C.
And so the region that it bounds
is this half of the
circle, the semicircle.
I keep saying half of
the semicircle.
Sorry about that.
This upper half of the circle,
of the disc, in fact.
That region of the plane.
OK, so what Green's theorem
tells us is that when we
compute the surface integral--
sorry, the double integral--
of the divergence of F over this
region, that should be
the same as what we do if we
compute F dot n around the
boundary of the curve.
And now we're going
to check it.
So let's do the double integral
first. The double
integral in this case, so it's
the double integral over--
let me call that region R--
so it's the double integral
over R of the
divergence of F dA.
So what is the divergence
of F?
Well, here's F. It's
xi hat plus yj hat.
So it's divergence is the
partial of x with respect to
x, plus the partial of
y with respect to y.
So that's 1 plus 1.
So the divergence of F is
just 2, in this case.
So it's equal to the double
integral over the
semicircle of 2 dA.
And of course when you integrate
a constant over a
region, what you get is just
that constant times the area
of the region.
So dA here is the area of the
semicircle, it's half of a
circle of radius 1.
So circle of radius
1 has area pi.
So this is 2 times 1/2 pi.
So this is pi.
OK.
So that's the double integral
that we get from Green's
theorem in normal form.
And what Green's theorem says
is that this is equal to a
particular line integral.
So what is the line integral?
Well, it's the integral
around C of F dot n.
So let's write down what
it is, the line
integral part now.
So it's an integral.
It's a closed curve.
So it's in and around
C of F dot n ds.
So that is the line integral
that we're looking to compute.
So how do we compute this?
Well, usually we compute it by
using the coordinates of F. So
this is equal to, and we know
that this is always equal to,
the integral around C of--
and let me make sure I'm getting
this right before I
screw anything up.
Yes.
OK, I am.
Good.
M dy minus N dx, where M and N
are the coordinates of F-- or
the components of F. M and N are
the components of F. So M
is the first component and N
is the second component.
So in our case, F has this
fairly simple form.
So in our case this is equal to
the integral around C of--
so M, the first component
of F is x.
So this is xdy minus the second
component is ydx.
So this is the line integral
we're interested in computing.
But, of course, this curve
is not easy to
parameterize as a single go.
So we want to split it
into two pieces.
So let's look.
So the first piece we want
to split it into
is that line segment.
So let's call that maybe--
well, I'm not even going to
bother giving them names.
We want to split it into the
integral over the line segment
plus the integral over
the semicircle.
The boundary of that--
yes, the semicircle.
So this is equal to--
so it's the integral over
the line segment.
So let's see.
So that integral--
well, OK, I will give
them names.
I will give them names.
I take it back.
We'll call the line segment
C1 and we'll call
the semicircle C2.
So it's equal to the
integral over c1.
OK, well, what is the
integral over c1?
What are x and dy and y
and dx in this case?
So in this case, well, x is
what we're integrating.
But dy, we're on this line
segment, y isn't changing.
y is constant.
So dy is just 0.
So it's 0 minus--
OK, and now on this line
segment y is 0 also.
So it's 0dx.
So the first integral, the
integral over C1, is the
integral of 0.
Plus we have to integrate
over C2.
Of OK, so x dy minus y dx.
All right.
So this one's just going
to be 0, that's easy.
So now we just have to work
with this second one.
OK, so for the second one, we're
integrating over the
semicircle so we want
to parameterize it.
And we're going to use our
usual parameterization.
x equals cosine t,
y equals sine t.
And in this case, we just want
to do this semicircle.
So we just want to go from
(1, 0) all the way
around to (-1, 0).
So that is from going
from 0 to pi.
So this is equal to--
so this first integral
is just 0.
It's the integral of
0 and that's 0.
So it's the integral--
OK, so t is going to
go from 0 to pi.
So now x dy.
So x is cosine t.
y is sine t.
So dy is sine t dt.
Sorry, it's cosine t dt.
y is sine t.
dy is cosine t dt.
So it's cosine t times
cosine t dt minus.
All right, now y is
sine t again.
And x is cosine t.
So dx is minus sine t dt.
So this is times minus
sine t dt.
OK, well what happens here?
So this becomes cosine squared
t dt minus minus
sine squared t.
Minus minus is plus.
So it's cosine squared t dt
plus sine squared t dt.
But, of course, cosine squared
plus sine squared is just 1.
So we can write this even more
simply as the integral from 0
to pi of 1 dt or just dt, and
the integral dt is just t.
So this is t between 0
and pi, which is pi.
Whew!
OK.
Pi.
Good.
And what did we get before?
We also got pi.
Great.
So we have successfully verified
Green's theorem in
normal form in this particular
instance.
So let's just recap
again what we did.
We had this field F and this
curve C. This closed curve C
that bounded some region.
And so what we've done is we
computed the double integral
over the region of d of F dA.
So that's what we did first.
Double integral over the
region bounded by the curve.
And then second we computed the
line integral around the
boundary of F dot n ds.
So that was what-- this is
always a useful form in which
to write this F dot n dA.
OK, and then we substituted
and computed it.
And Green's theorem tells us
that the two intervals have to
be equal to each other.
And indeed, for this particular
F and this
particular C, we verified
that in this case they
both give us pi.
And, of course, Green's theorem
tells us that that
would have been true, that they
would have come out the
same, regardless of what the
choice of F and the choice of
C that we made were.
So I'll stop there.