JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
One of the things you've been
learning about in lecture is
how to solve some max-min
problems. How to find the
maximum or minimum of a given
function given some
constraints and figure out where
it reaches its largest
or smallest value.
So here I have a particular
example of such a problem.
So we're going to build
a cardboard box.
And our cardboard box has to
meet the following criteria.
So its volume has
to be 3 units.
The front and back of the
cardboard box are going to be
made just of single-thickness
cardboard.
But the two sides, the left
and right, are going to be
made double-thick.
And the bottom is going to
be made triple-thick.
We're not going to have
a top, it's just going
to be an open box.
So it's going to have five
sides: two of single
thickness, two of double
thickness, and with the bottom
of triple thickness.
So, the question is-- there
are, you know, a lot of
different shapes of box with
total volume 3 units.
So the question is what
dimensions should this box
have so that we use
the minimum amount
of cardboard possible?
All right?
So we want the dimensions of
the box that use the least
total amount cardboard.
So why don't you pause the
video, work on that for
awhile, come back, and we
can work on it together
I hope you had some fun
puzzling this one out.
Let's have a go at it.
So to start, I think I'd just
like to draw a little
picture of a box.
So here's my cardboard box.
Its top is going to
be open, say.
So let's give it--
we want to figure out what its
dimensions should be in order
to minimize some expression,
so let's give them names.
Right?
So I think a natural thing to
call them is we can call one
of them x and one of them
y and the height z.
There.
So if we give the box these
dimensions x, y, and z, we
need to ask, well first of
all, what is its volume?
And second of all, how much
cardboard is used?
And as long as we can keep the
volume equal to 3, what's the
least amount of cardboard
we can use?
So the volume of this box is
just xyz and that has to be 3.
So we know xyz is equal to the
volume, which is equal to 3.
So we have a constraint
on x, y, and z here.
And the thing that we
want to optimize--
that we want to find
a minimum for--
is the total amount
of cardboard used.
So let's talk about how much
cardboard is used.
So the bottom of the box
is triple-thick.
So its area is x times y.
So the total amount of cardboard
used is 3xy.
Now, the front and back of the
box are single thickness.
And they have area
xy, but there--
sorry, not xy, xz, right?
This height is z, so it's
x times z-- and
there are two of them.
So we have xz total cardboard
in front and xz total
cardboard in back.
Oh, I guess this has another
segment there in back because
it's an open box.
So xz and xz.
So that's 2xz coming from
the front and back.
And from the two sides, well
each side has area yz.
There are two of them and
they're double-thick.
So that contributes 4yz
to the total amount
of cardboard used.
So this is the total amount
And we know xyz is equal to 3.
So we want to minimize this, but
we want to minimize this
taking this into account, taking
this restriction on the
volume into account.
So what we can do is you can
realize that we can just
eliminate one of these
variables.
Right?
We can say z is equal
to 3 over xy.
That always has to be true.
And if we make that substitution
in here, then
we'll be able to minimize this
expression without regard to
any constraint anymore.
So from xyz equals 3, we have
z equals 3 over xy.
So we want to minimize what we
get when we plug z equals 3
over xy into here.
So that's 3xy, plus--
well, 2x times 3 over xy is--
6 over y, plus-- and 4y
times 3 over xy is--
12 over x.
And one other thing I guess we
haven't mentioned explicitly
is that this is a
physical box.
It has actual dimensions, so its
dimensions have to be, you
know-- they're lengths, they
have to be positive numbers.
So we want for x to be positive
and we want for y to
be positive numbers.
OK.
So now we've got
this function.
And there aren't--
x and y can be anything, any
value of x and y we choose.
This describes the amount of
cardboard used in a box with
those dimensions on its base
that has volume 3.
All right?
So we want to minimize that.
So now we've finally got to
the point of our calculus.
Let's call this function--
let's give it a name like,
I don't know--
f of x, y.
So we want to find the
global minimum of f.
We want to find the absolute
least amount of cardboard that
we can use.
So there are several
possibilities for where a
global minimum can occur.
It can occur on some critical
point of the function, or it
can occur on the boundary of the
region where the function
is defined.
And in this case, that includes
the possibility that
it can occur as x or y or
both go off to infinity.
All right?
So we have to look at
those possibilities.
In particular, we have to look
at the critical points.
That's one of the
possibilities.
So the critical points of f.
So we need to find out what
those points are.
So in order to find the
critical points,
well what do we do?
We do the usual thing.
We look at its partial
derivatives.
So we need the first and
second-- or sorry--
the first partial derivatives
with respect to x and y, we
need both of them to
be equal to 0.
So we need fx equals
0, and fy equals 0.
OK, so let's write down what
that means over here.
So what is fx?
Well, we just take
the partials.
So it's 3y--
plus we take the partial of 6y
with respect to x and we get
0, and we take the partial of 12
over x with respect to x--
and we get minus 12
over x squared.
So that's fx, and we need
that to be equal to 0.
And fy is equal to 3x minus 6
over y squared, and we also
need that to be equal to 0.
So if we solve this first
equation, for example, we can
solve it for y in terms of x.
And that tells me that
y is equal to--
I need-- let's see--
12 over x squared divided
by 3, so that's--
4 over x squared.
Now I can plug this 4 over x
squared in down here, and so I
get 3x minus 6.
Well, 6 divided by 4 divided by
x squared quantity squared
is 6 times x squared
over 4 squared.
That has to be equal to 0.
And I can-- let's see-
I can rewrite this.
Maybe I'll divide through
by 3 as that 3
isn't going to matter.
So it's x minus--
so then I'll be left with 2
times x to the fourth over 16,
so that's--
x to the fourth over
8 equals 0.
And you can see in this equation
that either x is
equal to 0, or we can divide
by x and then we get x
cubed equals 8.
So x equals 0 or x
The only solution
is x equals 2.
Now, it's easy to see that we
can't have a box with x equal
to 0, right?
Our function is not actually
defined at x equals 0 over
here, you'll see, right.
Our function had a 12 over x
in it, so we can't have x
equal to 0.
So that's not going to be
a critical point of this
function. x equals 0 isn't going
to lead to a critical
point, so, OK, so our only
critical points are going to
happen when x is equal to 2.
And when x is equal to 2, we can
go back up here and we see
that y was equal to 4
over x squared at
our critical points.
So the only critical
point is 2, 1.
OK.
So that's our critical point.
So now, we want to think about
is this point going to be a
maximum or a minimum or what?
And where is the global
minimum of this
function going to occur?
So remember that the global
minimum of this function can
occur either on the critical
points or on the boundary or
at a point where x or y
is going to infinity--
in the limit, I guess I mean.
So lets go back here and take
a look at our function here.
So we can see from the
expression for this function
that if x and y are going to
infinity, this is no good.
This part is going to
go to infinity.
3xy is going to go to infinity,
and these are going
to be positive, so f is going
to go to infinity.
OK, so as the dimensions of our
box get very, very large,
the total amount of cardboard
used becomes infinite.
Also, if x or y gets closer
and closer to 0--
that's at the boundary--
well, if x gets closer and
closer to 0, than 12 over x
gets closer and closer
to infinity.
And if y gets closer and closer
to 0, then 6 over y
gets closer and closer
to infinity.
And again, all these terms are
going to be positive because x
and y have to be positive.
So in those limiting cases, the
function f of x, y gets
infinitely large.
So along the boundary and as x
and y go to infinity, this
function blows up.
It gets very, very big.
So that means the only place it
could have a global-- so it
has a global minimum-- the only
place that global minimum
can be is at a critical point.
And we saw, if we walk back over
here again, that the only
critical point is
the point 2, 1.
All right?
So that means this point
has to be a global
minimum for the function.
Now, you might, out of
curiosity, you might ask how
much cardboard are we actually
talking about in that case?
Since that's really the one
part, I guess wan't really
part of the question, but its
an interesting thing to ask.
So in this case, we use f of 2,
1 equals-- well let's see--
so that's 6 plus 6
plus 6 equals 18
units squared of cardboard.
Now, I guess one thing you might
notice is we didn't use
the second derivative
test here.
And the question is why--
I mean, we concluded it was a
global maximum without ever
using the second derivative
test. Sorry, global minimum.
Pardon me.
And the second derivative test
is the thing that tells us
whether things are minimum or
maximum or saddle points.
So why didn't we use it?
Well, the answer is the second
derivative test tells you
whether something is a local
minimum or maximum or whether
it's a saddle point.
So if we had applied the second
derivative test at this
critical point, what we would
have learned is that this
critical point is
a local minimum.
But being a local minimum isn't
enough to guarantee that
it's a global minimum.
Because we could have
on the boundary--
or as x or y goes
to infinity--
we could have that the function
value get smaller and
smaller without bound.
Now in this case, we
showed that the
function doesn't do that.
It gets larger and larger
without bound.
And so that meant that that
minimum point really is the
global minimum.
But the second derivative test
isn't enough to conclude that
something is a global
minimum on its own.
You really do need that extra
analysis that we did.
I'll end there.