JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been
learning about triple
integration.
And I have a problem here for
you on computing a volume of a
region using a triple
integral.
So let's look at this.
So I have a volume and I'm
describing it to you; it's the
volume inside the paraboloid
z equals x squared plus y
squared and bounded by the
plane z equals 2y.
So I've drawn a little
picture here for you.
So this is the paraboloid
here.
And we're just taking
a plane cut of it.
And so this is going to slice
off some chunk of that
paraboloid, and what I want to
know is what the volume is of
that piece that gets cut off
by that plane there.
So below the plane and
above the paraboloid.
So, why don't you pause the
video, take some time, work
out this problem, come
back, and we
can work on it together.
I hope you had some luck
with this problem.
I think it's a bit of a tricky
one, so let's start to work
through it together.
So sometimes you have a problem
with a triple integral.
And you need to set up your
bounds of integration.
And sometimes you can look
at it and it's just
clear what they are.
If you're integrating over a
cube, life is really easy.
But in this case, this region
that we want to integrate over
is kind of more complicated
to understand.
Right?
So it's easy to see-- well,
relatively easy to see-- what
the bounds on z are.
So let me draw a couple of
two-dimensional pictures.
So I'm going to draw the
yz-plane cross section here.
So in the yz-plane cross
section, this paraboloid just
becomes a parabola.
So that becomes the parabola z
equals y squared, which is a
plane section of the paraboloid
z equals x squared
plus y squared.
And this plane z equals 2y
becomes the line z equals 2y.
And this little sliver
is a plane section of
the region in question.
So we see that z is going from
the paraboloid to the plane.
And over here, we see that z is
going from the paraboloid
to the plane.
But what we really need to
understand then is what the
relationship between
x and y is.
So what is the shadow
of this region?
How are x and y related
to each other?
How can we bound x in terms
of y or y in terms of x?
Or should we use cylindrical
coordinates or what?
And so in order to that what
we need to do is we need to
figure out--
when you project this region
down, when you flatten it
along z, so you're disregarding
z now, and then
you're just looking
at its shadow, its
footprint, in the xy plane--
you want to figure out,
what is that region?
What does it look like?
So somehow we'll project down
and there will be some region
R down here.
So I'll call this region R. And
that region will be the
projection of this solid
region down.
And it has some boundary
curve--
C, say-- the boundary curve of
the region R. Just in case we
need to refer to them later,
it's good to give them letters
so that they have names.
So what we need to figure out
now is what is this region R?
Now this is tough to do by just
intuitive reasoning or
just by looking at this
picture I've drawn.
So in this case, we're kind of
forced to use some algebra.
All right.
So what do we know about this
region R and this curve C?
Well, C is the projection
downwards of the curve of
intersection of this plane with
this paraboloid, right?
So it's the projection down at
this curve intersection.
So what does that mean
about its equation?
Well, it means it's what we get
if we solve for z in one
of the two equations
of the surfaces and
plug it into the other.
And that will give us an
equation with just x and y,
and that will be the equation
of this curve C. OK.
So in our case, that means
that C is given by this
equation x squared plus
y squared equals 2y.
All right.
So whenever x squared plus y
squared equals 2y, that's a
point x, y such that directly
above that point is a place
where the plane intersects
the paraboloid.
Well, OK.
So what is this curve?
Well, a little bit of algebra
can help us sort that out.
If you bring the 2y over here
and complete the square, you
can see that we can rewrite
this as x squared plus (y
minus 1) squared equals 1.
I brought the 2y over, I've
added 1 to both sides, and
I've factored the y part.
And so this is an easy equation
to recognize.
This is the equation of a
circle with center (0,
1) and radius 1.
So let's draw that.
And so here is a picture of what
the shadow looks like in
the xy plane.
So the center is at height 1,
and then it's this circle.
That's almost a circle.
It looks enough like a circle
for my purposes.
So this is the region R. It's a
circular region of radius 1
with center (0, 1).
OK, great.
So I'm just going to shade that
in again because I like
doing that.
OK.
So that's the region R.
So what is this region R?
Let's look back over here.
It's the shadow of our solid
region in the xy plane.
So when you project
down, that's the
region that you get.
So why do we need that?
So we know when we set up this
triple integral, z is going to
be going from the paraboloid
up to the plane.
That's going to be the innermost
integral, but then
the middle integral is going to
be y in terms of x or x in
terms of y.
Or if we do polar coordinates
or cylindrical coordinates,
it's going to be R in
terms of theta.
So we need to figure out what
the boundary is, what that
region looks like over which
we'll be integrating for the
outer two integrals.
OK, so now I've been saying we
could use cylindrical or we
could use rectangular.
What do we want to use?
Well, so this is a circle.
It's not centered at the origin,
but it is tangent to
one of the axes at the origin.
So this is a reasonably nice
situation to do polar
coordinates in, or cylindrical
coordinates.
You have to remember from when
you learned cylindrical and
polar coordinates what the
equation of such a circle is.
And so I'm going to write it
down here, and I'm going to
invite you to go look
up why this is true
if you don't remember.
This curve has an equation
in polar--
these are the x- and
y-axes here--
so this curve has in polar
coordinates the equation r
equals 2 sine theta.
All right.
So that gives me this
curve here.
The outer boundary.
And now what I want is, I don't
just want the curve.
I want to integrate over the
whole region, and I want to
integrate over it once.
Remember, polar coordinates are
a little tricky because
you have to worry about are
you overlapping and so on.
So how does this work?
At theta equals 0, or at the
origin, and then as theta
grows, we get further
and further away.
So this is our radius
growing out.
And then at pi over 2,
we're at the top
point of the circle.
And then as it comes back into
pi, it comes back in.
So we want theta going from 0
less than or equal to theta
less than or equal to pi here.
So at pi over 2 at the top, and
at pi it comes back for
the first time.
And what about r?
Well, it looks like r has
to go all the way
out to 2 sine theta.
And in fact, we always want
it to start at the origin.
So we always want r
to go from 0 to--
this outer boundary--
2 sine theta.
So this describes this region
big R that we're trying to
integrate over.
This circular region in
polar coordinates.
So OK.
So it's a fairly easy
description of polar
coordinates.
You could also describe it in
rectangular coordinates, and
you could try to solve
the problem that way.
I'm not going to do it for you,
but you could give it a
shot and see if you can come
out with the same answer in
the end that we do.
So OK.
So now, what have we done?
Well, I haven't written our
bounds, so let me write our
bounds on z right here.
So we know that z is going
from the paraboloid.
If we look at the paraboloid
z equals x
squared plus y squared--
but we're working in cylindrical
coordinates now,
so we need to write this in
terms of r and theta--
so that's z is going from r
squared, and it's going up to
the plane z equals 2y--
now y in cylindrical coordinates
is r sine theta.
So z is going from r squared
to 2r sine theta.
So let's go write that
down over here.
So z is going from--
just ignore that--
from r squared less than or
equal to z, and it's going all
the way up to 2r sine theta.
So these three equations
describe our region.
Yeah?
0 less than theta less than
pi: that just says theta.
OK?
Then when theta is going
from 0 to pi--
r going from 0 to 2 sine theta--
that says in the xy
plane we're tracing out
this circular shadow.
And then as z goes from r
squared to 2r sine theta, that
says above this shadow we're
above the paraboloid
and below the plane.
So that's exactly the
region that we want.
So OK.
So now how do we get it
to volume after we
figured this out?
Well, we write down the
triple integral.
So V, the volume of a region
D, is equal to the triple
integral over that
solid of dV. OK?
And in our case, in cylindrical
coordinates, dV is
going to be dz times r dr d
theta, or r dz dr d theta.
OK?
So this is equal to, if we're
integrating, r dz dr d theta.
And now we need to put
in our bounds.
If we look over on this side
of me, here they are.
And these are our bounds that
we're going to be using.
So theta is going
from 0 to pi.
And r is going from
0 to 2 sine theta.
And z is going from r squared
to 2r sine theta.
So this triple integral
gives us precisely the
volume of our region.
And in order to figure out what
that volume is, we just
have to evaluate
this integral.
So let's start doing that.
I don't think I'm going to go
quite all the way, but I'll do
most of the work.
So OK.
So let's do the innermost
integral first. Whenever you
have a triple integral
like this-- a
nice iterated integral--
you always start at the inside
and work your way out.
Well here, our integrand is r,
and we're integrating with
respect to z-- and r doesn't
have any z's in it--
so this inner integral
is going to be easy.
So I'm going to rewrite
this as equal to--
we keep our outer two bounds--
so it's still from 0 to pi,
and it's still from 0 to 2 sine
theta, of 2r squared sine
theta minus r cubed
dr d theta.
So what I've done here is
I've just integrated.
I get the anti-derivative
of r dz is rz.
And so then I take
the difference
between those two bounds.
So I get r times 2r sine theta
minus r times r squared.
So r times 2r sine theta is
2r squared sine theta.
Minus r times r squared
is minus r cubed.
OK, so I've just done
the first integral.
So now integrating with
respect to r.
OK, this second one isn't
so bad either.
As far as r is concerned, this
is just a polynomial.
Theta is constant with respect
to r when we're doing an
integral like this.
So OK.
So the second integral is
not too bad either.
So this is the integral
for our outer
integral from 0 to pi.
Sticks around--
lets not do this one in one
fell swoop I think--
so it's going to become 2r
cubed over 3, sine theta,
minus r to the fourth over 4.
And we're taking that between
r equals 0 and r
equals 2 sine theta.
And then that whole thing
is going to be
integrated d theta.
So what do we get when
we plug this in?
Well, at r equals zero, this
is just 0, so that's easy.
And so we need the top one,
r equals 2 sine theta.
So this is going to give me
something like 16/3 sine to
the fourth theta minus 4 sine
to the fourth theta, so I
think that works out to be 4/3
sine to the fourth theta d
theta, between 0 and pi.
So now you have to remember how
to do integrals like this.
So this is something you
probably learned back in the
trig integral section of your
Calculus I or 18.01 class.
So when it's an even power here,
I think the thing that
we do is we use our half-angle
formulas.
So now I'm going to tell you
what your final steps are.
So first, you're going to use
your half-angle formula.
So what is that half-angle
formula?
So it's sine squared theta is
equal to 1 minus cosine 2
theta over 2.
So you're going to have to
plug this in here, right?
Sine to the fourth is sine
squared quantity squared.
And then you're going to have
a cosine squared 2 theta, so
you're going to have to use
the double-angle formula.
This time you're going to have
to use the double-angle
formula for cosine, which is
very similar, although not
exactly the same.
So you're going to have
to use those two
double-angle formulas.
After that, you'll have
something that is
straightforward to integrate.
So you'll have something that's
You'll integrate it, and if I'm
not mistaken, what you get
at the end is that you just get
a fairly nice and simple
pi over 2 as your answer.
So you can check your work
there, and make sure that
you've got out pi over
2 at the end.
And hopefully, if you tried to
do this using rectangular
coordinates, you also came
out with something
like this as well.
In that case, you would have to
do a trig substitution at
some point to evaluate your
intervals, or you might have
an arcsine involved.
Something like that
will happen.
But it should also give you
pi over 2, of course.
Because it's the same region,
just described
in a different way.
So let me quickly recap
what we did.
Way back over here, we had this
description of this region.
So it was the region above our
paraboloid and below a plane.
And so when we're setting this
up, we have to figure out in
order to do a triple integral
over this region in order to
find its volume, we have to pick
an order of integration,
and then we have to know what
the bounds are for the inside
in terms of the outer two
variables, for the middle one
in terms of the outermost
one, and so on.
So in this case, that means it
was a natural choice to make z
the first variable-- the
innermost variable.
And so then after that, we
needed to project to find the
relationship in the xy plane
between the other variables.
Now in this case, we did that by
solving this little algebra
problem here.
We solved for z in the two
surfaces that we were given,
and we set them equal
to each other.
And so this gives us a
description for the boundary
curve for our region.
And because it's a nice circle,
this suggested that
one possibility was cylindrical
coordinates.
So we went ahead, and we found
in cylindrical coordinates the
description of this shadow.
And then we used the knowledge
we previously had to describe
the whole region in cylindrical
coordinates.
So we had this description
of our entire region.
And then to compute its volume,
we just set up the
triple integral volume is equal
to a triple integral dV.
In our case, dV--
since we're in cylindrical
coordinates--
that's r dz dr d theta.
We put in our bounds, and then
we evaluated the integral.
I'll stop there.