CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
work on the following problem.
So the problem is as follows.
For which of the following
vector fields is the domain
where each vector field is
defined and continuously
differentiable a simply
connected region.
So there's a lot there.
I'm going to break that down
first, and then show you the
vector fields.
So we're starting with some
different vector fields.
And we want to determine first
the domain for each vector
field where it is both defined
and continuously
differentiable.
And then once you've determined
that domain, the
next object is to determine
whether or not that region is
simply connected.
So there are two parts for
each of these problems.
So again, the first thing is you
want to determine all of
the values for which the vector
field is both defined
and continuously
differentiable.
You want to look at that region
that contains all those
values, and you want to
determine if that region is
simply connected.
So there are four different
vector fields, and I'll just
point them out here.
They're all in the plane.
So the first one is root
x i plus root y j.
The second one is i plus j,
divided by the square root of
1 minus x squared
minus y squared.
The third one looks fairly
similar to the second one, but
it's i plus j, divided by the
square root of the quantity x
squared plus y squared
minus 1.
And the fourth one is i plus j
times the quantity natural log
of r squared-- natural log of
x squared plus y squared.
So there are four different
vector fields here.
You have do two things
for each one.
So find the domain where it's
defined and continuously
differentiable, and then
determine if that domain is
simply connected.
So why don't you pause the
video, work on these, and then
when you're ready to see what
I did, you can bring
the video back up.
OK, welcome back.
So we're going to do
this problem one
vector field at a time.
We're going to take each vector
field, I'm going to
determine where it's defined and
differentiable, and then
I'm going to determine if that
region is simply connected.
So we're going to do each
one separately.
So I'm going to start off
with a, which was root x
i plus root y j.
And I want to point out first,
for the function f of x is
equal to square root of x, it
is defined for all x greater
than or equal to 0, and it
is differentiable for x
greater than 0.
I left out the T. There we go.
So it is both defined and
differentiable when x is
greater than 0.
And now if I replace this with
a y, the same thing is true
for y greater than or equal to
0, and y greater than 0.
So we know the region where
this vector field is both
defined and differentiable is
when x is greater than 0 and y
is greater than 0.
So we need the region--
let me draw it this way--
the region that is the first
quadrant in the xy plane.
And it's not including the
x-axis or the y-axis.
So it's this fully
shaded region.
OK, that is the region where
it's defined and
differentiable.
If I was going to write that
precisely, I would say
something like, all (x, y) with
x greater than 0 and y
greater than 0.
Right?
You need both.
So it's exactly the (x, y) pairs
with x positive and y
positive, and that's
the region.
And now the question is, is that
region simply connected?
Well, the way we think about
simply connectedness from what
you've seen in class, is you
want to show that if you take
a closed curve that's contained
in the region, that
everything on the interior of
that closed curve is also in
the region.
And you notice that is in fact
true for this first quadrant.
Any closed curve I draw that's
in the region, all the points
on the interior of the curve
are also in the region.
So this domain where it's
defined and differentiable is
simply connected.
So the first one is
All right.
So that's part a.
Part b--
let me rewrite that one so we
don't have to zoom over to the
other side--
this was i plus j divided by the
function square root of 1
minus x squared minus
y squared.
Well, we already know that the
square root function is
defined as long as the inside
function is greater than or
equal to 0.
Because it's in the denominator,
we actually need
this function 1 minus x squared
minus y squared to be
greater than 0.
And that's also where it's going
to be differentiable.
The differentiable and the
defined regions are exactly
the same, and they're both where
1 minus x squared minus
y squared is greater than 0.
Right?
The function is only defined
as long as this quantity is
greater than 0, and that's
exactly where it's
differentiable as well.
And so what does this
correspond to?
Well, if you think about it,
this is actually 1 is greater
than x squared plus y squared.
And what are the points
that look like this?
Well, the x- and y-points that
satisfy this inequality are
the x- and y-values
that are on the
interior of the unit circle.
So if I draw a picture
of that.
Let me try and dot
the unit circle.
It's not containing the
boundary, but it's all the
points that are on the interior
of the unit circle.
Every point here, when I take
the ordered pair (x, y) and
it's on the interior of the unit
circle, it satisfies this
inequality.
Those are the only points
that do that.
So this is the region that has
this vector field both
differentiable and defined.
Right?
Now, is this region
simply connected?
It is, again for the
same reason.
Because if you take any closed
curve here, and you look at
the interior of that closed
curve, every point on the
interior of that closed curve
is also in the region.
Right?
So it is also simply
connected.
OK.
So we had two so far that
were simply connected.
They were different looking
regions, but ultimately they
both had any closed curve-- the
interior of it-- was all
contained in the region that
we were interested in.
So now the third one we have is
somewhat similar-looking to
part b, except that what's
in the square
root is a little different.
So now we can use exactly
the same logic as what
we did in part b.
And what we see is by the exact
same logic that this
vector field will be defined and
differentiable as long as
x squared plus y squared
minus 1 is positive.
Because that's where the
square root function is
differentiable, and that's also
where 1 divided by the
square root of this
thing is defined.
So they correspond to exactly
the same regions.
And that is x squared plus
y squared greater than 1.
So if you think about that, what
we did previously was we
had x squared plus y squared
less than 1.
So obviously if you want x
squared plus y squared greater
than 1, we're taking all the (x,
y) pairs that are outside
the unit circle.
So again, we take
We don't include the unit
circle, because that's where x
squared plus y squared
equals 1.
And then we want all of the
values outside of that region.
So this extends off
to infinity.
All of the values outside
of that region.
Now, is this region
simply connected?
It is not.
And the point is that while you
do have some curves, that
if I take a closed curve, all of
the points on the interior
of that closed curve
are in the region.
There are some curves for
which that's not true.
For example, if I take the
circle of radius--
what does that look like--
2, 1 1/2, something like that?
If I look at all of
the points on the
interior of this curve--
I'm going to try and shade
it without getting rid of
everything, so you can see
still what's behind--
if I look at all those points,
notice in particular, there
are a bunch of points-- for
instance, this one here, this
one here, and this one here--
all the ones inside the unit
circle, are on the interior of
this curve, but they're not in
the region.
Right?
I'll shade it extra dark.
All the points that are in here,
that are inside the unit
circle, are actually still on
the interior of this curve,
but they're not in the region.
And while there are some curves
for which everything on
the inside is in the region, but
there are some curves for
which it's not true, and that
is what we know about
not-simply connectedness.
So we know this one is
not simply connected.
OK.
So now we have one left.
And the last one was i plus j,
times natural log of x squared
plus y squared.
So in this vector field, what
I'm really interested in is
the behavior of this function
natural log of x
squared plus y squared.
And the point I want to make is
that natural log is defined
as long as the input value
is positive, and it is
differentiable everywhere
it's defined.
And so this function will
be both defined and
differentiable as long as x
squared plus y squared is
greater than 0.
So it's defined for all of these
values, and natural log
is differentiable everywhere
it's defined.
So it's also differentiable
for all of these values.
And so we see that this vector
field is defined and
differentiable everywhere
except at one point.
And so let me draw--
this is zooming in showing that
it's missing that point--
I want to make it extra large.
But it's really only
missing one point.
And what point is that?
That point is the origin.
So everywhere except
the origin.
Maybe I should make it smaller,
because maybe it
looks like it's missing
a whole circle.
It's just missing the point.
It's just missing the origin.
But every other point on the xy
plane is a place where this
vector field is differentiable
and defined.
Right?
So it's only missing that one
point, but that still gives us
the fact that this region
is not simply connected.
And again, it's exactly the
same type of logic as the
previous problem, that I could
draw curves, where every point
on the interior is contained
in the region.
But there are curves
that also fail.
Right?
If I draw a curve that contains
the origin, every
point on the interior of this
region except the origin, is
contained in the domain
of interest, right?
But because the interior of the
curve contains the origin,
I know that this region is, in
fact, not simply connected.
So if I look at all of R2--
so if I look at all the x- and
y-values except x equals 0 and
y equals 0, except
the origin--
I get a region that's not
simply connected.
And this one is maybe a little
tricky, so I'm going to say it
one more time.
OK?
So while there are some curves
that we can see some portions
of this region behave like
simply connected regions, when
you're around the origin, any
curve you take around the
origin is going to contain the
origin on its interior.
Right?
But the origin is not in our
domain of interest. And
therefore, there are curves that
we can take that their
interior contains a point that's
not in the region.
And that's what it means to
be not simply connected.
OK?
So let me go back to the
beginning and just remind you
again real quickly
what we did here.
We had these four
vector fields.
We wanted to do two things
with all of them.
We wanted to first find the
regions where they were
defined and differentiable, and
then determine if those
regions were simply connected.
And so we had two examples
where the
regions were simply connected.
And then I gave you two examples
where the regions
were not simply connected.
And so hopefully this was
informative for how we can
understand that vector fields
are not necessarily always
defined everywhere, but also to
understand what this simply
connected region term
actually means.
And I guess that's
where I'll stop.