PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
Today what I'd like to do is
work on using Riemann sums to
approximate definite
integrals.
So, what we're going to do first
is I'm going to let you
work on the problem.
So, let me state the problem.
I'll give you a little
time to work on it.
And then I'll come back.
So the problem is
the following.
We want to use four subintervals
and left
endpoints to approximate the
following definite integral:
the integral from minus 1 to
3 of the function x cubed.
And I've drawn a rough sketch
of what x cubed, y equals x
cubed looks like to help you
out as the starting point.
So why don't you use the four
subintervals and left
endpoints to approximate the
definite integral, then I'll
come back and show
you how I do it.
OK, welcome back.
So what we want to do again,
is use Riemann sums to
approximate this defnite
integral.
And I've given you the
specifications of four
subintervals and
left endpoints.
So I'm going to draw what these
four subintervals and
their left endpoints are going
to give us on the graph.
Then we're going to calculate
what the actual value is of
this estimate.
And then I'll show you a way
you can write it in some
different notation.
So let me actually find
some blue chalk.
Excuse me.
So, using blue chalk I'm going
to show you where the four
subintervals and the
left endpoints.
So it's minus 1 to 3, so I've
conveniently done it so we
have every unit length is one
of the seven intervals.
They're all unit length.
And if I want left endpoints,
then my rectangle's heights,
if you remember, are going to be
the output at the left side
of the interval.
So I'm going to designate the
left interval's outputs.
And what do we have here?
I'm going to now draw rectangles
of those, using
those with the one side on
x-axis and one side at the
height of the left
endpoint output.
So there's one rectangle.
Oh, I almost did something
wrong here.
This left endpoint's rectangle
has no height.
Because the left endpoint's
value is 0.
The output is 0.
There's another rectangle.
And there's the last
rectangle.
So, to designate everything
carefully, I will call this
value y0, the output
value here y0.
This value will be y1.
The output value here
will be y2.
And to show exactly what do I
mean by output value, here I
have enough room to write
the height is really
what it is, is y3.
So y0, y1, y2 and y3 designate
the heights of these four
rectangles.
And the length of each
rectangle, if you remember, is
really what we designate
as delta x.
So this right here is delta x.
And in this case delta x is
each time equal to 1.
So, remember formally, what we
want to do is, if we want to
find this definite integral, we
want to find the area under
the curve between the x-axis
and the function x cubed.
And remember this
is sined area.
So anything below the x-axis
has a negative sign
associated to it.
Anything above the x-axis
has a positive sign
associated to it.
So, when I'm trying to determine
this, when I'm
trying to do an estimate, I'm
finding the areas of these
rectangles.
So my first approximation that
I've given here, is we want
the four subintervals and
the left endpoints.
What we really need is this
delta x, which is the base,
times the height, which is y0,
y1, y2 and y3 of each of these
rectangles.
So, to write it carefully--
well I guess this won't be the
most careful way we write it--
but I have the base, which is
delta x in each case, times y0
plus y1 plus y2 plus y3.
And the only thing I have to be
careful of is that the area
of the rectangle here
will be negative.
But how do I pick that up?
I pick that up because
this y0 value as an
actual output is negative.
So that actually will be picked
up automatically by the
value of the output
on the function.
So let's evaluate these things.
y0 should be the value
of the function at x
equal negative 1.
When x is negative 1, the
function, remember, is x
cubed, so I get negative
1 cubed, which is
just negative 1.
So delta x is 1.
y0 is negative 1.
y1 is the value the function at
x equals 0, because my left
endpoints are minus
1, 0, 1 and 2.
So the second one is
0 is the input.
at x equals 0 I get
0 as an output.
The y2 is going to be this
third left endpoint.
That's at x equal 1.
1 cubed is 1.
So I get a 1 there.
And then, the third left
endpoint, I had
minus 1, 0, 1, 2.
So the third left
endpoint is 2.
2 cubed is 8.
And so y3 is 8.
Hopefully the subscripts here
didn't confuse you because I
actually was very close to
having the subscripts
represent the x value.
But that's not in fact what
the subscripts are doing.
The subscripts are just
representing what interval we
are looking at.
So the four intervals are
designated by 0, 1, 2 and 3.
So I get, when I put this all
together I get 1 times--
well, minus 1 plus 1 is 0--
1 times 8.
So I get 8.
And if I wanted to look at
the picture, how is that
represented?
Well this rectangle has
base 1 and height 8.
So that has area 8.
This rectangle is actually
a square.
It has base 1, height 1.
And this one is also a square.
But because it's below, it has a
minus sign associated to it,
when I think about it
in terms of area.
So I get minus 1
plus 1 plus 8.
And that's where the
8 comes from.
Now if I wanted to write this in
terms of a Riemann sum, you
see them sometimes written
in this way.
You can think about it in a
formal sum in this way.
You've probably seen
this in the lecture
videos more like this.
The sum from i equals 0 to 3
of f of x sub i delta x.
And now, in this case, we could
even be more deliberate
if we wanted to.
And we could let x sub i be
designated by some value.
We could say, starting at
negative 1 and adding some
number to it each time based
on the interval.
But this is sort of the easiest
way to write out what
we're interested in.
And then the x sub i's are
going to be designated
separately.
We can write x sub 0 is
equal to minus 1 x sub
1 is equal to 0.
x sub 2 is equal to-- sorry,
not minus 1-- is
equal to plus 1.
An x sub 3 is equal to 2.
So in that case, that's what
we would get there.
And we could write it
in that way and then
get the same values.
So I think I will stop there.