PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video, what we'd like to
do is find the volume of a
paraboloid--
this one that I've drawn
on the board--
using what we know about Riemann
sums and integrals.
And so, this paraboloid, just so
you understand, what we do
is we take the curve y equals
x squared and we rotate it
around the y-axis.
And we're looking in particular,
from height, the
height of capital H. So from 0
to capital H, that's what our
y value is ranging over.
And what we'd like to do is find
the volume enclosed by
the rotation of y equals x
squared around the y-axis.
So what I'd like you to do is
to think about how you could
write the volume
as an integral.
And I would suggest that you
think about integrating in the
y variable as opposed
to the x variable.
So we're going to do it
in the y variable.
So I'll give you a little while
to think about that.
Start as a Riemann sum, take
it to an integral, and then
I'll come back and show
you how I did it.
OK, welcome back.
So again, what we're trying to
do is find the volume of this
paraboloid.
And we're hoping to write it
as an integral in the end.
So I'm going to give us a little
understanding of how we
start the process.
And what I want to do is break
up this paraboloid first, into
our first-best guess.
And I'm going to estimate the
volume using four different--
I'm breaking it up into
four pieces, so
I'll use four cylinders.
So let me actually just
draw these cylinders.
So I'm going to start
at the top radius.
And that would maybe be
my first cylinder.
And then the next radius would
be the one down here.
Actually maybe I can
alternate color.
You'd be able to see them
a little better.
The next radius would actually
be this one kind of right here
coming around that way, going
down, so it sticks out a
little bit from there.
Let me just kind of shade
that lightly.
And the next one is using
this cylinder.
So that's our diameter here.
And then the last one--
well, that doesn't
look very even.
But we'll just say that there
are four to keep it with four.
I'll say the last one is
starting right here.
So I don't have to draw
any more pictures.
And the last one is
that cylinder.
So there are four
cylinders here.
This one comes around behind.
There are four cylinders here.
There's the blue one here, a
white one, a red one and
another blue one.
And I can actually estimate the
volume of this paraboloid
by finding the volume
of these cylinders.
So we have to understand
how to find the
volume of the cylinders.
And then what we'd like
to do is to get better
approximations, we're going to
make these cylinders flatter.
So we're going to make
them not as tall.
And then as they get flatter and
flatter and flatter, we're
going to get better and better
estimates of the
paraboloid's volume.
And then in the limit, we will
get the volume of the
paraboloid.
So this again should remind you,
this sounds a lot like
Riemann sums. What we've been
doing with Riemann sums.
You're adding up your estimating
area under the
curve in the case that you've
seen mostly in class.
But maybe this reminds you of
the volume of the pyramid
problem that you saw on
the lecture videos.
So it's very similar
to that idea.
Now let's figure out how we can
write this sum of these
four cylinders in terms of y.
So what do we need to do?
Well, first we're going to
designate the height of the
cylinder as delta y.
That's the change in y.
That does not look like a y.
Let me try that again.
Delta y.
OK.
So each height-- and even though
it doesn't look like
it, we're going to say that
they're evenly divided.
So let's make, in your mind
this one should be a bit
bigger and this one should
be a bit smaller.
So delta y is going
to be a constant.
And then I have to figure
out the radius.
Right?
Well, we know that at
height y the radius
squared is height y.
Right?
r squared equals h.
So what I actually need is that
at height h, or at height
y, the radius is square root y.
Right?
So at height y radius is
the square root of y.
So when I want to look
at the volume of the
cylinder at height y--
I'm using the upper value here--
so at height y, what is
the volume of the cylinder?
We know in general the volume
is equal to pi r squared h.
And so, the height here of the
cylinder-- this is not the
height on the whole thing; this
is the height of that
individual cylinder--
the height of the cylinder
is delta y.
And r is square root y.
So r squared is just y.
So the volume of a single
cylinder is pi y delta y.
So again, we find the volume of
this cylinder by taking the
y value here, multiplying it by
pi and then multiplying it
by delta y.
And I do that for this
one, this one, this
one, and this one.
And then I add them up.
And that's my estimate of
the volume of the whole
paraboloid.
So now what can I do?
Well, again, I mentioned
we can divide into more
subintervals.
And let's say we only divide,
let's say we divide it into n
subintervals. right?
What would this look like?
I'm going to be taking a sum
to find the volume of the
whole thing.
I'm going to take a sum from
i equals 1 to n of
these kinds of things.
Pi, y sub i delta y.
So each y sub i represents the
y value at the different
height where I'm taking
my cylinder.
Now delta y, in this case,
if I divide into n equals
subintervals, delta y
is H divided by n.
And then you can actually
figure out the y
sub i's from that.
The first one would
be H over n.
The second one would be 2H over
n and so on until the top
one would be Hn over
n and you'd have
H as the top height.
So those are the values that
we're ranging over.
And now, as we let n go
to infinity, this
is our Riemann sum.
This is actually going
to be an integral.
Delta y goes to dy.
And let's look at
what happens.
So we get dy here.
We're going to have
an integral.
And what are we actually
evaluating?
We're evaluating the function
pi y at what places?
Well, as delta y goes to 0,
the first value of y sub i
that I get is pushing
down to 0.
And the last value we know is H.
So we're actually taking an
integral from 0 to
H of pi y dy.
And that is the integral
representation of the volume
of the paraboloid.
Now this is a very easy thing to
take an integral on, so you
could actually evaluate
this and find it.
I believe you'll get something
like pi y squared over 2 from
0 to H. So you should get
something like pi over 2
capital H squared.
You can check my math, but
I think that's correct.
So that is actually the volume
of the paraboloid carved out
by this particular curve, y
equals x squared, from, or at
height capital H. So that's
where we'll stop.