PROFESSOR: Hey, we're back.
Today we're going to
do a singular value
decomposition question.
The problem is really simple
to state, find the singular
value decomposition of this
matrix c equals 5, 5, -1, 7.
Hit pause, try it yourself, I'll
be back in a minute and
we can do it together.
All right we're back, now
let's do it together.
Now, I know Professor Strang has
done a couple of these in
lecture, but as he pointed out
there, it's really easy to
make a mistake, so you can never
do enough examples of
finding the SVD.
So, what does the
SVD look like?
What do we want to
end up with?
Well, we want a decomposition c
equals u sigma v transpose.
u and v are going to be
orthogonal matrices, that is,
their columns are orthonormal
sets.
Sigma is going to be a
diagonal matrix with
non-negative entries.
OK, good, so, now how do we
find this decomposition?
Well, we need two
equations, OK?
One is c transpose c is equal to
v, sigma transpose, sigma,
v transpose.
And you get this just by
plugging in c transpose c here
I'm noticing that u transpose
u is 1, since you as an
orthogonal matrix.
Okay, and the second equation
is just noticing that v
transposes v inverse, and moving
it to the other side of
the equation, which is
c v equals u sigma.
OK, so these are the two
equations we need to use to
find v, sigma, and u.
OK, so let's start with
the first one.
Let's compute c transpose c.
So c transpose c is that--
Well if you compute we'll
get a 26, an 18, an
18, and a 74, great.
Now what you notice about this
equation is this is just a
diagonalization of
c transpose c.
So we need to find the
eigenvalues, those will be the
entries of sigma transpose
sigma, and the eigenvectors
which will be the columns
of a v. Okay, good.
So how do we find those?
Well, we look at the determinant
of c transpose c
minus lambda times the identity,
which is the
determinant of 26 minus lambda,
18, 18, and 74--
74 minus lambda, thank you.
Good, OK, and what is
that polynomial?
Well, we get a lambda squared,
now the 26 plus 74 is 100, so
you get minus 100 lambda.
And I'll let you do 26 times
74 minus 18 squared on your
own, but you'll see you get
1,600, and this easily factors
is lambda minus 20 times
lambda minus 80.
So the eigenvalues
are 20 and 80.
Now what are the eigenvectors?
Well, you take c transpose c,
minus 20 times the identity,
and you get 6, 18, 18 and 54.
To find the eigenvector with
eigenvalue 20 we need to find
a vector in the null space
of this matrix.
Note that the second column is
three times the first column,
so our first vector, v1, we
can just take that to be,
well, we could take it to be -3,
1, but we'd like it to be
a unit vector, right?
Remember the columns of v should
be unit vectors because
they're orthonormal.
So 3 squared plus 1 squared is
10, we have to divide by the
square root of 10.
OK, similarly, we do c transpose
c minus 80 times the
identity, we'll get -54, 18, 18,
and -6, and similarly we
can find that v2 will be 1 over
square root of 10, 3 over
the square root of 10.
Great, OK, so what information
do we have now?
we have our v matrix which is
just made up of these two
columns, and we actually have
our signal matrix too, because
the squares of the diagonal
entries of
sigma are 20 and 80.
Good, so let's write those down,
what we have. So we have
v, I just add these vectors
and make them the
columns of my matrix.
Square root of 10, 1 over square
root of 10, 1 over
square root of 10, 3 over square
root of 10, and sigma,
this is just the square roots of
20 and 80, which is just 2
root 5 and 4 root 5 along
the diagonal.
Squeezing it in here, I hope
you all can see these two.
Good, so these are two of the
three parts of my singular
value decomposition.
The last thing I need to find
is u, and for that I need to
use this second equation
right here.
So you need to multiply c times
v, okay, so c is 5, 5,
-1, 7, let's multiply it by v,
1 over root 10, 3 over square
root of 10.
What do we get?
Well, I'll let you work
out the details, but
it's not hard here.
You get -10 over root 10, which
is just negative square
root of 10 here.
Then I just get 2 square root of
10, and then I get, 1 is 2
square root of 10 and --
I think I made an error here.
Give me a second to look through
my computation again.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: The two, one
entry should be--
oh, yes, thank you.
The two, one entry should be
the square root of 10.
Good, yes, that's what I was
hoping, yes, because we get--
Yes, I did it in the wrong
order, right, so your
recitation instructor should
know how to multiply matrices,
great, yes, thank you.
You multiply this first, then
this, then this, and then
this, and if you do it correctly
you will get this
matrix here.
Good, great.
So now I'd like this to be my
u matrix but it's actually u
times sigma, so I need to make
these entries unit length.
OK, so I get -1 over root 2, 1
over root 2, 1 over root 2, 1
over root 2, times my sigma
matrix here, which is
remember, 2 square root of 5, 4
square root of 5, and these
constants are just what I needed
to divide these columns
by in order to make
them unit vectors.
So now, here's my u matrix, 1
over square root of 2, -1 over
square root of 2, 1 over square
root of 2, 1 over
square root of 2, good.
So now I have all three
matrices, u v and sigma and
despite some little errors here
and there, I think this
is actually right.
You should go check it yourself,
because if you at
all like me, you've screwed
up several times by now.
But anyway, this is a good
little illustration of how to
find the singular value
decomposition.
Recall that you're looking for
u sigma v transpose where u
and v are orthogonal matrices,
and sigma is diagonal with
non-negative entries.
And you find it using these two
equations, you compute c
transpose c, that's v sigma
transfer sigma times v
transpose, and you also
have c v is u's sigma.
I hope this was a helpful
illustration.