Welcome back to recitation.
In this video I'd like us
to work on the following
application for spherical
coordinates.
So what I'd like us to do is
find the gravitational
attraction of an upper solid
half sphere of radius a and
center o, that's the
gravitational attraction on a
mass m naught at o.
So the m naught is sitting at o,
we have a solid half sphere
of radius a and center o,
and we want to find the
gravitational attraction of the
half sphere on the mass.
And we're going to assume that
the density delta is equal to
the square root of x squared
plus y squared.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a little while to
work on it, and when you feel
good about your solution bring
the video back up, I'll
show you what I did.
OK.
Welcome back.
Again what we're going to do
is we're going to do an
application problem.
And what we have is we have
the solid half sphere of
radius a and center o, and we
want to know the gravitational
attraction of it on
a mass m naught.
So the first thing I'm going to
do is draw a picture, just
so I can get myself oriented.
The easiest thing to do--
obviously, when I'm going to
try and figure this out, I'm
going to use spherical
coordinates.
I have an upper solid half
sphere, so that should tell me
spherical coordinates
will be good.
And the easiest way to deal with
spherical coordinates is
obviously to choose o
to be the origin.
So I'm going to have m naught
sitting right at the origin.
And then I'm going to have--
oops, I should write that
somewhere else.
Maybe, well, I'll just leave it
there-- and then I'm going
to have the solid half sphere,
which I'm going to just draw
sort of like this.
Maybe that doesn't look
like a sphere to you.
But we have the solid half
sphere and it's exerting a
force on m naught.
And if I want to know the force,
how we denote the force
in lecture was the components
were the x component of the
force, the y component of
the force, and the z
component of the force.
And so I want to point out
these are not partial
derivatives.
This is the standard notation
you use for force in this
case, and so these are not
the partial derivatives.
They're just the x
component, the y
component, and the z component.
And if you notice, this upper
solid half sphere--
because of where m naught is--
the x component and the y
component of the force are 0
based on symmetry.
So all I really need to worry
about is the z component.
I'm only really interested in
one component of the force and
it's the z component.
Because the other two are going
to be 0, just by the
symmetry of this solid
half sphere.
So I really only need
the z component.
So what I have to do in order
to calculate the force is I
have to figure out the magnitude
and the direction.
So let's write down the
two components.
These were given to
you in class.
So the magnitude is going to
be equal to G m naught dm
divided by rho squared.
So this was given to you
in class already.
So G is some constant; m naught
is the mass you have;
dm, we have to determine a
little bit about it; and then
we're dividing by rho squared.
And the direction--
because I'm only interested
in the z component--
the direction is just z, but
then I want to make sure that
the direction component
is z divided by rho.
The full direction is x, y, z
divided by rho but I'm only
interested in that
last component.
So the z component is
just z over rho.
If that confused you, I just
want to remind you that you
had x, y, z over rho is the full
direction of the force,
we're just pulling off
the z component.
So what we're going to be trying
to figure out-- we need
to integrate the product of
these two things but I need to
figure out what dm
actually is.
So let me remind you also what
dm is and then we'll put it
all together.
dm, to remind you, is supposed
to be the density times dV.
And the density in this case was
square root of x squared
plus y squared, that's
just equal to r.
So it's just r dV. So there's
a bunch of little pieces and
now I have to put
them together.
So if I want to determine the
full attraction in the z
direction, because the other two
are 0, I just need to do
this triple integral.
I'll figure out my bounds
momentarily.
I'm going to leave a lot of
room to write my bounds
because I always run
out of room.
And then I just need to
integrate G m naught divided
by rho squared times z divided
by rho times r dV.
Actually I won't even do the
bounds yet because I have to
change everything into
polar coordinates.
So let's figure out
how to do that.
What is z in polar coordinates?
z in polar
coordinates we know
is rho cosine phi.
So I'm going to have
a G m naught--
I'm going to keep this rho
cubed right here--
and then I'm going to have
a rho cosine phi.
r is rho sine phi, so I'll just
put another rho, and then
a sine phi.
And then dV is rho squared sine
phi d rho d phi d theta.
So what I'm going
to do here is--
I have to add in a rho
squared, so I'm just
going to cube this.
And another sine phi, so I'm
going to square that.
And then I'm going to have
a d rho d phi d theta.
Hopefully that wasn't
too scary.
But the z is my rho
cosine phi.
The r is a single
rho sine phi.
And then dV includes a rho
squared sine phi, so I put a
cubed here and a squared here,
and then d rho d phi d theta.
So now I just have to integrate,
so I have to figure
out my bounds.
So we're integrating
first in rho.
And rho, it's a sphere- a
half sphere of radius a.
It's a solid half sphere.
So I'm just integrating
from 0 up to a.
And then phi--
because it's a solid half
sphere-- phi is starting at 0
and it's going down until
it hits the x-y plane.
And so that's pi over 2.
We know we start at 0, we go
to pi over 2 when we go a
quarter turn, basically.
When we go 90 degrees, right?
So we go 0 to pi over 2, and
then theta-- once I've taken
my rho and I've gone up as far
as I can, and I've gone down
this way, I have to rotate
it all the way around--
and so theta is actually
going from 0 to 2 pi.
All right.
So this is my full integral
I have here.
And now let's do some
simplifying before we integrate.
Notice I have a rho cubed in the
denominator here and a rho
cubed in the numerator there.
So when I integrate in rho, I
only have this single rho.
When I integrate that rho,
everything else is fixed.
So I integrate that rho, I get
a rho squared over 2, and I
evaluate it at 0 and a and so I
get an a squared over 2, as
integrating this part.
I'm going to pull all that to
the front and then write what
I get next.
Let me write what I get next.
I'm going to have a G m
naught as a constant.
I'm going to be multiplying
by a squared over 2
from the rho integral.
And then I have 2
more integrals.
Integral from 0 to 2 pi.
And the integral from 0 to pi
over 2 of cosine phi sine
squared phi d phi d theta.
So how do I integrate
this in phi?
Looks like it's going to be
sine cubed phi over 3.
Let me just double check.
The derivative of that is 3 sine
squared phi cosine phi.
Yes.
So, this is going to be sine
cubed phi over 3 evaluated at
0 and pi over 2.
This inner part is.
And so let's see what
we get there.
Sine of 0 is 0.
Sine of pi over 2 is 1.
So I just pick up a 1/3
from this integral.
So now I'm going to pull
that out in front.
So again, the thing I've written
down here is just the
integral of this.
So I just get a 1/3
out of that.
Let me double check.
Yep, sine of pi over
2 is still 1.
Good.
So I get a 1/3 out of that.
That's a constant.
So I'll pull that
to the front.
And then notice what
I'm left with.
I'm just integrating 0
to 2 pi of d theta.
Well that's just 2 pi.
So I've got a 1/3 from the
inside one, times a 2 pi from
the outside one.
So I just end up getting
2 pi times--
or 2 pi over 3, because
there's my 1/3 also--
times G m naught a
squared over 2.
And if I simplify that, I
just get G m naught a
squared pi over 3.
And so if I want to know the
force of this solid half
sphere acting on the mass m
naught, where the mass is
positioned at the center of
the base of the solid half
sphere, it's going to be exactly
the following thing.
By symmetry, the first two
components are 0 and the last
component is this G m naught
a squared pi over 3.
And so that's my
final solution.
Let me just take us back and
remind us where we came from.
So we wanted to find the force,
the gravitational
attraction of this solid half
sphere that had a radius a,
was centered at o, and had
mass m not sitting at o.
And so we were interested
in drawing the
easiest picture possible.
We're going to put o
at the origin, so m
naught's at the origin.
Then we have a solid half
sphere of radius a.
So this is--
you know, if I come all
the way out, my
radius length is a.
And I gave you the density
was equal to r.
So we know the force we're
interested in is f sub x, f
sub y, f sub z.
From the picture alone, we see
f sub x and f sub y are 0.
So we really only need
the z component.
So you know how to find the
magnitude and you know how to
find the direction of
the vector field.
The reason that you've divided
by rho here, just to remind
you, is that the direction you
want it to be a unit vector.
And so this is what makes
it a unit vector.
And so the direction
part that I'm
interested in is the z part.
So it's z over rho.
And so all I need to do is take
the z over rho, multiply
it by the magnitude, and replace
the dm by what it is
in terms of the volume form.
And in terms of the volume form,
it's the density times
dV and so in this case
it's just r dV.
So I made all those
substitutions.
And then all I had to do is
do a lot of replacement.
And that was kind of the messy
part, and then the integral's
fairly easy.
So the messy part is z I
replaced by rho cosine phi.
r I replaced by rho sine phi.
And dV I replaced by rho
squared sine phi
d rho d phi d theta.
And then I just have to figure
out what the bounds are for
the half sphere, solid
half sphere.
And then I integrate.
And the integration is all
ultimately one step at a time,
single variable.
And they were all fairly
simple integrals.
So in the end, we see that your
mass m not sitting at the
origin, the force exerted on it
by this solid half sphere
is 0, 0 comma G times m
naught times a squared
pi divided by 3.
All right, that's
where I'll stop.