CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
work on the following problem
that has to do with tangent
planes and approximations.
So we know that a rectangle--
we'll say a rectangle has
sides x and y, and we know that
to find the area of the
rectangle then, we just take x
times y, and I would like us
to approximate the area
for x equal to 2.1
and y equal to 2.8.
And obviously, with this type of
equation, it's not hard to
just compute this, but I'd like
us to use the tangent
plane approximation to determine
the value, and then
we'll compare it to the actual
value, just to give us an idea
of how we can use the tangent
plane to approximate things.
And obviously, I'd like to
do this near x equal
2 and y equal 3.
So when you're doing your
tangent plane approximation,
do the approximation at x
equal 2 and y equal 3.
And then when you're done with
that, I would like you to
answer this question.
So near x equal 2 and
y equal 3, which
has the greater effect?
A change in x or an
equal change in y?
So if I change by x in the same
value as I change by y,
which will have the
greater impact?
So why don't you pause the tape,
work on the problems,
and when you're ready to see how
I do them, bring it back
up, and I'll come back
and show you.
OK, welcome back.
So we're going to work on this
problem, and as I mentioned,
the first thing we want to
do is do a tangent plane
approximation near x equal
2 and y equal 3.
So let me write down what we're
going to need in order
to do that.
First, we'll remind ourselves
that in this case, what I'm
going to approximate is the area
function for a rectangle,
which is A of x, y is
equal to x times y.
So that's the function I'm going
to be approximating.
And now the actual
approximation, the tangent
plane approximation, has
the following form.
So we know A of x, y
is approximately--
well, it's going to be the area
evaluated at the point
I'm interested in, which we
said was 2 comma 3, right,
plus the x-derivative of area
evaluated at 2 comma 3 times
the change in x.
And the change in x is where
x is now versus where we
started, which is
at x equal 2.
And then the same thing
in terms of y.
So you do the y-derivative
evaluated at 2 comma 3, and
then you do the change in y.
And since we started at y equals
3, the change in y is y
minus 3, OK?
So now we obviously need to fill
in three quantities here.
The three things we need to
evaluate: area evaluated at 2,
3, its x-derivative evaluated at
2, 3, and its y-derivative
evaluated at 2, 3.
So let me just point
out what we have.
Area evaluated at 2, 3, well,
that's just 2 times 3, which
we can do, so that's 6.
That's pretty easy.
Now A sub x, so the derivative
of the area function with
respect to x.
The derivative of the area
function with respect
to x is just y.
y in that case we treat
as a constant.
We take this derivative.
We just get y back.
And so, A sub x evaluated at 2,
3 is going to be y, which y
here is 3, so we get A sub
x is equal to 3 at 2, 3.
In a similar vein, we can
immediately look and see that
A sub y evaluated at 2,
3 is going to be 2.
And the reason for that, of
course, is if we look back
here, the derivative of A with
respect to y is x, so
evaluating it at 2,
3 gives us 2.
OK.
So now we just have to
fill everything in.
So my tangent plane
approximation now says I get 6
plus 3 times x minus 2 plus
2 times y minus 3.
And what I wanted was the
area at 2.1 comma 2.8.
So if I fill in those values for
x and y-- so 2.1 is x and
2.8 is y-- if I fill those in,
I get that this is equal to--
well, I'll keep writing
approximately just to be safe--
is 6 plus 3 times--
well, 2.1 minus 2 gives me a
0.1 there and 2 times 2.8
minus 3 gives me a negative 0.2
there, so I get a negative
0.4, I get a positive 0.3,
so together this
is a negative 0.1.
6 minus 0.1 gives me 5.9.
So the area based on
the approximation
is 5.9 square units.
And, in actuality, if you
multiply it out, I think you
get something like 5.88, so
the approximation is very
good, right?
We're close to 2, 3 and that is
one of the reasons we can
know it's going to be very,
it should be very good.
It should be pretty good, OK?
Now, I just have to answer the
second part of the question.
So let me remind us what
the second part was.
It was near x equal 2
and y equal 3, which
has a greater effect?
A change in x or an
equal change in y?
And to do that, it's really
easiest to come back and look
at maybe this line.
I'll underline this
line right here.
Actually, I'll box it, OK?
This value will represent
the change in x.
So we started at 2, and we
go somewhere, and that'll
represent the change in x.
This value represents
the change in y.
So if we look at which has a
greater impact near 2, 3, if
my change in x and my change in
y are equal, then obviously
this term has a bigger impact,
because there's a 3.
The coefficient here is 3 and
the coefficient here is 2.
And so the point is, changes
in x will have a greater
effect than changes in y.
And what this corresponds to
pictorially is if we make a
slice where we keep y constant
and we look at the curve in
the xz-plane, that corresponds
to the fact that the
derivative in the xz-plane of
the curve there is more
significant-- the curve there
has a steeper derivative--
than if I kept the x-value
fixed and I looked in the
yz-plane and I looked
at the curve there.
So the sort of one-dimensional
picture is that the derivative
of a curve in the x-direction,
keeping y fixed, is steeper
than the derivative of the
curve in the y-direction,
keeping x fixed.
So maybe hopefully that wasn't
more confusing than
it should have been.
From here, you can see it right
away, but that's sort of
the picture of it as well.
So I think that's
where I'll stop.