When I expose material to an
external magnetic field,
then we learned last time that
the field inside that material
is modified.
And we expressed that in terms
of an equation,
that the field inside the
material is kappa of M,
which is called the relative
permeability,
times the external field,
and I will refer to that all
the
time as the vacuum field.
And when we have diamagnetic
material, kappa M is just a hair
smaller than one;
with paramagnetic material,
it is a hair larger than one;
but when we have ferromagnetic
material it can be huge.
It can be thousands,
ten thousands,
and even higher.
Now in the case of para- and
ferromagnetic material,
the kappa of M is the result of
the fact that the intrinsic
dipoles of the atoms and the
molecules are
going to be aligned by the
external field.
And today I want to raise the
question, how large can the
magnetic dipole moment of a
single atom be?
And then comes the logical
question, how strong can we
actually, then,
have a field inside
ferromagnetic material?
That means if we were able to
align all the dipole moments of
all the atoms,
what is the maximum that we can
achieve?
To calculate the magnetic
dipole
moment of an atom,
you have to do some quantum
mechanics, and that's beyond the
scope of this course.
And so I will derive it in a
classical way,
and then at the very end I will
add a little pepper and salt,
which is quantum mechanics,
just to make the result right.
But it can be done in a
classical way,
and it can give you a very
good, good idea.
If I have a hydrogen atom,
which has a proton at the
center, has a charge plus E -- E
is the charge of the electron
but this is the plus charge.
And let this have an orbit
R, circular orbit.
And the electron here E,
I'll give it the minus sign to
make sure that you know that
it's negative.
Say the electron goes around in
this direction.
This is the velocity of the
electron.
That means that of course the
current around the proton would
then be in this direction.
If an electron goes like this,
the current goes like that,
that's just by convention.
The mass of an electron -- you
should know that by now -- is
approximately nine point one
times ten to the minus
thirty-one kilograms.
The charge of the electron,
one point six times ten to the
minus nineteen coulombs.
And the radius of the orbit in
a hydrogen atom -- it's often
called the Bohr radius,
by the way -- is approximately
five times ten to the minus
eleven meters.
We're going to need these
numbers.
That's why I write them down
for you.
If you look at this current
running around the proton,
it's really a current which the
current, say,
goes in this direction.
And here is that proton --
trying to make you see three
dimensionally.
Then it creates a magnetic
field in this direction,
and so the magnetic dipole
moment mu is up.
And the magnitude of that
magnetic dipole moment,
as we learned last time,
is simply this current I times
the area A of this current loop.
Now the area A is trivial
to calculate.
That's pi R square,
R being the radius of the
orbit.
And so A, that's the easiest,
is pi R squared.
And if I use my five times ten
to the minus eleven,
then I find that this area is
eight times ten to the minus
twenty-one square meters.
So that's easy.
But now comes the question,
what is I?
What is the current?
So now we have to do a
little bit more work.
And we have to combine our
knowledge of,
uh eight oh two with our
knowledge of eight oh one.
If this electron goes around,
the reason why it goes around
is that the proton and the
electron attract each other.
And so there is a force in this
direction.
And we know that force,
that's the Coulomb force.
It's an electric force.
That force is this charge times
this charge, so that's E
squared, divided by our famous
four pi
epsilon zero,
and then we have to divide it
by the radius squared.
So that's Coulomb's Law.
But from eight oh one,
from Newtonian mechanics,
we know that this is what we
call the centripetal force that
holds it in orbit,
so to speak,
and that is M V squared,
M being the mass of the
electron, V being the speed of
the electron,
and V squared divided by R.
And so this allows me to
calculate
as a first step,
before we get into the current,
what the velocity of this
electron is.
It's phenomenal.
It's an incredible speed.
So V then becomes -- I lose one
R -- so I get the square root,
I get an E squared upstairs
here, my M goes downstairs,
I have four pi epsilon zero,
and I have here an R.
And I know all these numbers.
I know what E is,
I know what capital R is,
I know what four pi epsilon
zero is --
one over four pi epsilon zero
is the famous nine to the power
-- nine times ten to the power
nine.
And so I can calculate what V
is.
And if I stick in the numbers
and if I did not make a mistake,
then I find about two point
three times ten to the six
meters per second.
It's an immensely high speed,
five million miles per hour.
If this were a straight line,
you would make it to the moon
in three minutes.
Five million miles per hour
this electron goes around the
proton.
Now I have to go to the
current.
I have to find out what the
current is.
So the question that I'm going
to ask now is how long does it
take for this electron to go
around.
Well, that time,
capital T, is of course the
circumference of my circle
divided by the speed of the
electron.
Trivial.
Even the high school students
in my audience will understand
that one, I hope.
And so I know what two pi R is,
because I know R and I know V
and so I can calculate that
time, just by sticking in the
numbers.
And I find that it is about one
point one four times ten to the
minus sixteen seconds.
Just imagine how small that
time is.
You cannot even -- we cannot
even imagine what it's like.
It goes ten to the sixteen
times per second around,
because it has this huge speed.
The one point one four times
ten to the minus sixteen really
should have been one point four
times ten to the minus sixteen.
Of course, it doesn't make much
difference, but in case you
substitute in the
numbers, it is one point four
times ten to the minus sixteen.
Now, we still haven't found the
current, but we're almost there.
Because when you look here,
there is this electron going
by, and every one point one four
ten to the minus sixteen
seconds, that electron goes by.
So the current I,
that's the definition of
current, is the charge per unit
time.
And so every capital T seconds,
the charge E goes by,
and so this is
per definition the current.
And so this current,
then, that you have,
which is simply due to the
electron going around the
proton, is about one point one
times ten to the minus three
amperes.
And that is mind-boggling.
A milliampere.
One electron going around a
proton represents a current of a
milliampere.
And now of course I have the
magnetic moment mu,
that is I times A.
We already calculated A,
and now we also have the
current I, and so we now get
that mu is approximately nine
point three, if you put in all
the decimals correctly,
times ten to the minus
twenty-four, and the unit is of
course amperes square meters.
This is area,
and this is current.
This A has nothing to do with
that A, hey.
This is amperes.
Be careful.
And this is square meters.
But these are the units.
And this has a name.
This is called the Bohr
magneton.
Bohr magneton.
What we cannot understand with
our knowledge now,
but you can if you ever take
quantum mechanics,
that the magnetic moment of all
electrons in orbit can only be a
multiple of this number,
nothing in between.
Quantum mechanics,
the word says it is
quantization.
It's not in between.
It's either or.
It includes even zero,
which is even harder to
understand, that it could even
be zero.
In addition to a dipole moment
due to the electron going around
the proton, the electron itself
is a charge which spins about
its own axis,
and that also means that a
charge is going around on the
spinning scale of the electron.
And that magnetic dipole moment
is always this value.
And so the net magnetic dipole
moment of an atom or a molecule
is now the vectorial sum of all
these
dipole moments,
all these electrons going
around, means orbital dipole
moments, and you have to add
these spin dipoles.
Some of these pair each other
out.
One electron would have its
dipole moment in this direction
and the other in this direction,
and then the vectorial sum is
zero.
The net result is that most
atoms and molecules have dipole
moments which are either one
Bohr magneton or two Bohr
magnetons.
That is very common.
And that's what I will need
today to discuss with you how
strong a field
we can create if we align all
those magnetic dipoles.
The magnetic field that is
produced inside a material when
I expose it to an external
field, that magnetic field B is
the vacuum field that I can
create with a solenoid -- we
will discuss that further today
-- plus the field which I will
call B prime which is that
magnetic field that is the
result of the fact that
we're going to align these
dipoles.
The external field wants to
align these dipoles,
and the degree of success
depends on the strength of the
external field and of course on
the temperature.
If the temperature is low,
it's easier to align them,
because there is less thermal
agitation.
If, and that's a big if --
today you will see why it's a
big if -- if B prime is linearly
proportional to B vacuum,
if that is the case -- today
you
will see that there are
situations where that's not the
case -- then I can write down
that B prime equals xi of M --
we called that last lecture the
magnetic susceptibility -- times
B vacuum.
The linear proportionality
constant.
If I can do that,
then of course B is also
proportional to B vacuum because
now I can write down that B is
one plus
xi M times B vacuum.
And that, for that we write
kappa of M times B vacuum,
which is the equation that I
started out with today.
And so that is only a
meaningful equation if the sum
of the alignment of all these
dipoles can be written as being
linearly proportional with the
external field.
And this is what I want to
explore today in more detail.
With paramagnetic material,
there is never any worry that
the linearity doesn't hold.
But with ferromagnetic
material, that is not the case,
because with ferromagnetic
material, it is relatively easy
to align these dipoles,
because they already group in
domains, as we discussed last
time, and the domains flip in
unison.
And so with ferromagnetic
material, as you will see today,
we can actually go into what we
call
saturation, that all the
dipoles are aligned in the same
direction.
And now the question is,
how strong would that field be?
I'm going to make a rough
calculation that gives you a
pretty good feeling for the
numbers.
It depends on what material you
have.
I will choose a material
whereby the magnetic dipole
moment is two Bohr magnetons,
so this is -- I told you it's
either one or two or three,
I pick one for
which it is two.
And I have them all aligned.
So I take the situation that
they're all aligned.
So here is the current going
around the nucleus,
here's another one,
here's another one.
This is a solid material,
so these atoms or these
molecules are nicely packed.
And here we see all these
currents going around,
and all these magnetic dipole
moments are nicely aligned.
And so these magnetic fields
are supporting each other.
And the question now is,
what is the magnetic field
inside here?
Well, that's an easy
calculation, because this really
looks like a solenoid,
like you have windings,
and you have a current going
around.
And you remember,
or should remember,
that if we have a solenoid and
we run a current through a
solenoid that the magnetic field
in the solenoid is mu zero --
this mu zero is not this mu,
this mu zero is the same one
that -- oh no,
it's no- we don't have it on
the blackboard.
You know, that's the famous
four pi times ten to the minus
seven.
And then we have the current I,
and then we have N,
if that's the number of
windings that we have in the
solenoid, and then we have L,
which is the length of the
solenoid.
So this is the number of
windings of the solenoid per
unit length, the number of
windings per meter.
So if we could figure out,
with this arrangement,
what this
quantity is,
then we're in business.
I take a material,
which is not unreasonable,
whereby the number density of
atoms, I call that capital N,
written in the subscript way,
is about ten to the
twenty-nine.
So this is atoms or molecules,
whatever may be the case,
per cubic meter.
That's not unreasonable.
And now I have to somehow
manipulate, massage the
mathematics, so that I get in
here this magnetic
moment, this Bohr magneton.
The two Bohr magnetons.
And there are several ways of
doing that.
I have chosen one way,
and that's the following.
I take here a length of one
meter.
So this is a solenoid,
and I take only one meter.
Could have taken three or five
meters, makes no difference.
I take one meter.
And each one of these loops
here has an area A.
So we would agree,
I hope, that the area --
that the volume,
the volume of this solenoid --
this has a length one meter --
that that volume is A square
meters times one.
And so the volume is A cubic
meters.
A times one meter is A cubic
But the number of atoms per
cubic meter is ten to the
twenty-ninth,
and so the number of atoms that
I
have in this solenoid per meter
is this A times that N.
So this is the number of
windings, if I call this one
winding, the number of windings
per meter.
Or you can think of it the
number of atoms per meter,
the way they're lined up.
And so now I am in business,
because this now is my N
divided by L.
And so I can write now mu zero
times
the current I times that area A
times N, which is ten to the
twenty-nine.
But look now.
Now you see why I did it this
way, because I times A is the
magnetic dipole moment of my
atoms.
And that was two Bohr
magnetons.
And so this now also equals mu
zero times twice mu Bohr times
N.
And I'm finished,
because I know what mu zero is,
and I know what moo- mu Bohr is
-- we calculated that,
it's still here,
this number -- and I know what
my capital subscript N is,
ten to the twenty-nine atoms
per cubic meter.
And so I just shove those
numbers in my equation,
and I find that this is
approximately two point three
tesla for the numbers that I
have chosen.
It's not for all materials this
way, because I have adopted two
Bohr magnetons for the magnetic
dipole moment of each atom,
and I have adopted a density of
ten
to the twenty-nine atoms per
cubic meter.
And for that situation,
you get two point three tesla.
Now I want to use this number
and understand what's going to
happen in ferromagnetic
material.
I take ferromagnetic material
and I expose it to an external
field, I call it the vacuum
field.
So I stick it in a solenoid and
I can choose the current
through my solenoid.
And I'm going to plot for you
the vacuum field.
This vacuum field is linearly
proportional to the current
through my solenoid.
This is an actual physical
solenoid.
I have a wire,
it goes around like this.
I don't have one here now.
And I run a current through
there.
And that vacuum B field equals
mu zero times I times N divided
by L, except that this N divided
by L is now the number of
windings of my current wire,
and this is the length of my
solenoid.
So don't confuse it with the
one we had there,
because that was on an atomic
scale and this is on a
macroscopic scale.
How many windings you have
could be -- where you had a big
one here in class,
twenty-eight hundred windings,
and we had sixty centimeters
long, and so that's what this
number is all about.
So the moment that I know what
the current is through my
solenoid, I immediately know
what my vacuum field is.
There's a one-to-one
correspondence.
And now I'm going to measure
inside
the ferromagnetic material,
which I stick in the solenoid.
I'm going to measure there the
magnetic field.
And what's going to happen now?
Well, first of all I cannot at
all plot this curve on a
one-to-one scale,
the reason being that kappa of
M for ferromagnetic material is
so large -- let us adopt for now
a number of one thousand,
say.
Or it could be larger,
even.
Let's say kappa of M is one
thousand.
That means that if the magnetic
field in terms of a vector is
this big, one centimeter in the
length of the vector,
that the field inside the
ferromagnetic material is a
thousand times higher.
If this is one centimeter in
length, a thousand times higher
is ten meters.
So this is the length of the
vector
of the magnetic field inside
the ferromagnetic material.
That's why I cannot do it to
scale.
So when I draw this line here,
keep in mind that if I did it
to scale, if I did,
but I can't,
then the tangent of alpha would
be kappa of M,
which in this case would be ten
to the third.
And so this angle alpha is
something like eighty-nine point
nine something degrees.
So I cannot do it to scale.
Keep that in mind.
So in the beginning I get a
nice linear curve,
but now slowly I'm beginning to
reach saturation,
that all these dipoles are
going to be aligned,
and what you're going to see is
that this curve bends over and
bends over and bends over,
and the magnetic field that you
finally achieve here is the
famous two point three tesla,
which I calculated for that
imaginary material,
plus B vacuum.
The two point three is now the
field
which I will call B prime.
This is the field that is the
result of the alignment of all
those dipoles.
And so when I increase the
vacuum field,
this goes into saturation,
and settles for two point three
and can no longer increase,
because I have aligned all
these magnetic dipoles.
And so if your vacuum field is
this strong, then this field is
no longer thousand times
stronger than the vacuum field.
You're no longer in the linear
part.
So you could also think of it
as
kappa of M being smaller than a
thousand.
Whichever way you prefer is
fine.
But it's no longer proportional
to the value of one thousand.
If the temperature is lower of
the material,
it's easier to align them,
and so you will achieve
saturation earlier,
and so your curve would go like
this.
So the curve is also a function
of temperature.
So this is if the temperature
is low relative to this one.
So these curves depend on,
on temperature as well.
The lower the temperature,
the easier it is to align them.
If I reach this point here,
when my B prime goes into
saturation, I can only increase
the field, the B field in the
material, by increasing the
vacuum field,
because B prime is not going to
go up again.
And so I can only get a higher
field by increasing this current
so that this B,
this B vacuum goes up.
And that goes up very slowly,
because this huge magnification
factor of one thousand is gone
now.
So the slow,
it's very slow,
the growth, and that's why you
see that I drew it like this,
that it increases very slowly.
But my plot is not to scale
anyhow.
Now I want to discuss with you
what happens with the material
once I have driven it into
saturation.
What happens if now I change
the current and I make my vacuum
field zero again?
And now you get a very unusual
behavior.
Let me do that here on the
blackboard.
So I'll make a new drawing.
I could have continued with
that one, but let me make a new
one.
So I'm going to do the
following experiment in my head.
I have a solenoid and I run a
current through that solenoid.
And if the current is in
clockwise direction,
my vacuum field will be in this
direction.
And when the current is in
counterclockwise direction,
I will assume that my vacuum
field is in this direction.
So there is ferromagnetic
material in here.
If the current flows in
clockwise direction,
the vacuum field is in this
direction.
If I run it in counterclockwise
direction, the vacuum field is
in that direction.
And here is going to be my
vacuum field.
Easy for me to know what that
is, because if I know the
current
through my solenoid,
this equation will immediately
tell me what the vacuum field
is.
So I have never any problems
with the vacuum field.
I stick a probe in here and I
measure the magnetic field
inside that material.
How we do that is not so easy,
but we can do it.
There are a few things that I
can't tell you.
This is one of them.
So here is the magnetic field
inside the material.
All right, so there we start.
We do the same thing that we
did here.
So we approach the saturation.
But now when I'm here,
I am reducing the current and
go back to zero.
Remember that when we are here,
all these domains that we
discussed last time have all
flipped in the direction of the
vacuum field.
So this field is enormous.
But now I make the current go
back to zero.
And what happens now is I end
up here, at this point P here.
The current now is zero.
There is no current going
through the solenoid.
Notice the vacuum field is
zero.
I can take the material out,
the ferromagnetic material.
The material itself is now
magnetic.
And you see there is a magnetic
field inside it.
Why is that?
Because some of those domains
remain aligned,
so they don't go back.
And so we have created
permanent magnetism.
And so in the location,
at the location P,
we have B vacuum is zero,
but B prime,
which is the result of those
aligned magnetic moments,
is still in this direction.
Nothing is to scale here,
of course.
And so you still have a
magnetic field.
Now I reverse the current.
I go counterclockwise.
So I'm creating a magnetic
field vacuum now in this
direction.
And so now what will happen
with this curve?
I come up here.
And look now here,
at this location Q.
What do I have now?
I have something very bizarre.
I have now a situation whereby
the vacuum field is in this
direction but there is no
magnetic field inside the
material.
The magnetic field inside is
zero.
So when we have point Q,
so we have B vacuum is in this
direction, but B inside,
B prime -- oh no,
it's not B prime,
it's B.
It's the total field inside,
is zero.
The reason being that B prime
is still in this direction.
The reason being that the
domains are still aligned in
this direction,
and so the vacuum field plus
the B prime field,
which has to be vectorially
added, adds up with a net field
zero.
Quite bizarre,
isn't it.
Now I increase the current,
but I keep going
counterclockwise,
and so the magnetic field of
the vacuum remains in this
direction.
I go into saturation again,
in a similar way that I went
into saturation here.
And now I stop here -- OH,
I don't want to lose my brooch.
And now I stop here and I say
to the current,
go back to zero again.
So my current now goes back to
zero.
There we go.
And now I arrive here,
point S.
And again, I have a situation
that my vacuum field is zero.
I could take the material out
of the solenoid,
just walk around with it on the
street.
It will be a permanent magnet.
But now the magnetic field
inside this material in point P
it was in this direction.
If I take it out here,
then it is in this direction.
Now some domains say aligned in
this direction.
The reason was that I had
counterclockwise current,
and so those domains flipped
over.
And they're not all willing to
flip back again.
So I've also made a permanent
magnet here.
Vacuum field zero,
but B prime is now in the
opposite direction.
And then if I continue now to
go clockwise with current again
and increase the current,
I end up there.
And this is a bizarre curve.
We call this the hysteresis
curve.
If you look at this curve,
it's really amazing.
It's actually hard to,
to digest this.
You, you have to give it a
little bit of thought.
Because for one particular
value of the current,
for instance here,
once I have a particular value
of the current,
I know that B vacuum is a
given, I have two possibilities
here for the magnetic field.
And for the current here,
I have two possibilities for
the magnetic field.
And so I cannot even know when
I take this material and I
expose it to an external field,
I can't even calculate what the
magnetic field inside will be.
It depends on the history of
this material.
Look at this point here and at
this point there.
If I asked you what is kappa of
M, *pff* it's almost a
ridiculous question.
Because what is kappa of M?
I have, um, I have a vacuum
field,
but I have no field inside.
So the field inside,
which is B, is zero,
and the vacuum field is not
zero.
So you would have to answer,
kappa M is zero.
That's the only thing you could
say.
Quite bizarre,
right.
But right here,
there is a vacuum field but no
field inside.
So kappa M is zero here and
kappa M is zero here.
And remember,
here it was one thousand.
Look at the situation,
take this point of the curve
and this point of the curve.
Kappa M is less than zero,
is negative,
because here the vacuum
field is in this direction,
but B prime is in that
direction, so they are in
opposite directions,
so the net field is in that
direction, but B vacuum is in
this direction.
And here it's also reversed.
So there's a bizarre situation
that you are effectively having
situations whereby kappa of M is
zero and kappa of M can also be
negative for those s- points
that I have there.
I can show you this hysteresis
curve, and I do it exactly the
way that I explained to you,
except that I will not be able
to run this current very slowly
up and down.
I do it with sixty hertz
alternating current,
just get it out of the,
the wall.
And so I run through this
solenoid n- sixty hertz
alternating current.
That means we go through this
curve very quickly back and
forth.
Between this point maximum
current and this point maximum
current.
The current clockwise
counterclockwise clockwise
counterclockwise,
and we change that sixty times
per second.
And then I will show you this
curve, again,
highly distorted.
I cannot plot it one-to-one,
for the reasons that I
explained to you.
And you will see then the
hysteresis curve.
That's called the hysteresis
curve.
And for that,
I have to do several things.
And I always forget what I have
to do, but just don't worry
about it, I will find out.
My TV goes on.
This light goes off and this
light goes off.
Look there on the screen,
and you will see within seconds
there is the hysteresis curve.
And as I said to you earlier,
I cannot start here,
unfortunately,
because we switch it so fast
back and forth that this part of
the curve, by the way,
which is called the virginal
curve -- virginal,
because it's once and never
again.
Once you have reached that
point, from that moment on,
you always stick to this -- I
know, you should know about
that.
[laughter].
And so here you see a striking
example of a hysteresis curve.
And so you can ask yourself now
the question,
can we make this material
virginal again?
And then the answer is yes.
There are various ways you can
do that.
One way is you could take the
material out,
so that means you take it out,
for instance,
when there is remnant magnetism
here, so it's a magnet,
and now you heat it up above
the Curie point,
as we did last time in my
lecture, and then the domains
completely fall apart,
and then you cool it again
below the Curie point,
and then it is virginal
material again.
And then you could start here
again.
That's one way you could do it.
There is another way you could
try to do it.
You take a hammer and you just
bang on it.
So you take it out and you have
permanent magnetism,
either here or there,
and you bang on it,
and you hope for the best.
And maybe you can get it back
to here.
There is another way,
which we call demagnetization,
and I think that's what happens
when you steal a book in the
library and you try to get away
with it, and the alarm goes off.
Someone hasn't demagnetized the
magnetic strip in the book.
You may have noticed that when
you take it out,
that someone under the table
goes like this.
And what they are doing then is
they are demagnetizing that
strip.
And the way you do that is as
follows.
Here the current goes back and
forth between this value and
this value.
That means the vacuum and I are
directly coupled to each other.
So I think of this as being
current.
And now I go up to here and
then back and then here and here
and here and here and here and
here and here and here and here
and
I end up there again.
And I can show you that.
So again you have alternating
current, but the amplitude of
the current you decrease and
decrease and decrease,
and you're going to see that
there.
And you see that I can turn
this material -- see the
hysteresis curve changes.
So the amplitude of the current
is not as large,
so the amplitude of the B
vacuum is not as large,
and I slowly go back.
And I can change a non-virgin
back into a virgin.
And that's the way we do it as
physicists.
Demagnetization.
Did I turn that off?
Yes, I did.
I have here a,
a coil.
You can't see that there is a
coil inside here,
but there is.
I can, uh, power this coil,
putting a current through it.
Ferromagnetic material,
I don't know what kappa is,
but, uh, at least a thousand.
I get an enormously strong
field inside here.
And this field is so strong
that this piece of ferromagnetic
material will be attracted.
The field is non-uniform
outside.
We discussed last time that it
will go clunk,
it will stick there.
So let's do that.
So I power this electromagnet
-- you can't see that I did,
you have to take my word for
it, but you believe it now.
There it goes.
Oh boy.
The force is so large that I
would ask two people to come and
see
whether they can pull it apart.
The force that the two are
together is so large that you
may not even be able to separate
it.
Do we have two strong people?
One strong woman,
one strong man.
You look very strong to me.
[laughter].
Come on.
It's not going to be a tug of
war between the two of you.
That's not my plan.
Be very careful,
because if you touch this,
you get electrocuted.
So don't do that.
[laughter].
But make sure that everyone can
see you.
Because there is a current
running through this solenoid
now, yeah?
OK.
Now just in case that you
succeed, I don't want you to get
hurt.
Student: OK.
So make sure that you secure
yourself.
[laughter].
Because suppose the current
stopped running all of a sudden.
It's possible,
it's MIT [laughter] right,
anything could happen.
Then, of course,
it's no longer a strong magnet.
It's only a strong magnet as
long as the current is running
through the solenoid.
So you secure yourself too.
OK, three two one zero go.
[laughter].
Don't worry.
I knew
that in advance.
But thank you very much.
[laughter].
Very kind of you.
[applause].
Now comes something that you
will understand.
If I make the current go to
zero, then the vacuum field goes
to zero.
That means the field that is
generated by the solenoid goes
to zero.
I will do that now in front of
your own eyes.
No more current,
right?
Why is this still hanging
there?
Yeah?
The solenoid [inaudible]
magnetize the ferrous
[inaudible].
You hear?
You've taken the vacuum field
out, but the domains to a
certain degree are still
aligned, and so the whole thing
is still a magnet.
Not as strong as magnet -- if I
were to invite you to come now
and take it apart,
you could.
But it still takes sub-
substantial force.
And I will show you how
large that force is.
I'm going to load it down now.
There's now one kilogram
hanging on it.
Ooh, let me make sure I secure
that, otherwise I can get killed
for a change.
OK, three kilograms is hanging
on it now.
Five kilograms is hanging on it
now.
Seven kilograms is hanging on
it now.
Nine kilograms is hanging on it
now.
Oh boy, we may never make it.
Ten kilograms is -- there it
goes.
[laughter].
Ten kilograms.
Now the show is not over yet.
What is very interesting,
and I want you to think about
it, that if now I take these two
pieces of -- [laughter].
If I take these two pieces of
ferromagnetic material,
that -- nothing.
Do you know why?
I dropped it on the floor.
[laughter].
That's really why.
I dropped it on the floor,
and that is like banging it
with a hammer,
and then the domains go away.
Had I not dropped it on the
floor [laughter],
there would have been something
left, but very little,
which is interesting by itself.
The shock of the separation,
when that happened,
already makes many of the
domains flip back,
and there would be very little
left.
Not enough to carry this weight
anymore, but that's largely
because I dropped it on the
floor.
I did that purposely so you can
see
when you drop [laughter] things
on the floor.
If I bring ferromagnetic
material in the vicinity of a
magnet, I change the magnetic
field configuration,
and that's very easy to
understand now.
Suppose I have here a magnet,
north pole, south pole,
and the magnetic field,
magnetic dipole field is sort
of like this.
And now I bring in the vicinity
here
a piece of ferromagnetic
material.
Could be a wrench.
What happens now is that this
ferromagnetic material will see
this vacuum field -- this is
called the vacuum field,
is an external field.
And so these domains in there
trying to align a little bit.
Degree of success depends on
how strong the field is,
depends on the temperature,
depends on the kappa M of that
material.
But certainly this will become
sort of a south pole,
this will become a north pole.
That's the way that these
dipoles
are going to align themselves.
They are going to create
themselves a field in this
direction.
They're going to support that
field.
And so the net result is that
the field inside here becomes
very strong.
And so what happens with these
field lines, they go like this.
They're being sucked into this
ferromagnetic material.
It's very hard to know exactly
how they go.
And the field here will weaken.
And I'm going to demonstrate
that to you.
This is actually very easy to
demonstrate.
And the way I'm going to
demonstrate that is as follows.
I have there a setup whereby we
have a, a magnet and we have a
nail and we have a strong.
And the nail wants to go to the
magnet.
The mail its- the nail itself
is, uh, ferromagnetic.
So the nail would love to go in
this direction,
but it can't.
So it just sits there,
hangs there in space.
First of all,
what I want to show you is that
if I bring paramagnetic material
in the vicinity,
that that magnetic field
configuration here is not going
to change at all.
Paramagnetic material has a
kappa of M so close to one that
nothing is going to happen.
But the moment that I bring
ferromagnetic material,
for instance,
here, then you get a field
configuration change,
and if I do that just the right
way, then the nail will fall.
In other words,
there is not enough magnetic
field here in order to hold the
nail in that direction.
And I'm going to show that for
you, to you there.
Need some power here,
I believe, and we have to make
it dark here.
I'm going to shadow project it
for you.
And the shadow projection you
will see coming up very shortly.
This is a carbon arc.
You have to give it a little
bit of time to start.
There is the carbon arc.
So there you see the nail.
And here you see the magnet.
You see that?
That's exactly the way I drew
the picture.
And here, you hav- I have here
a piece of aluminum,
which is, paramagnetic.
I can bring that through the
field here.
Nothing happens.
My hands, believe it or not,
are definitely not
ferromagnetic,
so I can also bring my hands
here.
Nothing.
So magnetic fields is not
disturbed in any way,
in any serious way,
either by paramagnetic
material, aluminum,
or my hands,
which I think are also
paramagnetic,
but I'm not sure.
I'm not sure whether I'm
diamagnetic or paramagnetic,
but it doesn't make any
difference, because in both
cases there is no significant
change of the magnetic field.
But now I have a wrench here.
Here, there's a wrench.
You see it?
[laughter].
OK.
And now I'll bring the wrench
close to that magnet.
My major worry is that magnetic
field is so strong that once the
wrench go- there's no way I can
get it off again.
So I get only one shot at it.
And there goes the nail.
So what I -- what you saw now
in front of your eyes is that I
changed the magnetic field
configuration in such a way that
the field was not strong enough
to pull in the,
the nail.
Now comes an important
question, a big moment in our
life.
And that is,
what now is the effect of
magnetic material on Maxwell's
equations?
And let's take a look at
Maxwell's equations.
Here we have Maxwell's
equations the way we know them.
[laughter].
And let's first look at number
one.
That's Gauss's Law.
Gauss's Law says that the
closed surface integral of E dot
DA -- that's the electric flux
through a closed surface -- E is
equal to all the charge inside
divided by epsilon zero,
but you have to allow for the
kappa, for the electric,
dielectric constant.
The kappa, by the way,
always lowers the field inside
the material when we deal with
electric fields.
It never increases it like
magnetic
fields.
It always lowers it.
Kappa is normally a few --
except for water,
it is eighty,
it's quite large,
and there are some ridiculous
substances whereby kappa can be
as large as three hundred.
I think strontium titanate -- I
just looked it up this morning
-- has a ridiculous value of
kappa of three hundred.
So that's Gauss's Law.
Nothing's going to change there
as far as I can see.
And then we have the second
one.
The closed surface integral of
B dot DL equals zero.
Oh, it says an,
it says an L.
That shouldn't even be an L.
Ho, I hope you caught that.
This is an A,
of course.
How could I?
This is the closed surface
integral of B dot DA is zero.
What this is telling me is that
magnetic ma- magnetic monopoles
don't exist.
At least we think they don't
exist.
Don't think that people are not
trying to find them.
And if you find a magnetic
monopole, and if you put that
inside a box,
then the closed surface
integral of the magnetic flux
through that box
would not be zero.
And so then this is not true.
But as far as we know,
it's always true,
because we don't think that
magnetic poles- monopoles exist.
And so then we come to the
Faraday's Law.
Faraday's Law runs our economy.
Faraday's Law tells you when
you move conducting loops in
magnetic fields that you create
electricity.
This equation runs our economy.
And now we come -- none of
these, by the way,
require any adjustment in terms
of kappa of M.
But now we come to Ampere's
Law.
Ampere's Law,
which was amended by Maxwell
himself, tells me what the
magnetic field is,
and all these results are for
vacuum.
But now we know that that's not
true anymore.
So this has to be adjusted now
by a factor of kappa of M,
which is the relative
permeability.
And kappa of M is perfectly
kosher for paramagnetic and
diamagnetic
materials.
There's never any problem
there.
So here it comes.
For diamagnetic materials,
it's a little less than one.
For paramagnetic materials,
a little larger than one.
But when we deal with
ferromagnetic materials,
you have to be very careful,
because we have seen today this
hysteresis phenomenon,
that there are even situations
whereby kappa of M is negative,
whereby kappa M is zero,
and whereby kappa M can be
huge, can be ten to the third.
So there you have to be very,
very careful when you apply
this equation without thinking.
Maxwell's equations are so
important that I'm sure you want
to see more of them.
So you see them there again.
And maybe that's not enough.
[laughter].
Maybe you want to see even more
of them.
So look at them.
Inhale them.
Let them penetrate your
brains.
[laughter].
I don't care in which direction
you look now.
It's hard not to see them.
Today is therefore very
special, because today we have
all four Maxwell's equations in
place.
And this was one of the main
objectives of eight oh two.
So we have completed the long
journey, and on April five we
have reached the summit.
Now I realize that the view is
not spectacular for all of you
yet, because often at the summit
there is some fog.
But the fog will clear.
And I can assure you that from
here on on, it's climbing
downhill.
I think this moment is worth
celebrating, and therefore I
bought six hundred daffodils for
this occasion.
[laughter].
And I would like you to come at
the, at the end of the lecture
and pick up one of these
daffodils and take it back to
your dormitory.
I don't know whether I have
enough for all these high school
students and all their parents,
but why not,
give it a shot,
and take one.
And when you look at it tonight
at home and tomorrow,
remember that you only once in
your life go through this
experience, that for the first
time you see all four Maxwell's
equations complete,
all of it, and that you're
capable of appreciating them,
at least in principle.
This will never happen again.
You will never be the
same.
[laughter].
To put it in simple terms,
as far as eight oh two is
concerned, you are no longer
unspoiled virginal material
[laughter].
You've lost your virginity.
Congratulations!
[laughter].
[applause].
[crowd noise].