CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
practice integration by parts.
Specifically, I'd like to
solve the following four
problems. Or I'd like you to
problems. I'd like us to find
antiderivatives for each of
these functions. x e to the
minus x, x cubed over the
quantity 1 plus x squared
squared, arc tan x, and
natural log x over x squared.
And so the main goal, because
we're using integration by
parts, is to figure out what
you should make u, and what
you should make v prime.
And why don't you
give it a shot.
Work on that for a little bit.
I'm actually going to give you
one hint, and that's that this
one, you may want to break up
in a nontraditional way.
You may not want to break
it up as x cubed
and 1 over this function.
You're going to want
to split up this
function in the numerator.
Part of it will be in u, part
of it will be in v prime.
So that's my hint on number 2.
So now with that information,
I'd like you to give it a
shot, and then I'll come back,
and I'll show you how I do it.
OK, welcome back.
So again, what we're looking
for is antiderivatives for
each of these four functions.
And now, what I'm going to do,
is I'm going to help you pick
u and v prime, and then
I'm going to show you
what answer I got.
And I'm going to let you do
the work in the middle.
So let's start off
with number 1.
So if I have xe to the minus x
integral of xe to the minus x
dx, it's very easy to do either,
to make either e to
the minus x either
u or v prime.
Doesn't really matter.
Because an integral of e to the
minus x is going to have
an e to the minus x again, and
a derivative is going to have
an e to the minus x again, with
a minus sign in front, in
both cases.
But this doesn't
really change.
So we have, when we go up or
down, it doesn't really matter
if we integrate up or
take a derivative.
So really it's, we get to pick
what we do with the c to the
minus x based on what we
want to do with the x.
Well, we like taking derivatives
of things that
don't have two functions of x,
so it would be nice if we
chose our integration by parts
pieces so that this thing
wasn't there anymore.
So let me write down, actually,
before I even do
number 1, maybe I should
remind you what the
integration by parts
formula is.
So let me just, I'll scratch
that out for a second.
And what we're doing, is we're
going to have integral
of u v prime dx.
And if you recall what you saw
in lecture, is this should be
equal to uv minus the integral
v u prime dx.
And we'll put that plus c,
because sometimes I forget to
write it at the end.
So I'll put it there,
so I don't forget.
So really, what we're trying
to do, right, is pick the u
and v prime.
And so we want to make this
thing, this v u prime, as
simple as possible.
So what I was saying is if we
make this v prime or this u,
it doesn't matter.
So let's pick whether we want
this to be u or v prime.
Well, if I make this u,
then u prime is 1.
That's good.
If I make it v prime, then
v is x squared over 2.
That's more complicated.
So we obviously want
to make this u.
So for number 1, we're going to
choose u is equal to x, and
v prime is equal to
e to the minus x.
And then you can proceed
from there.
And I'll leave it at that.
Well, actually, just to make
sure we're OK, I'll even write
u prime is equal to 1, and
v is going to be equal to
negative e to the minus x.
So we'd be able to proceed
from there, right?
We have all the pieces
we need.
Now, number 2--
I'll give you the final
answers at the end.
Number 2, picking u and v
prime is a little more
complicated.
And let's look at
this function.
x cubed over 1 plus
x squared squared.
The problem with picking--
that does not look like a 2.
Sorry.
The problem with picking u and
v prime here, is that it's
hard to see what's going to
be easy to integrate.
So what we want to do
is rewrite this as--
let's see-- x squared times x
over 1 plus x squared squared.
And now, why is this
any better?
Well, I mean, it's
the same thing.
But why does this help us
see what we want to do?
Well, if you notice this
thing right here--
1 plus x squared.
What is its derivative?
Its derivative is 2x.
Up here we have an x.
So this piece right here looks
like it could be much more
easily integrated then
this right here.
So this might be a little
counterintuitive, because
we're going to take the
harder-looking thing, and make
that our v prime.
But the nice thing is
that we can actually
integrate this quantity.
So we choose, in this case,
this is our u, and
this is our v prime.
So how do I integrate this?
Well, I integrate this by
using a substitution.
And that will give me v. And
the derivative of this is
quite simple.
It's just 2x.
Right?
But this is the strategy
that we want here.
Why did we even think to split
that up like that?
Well, we knew we had to deal
with the denominator in some
fashion, and taking a derivative
with this in the
denominator, so putting this
part of the function in u--
when I look at u prime, it's
going to be even worse.
It's going to be a higher
power here.
It's going to be a cubic
in the denominator.
That's just making
things worse.
So we know we'd like to
integrate this denominator.
We'd like it to be a
part of v prime.
But the problem is that if I put
all the x cubed in the u,
and if I just had a 1 here for
my v prime, that's, I can't
really integrate
that very well.
But if I keep one of the x's,
then I can integrate this
quite simply with
a substitution.
So that's the sort of reasoning
behind why we choose
it that way.
All right.
We've got two more to look
at, and then I'll
give you the answers.
3.
OK.
3, you've seen this
trick before.
The function was arc tan x.
Now, you've seen this trick
I'm about to do with
natural log of x.
The same kind of thing with
You actually saw this in one
of the lecture videos.
Because there's only one
function here, you might
think, well, I have no idea what
I'm supposed to pick for
u and v prime.
But remember, it's really
arc tan x times 1.
Now I have two functions.
And what gives us a hint for why
we would want to do this,
is that what's the derivative
of arc tan x?
Let me just remind you.
d dx of arc tan x is 1 over
1 plus x squared.
Right?
We're back to actually an almost
similar situation to
what we had in the
previous thing.
d dx of arc tan x is 1 over
1 plus x squared.
So taking a derivative of this
puts it in a form that almost
looks easy to integrate.
What would make this function
easy to integrate?
If there was an x up here,
instead of a 1.
Then I could use substitution.
Where do we get that x from
when we're solving this
problem, where we're
actually finding an
antiderivative of arc tan x?
Well, it's going to come from
the fact that I make this u,
and I make 1 v prime.
So let me write that
out explicitly.
u I make arc tan x, and
v prime I make 1.
What does that do
in our formula?
Well, we're going to
be integrating
something that is v u prime.
Well, v is going to be x, and
u prime we see right here.
So it's going to be, I'm going
to be integrating x over 1
plus x squared when I
started doing the
integration by parts method.
That's much simpler, as we
talked about previously,
because the derivative of x
squared is 2x, and you have an
x in the numerator when
you put in that v.
So this is sort of the flavor
of how these things are
actually working.
So let me do the
final one here.
We have ln x over x squared.
OK.
Let me just tell
you right now.
In integration by parts, natural
log x is not something
you want to make the v prime.
You don't want to try and
take an antiderivative.
You know an antiderivative
of natural log of x.
x ln x minus x.
But that's certainly not going
to make things any easier.
Right?
You're actually, then you've got
a product of two functions
all of a sudden.
Everything's getting
more complicated.
But natural log of x has a very
nice derivative, because
you end up with something that
has just a power of x.
Derivative of natural log
of x, just 1 over x.
So that's probably the way you
always want to go when you see
natural log of x in these
integration by parts
techniques.
Because if I choose u is equal
to ln x, and then v prime.
In this case, I'm going to
write it as a power.
Let's think about
what happened.
u prime is 1 over x, right?
So u prime is x to
the minus 1.
What's v?
Well, it's something
like, let's see.
Negative x to the minus 1.
Something like that, right?
Let's make sure I
did that right.
Yeah, I think I did
that right.
So all of a sudden, if I
integrate v u prime, that's
just a power rule.
It's x to the minus 2, negative
x to the minus 2.
So that's quite easy
to integrate.
So again, when I see natural log
of x in an integration by
parts method, almost always, I
hate to say always, almost
always, almost a guarantee
that you want to take a
derivative.
You want to make that the u.
So hopefully that makes sense,
some of these strategies.
I tried to pick ones that were
somewhat different, so you
could see some different types
of strategies we needed.
And now I've done
these earlier.
So I'm just going to write down
what the answers actually
are, and you can compare
to what you got.
So the answer to number
1, just to check.
Number 2.
Some of these are
kind of long.
Number 3.
Number 4.
So let's just go through.
We get, In number 1, we get
negative x e to the minus x
minus e to the minus x plus c.
Number 2, we get negative x
squared over 2 times 1 plus x
squared plus 1/2 natural log
1 plus x squared plus c.
3 is x arc tan x minus 1/2
natural log of the quantity 1
plus x squared plus c, and 4 is
negative natural log x over
x minus 1 over x plus c.
So again, the whole point of
this exercise, in my mind, is
really to make sure we get a
good understanding of, when
we're doing integration by
parts, which function makes
the most sense to have as u, and
which function makes the
most sense to have as v prime.
So that was the main point
of this exercise.
Hopefully you're starting to
get a flavor for how these
problems actually work.
And I think I will stop there.