PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video I want us to work
on some problems looking
at integrals that may
converge or diverge.
So these are improper
integrals.
And we want to know if each of
the integrals below converges
or diverges.
And if they converge, I want
you to compute them.
I want you to actually evaluate
it, find a number
that is the area under
the curve.
So that's really remember
what the integral is.
So we should be able to find
actually the finite number
that represents that.
So there are three of them.
The first one is the
integral from 0 to
infinity of cosine x dx.
The second one is the integral
from 0 to 1 of natural log x
divided by x to the 1/2 dx.
So that's just square root x.
Remember it down there.
And the third one is the
integral from minus 1 to 1 of
x to the minus 2/3 dx.
So why don't you take a
while to work on this.
Pause the video.
When you're feeling good about
your answers bring
the video back up.
I'll be back then to show
you how I do them.
OK, welcome back.
Well hopefully you were able
to answer these questions.
The question again was that
we wanted to know if the
following intervals--
intervals--
integrals converged
or diverged.
And then I wanted us
to actually compute
them if they converged.
So again, we're going
to start with the
integral of cosine x dx.
Then we'll look at the integral
of natural log
x over root x dx.
And then we'll look at the
integral from minus 1 to 1 of
x to the minus 2/3 dx.
So let's look at
the first one.
And I'll rewrite it up
here so we have it.
OK.
And this is kind of interesting
because maybe this
is a little bit different than
what you have seen previously
in the way of saying this
is potentially improper.
Because cosine x certainly
doesn't blow up anywhere.
It's bounded between
minus 1 and 1.
So the function itself
is not blowing up.
But let's look at what we get
when we try and evaluate this.
So if we take this integral, we
know the antiderivative of
cosine is negative--
no it's just sine.
Sorry, it's just sine x.
Right?
The derivative of
sine is cosine.
So we get sine x.
And what we're supposed to do,
is that we're supposed to
take-- let me rewrite that x.
That's horrible.
We're supposed to take the limit
as b goes to infinity of
sine x evaluated from 0 to b.
Right?
And so this is pretty
straightforward.
Again now it's the limit at b
goes to infinity of sine b,
because sine of 0 is 0.
Now here's where we run into
trouble, because this limit
doesn't exist. Right?
because as b goes to
infinity,sine b, the function
sine x-- so now it's really the
function sine b, b is now
the variable if we think
about it that way--
as b goes to infinity, sine is
going to oscillate as it
always does between
minus 1 and 1.
And it's going to continue
to do that.
It's not going to approach
a certain value and stay
arbitrarily close
to that value as
be goes off to infinity.
So this limit does not exist.
And maybe what's informative
is to think about how could this
happen as an integral?
If we know that the integral
we're looking for is really
the sined area under
the curve.
So let me explain briefly
what's happening.
Let me just draw a quick picture
of cosine and explain
briefly what's happening.
So cosine starts off like this.
Right?
So what happens if I
wanted to integrate
cosine x from 0 to infinity.
I first pick up this
much area.
Sorry this graph is a little
sloped I realize.
I pick up this much area and
that's all positive.
And then as I keep moving over
here to here, I pick up the
same amount of area,
but it's negative.
So once I get to here my
integral, it'ss 0.
The area above and the
area below are equal.
So then I start the process
again with the value 0.
And so I accumulate some
negative area.
Then over here it's the same
amount of positive area, and
it kills it off.
So I start off, I have some
positive value, and then it
becomes less positive
and goes to 0.
Then I get some negative
value accumulated.
Then it comes up and
goes to 0 again.
So the point is as I'm moving
off to infinity, the area is
oscillating.
And the area, remember, is
actually what the value of
sine is at that point.
The area from under the curve
from 0 to any value for cosine
x is the value of sign
at that point.
That's what we're seeing here.
So the point is that this
integral, even though cosine x
is a bounded function, the area
is accumulating, then
disappearing, then becoming
negative, then disappearing,
then accumulating, then
disappearing.
So there's no value that
it's approaching.
It's varying between all these
values over and over again.
So this is a weird one maybe
where the integral doesn't
exist. But it actually, it
doesn't exists there.
So hopefully that makes sense,
and even though it's a little
different, you understand
the idea.
So now I'm going to go to b.
So what is b?
It's the integral from 0 to
1 of lnx over x to 1/2 dx.
OK.
And what I want to point is we
probably want to see why is
this improper.
Well at 1, we don't of
a problem because
natural log of 1 is 0.
And we can put a 1 down here
and nothing bad happens.
At 0 we have a problem.
A natural log of 0 actually
doesn't exist. The limit as x
goes to 0 is natural log
x is minus infinity.
And then natural log-- or
sorry, natural log--
0, evaluating square root
x at 0, gives you 0.
So we have something going
to minus infinity in the
numerator and 0 in
the denominator.
As we're trying to integrate
that function as it goes
towards that value.
So we have to figure out kind
of what's going on here.
So let's not worry about the
bounds at the moment.
Those are obviously going to
be important at the end.
But let's figure out
what we get as an
antiderivative for this.
OK?
And we don't worry about the
constant, remember, in the
antiderivative because we're
going to evaluate.
So what's the best way
to attack this one?
Well probably you should see
that you got a natural log and
you've got a power of x.
So this is really set up to do
an integration by parts.
Because remember you
like to take
derivatives of natural log.
And powers of x are happy to
be integrated or to take
derivatives of them.
The only power of x that's maybe
a little bit annoying to
integrate is x to the minus 1,
because it's integral, because
it's antiderivative is natural
log instead of like another
power of x.
But, this one is not that case
so it's looking good for an
immigration by parts.
So again we said for an
integration by parts, natural
log you love to take
it's derivative.
So we're going to let you be
natural log of x and u prime
be 1 over x.
And thenv prime is x
to the minus 1/2.
Right?
This is x to the 1/2 in the
denominator, so v prime is
actually x to the minus 1/2.
So v is going to be x to the 1/2
with a correction factor.
So it's going to need a
2 in front, I believe.
Let me double check.
Derivative of this is
1/2 times 2 is 1 x
to the minus 1/2.
So I'm doing OK.
So now what do I get when I
want to take the integral?
I take uv. So it's going to
be 2x to the 1/2 lnx--
and then now I'm going
to put in the bounds
variated from 0 to 1--
minus the integral
of vu prime.
So v is x to the 1/2, and u
prime is x to the minus 1,
really it's 1/x.
And so I'm going to keep the 2
in front integral from 0 to 1.
x to the 1/2 over x is
x to the minus 1/2.
This will be nice because
we've already taken an
antiderivative once, so
we know what we get.
All right, now this one we'll
have to look at, because
notice that as x goes to 0 we
have to figure out if this has
a limit, OK?
We have to figure out
of this has a limit.
And we'll probably need to use
L'Hopital's rule to do that.
So let's finish this part
up first. So I'll
just keep this here.
0 to 1, that's a 0,
and then minus.
OK, x to the minus 1/2,
its antiderivative
was 2x to the 1/2.
So I have another 2, so
I get a 4x to the 1/2
evaluated from 0 to 1.
So this is easy because
here, I just get 4.
Right?
This part right here, when I
evaluated it I'll just get 4
and the minus sign in front.
So this part is just -4, because
at x equals 1 I get 1
and at x equals 0 I get 0.
So that's fine.
This part is fine.
This part, when I put in 1 for
x, notice what happens.
I get a 1 here.
Natural log of 1 is
0, and so I get 0.
And so the question really is,
what is the limit as x goes to
0 of this quantity?
I know right here again,
I have a minus 4 here.
And then the question is
what do I have here?
it?
It could blow up still.
It could diverge.
We're going to see
what happens.
So let me just put a line.
It's the same problem, but I
want to distinguish for us.
So we're actually wanting to
find the limit as b goes to 0
of 2b to the 1/2 natural log b.
Right?
That's what we're
interested in.
That's the only part we
don't yet understand.
So let's see what happens.
Well, if I want to make this
into a L'Hopital's rule thing,
right now I have 0 times
negative infinity.
So to put it into a form I
recognize, I'm going to
rewrite this.
This is actually equal to the
limit as b goes to 0.
I'm going to keep the natural
log be up here, and I'm going
to write this as be to the minus
1/2 in the denominator.
Let's make sure we understand
what just happened.
I had a b to the 1/2
in the numerator.
If I put it to them minus 1/2 in
the denominator it's still
equal to the same thing.
Right?
b to the minus 1/2 in the
denominator is equal to b to
the 1/2 in the numerator.
OK?
Really I'm taking 1 over this,
and then I'm dividing by it .
That's the way you want
to think about it.
You want to think about saying
I'm taking 1 over this, and
I'm taking it in the numerator
and the denominator.
so I end up with it just here.
That might have been
confusing.
The real point is this quantity,
one over this
quantity is equal
to that quality.
And now what's the point?
Why did I bother to do that?
As b goes to 0, this goes to
negative infinity and this
goes to infinity.
So now I have something where I
can apply L'Hopital's rule.
So the limit as b goes to 0,
derivative of natural log of b
is 1 over b.
So I get 2 over b in
the numerator.
The derivative of b to the minus
1/2 is negative 1/2 b to
the minus 3/2.
There's a lot of denominators
in the numerator and
denominator, so let's
simplify this.
That's the limit
as b goes to 0.
OK, what o we get here?
We have 2 times minus 1/2, or
2 divided by minus 1/2.
So I'm going to get a negative
4 from this part, the
coefficient.
Then I have a b to the minus
1 up here divided by a b
to the minus 3/2.
That's actually going to be a
b to the 3/2 divided by b.
That's going to be
b to the 1/2.
That's algebra.
You can check it
if you need to.
I mean, you should
have gotten this.
But if you didn't get
this, check again.
Let me make sure I get it again,
b to the 3/2 divided by
b, b to the 1/2.
And that equals 0, because it
was a limit as b goes to 0 of
this quantity.
Now I've just got a continuous
function.
I am, notice, I didn't actually,
I kind of cheated a
little bit, because I just wrote
limit as b goes to 0.
But I'm always doing as b goes
to 0 from the right-hand side.
I'm starting at 1.
So you may have seen this, this
0 plus means I'm only
interested as b goes
to 0 from above 0.
OK?
I didn't write that in, but
notice our integral was
between 0 and 1.
So it only mattered values
to the right of 0.
So this function is defined
So I can just evaluate there.
I can just plug it in.
It's continuous, and so I can
just say at 0 it equals 0.
So now let's go back
to where we were.
What were we doing here?
We were taking this whole piece,
was to come back in
here and figure out what
this value was.
We knew at 1, we got 0.
And now we know at
0, we also get 0.
So that question mark I can
replace by a 0, and
I get 0 minus 4.
So the actual answer
is negative 4.
OK, we have one more.
What's the last one?
The last one-- let me write
it down over here again--
is the integral from minus 1 to
1 of x to the minus 2/3 dx.
Now this is interesting, because
this, you actually saw
an example kind of like this
in the lecture that at this
endpoint, it's fine.
You can evaluate the function
at that endpoint.
At this endpoint it's fine.
You can evaluate the
function there.
So it looks good at
the endpoints.
But the point is that at x
equals 0, because this minus
power is putting your x in the
denominator, you actually,
your function is blowing up.
It has a vertical asymptote
at x equals 0.
So what we want to do is we have
this strategy for these
problems, is to split it up into
two parts, minus 1 to 0
of x to the minus 2/3 dx plus
the integral from 0 to 1 of x
to the minus 2/3 dx.
Now the point is that now the
only place where I have a
vertical asymptote,
I see it as an
endpoint on both of these.
And this is again, just this
good thing we have an additive
property for these integrals,
that the sum of these two
integrals is going to
equal this one here.
As long as, you know, as long as
these are converging, then
I can say that if this converges
and this converges,
then there's some convergence
to this one here.
OK, so that's really what I'm
trying to exploit here.
Now what is the antiderivative
here for x to the minus 2/3?
This is going to be-- again, I'm
going to write something
down and then I'm going
to check it.
I think it should be
5/3, x to the 5/3.
And then I have to
multiply by 3/5.
Let's double check, because this
is where I always might
make mistakes.
If I take the derivative of 5/3
times 3/5 it gives me a 1.
5/3 minus 1 is 5/3 minus
3/3, and that's
2/3, and that's wrong.
Right?
Because I went too big.
It's supposed to be 1/3.
I knew I was going to
make a mistake.
Right?
I'm supposed to add
1 to minus 2/3.
That's just 1/3.
And so I should have
a 3 in front.
So for those of you who were
saying she's making
a mistake, I was.
OK, x to the 1/3.
So I take the derivative times
3, I get a 1 there.
I subtract 1 and I
get minus 2/3.
So now I'm in business.
OK.
And now I just need to a value
that here, here if I can, then
another one here from 0 to 1.
And the good news is x to
the 1/3 is continuous
at all these points.
It's continuous across negative
1, 0, 0, and 1.
So I can actually
just evaluate.
I don't have to worry.
There is a value for
the function there.
It's continuous through
all these points.
So I can just evaluate them.
So let's see what I get.
I get 3 times 0.
And then I get minus 3 times
negative 1, so I get a
negative 3 plus 3 times 1,
and then minus 3 times 0.
OK, so 3 times 0 minus
negative 3.
So that's a 3 plus
3, and I get 6.
And what's the picture
of this?
Well you should think about what
the picture of x to the
minus 2/3 looks like.
And you should notice that
across 0, it's even.
Right?
So it's actually going to have,
itt's going to look the
same in the left-hand side
and the right-hand side.
So if I had wanted to, I could
have just found the value of
say, this integral--
I like positive numbers better--
the integral from 0
to 1 of this function,
multiplied it by 2, and it
would have given me
the actual value.
Because it's exactly the same
function to the right of 0 and
to the left of 0.
It's a reflection across the
y-axis, so you get the same
value there.
So you actually would've gotten
3 for this multiplied
by 2 and you get the value.
If this one had diverged, that
one also would have had to
diverge, and the whole thing
would have diverged.
And that's because of
the symmetry of the
function over 0.
So I'm going to just briefly
review what we did.
And then we'll be done.
So we come back over here.
I gave you 3 integrals.
We wanted to see if they
converged or diverged, right,
and if they converged
find what they were.
So the first one was cosine x.
And we found that diverged for
a different reason than what
we've seen before.
Because as x goes to infinity,
the problem is the areas are
varying up and down and they're
bounded always.
But the area under the curve
is constantly changing and
it's not converting
to a fixed value.
It's varying between minus 1
and 1 over and over again.
And then b, we had this integral
from 0 to 1 natural
log x over root x dx.
And the point here was a little
more complicated, so
let me come to that one.
We used an integration
by parts.
We had an integral they
converged easily, because this
was an easy improper integral
to determine.
And then we had this other
thing that we now have to
evaluate it.
You wound up having
to use L'Hopital's
rule to evaluate it.
But then you're able to show
that this using L'Hopital's
rule, this actually has a value
at each endpoint, a
finite value at each endpoint.
It converges then to 0 as you,
as when you put in these
bounds, and then you have a
fixed value for this one when
you take that integral.
So you ended up with another
integral that was improper.
But you could show
it converged.
And then you could use
L'Hopital's rule to find what
happened at these endpoints.
And you get a value
of minus 4.
Then the third one was this
integral minus 1 to 1 x to the
minus 2/3 x dx.
And the point I wanted to make
there is that just because the
function is well-behaved near
the endpoints doesn't mean
that it's still, you know, that
everything is hunky-dory.
You have to be careful and you
have to check at places where
the value of the function is
going off to infinity.
So in the second case, the left
endpoint posed a problem,
and everything else was fine.
In this case, the left and right
endpoints are both fine,
but in the middle there's
a problem.
And so you split it up into it's
two pieces so that you
have the endpoints.
Now these two new integrals
represent where the problem
might happen, and then you
do your, find your
antiderivative, and evaluate,
and see if you can get
something that converges.
So that's the idea of these
types of problems. So
hopefully that was helpful,
and I think
that's where I'll stop.