PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video I want us to look
at the following problem.
We're going to let f of
x equal 1 over x.
And I want to consider the solid
generated by rotating f
of x about the x-axis
between x equal
1 and x equal infinity.
I want you to find the area of
a cross sectional slice, and
then I want you to find the
volume of the solid.
In the cross sectional slice,
the one I'm interested in is
the one that you see
in the xy plane.
So my suggestion to you is that
right away draw yourself
a picture, just at least a rough
sketch of the curve y
equals f of x and then what
that cross sectional slice
will look like and start
off from there.
And take a while to work on that
and then I'll be back and
show you what I did.
OK welcome back.
Well hopefully you were able to
make some headway on this
problem, and maybe you found
some interesting things.
Hopefully you did.
And we will see what I find and
if they are interesting,
which I think they are.
So let's start off.
I told you the first
thing you should do
is get a rough picture.
So I'm going to draw a rough
picture and make sure that
those match up well, if my
picture matches up with yours.
So let me give you
the xy plane.
And then y equals 1 over x is a
curve that at x equal 1 I'm
going to make y equal
1 up here.
y equal 1 up there. x equal 1.
So when x is 1, y is 1.
And then it's going
to decay down.
As x goes to infinity
it decays
So it looks something
like that.
And then I actually should have
moved this 1 because I'm
going to need that side to get
my cross sectional slice.
So my cross sectional slice, is
going to come down here and
look something like this.
Oops that's supposed
to be symmetric.
That's still supposed to
be something like this.
It's supposed to be symmetric
about the x-axis.
And the cross sectional slice
is the area of that.
Now, if you remember what
you saw in lecture.
You saw I believe that the
integral from 1 to infinity of
1 over x dx diverges, because
you end up with log evaluated
at infinity and that is
infinite and so you
wind up with this.
This actually diverges.
That was the area of the top
part from 0 to f of x.
So of course if I double
that, I'm still going
to get that it diverges.
So in fact the cross sectional
slice area,
CSS area, is infinite.
OK, so that's one part.
The other part is to find the
volume of the solid of
revolution.
So the second part was take this
piece from 0 up to f of
x, rotate it around the x-axis
and compute the volume.
Now we know how to compute
the volume.
This is the disc method that
I'm going to use here.
And I will write out what we
need to do and then we'll look
at what the integral gives us.
So for the disc method,
so let's say this
is the volume part.
So the volume, it's going
to be the disc method.
So I need to do pi r squared.
And in this case I'm integrating
from 1 to
infinity, so I need
pi r squared dx.
I'm going to be integrating
something that's
pi r squared dx.
And I know the bounds are 1 to
infinity, and so I need r in
terms of, as a function of x.
That's fairly easy. r is
just the measure from
0 up to f of x.
So that's just 1 over x.
So this is actually
the integral--
I'm going to pull the pi out
--of 1 over x squared from 1
to infinity dx.
OK so how do I do
this integral?
Well you were shown in class
that in actuality this is the
limit-- as some value up here
goes to infinity --of this
integral, but we're just going
to do it the shorthand way
that he also mentioned
in class and keep
the infinity around.
So we can keep that as our
bounds, knowing we're taking
limits as this thing
goes to infinity.
So the integral of 1 over x
squared is negative 1 over x.
So I get minus pi times 1 over
x, evaluated at 1 in infinity.
I can just check that if I need
to, but this is x to the
minus 1 and it's derivative is
negative x to the minus 2.
So I needed that
negative there.
And then I evaluate this.
Well at infinity 1 over x as x
goes to infinity, this first
part goes to 0.
So this is 0 minus negative
pi times 1 over 1.
So negative pi times 1.
So this is just pi.
OK, so hopefully that kind of
blows your mind a little bit,
that you could have something
where this cross sectional
slice is infinite, but in fact
if you look at it the way we
computed the volume, we have
in fact a finite volume.
So I don't know what else I'm
going to say about that except
I think it's really cool.
And you can think about
why that is.
And in fact you might want to
notice that we had to, we
computed things in terms of
cross sectional slices coming
from the other direction.
So we looked at these cross
sectional slices and we got
our, we showed our volume
was finite there.
So we had a sum of a bunch of
finite things and so it made
sense that you were going to
get, and the finite things
were getting small
fast enough.
That's the point.
That when you add up these
finite things that are getting
small fast enough, you
can still end up
with a finite number.
But I guess, yeah, that's
where I'll stop.
So just to say that we were
looking at this sort of solid
of revolution problem again,
but we were dealing with
improper integrals, and we were
showing how you can do
these kinds of problems with
improper integrals.
So now I really will
stop there.