PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome to the second special
recitation on
exam problem solving.
As you may have experienced,
when you do homework problems,
you can give every problem
or even every
step a careful thought.
You may even try different
methods in solving one
problem, just to check your
answers and also to find the
optimal way.
But in the real exam, these may
not be available to you
anymore, because time
is the main issue.
So you want to do
things fast but
accurately at the same time.
Today's recitation is going
to focus on that.
So we're going to look at
a real exam problem.
So this is the problem from a
15-minute linear algebra exam.
OK.
By now, you've developed
enough background to
completely solve this problem.
So because this is a 15-minute
exam, a good suggestion on
time spending on this problem
would be no more than 15
minutes, which means within 15
minutes, you have to read
through the questions,
understand what they're asking
for, and completely solve
all three parts.
Why don't you hit Pause now,
and try to complete this
problem as if you
were in an exam.
And time yourself
for 15 minutes.
If you finish early, don't
forget to check your answer.
You want to get all
the credits you
deserve in an exam.
OK.
I'll come back later and
show you how I would
speed up in the exam.
OK.
Have you finished?
Well, let's solve this
problem together.
We are looking at a 4
by 4 matrix A here.
As you can see, this matrix is
made up by the examiner in a
rather casual way, because you
have numbers from 1 to 12 as
the entries of this matrix.
And in the first part, we want
to find all the non-0 terms in
this big formula to compute
determinant of A. So the
determinant of A--
so that's Part 1--
that's equal to a big summation
of plus or minus A1
alpha, A2 beta, A3 gamma
and A4 delta.
So what I'm doing here is I
choose one entry from each row
with the columns being
all different.
So in other words, if I take
this column numbers down-- let
me write it here--
alpha, beta, gamma, and delta.
I want this to be
a permutation of
numbers 1, 2, 3, 4.
OK.
So how would you do it?
Well, if you follow this order,
you may want to start
with the first row.
And you go through all the
possibilities of this alpha,
beta, gamma, and delta, and at
the end, you drop the terms
which are 0.
But if you do it in that
way, how many terms
do you have to compute?
This is a 4 by 4 matrix.
So in general, this sum will
contain 4 factorial, which is
24 terms.
That sounds time consuming.
So can you do it in
a faster way?
Well, since we only care about
non-0 terms in this sum, let's
look at where 0 occurs in
matrix A. They're here.
You have 0 entries in
these four spots.
OK.
So they all occur in the third
row and the fourth row, which
means when you make your
choice of the last two
entries, in order not to get 0,
you can only choose within
this red box.
Because you want to
avoid these 0s.
Which means the choice of the
last two entries can only be
either 9, 12 or 10, 11.
OK.
Now, if that's the case, what
would happened to the first
two entries?
Since they all have to come from
different columns, which
means when you choose the first
two entries, they can
only be from this red box.
Which means the choice of the
first two entries can only be
either 1, 6 or 2, 5.
So how many terms am
I talking about?
Two possibilities here and two
possibilities here, which
comes to four.
So in other words, instead of
computing 24 terms, you only
need four terms here.
Let's put them down.
OK.
So we start with this
choice 1, 6, 9, 12.
So that's 1 times 6
times 9 times 12.
Well, these are from
diagonal, right?
So of course, this coordinate
numbers would just be A11,
A22, A33, A44.
This is the perfect alignment
of 1 2, 3, 4, so the sign of
this term is just a plus sign.
Let's continue.
Now I'm going to look
at 1, 6 but 10, 11.
So 1 times 6 times
10 times 11.
What is the coordinate
number--
what are the coordinate numbers
of this choice?
A11, A22, 10 comes from A34.
So here I have 4 in the front.
The last one is A43,
so right here.
This is the permutation
of 1, 2, 3, 4.
In order to get back to this,
I have to exchange 3 and 4.
Just do it once.
OK.
Which means I need a negative
sign in front.
A negative sign in front
of the entire product.
Well, let's continue.
I'm going to write
it down here.
As you can see the blue
part indicate the
signature of columns.
So next term, I'm
going to put--
I've exhausted the first
possibility of
choosing 1, 6, right?
So let's look at 2, 5.
2 times 5 times 9 times 12.
What is the column?
What are the column numbers?
2 comes from 1, 2 entry, so
I have a 2 in the front.
5 is 2, 1 entry, so 2,
1, and then 3, 4.
3, 4.
Again, I need one exchange to
get back to 1, 2, 3, 4, which
means I have a negative
sign in the front.
The last one would be 2, 5.
2 times 5 times 10, 11,
so times 10 times 11.
Columns are A12,
A21, A34, A43.
So you exchange the first two
spots, and the last two spots.
You get back to 1, 2, 3, 4.
But you have to do twice, two
exchanges, which means you
need a plus sign in front.
That's it.
This big summation formula comes
down to the sum of four
terms. And you can compute it.
If you don't make any
algebra mistake, the
result should be 8.
Did you get the right answer?
All right, time is
really precious.
Let's move on to the
second part.
In the second part, we need
to find cofactor C11,
C12, C1,3 and C14.
Let me put the second
part here.
So we're looking for the
cofactors of the first row of
matrix A. Let's just write
everything down.
C11.
C11 is the cofactor of
this entry here.
So you're looking at the
determinant of this left over
3 by 3 matrix.
So that's the determinant of--
copy it down--
6, 7, 8, 0, 9, 10, 0, 11, 12.
How would you compute this?
This is a 3 by 3 matrix.
Of course, you can use the big
summation formula again.
In other words, you can write
down this determinant--
this formula, but for the
specific 3 by 3 matrix.
But that will involve three
factorial terms, right?
Which is
six terms. All right.
Is there a way that you
can do it faster?
Just notice that the first
column of this matrix has only
one non-0 entry, which
is this 1,1 entry 6.
So why do we just expand
this along the first
column and use cofactors?
Let's do it.
This determinant is equal
to 6 times its cofactor.
And its cofactor comes to the
determinant of this 2 by 2
matrix, which is easy.
That becomes 9 times 12
minus 10 times 11.
And if you compute this
correctly, that should be -12.
That's not too bad.
Let's look at the
second one, C12.
C12 is the determinant of
this 3 by 3 matrix.
So I have to delete the first
row and the second column.
And I raid what is left over
and I put it here.
So that's 5, 7, 8, 0,
9, 10, 0, 11, 12.
Same thing.
The first column has only
one non-0 entry.
You expand it along the first
column, use cofactors, the
result will be 10.
There's one thing that
I've forgotten here.
Because we are looking
at 1,2 entry.
So for the cofactor, I
have to put an extra
negative sign here.
So this is actually -1
times the determinant
of this 3 by 3 matrix.
And the result will be 10.
OK, let's continue.
C13.
Let's hope the computation
is going to
get easier and easier.
So C13 is the determinant of
the leftover 3 by 3 matrix.
So I'll directly
raid from that.
That's going to be 5, 6, 8,
0, 0, 10, and 0, 0, 12.
What is the determinant
of this matrix?
Again, you can use the same
method as we did for the first
two, because the first column
has only one non-0 entry.
And if you do that, the
result should be 0.
But you should be able to tell
it without any direct
computation.
Why is that?
Well, clearly the first two
columns are linearly
dependent, because the second
column is 6 over 5 times the
first column.
So this is a singular matrix.
Right away, the determinant
is 0.
So what is C14?
C14 is the determinant of
the matrix of 5, 6, 7,
0, 0, 9, 0, 0, 11.
Same thing.
It's singular, so its
determinant is 0.
All right.
So that completes
the second part.
You can move on to the third
part now, but before you do
that, just notice this may be
a good point to check your
answer from the first part.
Because you have all the
cofactors of the first row of
A, and if you use the other
formula to compute the
determinant of A, you can see
the determinant of A is equal
to the dot product of the first
row with its cofactors.
So because the last two
cofactors is 0, so I only have
two terms in the sum.
So determinant A is equal to
A11 entry, which is 1 times
C11 which is -12 plus A12 entry
which is 2 times C12
which is 10.
What is that?
-12 plus 20, that give you 8.
OK, at least the answers from
the first two parts are
consistent.
So by now, you should be more
confident to move on to the
third part.
I have a problem of space.
So please allow me to put
the third part here.
I'm going to come all
the way back here.
So that's my third part.
What is the third part?
Third part asks you to find the
first column of A inverse.
Well, it seems that involves
more computation of cofactors,
but as many well designed exam
problems, the answer from
third part can be directly
derived from the first part
and the second part.
That's how you should do it.
So what is A inverse?
The formula for A inverse is
equal to 1 over determinant of
A times the transpose of a
matrix C. This matrix C is
composed by cofactors of matrix
A. We want to find the
first column of A inverse.
So the first column of A inverse
should be one of our
determinants of A, this
constant, times the first row
of C but transpose, right?
So I have to put here, first
row of C but transpose.
Determinant of A comes from the
first part and the first
row of C comes from
the second part.
So I just copy what I have from
the first two parts down.
That's 1 over 8.
This column vector will
become -12, 10, 0, 0.
That's it.
That completes this problem.
Have you got your
answer right?
OK, before I finish, there are
two things that I like to
remind you.
First, as you can see, this
is an exercise on the big
summation formula to compute
determinant of A. In previous
recitation, we practice using
the combination of elimination
and the method by cofactors
to compute determinants.
But we should never forget
this formula.
Because it always works.
And in a lot of cases, this will
turn out to be an easy
way to compute determinant.
For example, for this
matrix A here.
And second in your real exam, it
would be really helpful if
you can put down your work like
this, because it helps
you to check your work.
And also, even if you don't get
your final answer correct,
this may get you some
partial credits.
OK, I'm going to stop here, and
thank you for watching.