Welcome back to recitation.
In this video I want to talk to
you about another test for
convergence we have for series,
that you haven't
really spent any time looking
at this particular one.
And it's pretty helpful, and
also will help us understand
something about Taylor
series, which I'll
do in another video.
So this is the ratio test. And
you'll understand the name of
this test, momentarily.
So we're going to start with a
series-- sorry-- we're going
to start with a series that
we'll just say, we'll call
each term a sub n.
And I'm not going to tell you
where n starts, because it
doesn't matter.
It's really going to
only matter what's
happening out at infinity.
And to make things simpler,
we're going to let all the
terms be positive.
OK?
You, if they're not positive,
you can take the absolute
value of all the terms and still
make some conclusions in
terms of absolute convergence.
So that's just a
little sidebar.
But let's just deal with all
the terms positive, so we
don't have to worry
about anything.
And now, what does the
ratio test say?
Well, the ratio test
says that first, we
consider a certain ratio.
The limit as n goes to infinity
of a sub n plus 1
over a sub n.
OK?
So we consider this limit.
Well, that's your ratio.
What is this doing?
This is taking a term,
and it's dividing by
the previous term.
You do that for all of the
values for n, as n goes to
infinity, and you look at
the limit, if it exists.
OK?
If the limit doesn't exist, then
you can't use this test.
So sometimes that will happen.
But if the limit exists, you can
use this test, and you say
it equals l.
And then you have the following
conclusions you can make.
So here are the conclusions.
There's three of them.
So if l is less than 1, then
the series converges.
OK?
That's nice.
That's good.
If l is bigger than 1,
the series diverges.
OK?
That's another good thing.
And then the last one
is, if l equals 1.
You can't conclude anything.
So I will try and convince you
of that fact with a few
examples later.
But let's look at this.
So you look at the ratio, and
if the ratio is less than 1,
then you actually can conclude
the series converges.
And if the ratio is bigger than
1, you can conclude that
the series diverges.
So let me just give you a little
understanding of why
this one is true, and then the
same kind of logic can be used
for this second one.
So we'll try and understand
just at least a little bit
why, when l is less than 1,
the serious converges.
OK.
So let me just start
writing here.
So if l is less than 1, then
this means that we have that a
sub n plus 1 over a sub n as n
goes to infinity is equal to
l, which is less than 1.
Right?
So we can pick something
between l and 1.
We can pick a number between 1
and 1, because I is strictly
less than 1.
And so what I'm going to do, is
I'm going to say, I'm going
to call this thing r.
Some number between l and 1.
OK?
So what does that mean?
That means that for large n, we
have a sub n plus 1 over a
sub n-- sorry, that looks like
I'm adding 1 to the a sub n--
that's a subscript--
a sub n plus 1 over a sub n
is less than some fixed r.
So I'm picking a value
r between l and 1.
And then this is true for all
large N. And when you're doing
math, sometimes people say, for
n, you know, bigger than
or equal to some fixed value.
Basically, if you go far enough
out in the sequence,
then all the values
bigger than some
fixed 1 have this ratio.
OK?
But let's get fancy with this.
This we can rewrite as r to the
n plus 1 over r to the n.
Right?
This is just r.
And now if I do a little moving
around, what do I see?
I see that a sub n plus 1 over r
to the n plus 1 is less than
a sub n over r to the n.
Now, this might be weird.
What did I do?
I just multiplied through by the
a sub n, and I divided by
the r sub n plus 1.
I get this thing, and then I see
that this ratio, as n goes
to infinity, the ratio between
a sub n and r to the n is
decreasing.
It's a decreasing, because the
next term, it's smaller.
Right?
And so the point is that if I go
far enough out, if I start,
say, past this n naught, if I
go far enough out, then I
always have that a sub n is less
than some constant times
r to the n.
OK?
So this means--
this is implies--
a sub n is always less
than some constant
times r to the n.
Right?
And now, what do we do?
We do our comparison test. OK?
We do our comparison test. This
is what's going to tell
us that the series converges.
Now, again, this isn't
necessarily true all the way
through the series, but it's
true when you're far enough
out, after this n naught.
And if a series converges at the
end, the beginning is just
a finite sum.
So we don't have to
worry about what's
going on at the beginning.
So again, we're at this place.
We want to know what happens to
the sum of a sub n of all
the terms a sub n.
Well, we know that's going to
be less than k times the
sum r to the n.
Right?
Because each a sub n is less
than some constant
times r to the n.
Now why does this converge
What do we know about r?
r we chose, we said it's
between l and 1.
In particular, it's
less than 1.
This is a geometric series.
Geometric series, when
r is less than
1, we know it converges.
And so this one converges, so
then this one converges.
So that's the logic behind it.
We're going to now, you know,
we're going to now use it.
But I want to point out that
if you liked that, you can
come back over here, and you
can do the same kind of
reasoning for why, if l is
bigger than 1, a sub n, the
series, the sum of the
a sub n's diverges.
And that's going to come down
to, now you choose an r that's
between l and 1, but it has
to be bigger than 1.
OK?
And then you can you
can look at that.
Or maybe r has to be
bigger than l.
I didn't even work that
one out all the way.
But you can do it.
You put an r in there
somewhere.
And the same kind of logic,
because the r will be bigger
than one, you're going to get to
a place where probably the
inequality sign is going to go
the opposite way, right?
And then you'll have a series
that diverges, and the other
one will be bigger
than that one.
And so that's how the logic
is going to work.
So you have to figure out
where the r goes, but I
guarantee you'll want
the r bigger than 1.
And then you can, you'll have
to have the inequality signs
be opposite what they are here.
OK?
You'll see, they're going
to be opposite there.
OK.
Now let's get some examples.
Example 1.
Let's look at some that we know,
and then let's look at
some that we don't know.
OK?
So let's look for example
first at 1 over n.
Alright?
And let's use the ratio
test on 1 over n.
Maybe this seems funny, 'cause
what do we know about it?
We know it diverges, right?
But let's check, if
this tells us.
The limit of n goes
to infinity of--
well, what's the n plus
first term of this?
It's going to be 1
over n plus 1.
And what's the nth
term of this?
It's going to be 1 over n.
And so we get, it's the limit
as n goes to infinity of n
over n plus 1, and
that equals 1.
Hm.
So this one didn't work.
This one didn't tell
us anything.
And, OK.
But we know this one diverges.
So we know that this makes us
think, well, maybe when l is
1, then we know it diverges.
But just to make sure we don't
make that conclusion, we don't
draw that conclusion, let's
look at 1 over n squared.
And what are the terms there?
a sub n plus 1 and a sub n.
The limit as n goes
to infinity.
Well, the n plus first term is
going to be 1 over n plus 1
quantity squared, and the nth
term is going to be 1 over n
squared, which is going to
be the limit as n goes to
infinity of n squared over n
plus 1 quantity squared, which
is also equal to 1.
And what do we know
about this one?
This one converges.
So this one gave us the l is
equal to one, and but we know
this one diverges.
And this one gave us
l is equal to 1,
and we know it converges.
So we know that when l equals
1, we really cannot conclude
convergence or divergence.
OK?
l equals 1 doesn't let us
draw any conclusions.
But now let's see something
where, you know, we can draw a
conclusion, because it would be
no fun if this test never
told us anything.
It probably wouldn't
be a test, then.
So let's try this one.
Let's try 4 to the n over
n times 3 to n.
Let's see what that one does.
All right?
So let's see.
What is, we need the limit
of n goes to infinity.
We need the n plus first term,
so let's plug in n plus 1 for
all of these.
And I'm actually going to do a
little trick here, and I'll
explain it as I go.
4 to the n plus 1 over n plus
1 3 to the n plus 1.
I'm going to multiply
by 1 over a sub n.
Because sometimes that's
a lot easier to do.
I could have done it on these
other ones, maybe, but now I'm
going to do it on this one.
So this is actually what
the a sub n is going
to look like, right?
I had to put in n plus 1
to get a sub n plus 1.
This is a sub n.
I'm going to write down 1 over
a sub n, and that's going to
give me n times 3 to the
n over 4 to the n.
And now let's start
simplifying.
I have 3 to the n over
3 to the n plus 1.
I'm left with just a 3 there.
4 to the n and 4 to
the n plus 1.
I'm left with just a 4 there.
And now the limit as
n goes to infinity.
Let's just rewrite it so
I know what it is.
Let's see.
I have 4n over 3
times n plus 1.
Well, the 4 and the 3 I can
actually just pull out.
But what did I have here?
n over n plus 1?
The limit of n goes to
infinity of that,
that equals to 4/3.
That's bigger than 1.
So that actually diverges, OK?
And I have one more example, and
I'm almost out of space.
And let me actually come over
here and figure out what
example I wanted.
Ah.
Sorry about that.
I knew I had one more.
OK.
n to the tenth over
10 to the n.
So it's kind of interesting
one, because you have, you
have an exponential and then
you have a power of n.
So let's look at this one.
So we need to consider limit
as n goes to infinity.
So I put in n plus 1 first. n
plus 1 to the tenth over 10 to
the n plus 1.
And then I'm going to just,
remember, do times
1 over a sub n.
So I'm going to have 10 to the
n over n to the tenth.
So again, I took a sub n, I did
1 over that, that's just
the reciprocal.
And now let's start dividing,
if I'm allowed to divide.
Yeah, I've got 10 the n there,
and 10 to the n plus 1 there,
so that gives me a single
10 in the denominator.
And so now I really have the
limit as n goes to infinity of
1 over 10 times n plus 1 to the
tenth over n to the tenth.
Well, that's equal to n
plus 1 to the tenth
over n to the tenth.
You might start to get nervous
and think, "Oh my gosh!
These powers are getting
really big!
It might make a difference
that that 1 is there." It
doesn't make a difference that
that 1 is there, because if
you actually expand this out,
the leading term is
just n to the tenth.
And we know that the highest
order, or the highest degree
is going to win out, so it's
going to be n to the tenth
over n to the tenth is
how it's going to
behave in the limit.
So this part's just going to
go to 1, so I get 1/10.
Oh, that's less than 1!
Yay!
So this series converges.
OK?
So we had one that diverges, one
that converges, and a few
where we couldn't get
conclusions by this test. And
one point I want to make about
this, is that in some cases,
you have the integral test
already, and sometimes that's
easy and that helps you.
In the case of these examples
where we couldn't tell where l
was equal to 1, the
integral test is
going to tell you something.
But in this case, it's a little
bit harder to deal with
this as an integral test. You
can still do it, but it's a
little bit harder.
And so this, maybe, is a little
bit quicker way to deal
with these types of,
types of problems.
And the big thing we're going to
do, is in the next video on
the ratio test, I'm going to
show you how you can use this
to determine the radius
of convergence for
these Taylor series.
So that's actually going to be
kind of exciting, and that'll
be in our next video.