Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
You've been learning about
infinite series of constants.
Adding up, you know,
series of numbers.
And one thing that we've talked
about are divergent
series and convergent series,
and rates of divergence a
little bit.
So suppose you wanted to
run an experiment.
So suppose you started with the
series, log n over n, and
you started summing--
I picked n equals 3.
It doesn't actually
matter that much--
started summing at n equals
3, and going to infinity.
And you set your computer to
sort of keep track of what the
partial sums are as
it does this.
So you wanted to produce a list
of partial sums. And you
know, maybe to get a good feel
for this rate of divergence,
what you want to do is let it
run for a long time, collect a
whole bunch of values.
Say, you know, stop when
it gets to some
fairly large number.
So suppose we run this, and we
ask it to stop when it gets to
a partial sum that's greater
than or equal to 5,000.
You know, whatever.
A moderately large integer
or number.
Doesn't have to be an integer.
So it's going to stop as soon
as it reaches a partial sum
that's bigger than 5,000.
So what I want to know, is how
long is that going to take?
Now of course, that depends
on your computer.
So let's just say, you know,
for sake of argument, that
your computer--
this is generous to
your computer.
At least my computer doesn't go
this fast-- that it takes
10 to the minus 20 seconds to
add an additional term to the
partial sums.
So suppose that your computer
takes 10 to the minus 20
seconds for each additional
summand.
How long, how many terms of the
series, how long are you
going to wait around, waiting
for this sum to get to 5,000?
So that's the question.
Why don't you pause the video,
take some time, try
and work this out.
This is probably not a quite
good question for
experimentation.
I would advise against actually
running it while you
wait to continue
with the video.
But of course, you're
welcome to try.
But you can, you know, work this
out, come back, and we'll
talk about it together.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you had some fun
with this problem.
Let's let's talk about it.
So what we want to do, is we
want to look at this series
and say, you know, about
how long it's going to
take to get to 5,000.
What we want-- which partial
sum of this series is about
equal to 5,000 for
the first time?
So let's give a notation
there.
So let's call sN, big N now, s
big N is equal to nth partial
sum-- well, OK.
Let me not make it the
nth partial sum.
Let me just make it the sum
when the top is big N. So
going from 3 to big N of log
little n divided by n.
So first of all, the answer
could be a priori.
The answer could be forever.
It might be that series
converges to some number less
than 5,000.
So if that were to happen, then,
you know, no matter how
long you waited around, you
wouldn't get there.
But we can check that
that's not the case.
So we can check that this
series diverges.
So how can we check that?
So the series diverges by the
integral test, because the
integral of log x over x dx
from, say, 3 to infinity,
though of course the bounds,
the lower bound, 3, is not
crucially important.
This is something we know
how to integrate.
This is equal to 1/2 log of
x quantity squared, taken
between, well, 3 and infinity.
And anyway, you see that as x
goes to infinity, log of x
goes to infinity, and so log of
x squared goes to infinity.
So this diverges.
So the series does diverge
to positive infinity.
And as a result of its
divergence to positive
infinity, we know
that eventually,
we do get to 5,000.
OK, so this is, the
answer is not, an
infinite amount of time.
The answer is some finite
amount of time.
So now the question
is, how much.
Now, the thing to remember about
the integral test is not
only can it tell you whether
something converges or
diverges, but it gives you a
really good estimate of how
quickly it converges
or diverges.
So I have over here
a little picture.
This is the function y equals
log of x over x.
So at x equals 1, this function
is 0, and then it
reaches a maximum, and
then tapers down.
And as x gets larger--
so it's a little hard to
tell in this picture--
at x equals 6, this is still--
well, so the peak here is a
little bit less than 0.4.
At x equals 6, this, the
function value is still bigger
than a quarter.
But it does eventually go down
to 0, because x grows faster
than log x.
And of course if you were
interested, an interesting
exercise might be really
precise, you know, where, to
figure out precisely, what is
this peak, and what's the
x-value, and what's the y-value
of that peak point
before it starts turning down.
If you wanted something
fun to work out.
And OK.
But that doesn't actually have
anything to do with our
problem, which has to do with
this integral test. So
remember that the integral in
question is the area under
this curve from 3 onwards, and
a partial sum is what you get
when you take a bunch of these
left endpoint rectangles.
And because this function is
decreasing, the rectangles
completely cover the region.
And so the integral test tells
us that the integral from 3 to
big N of our function, log x
over x dx, is strictly less
than, well, we want the partial
sum that goes up to,
so whose right interval here
ends at big N. So that's
actually the n minus
first partial sum.
So maybe what I'll do, is I'll
add a plus 1 here, and I'll
make this the big Nth partial
sum is bigger than the sum
from 3 to n plus 1
of the function.
And also, if you turn this
around, and you took right
endpoint rectangles instead, you
see that if you chop off
the first rectangle, then what
you get is the, you get an
area less than the integral.
So we also have an
upper bound here.
This is less than or equal to
the very first term, which in
our case is ln 3 over 3 plus
that same integral.
So this is this formula that
Professor Jerison showed you
in class that bounds
the partial sums
in between the integral.
So here, where the integral,
instead of being an improper
integral, just goes
up to n plus 1.
So the integral test gives us,
it tells us that this diverges
if and only if this does, but
it also gives us explicit
bounds for those two
expressions, how they relate
to each other.
And so it says that the rate of
divergence of sN is very,
very closely tied
to the rate of
divergence of this integral.
Well, so what?
So OK.
So we said, we know, you
know, about how big
this integral is.
How big is it?
Well, we saw that
it's about log x
squared between the bounds.
So this is equal to, well, it's
about, it's 1/2 log of n
plus 1 squared minus 1/2 log 3
squared is less than sN, which
is less than log 3 over
3 plus the same thing.
So this is log n plus
1 quantity squared
minus 1/2 log 3 squared.
And here this is log n plus
1 quantity squared.
OK.
So this right, this right
hand side is equal to
this right hand side.
OK.
So we have that s--
and this is a big N. So we have
that sN is about bounded
by these-- sorry-- is definitely
bounded by these
two expressions.
Another thing to note is
that the constants
here are pretty small.
Right?
This 1/2 log 3 squared and log
3 over 3 times 1/2 log 3
squared, those are
pretty small.
From this point on in this
problem, I'm going to stop
worrying about precise constants
like that, and I'm
going to start using an
approximate sign.
So another way to write this
is to say that sN is
approximately--
so this is like an
equals sign, but
both of them are curvy.
So what I mean by
this, it doesn't
mean anything formally.
So it's not a precise meaning.
In this case, it's going
to mean always
about the same size.
For purposes of this argument,
it's going to
be about the same.
So this is about equal
to 1/2 ln of n
plus 1 quantity squared.
OK. and what we want, So OK.
So good.
So we have a good approximation
for about how
big the nth partial sum is.
Well, all right.
So why?
Well, because I know that what I
want to do is I want to keep
going until I reach a partial
sum that has size about 5,000.
So I want to know how,
many terms do I need.
Right?
That's going to tell me how much
time it requires, and I
need to know how many
terms there are.
So I need to know when sN is
about 5,000, how big is N?
So coming back over here, so I
need to take this equation,
and I need to solve it
for N in terms of sN.
Because I know that sN is going
to be about 5,000, so I
want to know, how big
is N going to be?
So OK.
So let's do that.
So we can multiply by 2,
take a square root, and
exponentiate.
And what we get--
so I'm going to move up here.
So from this expression, what
I get is that n plus 1 is
approximately equal to-- so I'm
going to multiply by 2,
take a square root, and
exponentiate, so that e to the
square root of 2 sN.
And you know what, I don't
care about this plus 1.
I'm going to forget about it.
So N is approximately equal to
e to the 2 square root of sN.
Now in our case, we want to know
particularly when sN is
equal to about 5,000.
So when sN is approximately
equal to 5,000, this means
that N is approximately--
well, 2 times 5,000 is 10,000,
square root of 10,000 is 100,
so N is approximately equal
to e to the 100.
Now e is between 2 and 3--
so OK, so you know, I don't,
I can't really give a very
precise estimate of this
off the top of my head.
But luckily I used a computer
ahead of time
to approximate it.
So e to the 100 is about equal
to 2 times 10 to the
forty-third power.
So that's the number, so that's
about how big N is,
order of magnitude.
So we need to do about 2 times
10 to the forty-third terms.
So now that's the number of
terms. Now, if you remember,
back in our question, we were
asked, on the assumption that
each term takes 10 to the minus
20 seconds, how long is
this going to take.
So if each term requires 10 to
the minus 20 seconds, this
means we're dealing with 2 times
10 to the 23 seconds.
That's how long you'll
have to wait.
Now, this is a big number.
Right?
So let's think about how
big a number this is.
Because there are big numbers,
and then there are
ridiculously big numbers.
So, a big number would be a
number where like, maybe this
10 to the minus 20 is a
bad estimate, right?
I mean, maybe you are emperor
of the world, and you can
harness all the computing power
in the entire world to
work on this problem.
And so then, in that case, maybe
you can do, say, 10 to
the 25 computations per
second, something.
Or whatever.
So how much of a dent would
that make in this number?
Like 2 times 10 to 23.
OK.
It's not going to be done before
lunchtime, but how long
will it take?
So just to--
let's see.
I have this written down here.
OK.
So for comparison, this is about
equal to 50,000 times
the age of the universe.
So if you had, if you harnessed
all the computing
power on earth, you could
probably get this done in a
few billion years.
So OK, so just a sense
of just how slowly
this thing is getting.
If you wait, and you have all
the computer power on earth
adding terms of the series, in,
say, a few billion years
you will be able
to figure out--
you will sum up terms that
pass 5,000 in value.
So OK.
So I don't know.
I find that amusing.
And remember that the key here
to this whole problem was just
that we were using this
integral test here.
And specifically, we were using
in the form that I have
over here, this form that lets
you bound the partial sums
between two values
of the integral.
And because we have those
very tight bounds, these
approximations are all valid,
and so we can really say, yes,
this problem that I've described
is really something
you can't do in an afternoon
or whatever.
So I'll stop there.