Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about computing,
rather not computing, but
determining whether series
converge or diverge, and
different tests for that.
In particular, you've learned
the integral test.
So here are a couple of series
that you haven't seen before.
The sum from n equals
2 to infinity.
2, just so I don't have any
funny business here, of
dividing by 0, of 1 over
n times log of n.
And a second series, sum from
n equals 2 to infinity of 1
over n times log of n
quantity squared.
So the question is, do these
series converge or diverge?
So why you pause the video, take
some time to work on this
question, come back, and we
can work on it together.
Welcome back.
Before you left, I gave you a
little hint that these might
be questions that are amenable
to the integral test. One
thing we can do, you know, if
you, if I hadn't given you
that hint, how could you
figure this out?
Well, you can look at
these integrands.
And that there don't really
look a lot like anything
you've seen before.
But the associated functions,
right, so this is the
associated function,
1 over x log x.
This continuous function is
a function that we have--
you know, it looks sort of like
some things that we've
integrated before.
So that's one hint for the
integral test. Another hint
for the integral test is, you
just don't know very many
tests right now.
So it's kind of a small
selection of options.
Another thing is that, you know,
it's not going to be a
nice series.
It's not going to have a
nice numerical value.
This log n thing is
behaving badly.
You're not going to be able to
compute values, exact values,
of the partial sums, any nicer
than they looked just by
writing down that sum.
So OK.
So after we've got the idea
of the integrals--
that's how we get the idea for
the integral test. Now that
we've got the idea for the
integral test, what do we do?
Well, we know that this series
converges if and only if the
associated definite integral,
the associated improper
definite integral converges.
So let's do the first one first.
What's the integral
associated with it?
Well, we take the integrand,
and, you know, we frequently,
we replace the variable n with
the variable x, although that
doesn't really matter.
And so what we do, is we look
at the integral of this
integrand over the
same region.
So in this case, from
2 to infinity.
And so what we know is that this
sum converges if and only
if this integral does.
So then, the reason this is a
nice thing to do, is that
often there are integrals that
are easy to compute, while the
associated series are
hard to compute.
So in this case, this is an
integral that we have tools to
know, to compute with.
And in particular, the tool that
we have, is that there's
a simple little substitution
that will work on this series.
So that's the substitution,
u equals log x.
So we make the substitution
u equals ln of x.
Then du is equal to
1 over x times dx.
So this is the integral of--
so 1 over x dx, that's du.
And so it's 1 over u du.
This is a definite integral,
so I also need
to change my bounds.
So when x is 2, u is ln of 2,
although the lower bound
doesn't really matter very much
when we do the integral
test, because you know, if you
change it a little bit, that's
not going to change
the, you know--
as long as you don't move it
across a place where the
function explodes, all the
interesting stuff is whether
the function is big as
it goes to infinity.
So if you move a little round
at the bottom, you'll change
its numerical value, but you
won't change whether it
converges or diverges.
But in any case, ln of 2.
And then when x goes to
infinity, ln of x goes to
infinity, so the upper bound
is also u equals infinity.
And now this is an
easy integral.
This is just ln of u between--
well, ln 2, which again, really
doesn't matter, and infinity.
And we see that at the upper
bound, we get ln of infinity,
which is infinity.
So this thing is infinity.
So our original series
diverges.
OK.
So we've applied the integral
test here, and we've found
that our series diverges.
What about this second one?
Well, here, we can again apply
the integral test, the
similar-looking integrand.
And in fact, so we get, so the
integral that we want to look
at is the integral from 2 to
infinity of 1 over x times log
of x squared dx.
And the same substitution
is going to work here.
So we're going to use the
substitution u equals ln x, du
equals 1 over x times dx.
And the bounds are going to be
the same. ln 2 to infinity.
OK.
But what happens when we
make this substitution?
Well, the 1 over x dx
is still the du.
But then here, this time, we
have 1 over u squared, right?
Because we've got an ln of
x squared, and u is ln x.
So OK.
So we get 1 over u squared.
So again, this is easy
to integrate.
So this is 1 over u squared, so
that's going to be minus 1
over u when we integrate it
between ln 2 and infinity.
OK.
So we take the two values here,
as u goes to infinity,
minus 1 over u goes to 0.
So this is 0 minus, and now
with the lower bound, it's
minus 1 over ln 2, and
this is just ln 2.
So this integral converges to a
nice finite value, ln of 2,
so that means the sum
converges as well.
All right?
And in fact, if you go back and
look at the lecture video,
you'll see that you can actually
bound the value of
the sum in terms of this value,
ln of 2, the value of
the integral, and the first
terms of the sum.
I realized that I should have
said one thing at the
beginning, which is that we
didn't check that the
hypotheses of the integral
test are valid here.
So remember that the integral
test only applies if this
function that you use is a
decreasing positive function
on the interval in question.
And I didn't actually check
those conditions.
They're easy to see in
this case, right?
Because for n bigger than 2, n
is positive and increasing,
and log n is positive and
increasing, so the product is
positive and increasing, so
there the 1 over it is
positive and decreasing.
So it's easy to check, in this
case, that that the conditions
of the integral test apply.
In the, when you're doing this
out in the real world, if you
ever want to apply the
integral test, that's
something you should check
yourself before you go and
apply it to anything.
Make sure that you really
have a function to
which it does apply.
But then, once you have a
function to which it does
apply, especially if it's a
nice, easy to integrate
function like this, you
can easily apply it.
And in this case, we applied
it both directions.
We saw an integral where the
integral diverges, and an
integral where the integral
converges.
And so the corresponding sums,
the first one will diverge and
the second one will converge.
I'll end there.