JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about using the
method of Lagrange multipliers
to optimize functions of
several variables given
a constraint.
So here's a problem that you can
practice this method on.
So I've got a function f of x,
y, z equals x squared plus x
plus 2y squared plus
3z squared.
And what I'd like you to do is
find the maximum and minimum
values that this function takes
as the point x, y, z
moves around the unit sphere x
squared plus y squared plus z
squared equals 1.
So to optimize this function
given the constraint x squared
plus y squared plus z
squared equals 1.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to work
that out, come back, and we
can work it out together.
Hopefully you had some luck
working on this problem.
Let's have a go at it.
So remember that the method
of Lagrange multipliers--
in order to apply it-- what it
says is that when you have a
function being optimized on
some constraint condition,
what you do to find the points
where the function could be
maximum or minimum is that
first you look for points
where the gradient of your
objective function is parallel
to the gradient of your
constraint function.
So what that means is you take
the partial derivatives fx,
fy, fz, and you say fx has to
be equal to lambda times gx,
fy has to be equal to lambda
times gy, and fz has to be
equal to lambda times
gz, for some lambda.
And then you solve that
system together with
the constraint equation.
And so the points that are the
solutions of that system of
equations, those points are your
points that you have to
check for whether they're the
maximum or the minimum.
And also, sometimes you have
some boundary to your region
and you have to check
that as well.
So in this case, the sphere
doesn't have boundary.
Right?
So we don't have any boundary
conditions to check.
So we're going to have a really
straightforward problem
to solve where we just have
to look at the partial
derivatives.
So let's write down that system
of equations that we
have to solve.
So the partial derivative of f
with respect to x is going to
be 2x plus 1.
So we have to solve the system
2x plus 1 equals.
And the partial derivative of
our constraint with respect to
x is 2x, so 2x plus 1 has to
equal lambda times 2x.
That's what we get from the
x-partial derivatives.
How about from the y-partial
derivatives?
The y-partial derivative
of f is going to be 4y.
So that has to be equal to
lambda and the y-partial
derivative of the constraint
equation which is 2y.
And the z-partial derivative
of f is 6z.
So 6z has to be equal to
lambda times, well the
z-partial derivative
of the constraint
function which is 2z.
And we have the last equation x
squared plus y squared plus
z squared equals 1.
So we get four equations in
our variables x, y, and z,
plus this new parameter lambda
that we introduced.
And we want to solve these to
find the points x, y, and z at
which these equations
are all satisfied.
And then, once we get those
points, we have to test them
to see whether they
are the maximum or
the minimum or neither.
So OK.
So we have this system
of equations.
Now, this is a little
bit complicated.
It's not a system of
linear equations.
So we need to think about ways
that we can solve it.
And one thing that I think we
can do here, is if you look at
the second and third equations,
you see that in the
second equation, everything
has a factor of y in it.
So either y is equal to 0,
or we can divide by it.
So from the second equation, we
have that either y is equal
to 0, or we can divide by y, in
which case we get lambda is
equal to 2.
Similarly, from the third
equation, we have that either
z is equal to 0, or we can
divide by z and we get lambda
is equal to 3.
So from the third equation
we have z equals 0 or
lambda equals 3.
So now we have a bunch of
possibilities, right?
So either we have y equals z
equals 0, or we have y equals
0 and lambda equals 3, or
we have lambda equals 2
and z equals 0.
Or well, the other possibility
would be lambda equals 2 and
lambda equals 3, but
that can't happen.
So we have three
possibilities.
Three different ways that
this could be satisfied.
So let's go over here and
write down what those
possibilities are.
So case one, or maybe
I'll call it case a.
So the case a is when y is
equal to z is equal to 0.
So when y is equal to
z is equal to 0--
OK, we need to find x's still.
So let's look back
at our equations.
And when y is equal to z is
equal to 0, well we can solve
our constraint equation for x.
When y equals z equals 0, we
have that x squared equals 1.
So there are two
possibilities.
The point 1, 0, 0, and the
point minus 1, 0, 0.
So this gives us, in this case,
we have x equals 1 or x
equals minus 1.
So that gives us the points 1,
0, 0, and minus 1, 0, 0 that
we're going to have to
check at the end.
All right.
So the second case is we could
have y equal to 0 and lambda
equal to 3.
So in this case, let's go back
to our equations again.
So from lambda equals 3, we
have in our first equation
that 2x plus 1 equals 6x.
So 1 equals 4x or
x equals 1/4.
So this implies over here
that x equals 1/4.
And now, we still
need to find z.
So if we go back to our
constraint equation here, we
have that x is a quarter
and y is 0.
So that means 1/16 plus
z squared equals 1.
So z has to be the square root
of 15/16, plus or minus.
And z is equal to plus or minus,
so that we can also
write that as the square
root of 15 over 4.
So this also gives us
two points to check.
The points are 1/4, 0, the
square root of 15 over 4.
And 1/4, 0, minus square
root of 15 over 4.
And finally, we have
our third case.
So our third case is when lambda
is equal to 2 and z is
equal to 0.
So again, let's go back
over to our equation.
So when lambda equals 2 in the
first equation, we have 2x
plus 1 equals 4x.
So 2x equals 1 or x is 1/2.
So this gives us x
equals a half.
And now if you take z equals 0
and x equals 1/2, we can take
that down to our constraint
equation.
And we get a quarter plus y
squared equals 1, so y is a
square root of 3/4.
So y equals plus or minus
square root of 3 over 2.
And this gives us two points.
1/2, square root
of 3 over 2, 0.
And 1/2, minus square
root of 3 over 2, 0.
Those were our three cases.
We've solved each of them.
We've solved each of them all
the way down to finding the
points that they lead to.
Now remember, we said already
that there's no boundary to
this region.
It's just the sphere.
It has no edges.
So these are the only points
we have to check.
We have to check these
six points.
What do we have to
check them for?
Well, we have to look at the
value of f at each of these
six points.
And we want to figure out where
f is maximized and where
f is minimized, and these six
points are the only points
where that could happen,
where f could be
maximized or minimized.
So we just have to evaluate our
objective function f at
these six points and find
the largest value and
the smallest value.
So let's do that.
So our objective function,
remember, it's all the way
back over here.
It's this function x squared
plus x plus 2y
squared plus 3z squared.
OK.
So let's look at the value of
that function at these point.
So x squared plus x plus 2y
squared plus 3z squared at the
point 1, 0, that's
just equal to 2.
So I'm going to write the
function values just off to
the side of the points here.
So this gives me the value 2.
And I'm going to circle them.
So the point 1, 0, 0 gives
me the value 2.
The point minus 1, 0, 0--
so that's x squared is one, plus
x is minus 1, so that's 1
minus 1 is 0, and then the
y and z terms are both 0.
So at the point minus 1, 0, 0,
the function value is 0.
I'm going to circle that.
Oh boy.
OK, so at these points--
at the point 1/4, 0, square root
of 15 over 4, and 1/4, 0,
minus square root
of 15 over 4--
I'm going to cheat and look at
what I wrote down already.
So you could do the arithmetic
yourself, but I think it's not
that hard to work out that in
both of these cases, the
function value that you
get out is 25 over 8.
I'm not going to do the
arithmetic right now.
But you can double-check
that for yourself.
And at these last two points--
the points 1/2, root 3 over 2,
0, and 1/2, minus root
3 over 2, 0--
the function has the same value
at both of those points.
That value is 9/4.
Yeah, so 25 over 8 was the value
at both of these points,
and 9/4 is the value of
both of these points.
So now, to find the maximum
value of the function and the
minimum value of the function,
we just look at the values
that we got and say, which of
these is biggest and which of
these is smallest?
And in our case, it's easy to
see that 0 is the minimum.
You know, all the
other values are
positive, so 0 is the minimum.
So our minimum value of f is 0
at the point minus 1, 0, 0.
And if you just compare the
values 2 and 25/8 and 9/4,
25/8 is the largest. This is
bigger than 3, whereas both of
those are less than
3, for example.
This is one easy way
to see that.
So the max of f is 25/8, and
that's achieved at the points
1/4, 0, plus or minus square
root of 15 over 4.
So there you have it.
The method of Lagrange
multipliers.
We just followed exactly the
strategy that we have.
So you start out and you have
an objective function and a
constraint function.
And so what do you do?
You write down their partial
derivatives and you come up
with this system of equations.
So this system of equations that
you get by setting, you
know, fx equal to lambda gx,
fy equal to lambda gy, fz
equals lambda gz, and your
constraint equation g equals
some constant.
So then the one part of this
procedure that isn't just a
recipe is that you need to
solve this system of
equations, but sometimes
that can be hard.
So in this case, there were a
couple of observations that we
could make from the second and
third equations that made it
relatively straightforward
to do.
And that gave us some cases.
And then in each of those
cases, we were able to
completely solve for the
points x, y, and z.
Now we also could solve for
the associated values of
lambda, but lambda isn't
important to us.
It doesn't affect f.
We can forget about it as soon
as we found it, once we found
x, y, and z.
So we were able to solve.
In this case, we got six points
of interest. And then
you just look at the value of
your objective function at
those points.
So that was what I wrote
down in these circles.
So you look at the value of
the objective function.
And to find the maximum value of
the function, you just look
at which of those is largest.
Now sometimes--
not in this problem, but in
other problems, you'll also
have to check--
if the region has a boundary,
you'll also have to check for
possible maxima and minima on
the boundary of the region.
But a sphere doesn't have
any edges, so it
doesn't have any boundary.
So we don't have to
worry about that.
So that's how we apply the
method of Lagrange multipliers
to this problem.
And how you can apply it to
other problems as well.
I'll end there.