PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture you've been doing
definite integration for the
last couple of lectures.
And you've just started
with the
fundamental theorem of calculus.
So, that gives us this whole
powerful tool to compute a
bunch of integrals.
So, with that in mind I've got
a couple questions for you.
So compute the definite
integrals.
The integral from pi over 6
to pi over 3 of tan x dx.
And the integral of minus
pi over 3 to pi
over 3 of tan x dx.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a couple minutes
to work on those, come
back and we'll
work on them together.
All right.
Welcome back.
So, as we were saying
we have a couple of
definite integrals here.
So one tool for definite
integrals is Riemann sums. So,
in principle, we could write
down a Riemann sum for, say,
this first integral here.
And then try and compute it by
trying to compute the sum and
taking a limit of it.
But I think it's pretty clear
that, for a function like tan
x, that's going to be really,
really hard to do.
So we want to not use
Riemann sums here.
And the way we can not use
Riemann sums is using this
great tool that we have,
which is the
fundamental theorem of calculus.
So the fundamental theorem of
calculus says, when you have a
definite integral, instead of
computing Riemann sums, what
you can do is compute an
antiderivative and use the
antiderivative to find out
what the integral is.
Just compare two values with the
antiderivative and that'll
give you the value of the
definite integral.
So, in particular, let's do this
first integral first. So
we have the integral from
pi over 6 to pi
over 3 of tan x dx.
Well, so, we know what the
antiderivative of tan x is.
We did that in an earlier
recitation.
So that's ln of cosine x.
Or ln of the absolute
value of cosine x.
So, the fundamental theorem of
calculus says that the value
of this definite integral, in
order to compute it, we just
take the difference of that
antiderivative at pi over 3
and at pi over 6.
So, by the fundamental theorem
of calculus this is equal to
ln of the absolute value of
cosine x for x between pi over
6 and pi over 3.
So, OK, so this, you know, this
is this notation that
Professor Jerison introduced.
So what does this
actually mean?
It's just a shorthand for ln
of the absolute value of
cosine of pi over 3 minus ln
cosine of pi over 6.
Now, we could leave our answer
like this but we can also
manipulate it and put it
in a little nicer form.
So, cosine of pi over 3 is--
oh, I'm sorry I've
made a mistake.
So it's not ln of absolute
value cosine x.
It's minus ln of absolute
value of cosine x.
Sorry about that.
So this is minus ln cosine
pi over 3 plus--
OK, so minus and minus
there is plus.
All right.
Sorry about that.
OK, so, good.
All right.
And we can pick up where I was
in the middle of my sentence
and OK, so we can just
evaluate this by just
evaluating.
So cosine of pi over 3, that's
going to be 1/2.
So this is minus ln and
absolute value of
1/2 is just a 1/2.
Plus cosine of pi over 6 is
square root of 3 over 2.
So plus ln square root
of 3 over 2.
And now you can use your
logarithm rules to combine
those into a single
expression.
So this is equal to ln
of square root of 3.
Or you could even use one more
logarithm rule if you wanted.
So this is equal
to 1/2 ln of 3.
So all of those are, you know,
equivalent expressions for the
same number, which
is the value of
this definite integral.
OK, so, for the second integral
now, we can do
exactly the same thing
if we wanted to.
And it'll be a very
similar process.
You'll write down this
antiderivative here, you'll
take the difference in values.
We can also do something
a little bit
clever for this one.
Which is, definite integrals
have some geometric
interpretation, right?
And if you think about
the function tan x--
so we could put up a
little graph here--
so in between minus pi over 3
and pi over 3, tan x maybe
looks something like this.
Yeah, you know, give or take.
OK, so what's important
about this?
Well tan x is an odd function.
And this interval from--
this is minus pi over 3 to pi
over 3, and this is the curve
y equals tan x.
So this is an odd function.
So the integral in question is
this positive area minus this
negative area.
But since it's an odd function,
it's symmetric.
So those two cancel
out perfectly.
So for the second one,
you could do the same
process that we did.
But you can also use a little
bit of geometric reasoning to
realize that this second
one is just equal to 0.
In either case, doing either of
these integral with Riemann
sums would be really
atrocious.
So, in both cases, what we're
really happy about is that we
have these other tools that
allow us to evaluate definite
integrals without going back to
the Riemann definition of
the integral.
So, I'm going to stop there.