Today I want to talk with you
about Doppler effect,
and I will start with the
Doppler effect of sound which
many of you perhaps remember
from your high school physics.
If a source of sound moves
towards you or if you move
towards a source of sound,
you hear an increase in the
pitch.
And if you move away from each
other you hear a decrease of a
pitch.
Let this be the transmitter of
sounds and this is the receiver
of sound, it could be you,
your ears.
And suppose this is the
velocity of the transmitter and
this is the velocity of the
receiver.
And V should be larger than
zero if the velocity is in the
direction.
And in the equations what
follow, smaller than zero it is
in this direction.
The frequency that the receiver
will experience,
will hear if you like that
word, that frequency I call F
prime.
And F is the frequency as it is
transmitted by the transmitter.
And that F prime is F times the
speed of sound minus V receiver
divided by the speed of sound
minus V of the transmitter.
So this is known as the Doppler
shift equation.
If you have Volume one of
Giancoli you can look it up
there as well.
Suppose you are not moving at
all.
You are sitting still.
So V receiver is zero.
But I move towards you with one
meter per second.
If I move towards you then F
prime will be larger than F.
If I move away from you with
one meter per second then F
prime will be smaller than F.
The speed of sound is three
hundred forty meters per second.
So if F which is the frequency
that I will produce is four
thousand hertz,
then if I move to you with one
meter per second,
which I'm going to try to do,
then the frequency that you
will experience is about four
thousand twelve hertz.
It's up by oh point three
percent.
Which is that ratio one divided
by three forty.
And if I move away from you
with one meter per second,
then the frequency that you
will hear is about twelve hertz
lower.
So you hear a lower pitch.
About oh point three percent
lower.
I have here a tuning fork.
Tuning fork is four thousand
hertz.
I will bang it and I will try
to move my hand towards you one
meter per second roughly.
That's what I calculated it
roughly is.
Move it away from you,
towards you,
away from you,
as long
as the sound lasts.
You will hear the pitch change
from four thousand twelve to
three thousand nine hundred
eight-eight.
Very noticeable.
Have you heard it?
Who has heard clearly the
Doppler shift,
raise your hands,
please?
OK.
Chee chee chee chee it's very
clear.
Increased fre- frequency and
then when I move my hands away a
lower
pitch.
Now you may think that it makes
no difference whether I move
towards you or whether you move
towards me.
And that is indeed true if the
speeds are very small compared
to the speed of sound.
But it is not true anymore when
we approach the speed of sound.
As an example,
if you move away from me with
the speed of sound,
you will never hear me.
Because the sound will never
catch up with you,
and so F prime is zero.
And you can
indeed confirm that with this
equation.
But if I moved away from you
with the speed of sound,
for sure the sound will reach
with you.
And the frequency that you will
hear is only half of the one
that I produce.
So there's a huge asymmetry.
Big difference whether I move
or whether you move.
So I now want to turn towards
electromagnetic radiation.
There is also a Doppler shift
in electromagnetic radiation.
If you see a traffic light red
and you approach it with high
enough speed you will experience
a higher frequency and then you
will see the wavelengths shorter
than red and you may even think
it's green.
You may even go through that
traffic light.
To calculate the proper
relation between F prime and F
requires special relativity.
And so I will give you the
final result.
F prime is the one that you
receive.
F is the one that is emitted by
the transmitter.
And we get here then one minus
beta divided by one plus beta to
the power one-half.
And beta is V over C,
C being the speed of light,
and V being the s- speed,
the relative speed between the
transmitter and you.
If beta is larger than zero you
are receding from each other in
this equation.
If beta is smaller than zero
you are approaching each other.
You may wonder why we don't
make a distinction now between
the transmitter on the one hand,
the velocity,
and the receiver on the other
hand.
There's only one beta.
Well, that is typical for
special relativity.
What counts is only relative
motion.
There is no such thing as
absolute motion.
The question are you moving
relative to me or I relative to
you is an illegal question in
special relativity.
What counts is only relative
motion.
If we are in vacuum then lambda
equals C divided by F and so
lambda prime equals C divided by
F prime.
Lambda prime is now the
wavelength that you receive and
lambda is the wavelength that
was emitted by the --
by the source.
So I can substitute in here,
in this F, C divided by lambda
which is more commonly done.
So this Doppler shift equation
for electromagnetic radiation is
more common given in terms of
lambda.
But of course the two are
identical.
And then you get now one plus
beta upstairs divided by one
minus beta to the power
one-half.
The velocity there if I'm
completely honest with you is
the radial velocity.
If you are here and here is the
source of emission and if the
relative velocity between the
two of you were this,
then it is this component,
this angle is theta,
this component which is V
cosine theta,
which we call the radial
velocity,
that is really the velocity
which is in that equation.
Police cars measure your speed
with radar.
They reflect the radar off your
car and they measure the change
in frequency as the radar is
reflected.
That gives a Doppler shift
because of your speed and that's
the way they determine the speed
of your car to a very high
degree of accuracy.
You can imagine that in
astronomy
Doppler shift plays a key role.
Because we can measure the
radial velocities of stars
relative to us.
Most stellar spectra show
discrete frequencies,
discrete wavelength,
which result from atoms and
molecules in the atmosphere of
the stars.
Last lecture I showed you with
your own gradings a neon light
source and I convinced you that
there were discrete
frequencies and discrete
wavelengths emitted by the neon.
If a particular discrete
wavelength, for instance in our
own laboratory,
would be five thousand
Angstrom, and look at the star,
and I see that that wavelength
is longer, lambda prime is
larger than lambda,
then I conclude -- lambda prime
is larger than lambda,
that means the wavelength the
way I observe it is shifted
towards longer wavelength,
is shifted in the direction of
the red, and we call that red
shift.
It means that we are receding
from each other.
If however I measure lambda
prime to be smaller than lambda,
so lambda prime smaller than
lambda, we call that blue shift
in astronomy,
and it means that we are
approaching each other.
And so we make reference to the
direction in the spectrum where
the lines are moving.
I can give you a simple
example.
I looked up for the star Delta
Leporis what the red shift is.
There is a line that most stars
show in their spectrum which is
due to calcium,
it even has a particular name,
I think it's called the calcium
K
line, but that's not so
important, the name.
In our own laboratory lambda is
known to a high degree of
accuracy, is three nine three
three point six six four
Angstroms.
We look at the star and we
recognize without a doubt that
that's due to calcium in the
atmosphere of the star and we
find that lambda prime is one
point two nine eight
Angstroms higher than lambda.
So lambda prime is larger than
lambda.
So there is red shift and so we
are receding from each other.
I go to that equation.
I substitute lambda prime and
lambda in there and I find that
beta equals plus three point
three times ten to the minus
four.
The plus for beta indeed
confirms that we are receding,
that our relative velocity is
away from each other,
and I find therefore that the
radial velocity -- I stress it
is the radial component of our
velocity is then beta times C
and that turns out to be
approximately ninety-nine
kilometers per second.
So I have measured now the
relative velocity,
radial velocity,
between the star and me,
and the question whether the
star is moving away from me or I
move away from the star is an
irrelevant question,
this is always a relative
velocity that matters.
How can I measure the
wavelength shifts so accurately
that we can see the difference
of one point three Angstroms out
of four thousand?
The way that it's done is that
you observe the starlight and
you make a spectrum and at the
same time you make a spectrum of
light sources in the laboratory
with well-known and
well-calibrated wavelength.
Suppose there were some neon in
the atmosphere of a star.
Then you could compare the neon
light the way we looked at it
last lecture.
You could compare it with the
wavelength that you see from the
star and you can see very very
small shifts.
You make a relative
measurement.
So you need spectrometers with
very high spectral resolution.
So there was a big industry in
the early twentieth century to
measure these relative
velocities of stars.
And their speeds were typically
a hundred, two hundred
kilometers per
second.
Not unlike the star that I just
calculated for you.
Some of those stars relative to
us are approaching.
Other stars are receding in our
galaxy.
But it was Slipher in the
nineteen twenties who observed
the red shift of some nebulae
which were believed at the time
to be in our own galaxy and he
found that they were -- had a
very high velocity of up to
fifteen hundred kilometers per
second, and they were always
moving away from us.
And it was found shortly after
that that these nebulae were not
in our own galaxy but that they
were galaxies in their own
right.
So they were collections of
about ten billion stars just
like our own galaxy.
And so when you take a spectrum
of those galaxies,
then of course you get the
average of millions and millions
of stars, but that still would
allow you then to calculate the
red shift, the average red
shift, of the galaxy,
and therefore uh its velocity.
And Hubble, the famous
astronomer after which the
Hubble space telescope is named,
and Humason made a very
courageous attempt to measure
also the distance to these
galaxies.
They knew the velocities.
That was easy because they knew
the red shifts.
The distance determinations in
astronomy is a can of worms.
And I will spare you the
details about the distance
determinations.
But Hubble made a spectacular
discovery.
He found a linear relation
between the velocity and the
distances.
And we know this as Hubble's
law.
And Hubble's law is that the
velocity is a constant which is
now named after Hubble,
capital H, times D.
And the modern value for H,
the modern value for H is
seventy-two kilometers per
second per megaparsec.
What is a megaparsec?
A megaparsec is a distance.
In astronomy we don't deal with
inches, we don't deal with
kilometers, that is just not big
enough, we deal with parsecs and
megaparsecs.
And one megaparsec is three
point two six times ten to the
six light-years.
And if you want that in
kilometers,
it's not unreasonable question,
it's about three point one
times ten to the nineteen
kilometers.
So I could calculate for a
specific galaxy that I have in
mind, I can calculate the
distance if I know the red
shift.
I have a particular galaxy in
mind for which lambda prime --
for which lambda prime is one
point zero zero three three
times lambda.
So notice again that the
wavelength that I receive is
indeed longer than lambda,
so there is a red shift.
I go to my Doppler shift
equation which is this one.
I calculate beta.
One equation with one unknown,
can solve for beta.
And I find now that V is five
thousand kilometers per second.
Very straightforward,
nothing special,
very easy calculation.
But now with Hubble's law I can
calculate what D is.
Because D now is the velocity
which is five thousand
kilometers per second divided by
that seventy-two and that then
is approximately sixty-nine
megaparsec.
Again we have the distance if
we do it in these units in
megaparsecs.
That's about two hundred and
twenty-five million light-years.
And so the object is about two
hundred and twenty-five million
light-years away from us.
So it took the light two
hundred and twenty-five million
years to reach us.
So when you see light from this
object you're looking back in
time.
And if you have a galaxy which
is twice as far away as this
one, then the velocity would be
twice as high.
And they're always receding
relative to us.
I'd like to show you now some
spectra of three galaxies.
Can I have the first slide,
John?
All right, you see here a
galaxy and here you see the
spectrum of that galaxy.
That may not be very impressive
to
you.
The lines that are being
recognized to be due to calcium
K and calcium eight are these
two dark lines.
Some of you may not even be
able to see them.
And this is the comparison
spectra taken in the laboratory.
These lines are seen as dark
lines, not as bright lines.
We call them absorption lines.
They are formed in the
atmosphere of the star.
Why they show up as dark lines
and not as bright lines is not
important now.
I don't want to go into that.
That's too much astronomy.
But
they are lines and that's what
counts.
And these lines are shifted
towards the red part of the
spectrum by a teeny weeny little
bit.
You see here this little arrow.
And the conclusion then is that
in this case the velocity of
that galaxy is t- seven hundred
twenty miles per second which
translates into eleven hundred
fifty kilometers per second,
and so that brings this object
if you believe the modern value
for Hubble constant at about
sixteen megaparsec.
This galaxy is substantially
farther away.
No surprise that it therefore
also looks smaller in size,
and notice that here the lines
have shifted.
These lines have shifted
substantially further.
And if I did my homework using
the velocity that they claim,
which they can do with high
degree of accuracy because you
can calculate lambda prime
divided by lambda,
those measurements can be made
with enorm- accuracy,
I find that this object is
about three hundred five
megaparsecs away from us,
so that's about twenty times
further away than this object.
So the speed is also about
twenty times higher of course
because there's a linear
relationship.
And if you look at this one
which is even further away,
then notice that these lines
have shifted even more.
The next slide shows you what I
would call Hubble diagram.
It was kindly sent to me by
Wendy
Freedman and her coworkers.
Wendy is the leader of a large
team of scientists who are
making observations with the
Hubble space telescope.
You see here distance and you
see here velocity in the units
that we used in class,
kilometers per second.
Forget this part.
That's not so important.
But you see the incredible
linear relationship.
And Wendy concluded that
Hubble's constant is around
seventy-two.
It could be a little lower,
it could be a little higher.
She goes out all the way to
four hundred megaparsecs with
associated velocities of about
twenty-six thousand kilometers
per second.
That's about nine percent of
the speed of light.
So beta is about one-tenth.
So for this object lambda prime
divided by lambda would be about
one point one.
With a ten percent shift in the
wavelength.
Hubble, who published his data
in
the twenties,
his whole data set when he
concluded that there was a
linear relation had only objects
with velocities less than eleven
hundred kilometers per second.
And eleven hundred kilometers
per second is this point here.
So Hubble had only points --
there are not even any in
Wendy's diagram,
which are here.
And he concluded courageously
that there was this linear
relationship.
And you see it has stood the
acid test.
We still believe it is linear.
The only difference was that
Hubble's distances were very
different from what we believe
today.
They were about seven times
smaller.
So Hubble constant was
different for him but the linear
relationship was there.
OK, that's enough for this
slide.
So now comes a sixty-four
dollar question,
why do all galaxies which are
far away, why w- do they move
away from us?
Well,
I can uh suggest a very simple
picture to you.
We are at the center of the
universe and there was a huge
explosion a long time ago.
We refer to that explosion as
the Big Bang.
And since we are at the center
where the explosion occurred,
the galaxies which obtained the
largest speed in the explosion
are now the farthest away from
us.
Now assume that this explosion
is the correct idea.
Assume that there was a Big
Bang.
Then I can ask the question now
when did it occur?
I can now turn the clock back
and I can do the following.
I can take two objects which
are a distance D apart today but
they were together when the
universe was born at the Big
Bang.
And let's assume that they have
been going away from each other
always with the same velocity.
Let's assume that now for
simplicity.
So if they always went away
with the same velocity from each
other then the distance that
they are now today is their
velocity times the time T which
is then the age of the universe.
But we also know with Hubble's
law that the velocity V is H
times D.
And we assume that these
velocities are the same now for
simplicity.
You multiply these two
equations with each other and
you find immediately that the
age of the
universe is one over H.
And that indeed has the unit of
time.
If you take H,
the one that we believe in
nowadays, and you calculate one
over H, and you work in M K S
units, you'll find that T H is
about fourteen billion years,
I'll first give it to you in
seconds, it's about four point
three times ten to the seventeen
seconds.
And that is about fourteen
billion years.
So with this picture in mind,
the universe would be about
fourteen billion years old,
but because of the
gravitational attraction of
these galaxies,
they attract each other,
you may expect that the speed
of the galaxies was larger in
the past, and therefore the
speed that we have -- we assume
that the speed doesn't change is
not quite accurate,
and so maybe the universe is a
little younger,
maybe twelve billion years or
so.
We know from theoretical
calculations that the oldest
stars in our own galaxy are
about ten billion years old.
Therefore the universe cannot
be younger than ten billion
years.
And there is general consensus
in the community that our
universe is probably twelve to
fourteen billion years old.
Now the whole issue of this
deceleration that I mentioned as
the galaxies moved away from
each other is at the heart of
research in
cosmology.
And in fact it is now believed
that very early on in the
universe there was first
acceleration followed by
deceleration,
and maybe again acceleration.
That is quite mysterious.
Frontier research is going on
in this area.
At MIT we have three world
experts, Professors Alan Guth,
w- made major contributions to
this concept,
cosmology, we have Ed
Bertschinger and we have Scott
Burles.
If we take Hubble's law at face
value, I can calculate how far
the edge of our visible universe
is.
Which is the horizon.
We call that the horizon.
I can calculate what the
maximum distance is that we can
look.
D maximum can be found by
making the velocity C.
So that the galaxies are moving
-- we are moving away from the
galaxies, the galaxies are
moving away from us -- with the
speed of light.
And so you would find then that
D
max is C divided by H.
That is a distance.
And you will find then,
no surprise,
if you use the modern number,
that that distance is fourteen
billion light-years.
We can never see beyond that.
Because if V equals C then beta
becomes one and if beta becomes
one lambda prime becomes
infinitely large,
you have an infinite amount
of red shift,
and F prime becomes zero.
So the electromagnetic
radiation has no frequency
anymore and so there's no energy
anymore in the photons.
So that is then the edge of our
universe, of our visible
universe.
You can never see beyond that.
So now comes a reasonable
question.
How far have we been able to
see into the universe?
And to my knowledge the record
holder is a galaxy for which
lambda prime over lambda is
seven point five six.
Was published only two months
ago.
Seven point five six.
Now at such very large values
of red shift,
general relativity becomes very
important.
And the equation that we
derived here was derived for
special relativity.
And so with very high values of
red
shift like lambda prime over
lambda seven point five six you
cannot reliably calculate the
velocities using that equation.
And so you cannot use that
velocity then and shove it into
Hubble's law and find the -- the
distance.
But there is no question that
the -- that object is probably
at a distance of something like
thirteen billion light-years.
Very very far away from us,
near the edge of our universe.
I will show you an object that
is also believed to be near the
edge of the universe.
It comes up in the next slide.
The distance is roughly twelve
billion light-years.
So for one, when you look at
that object, there it is -- it
doesn't look very impressive but
what do you expect from an
object that is twelve billion
light-years away from us?
It's a quasar,
which is a very peculiar
galaxy.
It uh emits emission lines,
the spectra do not show these
dark lines that I showed you
earlier, but they actually have
emission lines,
and the light that you see here
was emitted some twelve billion
years ago.
And now comes the spectrum from
this object in the next slide.
This was published last year by
Scott Anderson and his
coworkers, University of
Washington in Seattle.
I have collaborated with Scott
on many projects.
So here you see the spectrum of
that quasar that you just saw.
And here you see a line,
an emission line,
at roughly seven --
seventy-eight hundred Angstroms.
And there are all reasons to
believe that this in the frame
of reference of that quasar was
the Lyman alpha line which is
emitted by hydrogen,
which is twelve hundred and
sixteen
Angstroms.
Now we have here five thousand,
four thousand,
three thousand,
two thousand,
one thousand,
so here is roughly where the
wavelength lambda is,
and here is lambda prime.
Lambda prime is six point four
one times larger than lambda.
He mentions five point four
one, but Z is what astronomers
in general quote is lambda prime
divided by lambda minus one,
so the ratio lambda prime over
lambda is six point four one.
Absolutely amazing that you can
make such accurate measurements,
such incredible beautiful data,
and this line is all the way in
the infrared,
you cannot see this with your
naked eye anymore,
our eyes I think can only see
up to sixty-five hundred.
So the twelve sixteen line was
in the UV, shifts all the way
into the infrared,
and this allows astronomers
then to measure the value lambda
prime over
lambda, and there is little
doubt that this object is also
near the edge of our visible
universe.
That's enough,
John, thank you.
I'd like to return to the Big
Bang, to the explosion some
twelve or fifteen billion years
ago.
And I'd like to raise the
question, are we at the center
of that explosion?
Are we really at the center of
our universe?
That cannot be of course.
It's an incredible arrogance.
It would be too egocentric.
I know that we all think very
highly of ourselves,
but this cannot be.
We are nothing in the framework
of the total universe.
We cannot possibly be at the
center.
So how do we reconcile this now
with what we observe?
Imagine that you were a raisin
in a raisin bread.
Quite a promotion,
from a human being to a raisin
in a raisin bread.
And I put you in an oven.
And the raisin bread,
the dough is going to expand.
All raisins will see other
raisins move away from each
other and the larger the
distance to your raisins the
larger the speed will be.
And each raisin will think that
they are very special.
Suppose here this is you,
one raisin, and here's another
raisin, and here's another
raisin.
After a certain amount of time
all distances have doubled.
So this one is here.
And this one is here.
So you can immediately see that
when you look at this one,
that its velocity is
substantially lower than that
one.
This is twice as far away,
you will see twice as high a
speed.
But this raisin will look at
this one.
And it will also conclude that
this raisin relative to this one
has a higher velocity than this
raisin has relative to this one.
So all of them will think that
they are special and you as a
raisin would
come up with Hubble's law.
You would conclude that the
velocity of your other raisins
are linearly proportional to the
distance.
There is an analogy which is
even nicer than raisin bread,
and that analogy is with
Flatlanders.
A Flatlander is someone who
lives on a two-dimensional
world.
He happens to live on the
surface of a balloon.
And light travels only along
the surface of the balloon.
So the two-dimensional world is
curved in the third dimension,
but the Flatlanders cannot see
in the third dimension.
They can only see the second
dimension.
So here you have such a world.
So here are the galaxies.
Flat world.
And the universe is curved in
the third dimension which these
Flatlanders cannot see.
And when you blow this balloon
up,
the galaxies move away from
each other, and the farther the
galaxies are away from each
other, the higher the velocity.
This model works actually quite
well and I want to pursue that
in my next calculations.
Let me first try to bring this
universe to a halt.
Because I don't want the
universe
to collapse again.
Ooh.
OK.
I succeeded.
So you can pursue this idea
very nicely and you can see that
the Flatlanders would draw quite
amazing conclusions.
Here is that balloon.
The balloon has a radius R.
Here is one galaxy.
And here is another galaxy.
And they are a distance S
apart.
I will call that later D.
But now I want to call it S.
You will see why.
A little later in time,
the universe has expanded,
this galaxy is here and this
galaxy is here.
And this distance now is R plus
dR and so this distance now
between the two galaxies is S
plus dS.
And it follows immediately from
the geometry that S plus dS
divided by S is R plus dR
divided by R.
Simple high school geometry.
I can work this out.
I get S R plus R dS is SR plus
S dR.
I lose this SR.
I divide by dT.
dS dT is the velocity with
which these two
galaxies move away from each
other.
That's they what they would
measure in their universe.
So there is a V here.
It's clear that S is the
distance between them.
I will call that D again now.
So that is D.
And then I have one over R
times dR dT.
One over R I will write this a
little higher.
dR over R.
No no no we had dR dT.
So now I have one over R dR dT.
And look at this.
I have V equals D times
something.
And that something at a given
moment in time has a unique
value.
R of the balloon has a unique
And dR dT which is the
expansion velocity also has a
unique value.
And so it's immediately obvious
that in this universe this is
Hubble's constant.
And this Hubble's constant is a
function of time.
It is changing with time.
And it's obvious that it should
change in time.
No reason why it shouldn't do
the same in our own galaxy.
Because R in the past was much
smaller.
So even if you take an
expansion velocity which is
constant, if R is smaller in the
past, then H was larger in the
past.
And that is the reason why if
you
ever see a quote of H to be
seventy-two kilometers per
second per megaparsec,
there's always a little zero
here.
And the zero means now.
The zero means not a billion
years from now and not a billion
years ago.
We really don't know what it
was a billion years ago.
Now don't get -- don't carry
this analogy between the two-D
balloon and the -- our own
universe too far.
But it gives some interesting
insights.
It is suggestive
of the idea that our own
three-dimensional space may be
curved in the fourth dimension
that we cannot see.
This is very fascinating and I
would advise you if you are
interested in this area that you
take a course in cosmology.
You should also take one in
general relativity.
It will open a whole new world
for you.
And both Allen Guth and Ed
Bertschinger and also Scott
Burles are the experts in this
area and they happen to be one
of our best
teachers.
So you can't lose there.
Now comes a key question and
that is will our universe expand
forever?
If the universe expands
forever, we call that an open
universe, that's just a name.
It's also possible that our
universe will come to a halt.
That means that H,
Hubble's constant,
will become zero,
that everything will stand
still, no relative motion
anymore, which then will be
followed by
collapse.
And so all the red shifts will
then come to zero and will turn
to blue shifts.
It's the same idea,
the same question,
when you throw up an apple,
will the apple come back or
will the apple not come back.
It depends on the speed of the
apple and on the gravitational
field of the earth,
and we all know that if you
throw it fast enough,
about eleven kilometers per
second in the absence of
atmosphere the
apple would never come back.
Now if only gravity played the
key role in our universe,
then we can do a very simple
calculation.
And the answer to whether or
not our universe is open or
closed would then depend on the
average density of the universe.
And when I say average density
then you have to think in terms
of a big scale.
You don't think in terms of
Cambridge.
That's not representative for
the average density of the
universe.
Nor is our solar system.
Nor is our galaxy.
But you have to think probably
on the scale of a few hundred
million parsecs.
Maybe five hundred megaparsecs.
And so I bring you out now into
the universe.
Here is the universe.
And these are galaxies.
And here is a sphere which has
a radius R and that's on a scale
of about five hundred
megaparsecs.
So rho, the average density,
is representative for the
universe.
And here let's suppose you were
here, or I can take any part in
the universe,
there's nothing special about
it, and you see here a galaxy
and that galaxy moves away from
you with a velocity V.
That galaxy has a mass little
M.
The mass inside here,
capital M, inside this sphere,
is four-thirds pi R cubed times
rho.
It's the average density,
right?
Now we know from Newton that
the force that this galaxy will
experience is only determined by
the mass inside this sphere and
not by the mass outside the
sphere.
And so if I want to calculate
whether these two objects will
forever move away from each
other or whether they will fall
back to
each other then all I have to
make sure that I make the total
energy zero, the sum of the
kinetic energy and the potential
energy must be zero.
So one-half MV squared of this
object, it must be M M G divided
by R.
That is when the total energy
is zero.
We will expand forever and ever
and ever and it will never come
back.
Little M cancels out.
Capital M I can write
four-thirds
pi R cubed rho.
Here comes my G and here comes
R.
Notice that the R cubed
upstairs becomes R squared.
And so if I have an R squared
here and I have a V squared
here, remember that V divided by
R, that is Hubble's constant.
Because R is D,
it's the distance between us
and the galaxy.
And so V squared divided by R
squared is the Hubble constant
as we measure it today squared.
And so you'll find then from
this simple result that rho as
it should be today,
that's why I put a little zero
there, is three divided by eight
pi -- I get a G there,
and I get H zero squared.
And so this tells me that if
the density, the average density
of our universe,
is larger than this value,
then our universe will come to
a halt and will collapse.
And we can calculate that
value.
Because we know H zero,
we think we know,
we know G, and so you will find
then -- I'll write it down here,
that rho zero is about ten to
the minus
twenty-six kilograms per cubic
meter.
And so if rho is smaller than
this amount then we will
continue to expand forever,
the universe would be open.
If the mean density right now
is larger than that amount,
then we will -- the expansion
will come to a halt,
red shift will become blue
shifts, and we will collapse
again.
The matter here,
this matter density,
doesn't have to be tomatoes or
potatoes.
It could be electromagnetic
radiation.
Because according to Einstein E
equals MC squared.
So any form of energy
represents mass.
So don't think of it
necessarily as this being the
stars and galaxies and tomatoes.
It is generally believed today
that the expansion of our
universe will not come to a halt
and collapse.
But our views could change.
Enormous development has been
going on in the last ten years
and you can read about that in
the New York Times.
Almost every month you will
read something about the
enormous progress that's being
made in cosmology.
And of course the idea of
whether or not the universe will
expand forever,
whether it's open or whether it
is closed, is something that's
emotionally an important issue
for us.
If the universe is open and it
will expand forever then stars
will all burn out and the
universe will
become a cold,
dead and boring place.
If however the universe is
closed, the expansion will come
to a halt, it will collapse,
and it will end up with what we
call the Big Crunch as opposed
to the Big Bang.
And it will be hot,
there will be fireworks,
it will be like the early days
of the Big Bang.
Temperatures of billions of
degrees.
I'd like to read a poem from
Robert Frost which he wrote in
nineteen
twenty.
It's called Fire and Ice.
Some say the world will end in
fire, some say in ice.
From what I've tasted of
desire, I hold with those who
favor fire.
But if it had to perish twice,
I think I know enough of hate
to know that for destruction ice
is also great.
And would suffice.
There are many people who want
our universe to be closed,
probably for emotional reasons,
maybe for religious reasons,
maybe
it's more esthetic,
maybe it's more reassuring,
maybe it's more romantic.
I don't know.
But if it's open the end is not
very spectacular.
T.
S.
Eliot wrote,
"This is the way the world ends
not with a bang but a whimper."
Now it is conceivable that the
expansion of the universe will
come to a halt and that the
universe will ultimately
collapse.
We will have a big crunch.
And it is even conceivable that
a
new universe will then be born
afterwards.
That there will be a new Big
Bang.
And if the evolution of that
universe were a carbon copy,
exact carbon copy of the
present universe,
a few thousand billion years
from now we may have a great
eight oh two reunion.
Same place same time same
people, perhaps see you then.