The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: So a lot of folks,
for instance, the rise in
online poker or something.
And they will say that, oh,
we don't fall into the tax
bracket for gambling because
we're a skill-based game.
But literally [INAUDIBLE]
is about competition.
In some ways, you can
class it as sport.
But the reason why I was asking
entirely is because the
way how Caillois writes it, or
at least the way how Roger
Caillois has been translated,
kind of makes it sound like
he's actually drawing hard
divisions between all these
categories.
But really they're
all adjectives.
AUDIENCE: What was the
original language?
PROFESSOR: French, I believe.
AUDIENCE: I believe that's
the original version.
PROFESSOR: Correct
me if I'm wrong.
[INTERPOSING  VOICES]
PROFESSOR: If anyone
can confirm that,
that would be awesome.
Write a blog post about it.
AUDIENCE: Jeremy,
you're on it.
JEREMY: Yeah, I'll try
and confirm that
it's actually French.
I'll confirm it, and then write
an obnoxious post about
translation errors.
[INTERPOSING  VOICES]
PROFESSOR: I'm sure it could
have been translated in far
more interesting language,
because it's kind of dull.
JEREMY: [INAUDIBLE]
French [INAUDIBLE] if it
actually it is French.
PROFESSOR: And then we
have more meetings
on Caillois on Wednesday.
Yay!
But it's an important text.
But [? Ellings ?]
will be, I use the word vertigo
a lot, because it
sometimes gets sort
of substituted.
But vertigo, I think people
have a very specific
understanding of vertigo
as getting
dizzy because of heights.
And obviously not all games
are about heights.
But people, sure, they use it
to describe the sensation of
taking a roller coaster, which
literally is about heights.
But it's also about speed.
And you can use the
same thing.
Have everyone played the game
called Descent on the PC back
in the day?
So imagine a first-person
shooter.
The game is filling up
the entire screen.
But there is no up.
There's no gravity.
Whenever you want, you can
turn yourself this way.
And you just stay that way
until you want to turn
yourself again.
By the way, the controls work
just pretty much the same way
as a first-person shooter.
That was Descent.
And the whole pleasure of that
game, you'll be doing this all
the friggin' time.
I'm going down this
straight corridor.
And I never just go down
the straight corridor.
I go down the straight
corridor, and I turn
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Inception.
[LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: Yeah!
That sort of thing.
If you ever get a chance to play
the game Prey, which is
probably like five dogs on like
a pre-owned nowadays.
You have that same
sort of thing.
And Portal has a lot of that
kind of loss of control,
physical sensation.
They're trying to get that.
But obviously real physical
experiences
that are half an inch.
They're talking about
three-legged races or that
horrible game where you
spin around on a
bat with your head.
[LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: And [? Ellings ?]
can be used to describe any
one of those things.
I like to use it as describing
the sort of fun
of the loss of control.
But that's not necessarily
the case.
Just the sheer physicality of
the game that's part of the
experience in a way that digital
chess doesn't really
have any of that.
Even real chess [INAUDIBLE].
So actually I'm just going to
write out those words for
those folks who didn't
get a chance to read
through that page.
So [INAUDIBLE]
is kind of like intercompetition
skill.
I talked about [? Ellings ?]
which is kind of jumping down
through the last one of
these such as-- am I
spelling this right--
where just kind of physicality
just kind of sucks.
[LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: Actually Jason,
can you turn the
light in the room on.
Its extremely dark.
Loss of control.
Other ones were--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Javier, what
was that again?
AUDIENCE: Chance.
PROFESSOR: Chance, luck,
not skilled.
You guys know the phrase
[INAUDIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: The die
had been cast.
PROFESSOR: Yes.
Yes, the die has been cast
right before Caesar
[INAUDIBLE]
and says I now am able
to attack someone.
I couldn't remember who.
But Javier needs
dice basically.
PROFESSOR: Actually--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Say what?
AUDIENCE: He matched on
the [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Matched?
AUDIENCE: Matched on
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
Although I've heard two
translations of The Die Has
Been Cast as a phrase
actually.
Because on one hand, you
can think of it as the
die has been cast.
So we'll see where fortune takes
us, and there's nothing
we can do wrong.
But I've also heard it described
as the die as in the
thing that you put molten
metal into, as in cast.
And so whatever we were
making is now set.
And they had that same idea, but
because we had because one
way that you can think of is
this is not auto control.
And the other way you can think
of this is and now this
is set in stone.
Which are two very different
connotations, but both saying
we don't really have control
of the situation.
AUDIENCE: Yassa means thrown.
PROFESSOR: Thrown away, yeah.
Yeah.
But the English phrase,
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Are there words in
English that [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
root to mean random?
In French the word for
random is aleatoire.
Come straight from
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Sure.
Yeah.
PROFESSOR: Which is undoubtably
why he chose that
word I just checked,
he is French.
PROFESSOR: Obviously that's
why Caillois used it.
But yeah, I can't think of any
English words that use that as
a root, although there
might be some.
I know there's a
game committee.
And I think they actually
make strategic games.
And there's one more
which is--
AUDIENCE: Mimicry.
PROFESSOR: Which is kind of odd
because that's in English,
not in French.
Mimicry's mimicry.
It's actually in English,
so role playing,
dress up, let's pretend.
Simulations sometimes?
You know, it might actually
fall into that.
So you can imagine in tactical
simulation, for instance,
being very much about
competition and skills.
But then if it's a tactical
simulation about Russian
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], something
like that, then
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
territory.
Do you--
It's part of the pleasure of
believing that you are
something else, as opposed
to I'm just guy playing
[INAUDIBLE]
as opposed to I am this 17th
century scholar [INAUDIBLE].
And making a game about that.
So these are the adjectives
that he talks about to
describe games, but in the bit
where we actually ask you to
read, it's more about why.
These words give you a clue to
think about why are people
playing games.
These are types of fun, much in
a way that gets touched on
by the MDA paper that we
had you read last week.
What are these aesthetics that
people are going for?
Are they going for the thrill
of competition or
the thrill of luck?
Are they going for physical
motion and how that feels, or
are they going for the feeling
of being someone else?
And it's not--
Again, these are not mutually
exclusive terms.
These are things that you could
have one game that has
all of this.
You could have one game that
has two in some strong
competition and the rest
are all minimized.
That's fine.
But understanding that this is
why people are enjoying the
game more, and more importantly
this is what
people are enjoying playing
with each other for.
One nice thing about this
is that fodder for
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and for mimicry, it's really,
really difficult to think
about those two in particular
without
thinking about the players.
Competition sucks if
there's no one else
you're competing with.
Sure playing against computers
nowadays, but
traditionally we couldn't.
At least you were playing
against the designer, and
especially when it
came puzzles.
It's really, really annoying to
pretend to be somebody else
when there's no audience, even
if that other person is
someone pretending
along with you.
[INAUDIBLE].
Now, luck--
you can continue to play
a game flipping a coin.
But even when it comes to
luck, and it comes to
experiences of physical motion,
these things tend to
be measurable [INAUDIBLE].
And that's why these four
particular divisions that
[INAUDIBLE]
picked out are really, really
good for [INAUDIBLE] social
[INAUDIBLE].
A game where is there a name for
this game where you put a
bat on the ground and
you go around?
AUDIENCE: Bat?
AUDIENCE: Bat irritating.
AUDIENCE: What is he
talking about?
AUDIENCE: Wait, wait, and
someone gets fixed and then?
PROFESSOR: So there's a type of
relay race where you pick
up a baseball bat, and you
put your head on it.
You go around it three times,
and then you just run back to
your team, carry the bat, and
try to hand the bat off to
somebody else on your team.
Usually ending up
hitting someone.
AUDIENCE: I've heard it
called Dizzy Bats.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Dizzy Bats.
PROFESSOR: Dizzy Bats.
Yeah.
So that game is a lot more
fun when there's
somebody else around.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: I do that by myself.
AUDIENCE: You start handing
it off to yourself.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Bats flying around.
PROFESSOR: And even with games
of chance, I mean sure, if you
cook the games of chance by
itself, but for the most part
most of my enjoyment of the game
of chance is usually with
a group of four people,
actually, either playing poker
or playing something
like mahjong.
So these are all very
support [INAUDIBLE].
If you think about when
someone's going to come down
and sit in front of your game,
and what sort of frame of mind
they're going to be in
to play your game?
What sort of frame of mind do
you want to put them in in
order to enjoy the games?
Think about why they
might want to hang
out with other people.
Because [INAUDIBLE].
So if there's this other person
they play with, that
you may or may not know, but try
to think about how you're
going to construct enough
clues to sort of get
them to enjoy it.
So the game is about pretending
to be someone else.
I'm going to make a game where I
am playing a negotiator in a
hostage situation,
for instance.
[INAUDIBLE], awesome.
I'm going to be the
negotiator.
You all are going to be the
guy taking hostages.
And then you want to play
that out, and harm them.
Friday we had the game Crunch,
where people were playing
CEOs, I think.
I'm hoping [INAUDIBLE]
that you will already
hate [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: That's awesome.
PROFESSOR: [INAUDIBLE]
less corrupt.
And you think about how does the
game, even from the rules,
even from the design of the box,
get you into the mood of
thinking, OK, whoever I am in
real life, I'm going to take
on this persona.
And I'm going to enjoy taking
on this persona for a while.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but then you're
really not [INAUDIBLE]
because they have this game's
kind of built in where you
actually hide cards
on yourself.
AUDIENCE: Did you guys catch
anyone doing that in the act?
AUDIENCE: I got caught.
AUDIENCE: No, I caught him.
AUDIENCE: I feel like
arguing about
that's part of the rules.
He already got it.
He had already hidden them away,
and then the cards were
sought way afterwards.
PROFESSOR: And even arguing
over whether something was
illegal or not, even when
there's evidence that it is,
no one caught you doing it.
It's appropriate for this theme
of being a CEO of a
failing bank.
It's like, well, so we have
all of these CDOs.
Yeah, we purchased them at some
point, but nobody caught
us while we were doing it.
So now you guys have
to help us fix it.
That's what the game's about.
Was there a game that was
particularly competitive that
people played on Friday?
AUDIENCE: That game
was pretty good.
PROFESSOR: Which one?
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: There was a
competitive moment in Saboteur
when Alec, revealed himself to
be a saboteur and ruined our
chance to find the gold.
PROFESSOR: Saboteur is what I
would describe as cutthroat.
It's a game that's deliberately
about winning by
other people losing.
AUDIENCE: It made me
upset with Alec.
AUDIENCE: It made me cry.
PROFESSOR: And John Nash,
actually, [INAUDIBLE].
Oh.
Because he did spend some time
here at MIT, possibly when
visiting, but he designed one
game called Hex, which is
ostensibly designed based on the
washroom tiles of one of
the Building 39 or Building
37 bathrooms.
But anyway, that game and
another game called Screw Your
Buddies are all cutthroat
games.
The only way to get them to win
this game is by screwing
over the other person playing.
Screw Your Buddies in particular
is just like boiled
down diplomacy.
The only way you're going to
win this game is to betray
someone else.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR: Let's see.
Games of chance.
What was kind of chancy
on Friday?
And you--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Think or go?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: That's 17.
[INAUDIBLE]
4:00 AM you've got--
AUDIENCE: Every threat
was on the board.
Two people go in.
17 drops.
Oh my God.
PROFESSOR: It's a
press-your-luck game, right?
Do you dare?
Do you think you can?
I enjoy that game a lot.
[INAUDIBLE].
I don't think that we had any
influence specifically.
It's hard to get really physical
in card games.
AUDIENCE: Maybe in that
that game, Falling.
Yeah.
That was a pit.
PROFESSOR: Pit actually, you're
right, two weeks ago,
some of the games that
were played were
really kind of kinetic.
So even with card games, you
already have very good
examples of that.
I want you to keep in mind
because today we're actually
going to start the process of
getting new folks to think
about what you're going to do as
social assignment and break
you up into teams.
Before we continue , Jason, do
you have anything to raise
regarding [INAUDIBLE]?
No.
Anybody else?
AUDIENCE: I'm still confused
about the whole Eskimo part.
AUDIENCE: Agreed.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Eskimos.
PROFESSOR: Take a look
at the French.
[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
and what took universities,
some are a good
friend of ours did.
I mean we might know someone
who knows him.
I'll find out tonight.
[INAUDIBLE]
is not that old.
So maybe--
AUDIENCE: We to just have him
come over over, chill at MIT
for a little bit.
We could talk to him
about the Eskimos.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: He is dead, but
I might know some
people who knew him.
Just be a necromancer,
that's OK.
PROFESSOR: All right.
So this is what we're
going to do.
We're basically going to
do brainstorming today.
The basic idea is that we're
going to have a bunch of index
cards and one job to make it
easier on the job of the
secretary is that you'd actually
be reading off
something written.
So especially while other people
are throwing out their
ideas, and you get something,
and that
person's still talking.
You might as well just
write down your idea.
So we'll have a whole
bunch of cards.
I'd also like you to start
off by writing your
name right on top.
And the reason for this is
because I don't think every
single person in this room knows
each other's names yet.
As we do this process, it's
more that you remember oh
yeah, it's that guy who came
up with that idea.
Oh, and that person's
name is so-and-so.
AUDIENCE: That's
what you want?
To have all the ideas from each
person on one card, or
have one idea per card?
PROFESSOR: All on one.
AUDIENCE: What if the professors
took notes and we
could just bounce out ideas?
PROFESSOR: Well that's what
the tape recorder is for.
But the thing about writing
your ideas down is that
someone can look at the card
and say, yeah, that guy.
I want to follow up
with this guy.
Because we're not actually going
to form the teams for
you by the end of this class.
The idea is so that after this
brainstorm, you've got a pool
of ideas of which you
guys can make games.
Actually, frankly, we don't
care if two teams ended up
making pretty much the same
game, out of the same concept.
Because I know that two
different teams of two
different sets of people are
going end up making different
games anyway, even if you
start from the same.
That's not a requirement.
You folks can make--
you can take any set of ideas
from the book today.
Obviously, if you're the one who
pitch an idea and somebody
else thinks, hey, that was
actually pretty cool.
Take that opportunity to
talk to the person and
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
That pretty much is going to
happen between classes.
So by Wednesday, I want
you all to come in.
This is basically one of the
ideas of the homework, is to
tell me which team you're on,
who's on your team, and what's
the general one line idea that
you're working with.
Now, the idea that they're
giving us is
what you started with.
It may not be what
you end with.
That's fine.
I'm very comfortable
that ideas change
while you guys work.
I think that's fine.
The teams shouldn't change.
So you're working with these
three other people,
or a team of a four.
Then that should be intact
for the rest of this--
for this assignment.
OK, so teams of four.
Now, one more clarification
about the project.
The card game, all the cards
need to be identically sized.
We do like cards that are going
to be legible, but you
don't need to spend
a whole lot of
time making them pretty.
I will just appreciate it that
by the time you actually hand
in your cards, you have
them written in ink.
Pencil is great when you're
prototyping because you can
erase [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Ink is great for creating the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Your game can be playable by
two, three, or four players.
It does not need to cater to any
grouping other than what
you decide.
So if you're saying, this is a
two-player game, we will test
it with two people.
If you're saying this is two
to four, we'll test it with
some number with however many
people we manage to
rustle up to test.
If you say it could be
two or four, but not
three, that's fine.
You think I kid, but there are
some games that work really,
really well with even numbers.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Keep it
four and under.
Or at least make it possible
for us to grade it with a
maximum of four people.
Because if you give us a game
that requires five people, we
have to find five people and get
them together in order to
create your [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I think there was one more
requirement for how long the
game could take.
AUDIENCE: I think it's
5 to 10 minutes.
AUDIENCE: It was short.
AUDIENCE: That's really short.
AUDIENCE: That's super short.
AUDIENCE: Falling
is really short.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Crunch is not.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So when you're
brainstorming for game ideas,
how much do we
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE] come
to up with in our brainstorm?
It's a cool idea.
It's an amusing space.
PROFESSOR: I will say that if
the character's the thing
that's encouraging you to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
I have this cool game
that comes to mind.
Then that's the thing that
you're throwing out.
If instead, I want to make
a game about fish.
I have no game mechanics
in mind, but I
think fish are awesome.
Then, OK.
That's the game you're
doing now.
Maybe that's the first bad idea
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: If we have like
several game ideas, should we
take several index cards
and write one per?
PROFESSOR: Actually, no I would
rather see them all on
one if you can fit them.
And if you run out of space,
flip them over.
Again, the idea of the index
cards is not just to record
the ideas down, because what I
am going to do is I'm going to
try to type them all out,
so that you can
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
But also to find you
folks again.
So I said, yeah that was
that guy who had
this idea about fish.
Who was that again?
So I guess I will leave you.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Want me to
write them down?
PROFESSOR: I think that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: I mean, you're
not a facilitator?
PROFESSOR: Yeah, I'm
facilitating.
AUDIENCE: I like clerk better.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: But I am actually
wonder whether we should
define this into two groups.
AUDIENCE: We get to
cross-pollinate.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Let's work as
a whole class first.
I know there were some folks who
actually started off with
ideas already on the forum.
So why don't those folks throw
your ideas first because you
already mentioned
in the forum.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I wasn't part
of that group in the forum.
AUDIENCE: Well, to start off,
Jeremy and I have been sort of
discussing the idea, you
want to go ahead?
AUDIENCE: Sure.
AUDIENCE: Two ideas, I guess.
AUDIENCE: But yeah,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
titles.
So the basic concept of the
game in which players are
forced by some game mechanic to
refer to each other by name
constantly throughout
the game, and at
a very rapid pace.
Their name is generated by
the game and accumulate
increasingly longer
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] this game as
they succeed.
So you would start.
You would be the lord of
something, and then you could
accumulate extra title,
son of this.
Like bringer of flame.
And you could just like have all
these modifiers and just
kind of accumulate and
accumulate until your title
becomes ridiculous.
And then, have people
start screwing up as
they say your name.
And it'd just be hilarious.
PROFESSOR: OK, I'm just
going to write down
like, memory jogs.
AUDIENCE: So like procedurally
generated names, titles.
AUDIENCE: Name game.
PROFESSOR: Yes.
AUDIENCE: You said you
had a second one?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, can I go
with the second one?
AUDIENCE: OK, so I had this
idea of sort of like a
survival horror game, kind
of inspired by falling.
Like the premise is, you have
a group of like player
characters that are charging
through a building, and you
can have like a dealer that is
putting down hallways as
you're going through.
And occasionally threats come
up and you have to react
really quick and be like,
it's a zombie.
We have to go upstairs.
And thrown down a
card to do that.
Then you have to keep doing this
until you get to the end
of it and people can die, and
get eaten, and stuff.
AUDIENCE: That's good.
AUDIENCE: I like that a lot.
AUDIENCE: Kind of like
cooperative falling off?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Should we be writing
his ideas down?
AUDIENCE: No, I'm writing
mine down and then.
AUDIENCE: Cool.
PROFESSOR: Write down
your own ideas.
AUDIENCE: So I have an idea.
I made this up a year ago
when I took Game Design.
Or not Game Design, Intro
to Video Game Studies.
Actually, it's like
majority rule.
So it's kind of like crunch
where you can just
hide cars and stuff.
But if you get caught, then
you get called out.
And in order to be penalized
for it, you have to be--
a majority rule has to be
by every one playing.
And so you can actually bribe
people to vote for you.
It's more of like a--
yeah, and then the way you get
points is, it depends on how
we'd [UNINTELLIGIBLE] it.
PROFESSOR: I'm just going
to go around this way.
AUDIENCE: OK.
So I have an idea of a card
game based on like having
success in life.
So the beginning of the game,
all the players are randomly
assigned different goals in
order, which are like wealth,
and adventure, and love,
and things like this.
And then all the cards represent
different activities
that take up a different
amount of time.
So you all these activities you
can keep in front of you.
And then, however much free time
you have, you draw that
many cards looking for
new opportunities.
So it's like you take
opportunities and leave
opportunities and things.
PROFESSOR: I could write out
time and opportunities.
Let's see.
Who's next?
AUDIENCE: I have a very
mechanically oriented idea.
Essentially I'm stealing and
trying to improve the drop
mechanic from Magic the
Gathering booster draft.
For those who don't know, the
idea is that you're trying to
collect a set.
And so let's do it in terms
of regular card games.
You're trying to collect a
straight flush as long as
possible, as high valued
as possible.
But other people may be trying
to collect that same suit.
So you want to collect
a different
suit from other people.
And you do this by looking at
the cards in your hand,
picking one of them, passing
the rest to the
person on your right.
and then, continuing to do this,
and then going back in
the other direction
with a new hand.
And then in the same direction
again with a third hand.
And the object is collect
a big, straight flush.
Also, guess what the person to
your right was collecting, and
guess what the person to your
left was collecting.
So you're trying to signal the
other people what suits are
open and collect the
suit which is open.
PROFESSOR: Let's see.
Who's next.
AUDIENCE: So it's going to be
there are different types of
cards, like action cards, like
pick up cards or lose cards.
But then [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Stock pile from your friend's
hand to the discard pile.
You can play a different card
in a different order so the
rule always changes.
Kind of mess other people
up or help yourself out.
PROFESSOR: I will just
write that the rules
are constantly changing.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but you get--
so there's actually
an order to it.
So you can choose.
So if it's going to be your turn
and it says pick a free
card, you can put down, like
from a friend's hand or lose
three cards [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Makes a lot of sense
in my mind.
PROFESSOR: So rules changing
with cards.
AUDIENCE: So one idea I have
is a game about character
growth through narrative arc.
So the start of the game you're
given a character, and
the idea is you want to follow
a certain narrative arc so
that they grow in terms
of the hands of
the game you're playing.
So if you start out with a cocky
character, then you may
want to actually lose a couple
of the hands of the game, such
that your character experiences
failure and his
character growth increases.
And so, basically the winner of
the game is determined by
who manages to get their
character to grow the most
emotionally.
AUDIENCE: It's very deep.
AUDIENCE: So I had this idea for
a poker-like game, except
it's played with more than one
deck, but the normal rules
still apply.
So if you get dealt five aces,
you can't actually play that
hand because that would
be cheating.
So you have an incentive to try
and like slip cards into
your sleeve, slip
back and forth.
So you're almost forced to cheat
at the game to be able
to actually play it.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
if you get caught then, just
pretty much you have to figure
out how to get out.
AUDIENCE: So the idea that
I had was kind of like
Bananagrams, but with
a card game.
So you have cards with lines
or preset lines or shapes,
just something on the card.
And you have to try to connect
them all in some way on your
personal board, so that it
forms a closed shape.
And once you're done, you have
to take another from the pile
and try to fix your shape so
that it's still closed while
trying to beat everyone else.
PROFESSOR: So collecting
cards, make shapes.
AUDIENCE: So my idea was just
using normal poker cards and
doing a trading game.
Just like trading four
kinds of pattern as
four kind of stocks.
And you can randomly draw the
card to be your own stock.
And everyday, you randomly
draw a card to
determine the day price.
And you can trade with bank
or other players.
I think you can use 8 and 10's
as the stocks and the J, Q,
and the K as the special
cards [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: OK.
AUDIENCE: So this was another
procedurally generated idea.
The game generates for
you encounters.
And it's supposed
to be ridiculous
and somewhat humorous.
You'd have a base card,
like a bear.
And then there are various
modifiers that you would draw
to create that encounter.
Or it could be like a
ninja zombie pair in
space wrapped in bacon.
And then those would
all give different
attributes to that encounter.
And then you'd have to find
a way to beat it.
And your characters might also
maybe be procedurally
generated in similarly
ridiculous ways and you'd have
to counter it with--
basically, I like procedurally
generated ideas.
Cards games that are never
played the same way twice.
PROFESSOR: I need something
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: With laser beams.
AUDIENCE: Of course.
AUDIENCE: Of course you
need laser beams.
AUDIENCE: So my idea was a
musical RPG in which players'
cards and musical notes.
And you build chords.
For example, to raise your
character's strength, you
might make an augmented
chord, et cetera.
And then you can chain chord
progression to attack players.
Diminished your life.
AUDIENCE: I just dominated
your [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I got obsessed
with drafting.
I have another drafting game.
Uses the same drafting mechanic
except that you're
drafting tiles.
You play the tiles in front of
you and they make a machine.
Drafting the same color of
machine bit or same type of
machine bit, and then laying
it in consecutive blocks.
Multiple [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
makes them better, and then
your machines like attack
other people.
Or they can do crazy shit.
But the challenge being that
you have to drop the piece
that fits into your machine.
AUDIENCE: That can
do crazy shit.
It has to be pronounced
like crazy.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So my idea to have
like a monarchy type thing.
So it starts out everyone is
like heir to the throne.
Everyone wants to become the
king, or queen, I guess.
And the point is you have to
get the king to really like
you, or to assassinate him.
But if you want to assassinate
him, you have to kill off all
the other players first.
So it's kind of a like a
betrayal and deciet game.
PROFESSOR: So a betrayal.
OK.
AUDIENCE: Yep.
So another game, it's about
reducing your opponents
mobility by placing cards that
represent walls, and placing
other cards to rotate
various walls.
And your opponent is doing
the same thing.
So you could sort of envision
the Tron Light Cycle game
without any hint of reflex
removed completely.
AUDIENCE: That would
be really cool.
AUDIENCE: So it's all just a
strategic placement of walls
to reduce your opponent's
mobility.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I think you can
just make a Tetris box and
then every time you select one
give to the other player
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: So Tetris blocks.
Got it.
OK?
AUDIENCE: This is kind of like
Pokemon, except now you raise
zombies or you catch zombies.
So you have different
types of zombies.
Like maybe you take some from
Left 4 Dead universe or
something, or just Resident Evil
or something, and you can
do like versus other people
or something.
AUDIENCE: I thought
of having cards--
I don't know whether they would
be like words or a few
words together.
But you would go around and each
round, the goal would be
to build a story.
So each person would play a card
face down, or something.
So it'd be a mechanic like
Apples to Apples, except
you're progressively building
a story and if people like
your addition to the story.
PROFESSOR: So Apples to Apples
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Sure.
Moving away from drafting.
OK, so I have another game idea
called, Are you a Cylon?
Essentially--
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: Are you a Cyclon?
Are you a Cylon.
And essentially broad brush
strokes steals the skill
resolution that came from
Battlestar Galactica the board
game, and then strips
it down to secret
Cylons sabotaging people.
And then people accusing them.
And then everybody crying.
AUDIENCE: So I really like
Harvest Moon, so I was
thinking that maybe there
could be Harvest Moon
competitive card game.
And I guess you have a certain
amount of stamina each turn
and cards are actions.
And whoever has the biggest
harvest at the end of
the game would win.
I don't know how many turns
there would be.
PROFESSOR: So stamina
in farming.
AUDIENCE: So sort of building
on the monarchy of the trail
idea, this is a game about
the heir to the throne.
The king is dying in x turns.
You and the other players are
going to compete to prove who
is the correct heir
to the throne.
And you can do so through combat
directly with other
players, assassinations, or
political machinations, such
as like accusing other players
of being base born.
PROFESSOR: Assassinations.
AUDIENCE: Actually, I just have
the paper when you throw
out your idea, also throw out--
also mention your name
because I'm still learning
everyone's name.
AUDIENCE: OK, so I'm Ian.
So I had this idea for a game
called Admiral Snack Bar.
It's a competitive game where
each player is building up
their own sort of like
snack shop, and they
make a certain product.
And the other players need that
product in some way to
enhance their own things.
But you can see secretly poison
parts of your product,
so that when they purchase them,
they'll like get messed
up in some way.
So it's sort of like a trade-off
and you can make
alliances and stuff like that.
AUDIENCE: So it's sort
of like a trap?
AUDIENCE: It's a trap.
AUDIENCE: There's the
tagline right there.
AUDIENCE: It's a snack.
AUDIENCE: So I'm thinking of a
game, I guess to have like the
total wars mixed with
Nazi Germany.
So the point of the game is
you want to snatch up
territories.
And you can do this by maybe
attacking other players.
Well, in particular it's
just like cards.
And you can do this by attacking
other players who
may be making alliances, which
you can easily betray.
Or maybe have like all the cards
in a pile and every turn
you can take one and try it.
And you get points by getting
certain combinations of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
More like Risk right
there as well.
PROFESSOR:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: I'm Brian.
So I was thinking of like
a trick taking game.
But the idea is there's four
players, and you're trying to
get the second most
tricks each round.
And then there are cards that
allow you to swap out other
cards at the end of
a round and other
things that are tricky.
PROFESSOR: So hit the
second-best trick?
AUDIENCE: Or second most tricks
or something like that.
But yeah.
AUDIENCE: So I was thinking
of sort of a--
put succinctly--
Scrabble meets chicken.
PROFESSOR: Hm?
AUDIENCE: What?
AUDIENCE: You have a
bunch of people.
And they play cards in the
middle and you have
to make words out.
And if you make longer
words, you get more
points and so forth.
So maybe your letter is more
rare, it gets more points.
But the catch is that if the
word is longer, you can't gain
as much point.
The point gain is--
AUDIENCE: Diminishing.
AUDIENCE: It's diminished
more.
It's proportional to how long
the word is you make.
AUDIENCE: I'm Bato.
And I wanted to combine Mario
Karts and Chrononauts.
So the idea of you're
racing through time.
Somebody is the main guy that's
trying to get to someplace.
Everyone else is trying
to stop him.
And your abilities or weapons
only work in certain time
periods and stuff like that.
And so you have the time travel
and the items from
Chrononauts and the racing and
attacking from Mario Kart.
AUDIENCE: Go, Michelle.
AUDIENCE: My name is Michelle.
So I was envisioning something
like Ricochet Robots but where
the two people-- basically, the
point is that everyone has
a set of cards that have
pathways or grids or walls
that you can bounce off of.
And you build a grid
with your opponent.
And there's one robot piece that
you have to try to bounce
off the walls to reach
some specific goal.
You can screw up the
other player.
PROFESSOR: Build walls and
bounce robots around.
Good.
AUDIENCE: I'm Patrick.
PROFESSOR: Go ahead.
Oh, Patrick, then Jeremy.
AUDIENCE: So this is a game
where the players are owners
of businesses.
And depending on the nature of
the business, they might have
mutual dependencies that would
be beneficial for people to
get more money.
But then as the market goes
bad, they'll have to play
cards to cut off the ties
between companies.
And so I call it Objectivism,
The Game.
AUDIENCE: That was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: OK.
You?
AUDIENCE: So just a slight
variation on the procedure
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] idea but now
I'm visioning it possibly as a
sort of Falling real-time
type deal.
So every turn, you're
getting dealt cards.
And you have cards that can
modify the dealing pattern so
they can discard other players'
cards or can get them
to be skipped, so
on and so forth.
And you also have cards that can
add various modifiers to
your beast.
And the goal of the game is that
by time the deck has been
entirely dealt, you have the
most bad-ass creature that
you've created and that-- you'd
have to figure out-- and
there might be an optimum way
to rearrange things, so as
you're getting cards, you have
to try to figure out how to
rearrange them.
And at the same time,
other players could
be discarding stuff.
And you have to deal with all
these things at the same time.
And then at the end of the game,
you have to freeze and
see who has the best one.
And it could be a really quick
game and very hilarious.
PROFESSOR: OK, so
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: So kind of like
building a creature, plus Uno.
AUDIENCE: OK, this game is
Monkey or Shakespeare?
So there are several different
piles of cards.
Each of them has words on them
in Shakespearean English.
Some of them are going to
be played by players.
Some of them are going to be
like random number generators,
essentially.
The players that are playing as
covert Shakespeares select
cards and then place them face
down in a common pool.
Then the top cards from all
the other decks get
placed in the pool.
And then everything
gets shuffled up.
And then each of these different
piles is going to be
a different color.
And so you will spell out
sentences in the color
progressively, based
on the card draws.
And the object of the game for
the other players who aren't
hidden Shakespeares is to try
to work out who's the
Shakespeare, who's just trying
to spell the prearranged
sentence beforehand is, and
who are just monkey piles.
All right.
So it's detect the random
number generator.
AUDIENCE: Bato, again.
I want to take that tanks versus
robot game that we
played before on the paper and
make it into a card game
between players.
And the tanks can level up.
And you could change your
specific strategy and that
kind of stuff.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Would the
robots still be
deterministic from something?
AUDIENCE: Up in the air.
PROFESSOR: Let's see.
Who from this side
hasn't gone yet?
I don't think you--
AUDIENCE: I did.
I had my convoluted idea.
AUDIENCE: I think
everyone's gone.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So one mechanic is
any game that has a high
amount of trading of cards.
You can imagine anything from
a Go Fish type thing to
something more complicated.
However, you don't mechanically
enforce the
traded cards.
So there is basically lying
in that [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Also, playing off of the robot
tank idea, a game where,
basically, your strategy is
mitigated by the cards you
play, rather than the actual
characteristics.
So the cards played dictate how
another deck or another
mechanic is run, rather
than you directly
interfacing with that.
PROFESSOR: Robots.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
robots with mechanical
modifications.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I am Justin.
So I just have an idea about
your asylum game that seems
very interesting.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Maybe it will help if
you can play two
characters instead of one.
So if you have four people,
you have eight characters
determined
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So two player asylum.
Two characters.
AUDIENCE: Sure.
Andrew.
So you could have something
that's sort of an MIT case.
So you're an MIT student.
And you're going through pizzas,
you're doing energy
drinks to help you
along through the
night, social events.
You can hang out at Harvard
for a night.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: That would
be a debug.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, exactly.
Sorry, you'd force other people
to hang out at Harvard
for a night.
PROFESSOR: Anything else?
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: Deion.
This is MIT or Harvard.
So let's say you're
in a design class.
And you're trying to
build a project.
So there's some students
that are MIT.
Most of them are.
But then there's one or
two Harvard students.
And so everyone's trying
to build this project.
But the Harvard student
is messing it up.
Or maybe it could be Harvard,
MIT, or Caltech.
So the other student, that's not
MIT, is trying to screw up
your project.
And so by the end of the game,
you want to figure out who
that person is.
Or maybe you take turns making
additions to it.
Something like that.
AUDIENCE: So this came up only a
few seconds ago in my brain.
The setting I imagine for this
might be something like a dark
elf realm underground.
And there's various
houses or various
families of dark elves.
And there's one that is not
controlled by players.
So I guess it's deterministic
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
set rules.
And players every turn can
place written cards to
influence the behavior
of this non-player
entity the next turn.
And basically, players are vying
for influence over this
non-player entity, which would
then do benevolent or
malevolent things
towards players.
And it might be only
semi-obvious, depending on how
cards are played who exactly
took certain actions to get
this master house to give favor
or remove favor from one
player to another.
And so it would be a game where
you're trying to beat
other players.
At the same time, you're trying
to figure out who's on
your side, who's not on your
side, and forging alliances
and betraying each other.
AUDIENCE: Second one is
a guy at a party.
He's trying to get the girl
at the end of the night.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Oh, frat boys.
AUDIENCE: Is that a card game?
AUDIENCE: You could screw other
people over by going up
to them and bringing up
embarrassing stories.
Or you could be really
nice and try to
meet the girl's friends.
It's all based off an AI kind
of [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: And hook up.
AUDIENCE: I'm Ian.
You have a game where the
objective is all the players
are actually trying to build
a physical house of
cards out of the cards.
But each card has an in-game
mechanical effect as well.
And then there's possibly the
actual structure determines
something as well.
You'd have to do it with
very thick cards.
AUDIENCE: So--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Jenga with
the cards.
AUDIENCE: Jenga cards.
AUDIENCE: There would be a
mechanic-- actually, my idea
was building a house, but not
with a house of cards.
But that's a better idea.
Adding a mechanic who'd be like
you can play an action
card that's like, a storm
destroys the west wall of your
opponent's house or something.
In your case,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Jason.
So you're on a student project
or corporate project or some
team doomed to fail.
So your objective is to make you
look as good as you can,
whether by making the project
better, or by making sure
other people are responsible
for it being worse.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: A terrible microcosm
for the first assignment.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Don't fail
too badly.
PROFESSOR: Who is next?
AUDIENCE: Brian.
PROFESSOR: Brian.
AUDIENCE: With all this talk
of drafting, I started
thinking about auction games.
So an auction game where there's
some different points.
And maybe if you collect
certain types of
points, it's good.
And then also some of the
cards, you can add a few
mechanics for yourself.
So you can bid for a card
that later you can play.
And have everyone else bid.
And then you have to go
bid after them, or
something like that.
But everyone has the same
amount of points at the
beginning
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: I'm Jason,
by the way.
Going back to my guys at a party
one, you could work in a
mechanic where people could
bring in real stories and real
traits that they have
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: But you could honestly
lie and make it worse
for someone else, but then you
lose points for lying.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
dishonest guy.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So again, it's like
an RPG card game, where you
each have your set of things
you can do and
equipment you have.
And then there's an
encounter deck.
And these keep getting
flipped over.
And then people have
to react to this.
But it's not quite cooperative
because at the end, there's
something that only one
person can get.
So maybe they have to duke it
out at the end if there's more
than one person left.
PROFESSOR: Sounds like
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah, kind of.
AUDIENCE: So bringing up auction
mechanics, there's a
bidding mechanic that is
interesting from a theoretical
standpoint that I never see
implemented, where if you have
a thing that's being
bidded for--
or you have everyone assign
something that they
get from some pile.
And then if someone feels that
they are unhappy with what
they have, they trade it with
someone else's, and either put
some amount of money on the
other item or some decremental
type object on their item.
The bidding system comes out of
the pirates trying to split
up booty and making
everyone happy.
PROFESSOR: So bidding by
reducing other people's bids--
is that a good description?
AUDIENCE: It's a bidding
system in which
everyone has something.
And then you trade and add value
until everyone feels
it's equal.
PROFESSOR: [INAUDIBLE]
something.
Let's see.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So my idea
was you have two
teams, maybe four players.
It's like an RPG.
And so before you start, you
have to draft the equipment
and spells you can do.
And so then you have team
battles against each other.
And the way you determine what
happens is maybe a War-like
system, where each one has
a deck which is shuffled.
Take the top card of the deck.
The highest card wins.
And so that determines
damage and such done.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I like it.
So searching off the RPG idea
but adding on a randomly
generated fort or castle that
one player has to defend and
everyone else is trying
to attack into.
And he has to set up his
defenses around.
But he's also controlling
a character.
And so he can move his guy
around the board to choose one
of the guys to defend against.
So essentially an RPG
with randomly
generated board as well.
PROFESSOR: Defend your castle?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, yeah.
AUDIENCE: Castle defense.
AUDIENCE: I like it.
AUDIENCE: So it's sort of
building off of the idea of
pirate's booty.
I like the idea that
you have a bunch of
items within the game.
The value for them is chosen
randomly so that it's unknown
what the value of
the items are.
So you just have the items and
various players can make
various moves like choose
to appraise an item
by paying some gold.
And the idea is you want to
try to get the item that's
worth the most amount of money
during any round to get the
most amount of gold.
PROFESSOR: Get the maximum
amount of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I'm running out of space, so I
better be ending this soon.
AUDIENCE: I'm out.
AUDIENCE: I'm Jason.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I kind of like the
bidding [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So you build competing
factories
with different products.
So you want to bid on different
items, but for some
people, it might be necessary
to have a certain
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Things are going to have
different values
for different people.
And you could also get high-end
stuff or low-end stuff.
And the randomness is going
come in where if you have
low-end stuff, a user could
hate your product.
And then you lose money
and stuff like that.
PROFESSOR: Michelle?
AUDIENCE: In a bidding sort of
game, you could be bidding for
space, let's say, space to
use the Hubble Telescope.
But before you can do this, you
have to pass a couple of
hurdles, like taking
J-lab, or--
AUDIENCE: Bidding.
AUDIENCE: Use the Hubble.
That's awesome.
AUDIENCE: One of the
first hurdles.
PROFESSOR: I wrote it
down as bidding
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: Tower Defense,
the card game.
Interpret as you will.
PROFESSOR: Tower defense.
AUDIENCE: That's
a lot of math.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Slight variation--
Dungeon keeper, the card game.
So I'd imagine that there would
be several lanes, down
which enemies would come.
And you would collaborate with
other players to create
buildings on the other end of
those lanes that would then
generate either traps along the
way or your own units that
would knock down the lanes,
taking out the enemies.
And every turn, you run
the game yourself.
So you run your opponent and it
automatically advances and
sends stuff at you that's
drawn from decks.
And you have to be able to time
stuff right and all that,
not to get your core destroyed,
basically.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I'm just thinking
of the idea of Tower
Defense, the card game.
Combine that with Falling, the
idea that turns are happening
at the same time.
So you have one player who's
playing the zombies invading.
And he's just basically going,
one, two, three, four.
That's like a zombie advance,
four steps, or something, by
placing cards down.
And then the other player is
trying to place defenses just
as fast, but has to discard
cards as well.
So it's really a game
of how well you are
able to handle cards.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I had another idea
in the vein of Falling.
But it would be like
Russian Roulette.
Everyone's trying
to have everyone
else die and not them.
And then you can play excuse
cards, be like, oh, I have to
go to the bathroom.
I'll be right back.
Or calling somebody else out and
calling them the chicken
or something.
You play with macho points.
PROFESSOR: I think that's
Russian Roulette with excuses.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So players take turns
being a prospective high
schooler who wants
to go to college.
And the other players are,
therefore, admissions officers.
And as a student, you're trying
to get into the college
that gives you the most--
AUDIENCE: Financial aid?
AUDIENCE: Most swag, anything.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: And as admissions
officers, you're trying to
give them the least.
PROFESSOR: So admissions
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Admissions
officer is easy.
You're just just like,
no, no, no.
You got into community
college.
AUDIENCE: I've come up with a
game mechanic for his idea.
So you could have bluffing where
you say, oh, I'm going
to the bathroom.
And then someone else could
call you out on it.
And you either have the bathroom
card and you're
actually going to the bathroom
or its an excuse.
So that's a mechanic
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: That's
AUDIENCE: Yeah, the
full bladder card.
AUDIENCE: Isn't there
a simple mechanic--
you basically place cards down
to try to create a path from
some predetermined point to
another but in that way, you
can block other players
by placing cards
PROFESSOR: So create impasse
and blocking them.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I think you're done.
AUDIENCE: I think we're done.
PROFESSOR:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
All right.
AUDIENCE: Just use the bottom.
PROFESSOR: I guess I could write
down to the bottom, but
it would be a pain for
folks to look at.
So these are just memory jogs
of what we've got up here.
None of these ideas need to be
taken up wholesale for your
original idea for the team.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
things that folks
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I would actually like folks to
grab one of the thumbtacks
over there.
Once you've written down your
ideas on the card and pinned
them up on the wall.
They don't have to be
closely packed.
In fact, spread them out a
little bit, so that people can
look at them one at a time.
And the rest of the class
basically is just time for you
guys to talk.
You [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
get to know each other's
games better.
And start discussing
about projects that
you're working on.