PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video I want us to
practice using Newton's Method
to find the solution
to an equation.
So what we're going to do in
particular is we're going to
use Newton's Method to
approximate a solution to the
following equation, 2
cosine x equals 3x.
And I'm going to tell
you where to start.
We're going to the have
our initial value,
x0, be pi over 6.
And I want you to find x2.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a little time to
work on that, and then I'll come
back and I will show you
how I did it.
OK.
Welcome back.
Again, what we're going to do
is use Newton's Method to
approximate a solution
to this equation.
And so what I want to point out
first is, I want to point
out why pi over 6 is a
reasonable first value to
choose, and I want to point out
that this, in fact, has
only one solution.
So what I'm going to do to give
us a reason for that is
I'm going to draw a rough sketch
of two curves and show
where they intersect.
And so I want us to notice that
if I were to look at the
two curves, y equals cosine x
and y equals 3/2x and I draw
them on the same x, y plane,
that where they intersect will
be where I have solutions
to this equation.
And that's because I just
divide both sides by 2.
Whatever solves this equation
solves the equation, cosine x
equals 3/2x.
So let me give you a rough
sketch of those two curves and
we'll see what the intersections
look like.
So I'm going to do that
right down here.
OK.
So let me, let me first draw,
make this y equals 1.
Make this y equals minus 1.
And I'm going to draw cosine x
first, y equals cosine x first
because I'm most likely to have
a hard time with that,
and I'll do my x scale
once I'm done.
And so cosine x, y equals
cosine x looks
something like this.
Maybe not the most perfect,
but again, it's kind of a
rough sketch.
That's pretty good.
Something like this.
So this is y equals cosine x.
And now I want to graph
y equals 3x over 2.
And that goes through
the point, 0, 0.
It also goes through the point
one comma three halves.
Well, this is pi over
2 right here.
So 1 is about here, we'll say.
Because pi over 2 is a little
bigger than 1 and 1/2.
So the 1 is about here, 1
and 1/2 is about here.
Or 3/2, if you need to
remind yourself.
So the line, y equals 3/2x looks
something like this.
So it's fairly straightforward
to see that these two curves
intersect at one spot, whenever
this spot is.
OK?
And notice, to the left
they don't intersect.
So we are just looking for
a single solution.
And then the other thing I want
to point out is, why is
pi over six potentially a good
guess to start with?
Well, the value, this is
the x value 1, and this
is the x value 0.
We know for a fact that we have
to have this x value line
between 0 and 1 because of where
my point is at the time
that x equal 1, I'm all
the way up at y
equals 3/2 up here.
So at least we know we're
between 0 and 1.
And then from there you could
even try some other values
like pi over 3 and pi over 4 and
put those in and see how
they compared.
But at least, we'll just say, at
least we know x is between
0 and 1, and pi over 6 is
certainly in that region.
So that's a good first
starting point.
Now I'm going to come
over here and
start to do some work.
If we want to solve the
equation, 2 cosine x equals
3x, what we're really doing
is we're looking
for 0's of this function.
So we find the 0's of this
function, which we know
there's only one of them.
We find the 0 of this function,
then we actually
have solved 2 cosine
x equals 3x.
So hopefully that makes sense
to you that we're actually
going to apply Newton's Method
to this function.
And so when we apply Newton's
Method, we need the function.
We also need to the
derivative.
So let me remind you, to
derivative of this is going to
be negative 2 sine x minus 3.
Right?
The derivative of cosine
x is negative sine x.
And so this is exactly
the derivative.
And then let me remind you what
Newton's Method says.
It says the next x value is
equal to the previous x value
minus the fraction of the
function evaluated at the
previous value divided by the
derivative evaluated at the
previous value.
Right?
So this is the formula you
have for Newton's Method.
So let's see if we can
get from x0 to x1
and then x1 to x2.
So in our case, we have x1
equals, well, x0 is pi over 6.
And then we have minus the
function evaluated at pi over
6, and then the derivative
evaluated at pi over 6.
So the function evaluated at pi
over 6-- cosine of pi over
6 is root 3 over 2.
So root 3 over 2 times
2-- we get a root 3.
Separate that out.
And then here, pi over 6
times 3 is pi over 2.
So we get a minus pi over 2.
Sine pi over 6 is 1/2.
So we get negative
2 times 1/2--
we get negative 1 and
then a negative 3.
And if you simplify this, you
get that this is approximately
0.564, or around that.
OK?
And now from here, you would
then, for x2, you're going to
take 0.564 minus these things
evaluated at 0.564.
This ratio, f of 0.564 divided
by f prime at 0.564.
But I'm not going to do that
because you should get
somewhere around, depending on
how many decimal places you
kept, you should get something
around one
of these two values.
So you actually get, after x0,
by x1, you have something that
is at least fixed to the first
two decimal places.
And then this third decimal
place, maybe it's going to be
a 4 or a 3 in the end.
But depending on what about you
we choose here, we might
get slightly different values
here based on the rounding.
So just suffice it
to say, I got x1.
Your x2 should be
about the same.
It should be one of these two.
OK.
So let me just remind you
what we were doing here.
We were trying to use Newton's
Method to find a solution to
an equation that I had written
up here, this 2 cosine x
equals 3x, and I pointed
out a couple things.
I pointed out that finding a
solution to this equation is
the same as finding a solution
to the equation, cosine x
equals 3/2 x.
And so I did that as a graph to
sort of see if I could get
an initial idea of what kind of
solution I was looking for.
And then we just started using
Newton's Method on a
particular function.
And that function was
this side of the
equation minus this side.
Because if 2 cosine x minus
3x equals 0, then 2
cosine x equals 3x.
So we had this function over
here, 2 cosine x minus 3x, and
I said I was looking for
0's of that function.
And that's where Newton's
Method comes in.
So I think that is where
I will stop.