in --
in just two dimensions,
I'd like to find the point
along this line so that line
through a is a one-dimensional
subspace, so I'm starting with
one dimension.
I'd like to find the point on
that line closest to a.
Can I just take that problem
first and then I'll explain why
I want to do it and why I want
to project on other subspaces.
So where's the point closest to
b that's on that line?
It's somewhere there.
And let me connect that and --
and what's the whole point of my
picture now?
What's the -- where does
orthogonality come into this
picture?
The whole point is that this
best point, that's the
projection, P,
of b onto the line,
where's orthogonality?
It's the fact that that's a
right angle.
That this -- the error -- this
is like how much I'm wrong by --
this is the difference between b
and P, the whole point is --
that's perpendicular to a.
That's got to give us the
equation.
That's got to tell us -- that's
the one fact we know,
that's got to tell us where
that projection is.
Let me also say,
look -- I've drawn a triangle
there.
So if we were doing
trigonometry we would do like we
would have angles theta and
distances that would involve
sine theta and cos theta that
leads to lousy formulas compared
to linear algebra.
The formula that we want comes
out nicely and what's the --
what do we know?
We know that P,
this projection,
is some multiple of a,
right?
It's on that line.
So we know it's in that
one-dimensional subspace,
it's some multiple,
let me call that multiple x,
of a.
So really it's that number x
I'd like to find.
So this is going to be simple
in 1-D, so let's just carry it
through, and then see how it
goes in high dimensions.
OK.
The key fact is -- the key to
everything is that
perpendicular.
The fact that a is
perpendicular to a is
perpendicular to e.
Which is (b-ax),
xa.
I don't care what -- xa.
That that equals zero.
Do you see that as the central
equation, that's saying that
this a is perpendicular to this
-- correction,
that's going to tell us what x
is.
Let me just raise the board and
simplify that and out will come
x.
OK.
So if I simplify that,
let's see, I'll move one to --
one term to one side,
the other term will be on the
other side, it looks to me like
x times a transpose a is equal
to a transpose b.
Right?
I have a transpose b as one f-
one term, a transpose a as the
other, so right away here's my a
transpose a.
But it's just a number now.
And I divide by it.
And I get the answer.
x is a transpose b over a
transpose a.
And P, the projection I wanted,
is -- that's the right
multiple.
That's got a cosine theta built
in.
But we don't need to look at
angles.
It's -- we've just got vectors
here.
And the projection is P is a
times that x.
Or x times that a.
But I'm really going to --
eventually I'm going to want
that x coming on the right-hand
side.
So do you see that I've got two
of the three formulas already,
right here, I've got the --
that's the equation -- that
leads me to the answer,
here's the answer for x,
and here's the projection.
OK.
can I do add just one more
thing to this one-dimensional
problem?
One more like lift it up into
linear algebra,
into matrices.
Here's the last thing I want to
do -- but don't forget those
formulas.
a transpose b over a transpose
a.
Actually let's look at that for
a moment first.
Suppose --
Let me take this next step.
So P is a times x.
So can I write that then?
P is a times this neat number,
a transpose b over a transpose
a.
That's our projection.
Can I ask a couple of questions
about it, just while we look,
get that digest that formula.
Suppose b is doubled.
Suppose I change b to two b.
What happens to the projection?
So suppose I instead of that
vector b that I drew on the
board make it two b,
twice as long -- what's the
projection now?
It's doubled too,
right?
It's going to be twice as far,
if b goes twice as far,
the projection will go twice as
far.
And you see it there.
If I put in an extra factor
two, then P's got that factor
too.
Now what about if I double a?
What if I double the vector a
that I'm projecting onto?
What changes?
The projection doesn't change
at all.
Right?
Because I'm just -- the line
didn't change.
If I double a or I take minus
a.
It's still that same line.
The projection's still in the
same place.
And of course if I double a I
get a four up above,
and I get a four --
an extra four below,
they cancel out,
and the projection is the same.
OK.
So really, this -- I want to
look at this as the projection
-- there's a matrix here.
The projection is carried out
by some matrix that I'm going to
call the projection matrix.
And in other words the
projection is some matrix that
acts on this guy b and produces
the projection.
The projection P is the
projection matrix acting on
whatever the input is.
The input is b,
the projection matrix is P.
OK.
Actually you can tell me right
away what this projection matrix
is.
So this is a pretty interesting
matrix.
What matrix is multiplying b?
I'm just -- just from my
formula -- I see what P is.
P, this projection matrix,
is -- what is it?
I see a a transpose above,
and I see a transpose a below.
And those don't cancel.
That's not one.
Right?
That's a matrix.
Because down here,
the a transpose a,
that's just a number,
a transpose a,
that's the length of a squared,
and up above is a column times
a row.
Column times a row is a matrix.
So this is a full-scale n by n
matrix, if I --
if I'm in n dimensions.
And it's kind of an interesting
one.
And it's the one which if I
multiply by b then I get this,
you see once again I'm putting
parentheses in different places.
I'm putting the parentheses
right there.
I'm saying OK,
that's really the matrix that
produces this projection.
OK.
Now, tell me -- all right,
what are the properties of that
matrix?
I'm just using letters here,
a and b, I could put in
numbers, but I think it's -- for
once, it's clearer with letters,
because all formulas are
simple, a transpose b over a
transpose a --
that's the number that
multiplies the a,
and then I see wait a minute,
there's a matrix here and
what's the rank of that matrix,
by the way?
What's the rank of that matrix,
yeah -- let me just ask you
about that matrix.
Which looks a little strange,
a a transpose over this number.
But well, I could ask you its
column space.
Yeah, let me ask you its column
space.
So what's the column space of a
matrix?
If you multiply that matrix by
anything you always get in the
column space,
right?
The column space of a matrix is
when you multiply any vector by
that matrix --
any vector b,
by the matrix,
you always land in the column
space.
That's what column spaces work.
Now what space do we always
land in?
What's the column space of --
what's the result when I
multiply this any vector b by my
matrix?
So I have P times b,
where I?
I'm on that line,
right?
The column space,
so here are facts about this
matrix.
The column space of P,
of this projection matrix,
is the line through a.
And the rank of this matrix is
you can all say it at once one.
Right.
The rank is one.
This is a rank one matrix.
Actually it's exactly the form
that we're familiar with a rank
one matrix.
A column times a row,
that's a rank one matrix,
that column is the basis for
the column space.
Just one dimension.
OK.
So I know that much about the
matrix.
But now there are two more
facts about the matrix that I
want to notice.
First of all is the matrix
symmetric?
That's a natural question for
matrices.
And the answer is yes.
If I take the transpose of this
--
there's a number down there,
the transpose of a a transpose
is a a transpose.
So P is symmetric.
P transpose equals P.
So this is a key property.
That the projection matrix is
symmetric.
One more property now and this
is the real one.
What happens if I do the
projection twice?
So I'm looking for something,
some information about P
squared.
But just give me in terms of
that picture,
in terms my picture,
I take any vector b,
I multiply it by my projection
matrix, and that puts me there,
so this is Pb.
And now I project again.
What happens now?
What happens when I apply the
projection matrix a second time?
To this, so I'm applying it
once brings me here and the
second time brings me I stay
put.
Right?
The projection for a point on
this line the projection is
right where it is.
The projection is the same
point.
So that means that if I project
twice, I get the same answer as
I did in the first projection.
So those are the two properties
that tell me I'm looking at a
projection matrix.
It's symmetric and it's square
is itself.
Because if I project a second
time, it's the same result as
the first result.
OK.
So that's -- and then here's
the exact formula when I know
what I'm projecting onto,
that line through a,
then I know what P is.
So do you see that I have all
the pieces here for projection
on a line?
Now, and those --
please remember those.
So there are three formulas to
remember.
The formula for x,
the formula for P,
which is just ax,
and then the formula for
capital P, which is the matrix.
Good.
OK.
Now I want to move to more
dimensions.
So we're going to have three
formulas again but you'll have
to --
they'll be a little different
because we won't have a single
line but -- a plane or
three-dimensional or a
n-dimensional subspace.
OK.
So now I'll move to the next
question.
Maybe -- let me say first why I
want this projection,
and then we'll figure out what
it is, we'll go completely in
parallel there,
and then we'll use it.
OK, why do I want this
projection?
Well, so why project?
It's because I'm as I mentioned
last time this new chapter deals
with equations Ax=b may have no
solution.
So that's really my problem,
that I'm given a bunch of
equations probably too many
equations, more equations than
unknowns, and I can't solve
them.
OK.
So what do I do?
I solve the closest problem
that I can solve.
And what's the closest one?
Well, ax will always be in the
column space of a.
That's my problem.
My problem is ax has to be in
the column space and b is
probably not in the column
space.
So I change b to what?
I choose the closest vector in
the column space,
so I'll solve Ax equal P
instead.
That one I can do.
Where P is this is the
projection of b onto the column
space.
That's why I want to be able to
do this.
Because I have to find a
solution here,
and I'm going to put a little
hat there to indicate that it's
not the x, it's not the x that
doesn't exist,
it's the x hat that's best
possible.
So I must be able to figure out
what's the good projection
there.
What's the good right-hand side
that is in the column space
that's as close as possible to b
and then I'm -- then I know what
to do.
OK.
So now I've got that problem.
So that's why I have the
problem again but now let me say
I'm in three dimensions,
so I have a plane maybe for
example, and I have a vector b
that's not in the plane.
And I want to project b down
into the plane.
OK.
So there's my question.
How do I project a vector and
I'm --
what I'm looking for is a nice
formula, and I'm counting on
linear algebra to just come out
right, a nice formula for the
projection of b into the plane.
The nearest point.
So this again a right angle is
going to be crucial.
OK.
Now so what's -- first of all
I've got to say what is that
plane.
To get a formula I have to tell
you what the plane is.
How I going to tell you a
plane?
I'll tell you a basis for the
plane, I'll tell you two vectors
a one and a two that give you a
basis for the plane,
so that -- let us say -- say
there's an a one and here's an a
-- a vector a two.
They don't have to be
perpendicular.
But they better be independent,
because then that tells me the
plane.
The plane is the -- is the
plane of a one and a two.
And actually going back to my
-- to this connection,
this plane is a column space,
it's the column space of what
matrix?
What matrix,
so how do I connect the two
questions?
I'm thinking how do I project
onto a plane and I want to get a
matrix in here.
Everything's cleaner if I write
it in terms of a matrix.
So what matrix has these --
has that column space?
Well of course it's just the
matrix that has a one in the
first column and a two in the
second column.
Right, just just let's be sure
we've got the question before we
get to the answer.
So I'm looking for again I'm
given a matrix a with two
columns.
And really I'm ready once I get
to two I'm ready for n.
So it could be two columns,
it could be n columns.
I'll write the answer in terms
of the matrix a.
And the point will be those two
columns describe the plane,
they describe the column space,
and I want to project.
OK.
And I'm given a vector b that's
probably not in the column
space.
Of course, if b is in the
column space,
my projection is simple,
it's just b.
But most likely I have an error
e, this b minus P part,
which is probably not zero.
OK.
But the beauty is that I know
-- from geometry or I could get
it from calculus or I could get
it from linear algebra that that
this this vector --
this is the part of b that's
that's perpendicular to the
plane.
That e is perpendicular is
perpendicular to the plane.
If your intuition is saying
that that's the crucial fact.
That's going to give us the
answer.
OK.
So let me, that's the problem.
Now for the answer.
So this is a lecture that's
really like moving along.
Because I'm just plotting that
problem up there and asking you
what combination -- now,
yeah, so what is it?
P.
What is this projection P?
This is projection P,
is some multiple of these basis
guys, right, some multiple of
the columns.
But I don't like writing out x
one a one plus x two a two,
I would rather right that as
ax.
Well, actually I should put if
I'm really doing everything
right, I should put a little hat
on it --
to remember that this x -- that
those are the numbers and I
could have a put a hat way back
there is right,
so this is this is the
projection, P.
P is ax bar.
And I'm looking for x bar.
So that's what I want an
equation for.
So now I've got hold of the
problem.
The problem is find the right
combination of the columns so
that the error vector is
perpendicular to the plane.
Now let me turn that into an
equation.
So I'll raise the board and
just turn that -- what we've
just done into an equation.
So let me I'll write again the
main point.
The projection is ax b- x hat.
And our problem is find x hat.
And the key is that b minus ax
hat, that's the error.
This is the e.
Is perpendicular to the plane.
That's got to give me well what
I looking for,
I'm looking for two equations
now because I've got an x one
and an x two.
And I'll get two equations
because so this thing e is
perpendicular to the plane.
So what does that mean?
I guess it means it's
perpendicular to a one and also
to a two.
Right, those are two vectors in
the plane and the things that
are perpendicular to the plane
are perpendicular to a one and a
two.
Let me just repeat.
This this guy then is
perpendicular to the plane so
it's perpendicular to that
vector and that vector.
Not -- it's perpendicular to
that of course.
But it's perpendicular to
everything I the plane.
And the plane is really told me
by a one and a two.
So really I have the equations
a one transpose b minus ax is
zero.
And also a two transpose b
minus ax is zero.
Those are my two equations.
But I want those in matrix
form.
I want to put those two
equations together as a matrix
equation and it's just comes out
right.
Look at the matrix a transpose.
Put a one a one transpose is
its first row,
a two transpose is its second
row, that multiplies this b-ax,
and gives me the zero and the
zero.
I'm you see the -- this is one
way -- to come up with this
equation.
So the equation I'm coming up
with is a transpose b-ax hat is
zero.
OK.
That's my equation.
All right.
Now I want to stop for a moment
before I solve it and just think
about it.
First of all do you see that
that equation back in the very
first problem I solved on a
line, what was --
what was on a line the matrix a
only had one column,
it was just little a.
So in the first problem I
solved, projecting on a line,
this for capital a you just
change that to little a and you
have the same equation that we
solved before.
a transpose e equals zero.
OK.
Now a second thing,
second comment.
I would like to since I know
about these four subspaces,
I would like to get them into
this picture.
So let me ask the question,
what subspace is this thing in?
Which of the four subspaces is
that error vector e,
this is this is nothing but e
--
this is this guy,
coming in down perpendicular to
the plane.
What subspace is e in?
From this equation.
Well the equation is saying a
transpose e is zero.
So I'm learning here that e is
in the null space of a
transpose.
Right?
That's my equation.
And now I just want to see hey
of course that that was right.
Because things that are in the
null space of a transpose,
what do we know about the null
space of a transpose?
So that last lecture gave us
the sort of the geometry of
these subspaces.
And the orthogonality of them.
And do you remember what it
was?
What on the right side of our
big figure we always have the
null space of a transpose and
the column space of a,
and they're orthogonal.
So e in the null space of a
transpose is saying e is
perpendicular to the column
space of a.
Yes.
I just feel OK,
the damn thing came out right.
The equation for the equation
that I struggled to find for e
really said what I wanted,
that the error e is
perpendicular to the column
space of a, just right.
And from our four fundamental
subspaces we knew that that is
the same as that.
To say e is in the null space
of a transpose says e's
perpendicular to the column
space.
OK.
So we've got this equation.
Now let's just solve it.
All right.
Let me just rewrite it as a
transpose a x hat equals a
transpose b.
That's our equation.
That gives us x.
And -- allow me to keep
remembering the one-dimensional
case.
The one-dimensional case,
this was little a.
So this was just a number,
little a transpose,
a transpose a was just a vector
row times a column,
a number.
And this was a number.
And x was the ratio of those
numbers.
But now we've got matrices,
this one is n by n.
a transpose a is an n by n
matrix.
OK.
So can I move to the next board
for the solution?
OK.
This is the --
the key equation.
Now I'm ready for the formulas
that we have to remember.
What's x hat?
What's the projection,
what's the projection matrix,
those are my three questions.
That we answered in the 1-D
case and now we're ready for in
the n-dimensional case.
So what is x hat?
Well, what can I say but a
transpose a inverse,
a transpose b.
OK.
That's the solution to -- to
our equation.
What's the projection?
That's more interesting.
The projection is a x hat.
That's how x hat got into the
picture in the first place.
x hat was the was the
combination of columns in the I
had to look for those numbers
and now I found them.
Was the combination of the
columns of a that gave me the
projection.
OK.
So now I know what this guy is.
So it's just I multiply by a.
a a transpose a inverse a
transpose b.
That's looking a little messy
but it's not bad.
That that combination is is our
like magic combination.
This is the thing which is
which use which is like what's
it like, what was it in one
dimension?
What was that we had this we
must have had this thing way
back at the beginning of the
lecture.
What did we -- oh that a was
just a column so it was little
a, little a transpose over a
transpose a, right,
that's what it was in 1-D.
You see what's happened in more
dimensions, I --
I'm not allowed to to just
divide because because I don't
have a number,
I have to put inverse,
because I have an n by n
matrix.
But same formula.
And now tell me what's the
projection matrix?
What matrix is multiplying b to
give the projection?
Right there.
Because there it --
I even already underlined it by
accident.
The projection matrix which I
use capital P is this,
it's it's that thing,
shall I write it again,
a times a transpose a inverse
times a transpose.
Now if you'll bear with me I'll
think about what have I done
here.
I've got this formula.
Now the first thing that occurs
to me is something bad.
Look why don't I just you know
here's a product of two matrices
and I want its inverse,
why don't I just use the
formula I know for the inverse
of a product and say OK,
that's a inverse times a
transpose inverse,
what will happen if I do that?
What will happen if I say hey
this is a inverse times a
transpose inverse,
then shall I do it?
It's going to go on videotape
if I do it, and I don't -- all
right, I'll put it there,
but just like don't take the
videotape quite so carefully.
OK.
So if I put that thing it -- it
would be a a inverse a transpose
inverse a transpose and what's
that?
That's the identity.
But what's going on?
So why -- you see my question
is somehow I did something
wrong.
That that wasn't allowed.
And and and why is that?
Because a is not a square
matrix.
a is not a square matrix.
It doesn't have an inverse.
So I have to leave it that way.
This is not OK.
If if a was a square invertible
matrix, then then I couldn't
complain.
Yeah I think -- let me think
about that case.
But you but my main case,
the whole reason I'm doing all
this, is that a is this matrix
that has x too many rows,
it's just got a couple of
columns, like a one and a two,
but lots of rows.
Not square.
And if it's not square,
this a transpose a is square
but I can't pull it apart like
this --
I'm not allowed to do this pull
apart, except if a was square.
Now if a is square what's
what's going on if a is a square
matrix?
a nice square inv- invertible
matrix.
Think.
What's up with that what's with
that case.
So this is that the formula
ought to work then too.
If a is a nice square
invertible matrix what's its
column space,
so it's a nice n by n
invertible everything great
matrix, what's its column space,
the whole of R^n.
So what's the projection matrix
if I'm projecting onto the whole
space?
It's the identity matrix right?
If I'm projecting b onto the
whole space, not just onto a
plane, but onto all of 3-D,
then b is already in the column
space, the projection is the
identity, and this is gives me
the correct formula,
P is I.
But if I'm projecting onto a
subspace then I can't split
those apart and I have to stay
with that formula.
OK.
And what can I say if -- so I
remember this formula for 1-D
and that's what it looks like in
n dimensions.
And what are the properties
that I expected for any
projection matrix?
And I still expect for this
one?
That matrix should be symmetric
and it is.
P transpose is P.
Because if I transpose this,
this guy's symmetric,
and its inverse is symmetric,
and if I transpose this one
when I transpose it will pop up
there, become a,
that a transpose will pop up
here, and I'm back to P again.
And do we dare try the other
property which is P squared
equal P?
It's got to be right.
Because we know geometrically
that the first projection pops
us onto the column space and the
second one leaves us where we
are.
So I expect that if I multiply
by let me do it -- if I multiply
by another P,
so there's another a,
another a transpose a inverse a
transpose, can you --
eight (a)-s in a row is quite
obscene but -- do you see that
it works?
So I'm squaring that so what do
I do-- how do I see that
multiplication?
Well, yeah, I just want to put
parentheses in good places,
so I see what's happening,
yeah, here's an a transpose a
sitting together --
so when that a transpose a
multiplies its inverse,
all that stuff goes,
right.
And leaves just the a transpose
at the end, which is just what
we want.
So P squared equals P.
So sure enough those two
properties hold.
OK.
OK we really have got now all
the formulas.
x hat, the projection P,
and the projection matrix
capital P.
And now my job is to use them.
OK.
So when would I have a bunch of
equations, too many equations
and yet I want the best answer
and the -- the most important
example, the most common example
is if I have points so here's
the --
here's the application.
v squared.
Fitting by a line.
OK.
So I'll start this application
today and there's more in it
than I can do in this same
lecture.
So that'll give me a chance to
recap the formulas and there
they are, and recap the ideas.
So let me start the problem
today.
I'm given a bunch of data
points.
And they lie close to a line
but not on a line.
Let me take that.
Say a t equal to one,
two and three,
I have one, and two and two
again.
So my data points are this is
the like the time direction and
this is like well let me call
that b or y or something.
I'm given these three points
and I want to fit them by a
line.
By the best straight line.
So the problem is fit the
points one, one is the first
point --
the second point is t equals
two, b equal one,
and the third point is t equal
three, b equal to two.
So those are my three points,
t equal sorry,that's two.
Yeah, OK.
So this is the point one,
one.
This is the point two,
two, and that's the point
three, two.
And of course there isn't a --
a line that goes through them.
So I'm looking for the best
line.
I'm looking for a line that
probably goes somewhere,
do you think it goes somewhere
like that?
I didn't mean to make it go
through that point,
it won't.
It'll kind of --
it'll go between so the error
there and the error there and
the error there are as small as
I can get them.
OK, what I'd like to do is find
the matrix a.
Because once I've found the
matrix a the formulas take over.
So what I'm looking for this
line, b is C+Dt.
So this is in the homework that
I sent out for today.
Find the best line.
So I'm looking for these
numbers.
C and D.
That tell me the line and I
want them to be as close to
going through those three points
as I can get.
I can't get exactly so there
are three equations to go
through the three points.
It would it will go exactly
through that point if let's see
that first point has t equal to
one, so that would say C+D
equaled 1.
This is the one,
one.
The second point t is two.
So C+2D should come out to
equal 2.
But I also want to get the
third equation in and at that
third equation t is three so
C+3D equals only 2.
That's the key.
Is to write down what equations
we would like to solve but
can't.
Reason we if we could solve
them that would mean that we
could put a line through all
three points and of course if
these numbers one,
two, two were different,
we could do it.
But with those numbers,
one, two, two,
we can't.
So what is our equation Ax
equal Ax equal b that we can't
solve?
I just want to say what's the
matrix here, what's the unknown
x, and what's the right-hand
side.
So this is the matrix is one,
one, one, one,
two, three.
The unknown is C and D.
And the right-hand side if one,
two, two.
Right, I've just taken my
equations and I've said what is
Ax and what is b.
Then there's no solution,
this is the typical case where
I have three equations --
two unknowns,
no solution,
but I'm still looking for the
best solution.
And the best solution is taken
is is to solve not this equation
Ax equal b which has which has
no solution but the equation
that does have a solution,
which was this one.
So that's the equation to
solve.
That's the central equation of
the subject.
I can't solve Ax=b but
magically when I multiply both
sides by a transpose I get an
equation that I can solve and
its solution gives me x,
the best x, the best
projection, and I discover
what's the matrix that's behind
it.
OK.
So next time I'll complete an
example, numerical example.
today was all letters,
numbers next time.
Thanks.