PROFESSOR: Hi, guys.
My name is Nikola, and in this
video, we're going to work out
an example of an orthogonal
projection matrix.
Specifically, we are gonna
compute the projection matrix
onto the plane given by
the equation x plus y
minus z equals 0.
So before we start, let
me just recall what a
projection matrix is.
So you've seen this sketch here
a million times already.
A projection matrix takes any
vector in three-space--
well, just in this case we are
dealing with a three-space--
and projects it down onto the
plane, a two dimensional
subspace of our three.
So I'll give you a few moments
to consider the problem for
yourselves.
And then you'll see
my take on it.
Hi again.
So in lecture, Professor Strang
derived, in meticulous
detail, the formula for
the projection matrix.
So it was given by the following
slightly complicated
expression.
It's A times A transpose A
inverse A transpose where A is
a matrix that somehow
encodes the subspace
we're projecting on.
In particular, A has, as
its columns, A1, A2--
I'm going to denote them--
a basis for the plane
we're projecting on.
So essentially, what we need to
do is find two such vectors
that span the plane and start
computing with a matrix.
This is fairly straightforward.
One choice that works, for
example, is 1, -1, 0 for the
first column, and 1, 0, 1
for the second column.
And let me write out the matrix
A. So in the formula,
the slightly more complicated
combination, this A transpose
A inverse, so let me compute
that first for you.
So A transpose A is
a 2 by 2 matrix.
And it's not so hard to figure
out that it's 2 and 1, 1, 2.
Now we shall invert it using
the familiar formula 1 over
the determinant.
2 times 2 minus 1 is 3.
And so we switch the diagonal
entries, and we flip the signs
of the other diagonal ones.
Right.
And therefore, projection matrix
given by the following
product of matrices 1/3, 2, -1,
-1, 2, and then transpose
of A, which is 1,
-1, 0, 1, 0, 1.
I'm gonna carry out this
multiplication in inhumanly
fast fashion.
So I'm just gonna write down the
answer, which is 1/3, 2,
-1, 1, -1, 2, 2, 1, 1, 1.
So what you can do now is--
well, you can check whether
this answer
actually makes sense.
One thing you can do is just--
well, a projection matrix is
supposed to take the normal to
the plane down to 0.
So you can just multiply P and
the normal vector 1, 1, -1.
And if you get 0, maybe you've
done a good job.
Another curious thing that I
would like to point out here
is so you see we had lots of
freedom choosing the matrix A.
We could have chosen any two
columns that span the
subspace, that spans
the plane.
The beautiful thing about it is
that in the end, we'll get
the same answer.
So I hope there will be many
of you who would say, hey,
there is an easier way
to do the problem.
And I'll agree with
these people.
So let's see what would
be an easier approach.
Well, let's go back to
the sketch here.
And let's make the following
observation, that any vector
is a sum of two components.
The first component is its
projection onto the plane.
And the other component is its
projection onto the orthogonal
complement of the plane, in
this case, onto the normal
vector through the plane.
So in the language of linear
algebra, this is just b equals
to its projection onto the plane
plus its projection--
I'm gonna call it PN--
onto the orthogonal complement
of the plane.
I'm gonna suggestively write
here the identity matrix so
that you can immediately read
off a matrix equality.
Associated with this equality
here, it's the identity
equals P plus PN.
And therefore, the projection
matrix is just the identity
minus the projection matrix
onto the normal vector.
Now, this object here, PN, is
much easier to compute, well,
for two reasons.
First one is that projecting
onto a one dimensional
subspace is infinitely easier
than projecting onto a higher
dimensional subspace.
And second, we already have--
well, immediately we can read
off from the equation of the
plane where the normal
vector is.
So we don't have derive
these guys.
We don't have to do
what we did here.
So essentially, PN will be N N
transpose N inverse N transpose.
And that's equal to 1, 1, -1.
And N transpose N inverse,
this is just a number.
It's 1 over the magnitude of the
normal vector, so that's--
then, the magnitude squared.
So that's 3 and 1, -1.
I'm gonna--
The answer here, it's 1/3, 1, 1,
-1, 1, 1, -1, and -1, 1, 1.
And in order to get the
projection matrix--
yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Oh.
Thank you.
And in order to get the
projection matrix, we just
subtract from the identity
this expression.
And you can confirm
that it's--
we get the same answer
as here.
I think we're done here.