The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
Some content in this audio is
not covered under a Creative
Commons license.
For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT
OpenCourseWare website.
PROFESSOR: OK.
So today we're going to,
I guess, kind of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
folks from [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
which is actually very
closely related.
These are folks that,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] the
Comparative Media Studies
Research Group, based in the
old Media Lab building
right now.
And you work with the shared
education program.
For folks who're unaware of
this, MIT actually has a
teacher education program.
So if you want to be a certified
teacher to teach--
AUDIENCE: Middle school
math and science.
Secondary math and science.
PROFESSOR: Then you can take
classes and basically get your
certification of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] certification
at the end of those classes.
But they also make games.
Games using portable devices
like iPhones and PocketPC
games that run on Flash to go
and prototype stuff before.
And focusing a lot on
games for learning.
So the education
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the research group.
The Learning Games Network is
kind of like a spinoff company
of the [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It basically sort of works on
projects that will be too
expensive to do inside
the university.
Because the university is
really inefficient.
Anyway.
Maybe you can start by
introducing yourself?
GUEST SPEAKER: I'm the latest
in the group, so OK.
I am Constantine.
I come from Austria.
I'm at the moment a visiting
researcher at
the Education Arcade.
And so I'd say I come from an
educational background.
So I did my Ph.D on learning
from failure.
And I worked on theories that
explain why we use, why we
learn through mistakes and why
most of them don't want to
learn from failure.
But in games we think it's
really funny, or entertaining,
or challenging.
So I was really interested in
how games can be tools to
understand learning and
also, is it possible--
this is one of my research
questions-- is it possible
that people may learn, through
playing games, how to cope
with failure better?
Like, being more open to
realizing that sometimes in
life we make failure and our
expectations are not true, or
sometimes maybe wrong.
So I do research on the
theoretical level with that,
and I do interviews with
players on learning
biographies and on how learning
experiences through
games were important
in their lives.
And in the summer I was happy to
work for Gambit and design
a game in the summer
production.
Maybe you heard about
that anyway, or--
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: So it's
just like 8 weeks.
I was on a team and my theory
was used as the basis to
develop a learning game
called Afterland.
And of course it's
free online.
And I think our students did a
really good job on this game.
And it's a platformer where--
I will not tell you what it's
about because then I would
ruin it, but there is a twist.
And what I'm going to do now in
the next year is, it looks
like I will try for a few months
and do research on how
the game is used by players.
How they learn in the game, how
they reflect on the game
and I will work with
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Johnson and hopefully even
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] in that.
Thank you.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Hi,
I'm Dan Reilly.
I'm a CMS alum.
I did a masters in,
finished in 07.
Worked with Philip a little
bit here and there.
Mostly I worked with the
Education Arcade during my
time at CMS and with Scott.
And we worked on a project
called Lunar the Labyrinth
which you may have heard of.
It teaches middle school math
and literacy skills,
particularly to the at-risk
population that I believe
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It's free and online.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Better
than after me.
Got to keep it interesting.
PROFESSOR: Is there a twist?
GUEST SPEAKER: Is
there a twist?
PROFESSOR: Yes, well--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] twist that
you originally wanted.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: There
was a twist in
the development process.
So, that one was feted by the
Department of Education.
And it was a larger scale
project, but the grant didn't
go to MIT, it went to Maryland
Public Television.
So that was part of the, I
believe, impetus, for the
spinoff of the Learning Games
Network, is to house a
structure that can accomodate
the sorts of larger scale
projects and think about them
in more sustainable ways.
I'll let Scott talk
about that.
So, how did I get into this?
My interest in learning games
is mostly around engagement.
I feel like people who are
extremely motivated and
enthralled with a particular
subject will find a
way to learn it.
And that a game may or may not
be the best way to learn
anything in particular.
But that there are many people
out there who struggle to get
interested in a topic
they're even trying.
And so a game can
be useful there.
So that's an exploratory tool
to say, well, I never really
thought about history, but I
like this game and I want to
spend some time with it and I
want to be good at it, and
it's social, so now I'm finding
myself asking the
kinds of questions that other
people are telling me
historians ask.
And I don't know what label they
want to put on it, but I
think it's interesting, and
just sort of having that
introduction to a topic.
Also I think games
are helpful for--
I guess I'd call it identity
exploration.
So for people, or particular
learners, who may not think of
themselves as learners or as
confident learners, that they
can put that enemy behind them
when they enter the game
because, it's a game.
And anyone can play it.
Or, maybe I'm particularly
good at games,
so I can play games.
And then I can suddenly realize
that I might be good
at other things as well, or I
might be interested in other
things that I wouldn't allow
myself to discover whether or
not I was interested,
because it was a
risky sphere to enter.
So, current projects.
We're doing a language
learning game.
It's attached to a massively
multiplayer online game, with
a grant targeting a population
of Spanish-speaking high
school students in the US.
And that grant is from the
Hewlett Foundation.
And then we have a couple of
other projects going as well.
We've got science and
some other stuff.
That's about it.
GUEST SPEAKER: So I'm
Scott Osterweil.
I'm the research director
of the Education Arcade.
I have two titles, research
director and creative director
of the Education Arcade.
But also one of the co-founders
of the Learning
Games Network.
And I don't want to repeat too
much of what's been said.
Except that at the same time as
I do this for a living, I
still struggle with the
term educational game.
Because it's not the way I think
of what I do, primarily.
The first game I designed,
before
working in this setting--
the first game I did was
a commercial game.
It wasn't designed as an
educational game, it was
designed just as a puzzle
adventure game.
It happened to be about math and
logic, but that was just
because that's what we thought
was interesting.
It got marketed because of the
changes in the marketplace as
edutainment.
But when I started in the
business there was no such
word as edutainment.
Most games, if you go back to
the early 90s, were sort of
exploratory environments.
Either they were twitch games
or they were exploratory
environments.
And I have nothing against
twitch games, but the
exploratory environments
were all about
thinking and problem solving.
And to me that's what's
interesting.
No matter what domain you're
working in, whether it's
mathematical or whether
it's historical, the
processes are the same.
And one slight twist I want to
put on what Dan said, I think
we're on the same page, but
because he led with the idea
of engagement, it's possible
to think that I'm talking
about games as an inducement
to do something you
don't want to do.
And I think that games are an
opportunity to discover how
much fun something is.
Which is very different from
sort of, ah, we tricked you .
But rather, this is really
interesting, don't you like
doing this and you
can do more.
And if that's all you can get
out of it, that's fine.
If you later realize, oh, I
like doing that and that's
math, and you do more of
that, that's awesome.
That's even better.
And I think it's not so much
because I just said it's fun,
it's because I think the very
process of thinking and
problem-solving [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
People do get that out
of games, and I
just think it's important.
It's how people realize, if you
enjoyed it in a game, you
can enjoy it in life.
And maybe this comes from
my own realization .
But when I was in sixth grade,
instead of them saying the
scientific method, and writing
this list of dull steps on the
blackboard, they said,
play this puzzle.
Now let's talk about how
you solved the puzzle.
That's science.
I think that I might have
ended up working at MIT.
So anyway, that's my spiel.
PROFESSOR: So talking a little
bit about identifying how
you're going to locate what's
enjoyable about the thing that
you want the people
to engage with.
Can you talk a little bit
about, maybe in a recent
project or in a past
project, how you
went about that process.
Let's talk about the things
that you worked out.
And maybe sometimes it was more
difficult and you had
challenges.
Maybe sometimes it was
just pretty obvious.
GUEST SPEAKER: I'll take it.
So--
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: I'd like to
congratulate Scott on his
personal growth.
So, with the language learning
game that we're working on at
the moment, there are approaches
to language
learning out there in the
world that emphasize
vocabulary memorization
or grammar.
Grammar, meaning, memorizing
tables of conjugations and
it's pretty much stripped
of any sort
of meaningful context.
So, and a meaningful context
could either be a text, and I
use that word loosely,
that is engaging.
It could be a film that you want
to see, that happens to
be in a language that you
are trying to learn.
Or it could be a means
of communication.
After all, that's what
language is.
So, if you're thinking about
using language as a means of
communication, then of course
you need to think about, well,
what are you communicating?
And, fortunately, games are
full of communication.
Between the game and
the player, and the
player and the game.
And if it's a multiplayer
game, between the
players in the game.
So it was almost--
if you start from that
philosophy, it's almost a
trivial exercise to say, OK,
well, what's something
interesting for people to
talk about in a game?
And so you come up with
an interesting game.
And instead of having the
mechanic be, click this button
to activate whatever the nuclear
missile, you have to,
you build in collaboration.
So, I have part of the piece
and you have part of the
piece, and we need to talk about
when to use what and in
which context, and on whom.
And so, suddenly we're talking
and it doesn't even feel like
we're learning a language,
it just feels like
we're playing a game.
And then, if you're doing it
in a language that you're
attempting to learn, then
there's the barrier there
where you might want to say
something that you just don't
have the skill yet to say.
So it's not quite as simple as
just saying, hey, go talk.
But there's slightly innovative
ways that you can
give people tools to allow
themselves to express
themselves in a fairly
constrained context.
So, because you've designed
the game, you
sort of rig the system.
You know that people aren't
going to talk
about absolutely anything.
Maybe they will, in the chat,
but primarily in the game
you're incentivizing their
discussion around
a particular topic.
So if you give them tools to
discuss that particular topic,
not only does it make the
gameplay more efficient, but
that's also how the learning
can happen.
Because there can be some sort
of selection mechanism,
whereby I am able to say
something that I want to say,
but without needing to bring all
of the knowledge of how to
construct that on my own.
There's some amount of, oh, I
can just recognize that that's
more or less what I want.
And then, by seeing it
repeatedly and by seeing other
players use the same tools to
communicate, and knowing that
the communication in a certain
context is valid, that I can
pay close attention to that,
and start to become
familiar and learn.
But it's not, I have
to memorize it so
that I can use it.
It's, I'm using it and I'm using
it so much that I just
can actually learn it.
AUDIENCE: Question on that.
So, if you're trying to
encourage me to talk Spanish
and you talk Spanish and we're
trying to work something out,
what prevents you from just
typing something in English
and having you read
it in English?
GUEST SPEAKER: Right, so
it depends on the game.
And in some games that's
totally fine.
In other games we have teams
moderate other teams.
In other games, we have some
sort of communication tool
that's not free text entry.
So it's not-- so one extreme
is, here's a list of 10
sentences that you could say.
Click one of them.
And that's not the direction
we tend to go in.
But that's an example of how
to communicate something
without free text entry.
So there could be some
sort of sentence
construction kit, let's say.
Where you have a pool of
different words that you can
assemble and a variety of orders
to express a small set
of meanings.
GUEST SPEAKER: And if you think
about it, games like
Charades or Pictionary, the
need to communicate with
constraints doesn't stop
us from necessarily
enjoying the game.
It could make it interesting.
So, that's part of the game.
Part of our insight was
thinking about our own
experiences learning language
in terms of the game of say,
and this gets at my core idea,
which is to find the game
that's already there.
So, a game that I always play
when I'm traveling with
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] when I travel
to France, where I speak the
language sort of, is how far can
I get into a conversation
before they figure
out I'm American.
So that becomes a game.
And so the whole, and how can I
have or if I notice someone
who's French, how much
of a conversation
can we have in French?
That's a game for me.
At that point it becomes
kind of fun.
So I think we were just really
trying to access that.
And I think that really gets
back to your larger question.
When you take on something new,
I want to know where's
the game already in this?
And I [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the first game I think, it was
math, and the colleague with
whom I co-designed the game,
we both spent a lot of time
saying, when we were kids, how
did we play with numbers, what
kind of things did
we do, what was
interesting us with numbers?
We really try to access
our own play.
And similarly, now, if I can try
to read practitioners in
the field and say, what do you
think about the shower, when
you run it-- where's the--
because that's where the play
is actually happening
in the field.
And I think that's where people
love their jobs, it's
the play in it that they
love about it.
And that's what I think you're
trying to access in any
simulation.
So Dan, talking about the
language one, we're doing a
game with the Royal Shakespeare
Company, if we can
get funding, around
The Tempest.
And we're trying to figure out
how to make a game of it.
And I realized that part of the
change with Shakespeare
is, to some degree, the
language, too, and sort of
making sense out of the language
which is now somewhat
archaic but really
interesting.
And so we tried to make a game
that's sort of a puzzle that
you assemble by finding the
pieces of the play and
associative things.
So you find a hedgehog and you
find some text that makes a
reference, that somehow makes
you think of the hedgehog and
you put them together and you
actually start building a
visual puzzle.
So it's really a challenge
of making sense of the
significance of text.
It [UNINTELLIGIBLE] you and your
picture of Shakespeare's
play, The Tempest, starts to
emerge through the gameplay.
So a story sort of appears that
way, the way a picture
appears in a jigsaw puzzle.
So it's a game you play without
knowing, without ever
having seen it.
But part of the experience of
theater is the way stories
emerge from different patterns
in the game.
We're still trying to make a
story [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
through exploration.
GUEST SPEAKER: Maybe if I talk
about my career as coming--
I think I come from
an area where we
make really bad games.
There's a saying that education
games are like
chocolate-covered broccoli.
It's not healthy
and not sweet.
And I actually come from a
background where teachers or
educators are asked to build
games for somebody.
And what you have is contents.
And I can say that, because I
think most of my colleagues
seem to know better.
They thought, OK,
I have content.
That content is good, and now I
just make do with a song and
the kids are going to love it.
And I think, as you all see,
Jeremy, we all know how quick
kids realize it is not fun.
And I think there are tons of
bad games out there that ruin
the reputation of educational
games in a sense.
And coming here to MIT and
working with Scott and people
like Dan, that I realized more,
the question is more,
what makes us curious about
the problem, about the
learning content.
Of course, we can have the
content of the game, something
we don't even have to call it.
It's more abstract.
We look for metaphors that are
kind of like, if you can
understand how to be interested
in history without
really learning all the real
data maybe you learn in other
history, but you get interested
in how history works.
And I think that's kind of like
what I learned here and I
realize now that it's really
useful, that we don't use the
chocolate covered broccoli
any more.
We ask more about, what
do we really want?
Do we want to have something
that is healthy or sweet, or
something different,
let's cook it.
Let's not just combine
two things.
And I think there's something
that also-- the good
educational games that
are out there are
heading in that direction.
PROFESSOR: Do you have
counter-examples from your
work, of something that seemed
fruitful but then kind of
maybe you were trying to address
some subject area and
then were trying to marry some
specific game mechanics you
thought might work, but
were disappointed?
GUEST SPEAKER: I could talk
about one that's not resolved
yet, that I'm struggling with.
We're doing a game with a
professor here at Ocean, in
environmental engineering,
about microbes.
He does all his work study
on microbes in the ocean.
Which I've learned about.
Half the biomass of the
ocean are microbes.
And we know almost nothing
about them, because until
people like him, he's one of a
few, built apparatus to study
ocean-like conditions in the
laboratory, we had no way of
knowing what was going
on with them.
So that's interesting
if you get into it.
It's not something that
middle school kids are
dying to know about.
So we're doing a simulation
where the premise is that
you've got a part of the ocean
that's dead and you're trying
to re-engineer it by introducing
nano-bots, which
you can build.
And these nano-bots would in
effect simulate the functions
of what looked like
processing oxygen.
Or rather, plants processing
either oxygen and producing
CO2 and energy, or
the reverse.
Taking CO2 and sunlight and--
Anyway.
So, the challenge, we made a
sort of interesting playable
simulation where you
build the stuff.
But I haven't figured out yet
I'm struggling with, have we
found a way to entice you to
do this, though, without
having to give you too
much information?
And I'm a big believer that a
game-- this game does not
start with instructions, because
I don't believe games
should ever start with
instructions.
But I'm still struggling with
the information we're
providing along the way.
There's too much read this now,
as opposed to-- and I
think the problem is, because
simulations are very wide open
environments, and it's very hard
to constrain a simulation
enough that the player goes,
ah, now I understand what
variable I just used.
And particularly because kids
have a tendency to see
simulations as black boxes.
So they'll change three
variables at once and not
notice they've changed three
variables, and not think about
what each variable was.
They just don't have the
practice of changing--
really, controlling
three variables.
And if you don't do that,
simulations do become black
boxes, and I'm still struggling
with how to-- not
to, say, mark the kid down the
road and say, OK, now make
this choice, now make
that choice.
Because that's too constrained
and not fun.
I want to have them have a lot
of choices but also have them
understand the effect of the
choices that they've made.
Maybe that's the best
way to sum it.
So just processing the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
GUEST SPEAKER: I can give
a better example.
So, I was working
on this game.
I wasn't even working on
that, to my excuse.
I was beginning to work with
these people, then realized
it's not the way I want to go.
And then I stepped out of it.
And I think it's a good
example of what
you shouldn't do.
So this small town in Austria
is using their waste to
produce renewable energy.
It's really interesting.
The town is somewhere in the
countryside and nobody was
interested.
It makes so much power now that
they can give power for
free in their town to companies
and the neighboring
companies in neighboring
towns.
So a lot of people
are interested
in how they do that.
And we thought, well, we want to
be a cool town, what if we
make a game instead of just
providing the content.
But what they did, they gave us
all the content and said,
this is what you should
teach the people.
And make it fun.
And in the end, these people
were sitting together, OK,
what do people like?
Comics?
And you have to a character
that is moving around.
And they would make small
multiple choice tests.
And afterwards they get their
rewards, and it says your name
and it says you're trained
in that discipline.
And what was interesting for
me, they built the game.
And the game's been bashed.
And it's very sad and
it's horrible.
But the funniest thing for me
was, who was the target group?
And they never talked
about that.
They always thought who cares
about target groups, we make
this game, everybody's going
to love it, everybody's so
interested.
The idea was who decides
if you can do that in
the majors of towns.
They say, well, we want to
have a company like that.
And so now we're talking
about Austrian,
European, majors of towns.
And they are normally fat
and like to drink wine.
Normally they sit with another
mayor and have lunch and then
they say, wow, this works.
And then they decide
to do it or not.
But now they were sending these
games to majors who did
not know at all what
to do with this.
They couldn't get
into the game.
And so, not that the
game was bad.
They didn't even think about
their target group.
And I think that one aspect that
interested me the most
is, you have to have the context
of the game as a
learning experience.
It has to be suitable.
If this is not happening,
you can play the
most interesting game.
If someone doesn't get the
problem, doesn't get engaged
to the problem, it's just
something happening.
It's not really interesting.
And I think that's a major
problem that this
example was totally .
PROFESSOR: So, know who you're
designing your game for.
And how do you think they get
engaged in the games.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
GUEST SPEAKER: Just to do a
simplistic example, but it's
one [UNINTELLIGIBLE] example.
If I wanted a game for my
mother, who occasionally would
play a casual game.
I wouldn't do a massively
multiplayer game with lots of
stuff going around.
All these senior citizens are
going to get into this
massively multiplayer game.
I mean, it sounds like it would
be really great, to come
up with a massively multiplayer
game for senior
citizens, because of
their eyesight.
But you also know that they
didn't grow up with computers,
and they're not going to be able
to navigate a 3D space.
So, that's a simplified example
of why it's important
[INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: And what is really
good about it is that game
like [? Revish ?] the
cancer game, maybe
some of you know about.
It's a cancer game
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: It was actually
mentioned in the reading
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: But it's
hopefully one of the best
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] learning
games out there.
But the good thing about them
is, people that play that game
have cancer.
So you have the problem to the
game is so close that people
who do not play the game say oh,
I don't care about cancer.
They care about cancer because
they have cancer.
The game is about cancer, and
the way chemotherapy works.
So the context of the engagement
is automatically,
the problem is solved.
But what about this cancer.
What about a learning
game where it's
about language learning?
Are these people already
interested
to learn the language?
Do they come there with their
language problem, or do we
want to introduce them to the
problem or show them maybe you
don't have to be afraid to learn
a language or whatever.
This question has to
be addressed at
a very early stage.
Otherwise, if you start
designing and then address the
question, it's late.
The question is sort of about
the explicit versus the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So if you play [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
that was
really designed to introduce,
basically, an idea that people
have struggled with, which are
what position and velocity
graphs actually mean.
But the game doesn't mention
velocity and it doesn't
mention graphs.
And in fact in the same reviews
that it got lots of
good reviews when it came out,
a lot of them said, I had no
idea this was educational.
I wouldn't argue that that's
fine, that people don't
necessarily know that as they're
playing the game, that
they are still building up some
conceptual knowledge.
I think that some large
percentage of the people who
play a game in that setting will
probably play the game
and do nothing else but then
three months later
they'll have gone.
That experience for most people
will not be resilient.
Not because they didn't enjoy
it, but because they have lots
of things going on in life and
there's more information
coming out of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
On the other hand, the kid plays
that game and then you
sit down and have a conversation
about velocity
and position graphs, there might
be some real meaningful
learning that occurs.
And so I think it's really
important to not overreach in
that sense.
I try to avoid, although we
still do the saying that our
games teach.
Because I think teaching is a
much more active and explicit
activity to learn games too.
I think our games let people
play with them, let people
learn from them.
And then just like if you
read a book, the book
doesn't teach anything.
The book puts information
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
And I think that's really part
of, I think, we have to be
modest and humble about it
as we do this stuff.
But that was [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
as the challenge
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
of thinking about, if you do
want some learning to occur,
where do you want the
learning to occur.
Is this for peoples' personal
lives, is it a mediated
setting like a hospital?
Or is it in a school--
those are really
critical questions .
It's not just the learning
but the setting.
PROFESSOR: And who's introducing
a game to them,
for instance.
Is it a teacher, a doctor.
GUEST SPEAKER: And were
they playing.
Like with Labyrinth, which is
this middle school math game
that Dan and I were
working on.
We knew that if we didn't push
in another direction, the
implementation was going to be,
well print this game and
it gets played in classrooms.
If you've ever seen--
if you remember your own
computer labs in school, that
that was [UNINTELLIGIBLE], which
is true actually for a
lot of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It meant every now and then you
had to line up and walk
down the hall to this other
place, that you would only get
to occasionally.
And by the time you settled into
your chairs and booted it
up, you had maybe 20 minutes
on the computer and then it
was time to go.
So if you design something for
schools, you're talking about
a 20 minute experience once
every two or three weeks.
I'm not sure that was
worth thinking about
anything for that.
So we design the game, we
play it online at home.
And encourage teachers to let
the kids just play it.
And there was another advantage
of that, which was
to go back to who
introduces it.
If you play that-- even if we
have the perfect 20 minute
game for the computer lab, if
the teacher's walking around--
I shouldn't say.
I've seen good uses
of that space.
But there's some greater
probability you're going to
feel like this is
just a lesson.
Whereas if the teacher says, go
play this at home, there's
some greater probability that
you will sort of forget about
the school and get
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And again, it's not that
we want to trick
you into doing math.
It's that we want to engage
with the math in the most
pleasant spirit possible.
And the less we give the wrapper
of school to it, the
more playful you're
likely to be.
Even if you're not denying that
it's math or science or
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So that was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
GUEST SPEAKER: So Constantine,
you had said the cancer game
is really well evaluated.
So did any of you have stories
or experiences from seeing
your games out in the
world that way.
You've gotten feedback from
teachers who have tried this
in the classrooms.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
so from the game I just talked
about, about renewable
energies that totally failed.
People played it but didn't
understand it, hated it, or
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So I think, total failure.
And I think just to start with
this conversation is, this is
a problematic thing.
Because there is very little
research going on on the
iteration of games, because
it's also very hard.
It takes lot of effort and it
also could take a lot of money
to evaluate the research, that
the success of the game for
learning purposes.
And I just know very
few studies that do
that, in the end.
And I think we've just reached
that moment where people start
to think that this is an
interesting way to do it.
And Remission, as I said,
is probably--
maybe you'll correct me in a
second, but I think it's the
only game I would put my hand
into the fire for it.
But the question is, what did
they learn in the game?
They learned about
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
They learned that there is
something they can do.
They learned a more positive
perspective, a more positive
relation to medicine.
They didn't learn
anything else.
In the research--
GUEST SPEAKER: It doesn't really
change their illness.
PROFESSOR: And they didn't
get happier.
It's not that they said, wow,
now, I couldn't cope better
with their illness.
They just took the medicine and
so the doctors were really
happy with that.
But--
GUEST SPEAKER: That's
the stated goal
of Remission, actually.
It's, this is a 3D game
where you play a
woman in space or something.
Shot down and [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
but the stated goal of the game,
at least of the people
who were making it, was to try
to encourage people who are
suffering from cancer to keep
up with their medication.
Don't fail keeping up the
schedule of taking your
chemotherapy drugs, basically.
And the game was designed to
show what happens, what these
drugs actually try to do in some
sort of fictional-- or
fantastical, I'm not going
to say fictional --
so that's Remission.
PROFESSOR: Is this a free
play game as well?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
Yeah.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: So, on Labyrinth
the original grant
include an excess of one year
evaluation on the game use.
And then when Congress cut back
the funding of the larger
program, of which Labyrinth was
just one small piece, that
got cut off.
And so the research
didn't happen.
We're now looking for a grant,
because Labyrinth has been
used aggressively in Maryland
schools [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So we are going to
look for funding.
But generally, there's
less money.
As little money as there is
you're developing this
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] there's even
less for researching them.
And I think some of what I think
our work is designed
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], we figure
out what we can learn by
making the game.
And we publish what we've
learned in the hope that other
people will pick up the ball,
people who have more of a
research bent in the
traditional sense.
Will start to do the
research about it.
I think we're on the
brink of that.
I think with stuff like the
Quest to Learn School.
Increasing numbers of
educators are using
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I do have only anecdotal
evidence, but the very first
game that I did, which was this
massive logic oriented
game, ended up being not
particularly well marketed.
It nevertheless sold
a million copies.
And the anecdotal evidence I got
was that it was one of the
rare cases where parents would
bring it in and recommend it
to teachers, and teachers would
recommend it to parents.
Or kids would come home from
school recommending it.
And there seemed to be this
fairly broad acceptance by
both parents and teachers and
kids, without kids having the
sense that, oh, my teacher's
making me do this.
And I hear that now that
everybody's rich and famous in
their 20s, I occasionally
hear from them.
And some of them say it's
what interested
them in math and stuff.
So that's all anecdotal, and
maybe [UNINTELLIGIBLE] has
some [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But I think the million copies
is beating towards the--
PROFESSOR:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Sure.
I'll just add a little
bit to that.
I also have some anecdotal
stuff I want to bring in.
But the most interesting thing
that I've discovered was with
Labyrinth and a target audience
that I've seen play
it, that it was not specifically
designed for.
Which is kids with some sort
of attention disorder.
Whether it's ADD, or autism
or something.
And seeing these kids engage
with the game, even engage
with the game in a social
way, and be
hyperfocused on the game.
And be highly competent with the
game, and to really calm
down and adopt pro-social
behaviors that were not
characteristic of them.
Or that their peers
or families hadn't
seen with them before.
I think there's a lot
of power there.
GUEST SPEAKER: The first two
teachers I've met who have
used Labyrinth said they were
seeing performance with kids
they didn't expect
to see before.
Because our sense was that lots
of kids have competencies
and skills that they
don't show off in
the format of school.
School being its own kind of
game which only certain people
are good at.
And so having a kid be able to
demonstrate a competency at a
different kind of game, and
let the teacher see it.
Because part of the design of
Labyrinth is that teachers can
track progress online.
That was one of our goals.
And that was [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: This is a very
good laptop actually.
So is it possible to look it up
and show some of Labyrinth?
Because we've been talking
about it in this aspect.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, sure.
Absolutely.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: It's just
a notion of a game.
GUEST SPEAKER: But other people
can [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: While we're setting
that up, I'd like to ask a bit
about prototyping.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
So, in the process of
designing-- these are mostly
digital games that we've been
talking about all the time.
But I'd like to talk about the
early stage, when you're
working with paper or simple
digital prototypes.
Maybe you can talk a little bit
about how that might be
similar or different from
designing other kinds of
computer games, or
even board games?
Do you test it differently
because you're designing it
explicitly for a specific
audience?
Do you test it with instructors
as well as
players, or [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
GUEST SPEAKER: I think it's
always best to try to test
with your target audience.
The things you'd learn
from [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
there's thing you learn, you can
learn from any audience.
Particularly usability,
which is important.
Frequently the flaw in a game is
not the core mechanic, but
the ease with which the player
can understand what they're
supposed to do.
But you can test that with
any wide range of people.
Anyone who you think is roughly
as computer game
literate as your target
audience.
But I think if your goal is to
interest middle-school kids
like we do with this game--
let me just turn this on--
then you do want to, because
there are questions about age
appropriateness.
Or [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
All right.
So we're about to get
this screen here.
So this is a login screen.
This is not the first screen
you would come to if you'd
started the game from scratch,
you get some more information.
But I've already logged in.
So what you'll notice--
let me just log in.
So it's online.
You can play from
any computer.
That was important because
we were concerned about
underserved populations who
either don't have computers at
home or who have less control
over their time, don't have a
computer in their
room, certainly.
Or might do all their work
in an after-school
setting or a library.
So basically, once you
have an identity you
can log in from anywhere.
I'm going to briefly enter
the game space but
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So here we're already in
the middle of the game.
This is a puzzle
adventure game.
And the plot is, someone's
stolen my pet.
I've tracked it down to this
underground factory that's
being run by monsters--
and there's middle schoolers--
with the help of a mysterious
woman with
bluish skin and wings.
I've been given a monster
costume, so in the guise of a
monster myself I can go around
and do jobs in the factory.
Find my pet, figure out what the
monsters are up to, which
is indeed no good.
And I'm in the middle of
this game, so I've
already advanced some.
There is a sequence of rooms,
which, part of the game is
just finding the rooms where
the puzzles are.
For example, we've
got it here.
This is one of the wings
of the factory.
There's a hundred doors here.
And I can click on every
door if I have to.
But I have a map, which is
itself a mathematical tool, to
find where I want to go.
And as I go through, each room
represents a different puzzle.
Anyway, having said
that, we're going
to actually go back--
And oh.
The other big feature in the
game is that if you play on
teams, then you can communicate
with your
teammates through this
communicator.
And the reason there is to
actually get kids reading and
writing about what they're
doing with math.
Because if you want to help
your teammmates, you can't
feed each other the answers
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
puzzle.
Every puzzle, every
time you play,
it's a different solution.
So you can't tell each other the
answer, all you can do is
talk about your strategies.
We're going to leave the game
and go to puzzle mode
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: This is a shortcut?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, shortcut
to puzzles, right.
You don't have to play it in
the context of the game.
You can play any puzzle
that you want.
I'm going to try one that
I've never played
with a group before.
So usually I pick the same game,
play it, and get used to
playing it with people.
But let's just try this one.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I think I've tried level one.
So I'm trying to remember
what you know here.
You're in the back in
the shipping area.
And you've got to come up with
a manifest to ship the number
of objects that you've got.
That's all you know.
You've basically got to
give them the right
instructions to ship it.
And so now, just tell
me what to do here.
AUDIENCE: Click something.
GUEST SPEAKER: Of course.
And that's [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Up into the slots up there.
There's ones and zeroes.
GUEST SPEAKER: Can we put that
crazy fish head second to the
right on every one in
the equals spot?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
You can.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: Want to try
it in the equals spot.
GUEST SPEAKER: And go to
the equals on this one.
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Just tell us what your
thinking was.
AUDIENCE: Well, it looks
like we're trying
to build math equations.
And usually they end with
equals something.
GUEST SPEAKER: Right.
And you saw that.
Now, just so you know, the
equation we're going to
build-- you're right, and just
as a shortcut-- is not about
arithmetic.
The equations are simple.
I'm not interested in drilling
kids on arithmetic.
This is really about number
systems, and number systems
are just simple systems.
But there's also some algebra
that's going to go on this, we
start to do this too.
And then in higher levels of the
puzzle, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
you start doing stuff in
base two and base six.
We sort of dovetailed with
the notion that our
representations of numbers
are just symbolic.
So zero, or one, or one
zero, doesn't have
to always mean 10.
It's just a symbol.
Anyway.
So now what should we do?
AUDIENCE: Pac-Man
should be minus.
Because the only ones with six
digits have Pac-Man as the
third digit.
PROFESSOR: Sounds good.
GUEST SPEAKER: I'm not sure
which one is Pac-Man.
AUDIENCE: Bottom right.
GUEST SPEAKER: This guy?
AUDIENCE: That guy's Pac-Man.
Pac-Man with an underline.
GUEST SPEAKER: I'm not sure
if we can actually
put that one there.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: If you look at the
top left, then what is the
number two digit number that,
minus the last digit, gives a
single-digit number.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, that's
a good point, yeah.
It has to be divided by
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: But now what
you're really doing is
thinking about the structure
of math.
Which is exactly what--
AUDIENCE: So when you
say that's divided--
AUDIENCE: So, I'm going to
guess the banana is four?
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: You
want to say why?
AUDIENCE: Because using that
same logic, that first
version, that something, n x
divided by x equals some
single digit number.
And I'm guessing x is 4.
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: By the way, you
guys have avoided, and not
noticed a piece of information
which would make your work
even more--
AUDIENCE: Oh, the thing
at the top.
AUDIENCE: What's the
thing at the top?
AUDIENCE: The thing
at the bottom.
AUDIENCE: It could be two,
actually, as well.
AUDIENCE: What are all
the green things?
GUEST SPEAKER: Those are the
things you're shipping.
Those are jars of stuff,
of pepper.
AUDIENCE: Oh, those
make sense.
AUDIENCE: Banana something
banana.
GUEST SPEAKER: Banana
something--
AUDIENCE: Equals something
banana.
So--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Banana could
actually be two.
Because 12 divided by two
is equal to six. six.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, and in that
respect, that means a little--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, the four
squares are signs.
You try that?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It has
to be zero on--
GUEST SPEAKER: Every time
you play the game
the symbols are different.
They're the same symbols but
they're a different--
AUDIENCE: Triple backlash
should be-- oh.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: By the way,
you're still missing a piece
of information.
But that's OK.
That's what games
are all about.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So what's this
thing in the top left?
Can we put things in there and
press enter, and will it
evaluate them for us?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, but right
now-- you're not done yet .
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah, triple dash
is definitely one.
GUEST SPEAKER: Triple
dash is--
AUDIENCE: Oh, triple dash
is one, because one
times banana is banana.
GUEST SPEAKER: Unless
banana's zero.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Banana's
six, I think.
AUDIENCE: It could be five.
GUEST SPEAKER: I've never
done this game before--
no.
The fact that you're naming
all these symbols, because
they were just symbols.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I think banana's
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], because banana--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
banana squared is equal to
something times banana.
AUDIENCE: Not something
times--
AUDIENCE: So, yeah, it
could be 25 actually.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: Remember, I
didn't know the solution to
this when it came in, but I
actually have enough data to
know that you're wrong.
It's on the screen.
AUDIENCE: Banana
definitely is--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Five because banana
squared is anchor banana.
But flower banana divided by
banana is also an integer.
So if flower banana and anchor
banana are local banana, then
banana should be five
and not six.
because flower minus anchor
times banana.
GUEST SPEAKER: I love your
mental calculation.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: So you're
saying it's what?
AUDIENCE: Five.
GUEST SPEAKER: Well, that could
work, but you could have
done it in a simpler way.
Or you could have surmised
it, not known it, but--
remember, this is only the
first time you played,
subsequent times you'd have
other information.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: You're a member
of the group, so don't give
away [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
but in fact you're making--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Anchor is 20.
AUDIENCE: Anchor is two.
AUDIENCE: Sorry, two.
Not 20.
AUDIENCE: Anchor's two.
Claw is zero.
GUEST SPEAKER: Where's claw?
AUDIENCE: Claw's the one
on the top left.
Of the squares that are left.
Left.
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, you
mean brass circles.
That makes sense.
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, that one.
AUDIENCE: That's zero.
Has to be zero.
PROFESSOR: Wait,
why is it zero?
AUDIENCE: Because if
you look at the
equation at the bottom--
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, I'm looking
at the wrong spot.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Yeah, sigma's nine.
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: OK, so
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
scythe is plus.
Scythe is plus.
AUDIENCE: No, it has
to be minus.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: Anyone who is
having trouble, and this
happens in a group.
So, anyone having trouble
following it as people were
making stuff up or
finding stuff.
Because if you did it's OK.
In fact, sometimes you've got to
play the game yourself for
it to make sense.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I could have told you--
I actually think I could have
told you a lot about the game
going into it.
And there would still be a high
probability that when you
started playing it you would
have not absorbed
anything I'd said.
That's my experience.
I could almost give it all away
but you still don't get
it until they play it.
PROFESSOR: So they
didn't know--
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Beta delta upside
down is eight.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Can we
enter that now?
AUDIENCE: Oh, so now you have
to type in one times
whatever-- equals--
GUEST SPEAKER: You've got
to type in what this is.
So and this is actually
getting at another
representation.
AUDIENCE: Eight plus nine.
AUDIENCE: Eight plus
nine is 17.
GUEST SPEAKER: How, here you
don't have to actually
remember the [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Just divide
it by six.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: It's puzzle mode.
GUEST SPEAKER: And by the
way, it could take
it in either order.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I agree.
Equals [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: I think this
level's only addition
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Or we could
do 10 minus two.
GUEST SPEAKER: Anyway.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
you were doing algebra.
When you were solving
for those numbers,
you were doing algebra.
You were really thinking about
x and the structure of the
math and the numerical
quality of it.
This is simpler, but it's still
getting at the fact that
there are multiple ways of
representing numbers
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Is there
any mechanic to
prevent brute force?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes, those
lights go out.
But, you do earn points along
the way in the game if you
make some progress.
And so, none of these puzzles
are brick walls.
Because you can always play
multiple puzzles at once.
You can leave this puzzle,
go to another puzzle.
And, if you make any progress
at all, you're accumulating
points for the end
of the game.
You could actually get to the
end of the game story without
having solved any puzzles.
Takes a long time.
The rewards are there
for doing well.
And there are rewards for doing
well, but there isn't
punishment for not doing well.
At least in sort of a--
we don't say you can't,
we don't make you
stop in your tracks.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
you can do it again.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes,
that's right.
You can do it again
instantaneously.
And there is no cost in the
game to having failed
repeatedly.
If you eventually solve it, you
end up with the same score
whether you solved it on the
20th time or the first time.
That's really what problem
solving is about.
It's not about being
the fastest.
It's just about learning
how to solve things.
Speed is overrated
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And in math it's
very overrated.
Kids [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
calculations in their head.
It's just more of this.
And the entire level's--
we came up with representations
of
subtraction, which is that you
have a large number, you have
10 jars and five of
them are empty.
So it's 10 minus five.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: How is division?
AUDIENCE: Are they
10 rows of jars?
And the rows are empty?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, I
think it's the same--
I think that's it.
I think that's the same.
It's in a grid pattern with
some [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: And I guess there's
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
but do you have any algebra
as such in this format?
GUEST SPEAKER: No.
But what we encourage
is that--
so what comes with this is
material for teachers to
relate this to the curriculum.
And what we really want to
happen is that kids have
played the game before
they get the subject.
And when the teacher introduces
symbol systems in
base six or whatever relates
to this, instead of saying,
all right, we're starting a
new unit, you again know
nothing, you're starting again
at square one and have to
start all over again
with something new.
Instead, the teacher comes in
and says, I want to introduce
a new concept, but it's one
that you've really already
begun to master.
And it's called bases.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
so how did you solve this?
What was going on
in this game?
And they have a conversation
about what they already know,
as a way of leveraging into--
I mean, things that I
arguably don't know.
Again, I would argue that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
you have things in cartons.
So a carton of six jars plus
some left over would be--
a carton of six jars plus three
left over would be one,
three, basically.
So anyway.
The point is that the kids begin
to build this robust
conceptual understanding.
And hopefully there's a
playfulness so that when the
teacher talks about it, that
some of them may actually feel
good about it.
Instead of, here's one more
reading --you'll never be a
mathematician.
I think math education is
largely designed to gate
everybody so that at the
end of high school,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] population
is good at math.
Which means that we're taking
12 years teaching 93% of the
population that's no good at
math and they should stop
doing that.
I don't know why we'd waste 12
years if you could just tell
them to go to kindergarten.
But that's what what
we end up doing.
Anyway, I think that's true
of every subject.
I'd like to turn it around.
Everyone says there's things
about math I can do.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Can you tell us a
little bit more about how that
process went?
GUEST SPEAKER: Sure.
And I also wanted to provide a
little extra nuance to one of
the questions about what if you
just brute-force your way
through it.
In the higher levels, it won't
tell you when you put a symbol
in a slot, whether it's
correct or not.
So--
GUEST SPEAKER: Which actually,
you could learn something
interesting.
Because you could start doing
something and [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
something that doesn't add
up, that's actually new.
You're learning something.
So, there's 10 puzzles
or-- how many?
GUEST SPEAKER: Nine.
AUDIENCE: Nine puzzles, and we
came up with nine plus x, and
some of that was slated for
school admission and
we never got there.
And some of that x was puzzles
or activities that we decided
were not as compelling
as the others.
In our process for that, we
did a hybrid approach with
paper and computer
prototyping.
In general the rule is, if there
can be paper prototypes,
paper prototype it.
Because it's so much faster.
But there are certain kinds of
activities that really can't.
So for instance, this one is
perfect for paper prototyping.
You just take out a
piece of paper and
a pen and you create--
I mean, you have to create some
of these equations so
that you then have a system
of equations to solve.
But once you've created some of
those is, as would need to
be done whether it's a paper or
a computer prototype, then
it's trivial to put it in front
of someone with paper.
So this is an example of
something where we would, for
the first round, test internally
with just symbols
and numbers.
And then probably
we would do--
we might even test that version
with people in our
target audience.
But probably we would try to
do some rudimentary art
treatment before we put it in
front of people, just so
there's a little bit of context
and it looks a little
bit more like a game.
And then--
GUEST SPEAKER: So
that we try to--
if there's story, this one has
less story about it, but if
there's story, as there are in
some puzzles, we actually try
to act it out.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
resistance to doing it.
So act out the character.
You're the computer, when
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and so even if it's just a
character giving a response to
something that the
player does.
You try to do it in character,
you try to get a sense of
what-- because I think, even
in that kind of rudimentary
form you're engaging the
player's imagination so you
know whether or not they're
interested in this character
or the idea [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: Because I do
master [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: And like a
dungeon master you need to
prepare, because it's hard to
be the computer without also
being the bottleneck
if you're a human.
And in fact we've done some
games, not represented here,
we've done some games that are
real time, that if you want to
prototype with people, then
especially on paper, and you
want to keep things moving,
then you need to have more
than one person be the computer,
because there's just
too much to track for one
person to do it all.
Or if you want to do--
sometimes we do hybrids, where
we'll do a computer prototype
but there's aspects of the game
that are not represented
through the interface or that
logically we have a model, so
we'll do players
directing human
interactions with the computer.
Not players, designers,
influencing those
interactions.
So anyway, this is a game that
moved pretty much all the way
to final design on paper, and
then went straight to
implementation.
Some of the other games-- for
instance, there's a game--
do you want to show
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: That's an example
of a game that's a
little bit harder to think about
playing just on paper.
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
we
implemented this early.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, we did.
GUEST SPEAKER: So this is a game
about modular arithmetic
and common multiples and
that sort of thing.
So it's very hard to
see on the screen.
In the upper left there
is an avatar.
GUEST SPEAKER: That's you.
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: And you know from
the story that your goal
is to get to the golden
eggs and avoid the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
That much you know.
And that you're in a factory
where they make stuff.
AUDIENCE: Do you move
your avatar?
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
GUEST SPEAKER: There is one
flaw, by the way, in the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
interface, because people don't
realize they have to
click to get their guy
onto that thing.
And it was supposed to start
with the [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
right where he was, that people
would [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
click.
Because now by-- what
should I try now.
AUDIENCE: Four.
GUEST SPEAKER: We're
going to go--
AUDIENCE: Four or nine.
AUDIENCE: Six.
AUDIENCE: Four.
Four.
AUDIENCE: Six.
Then you can let him get
the [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: I'll
go for six.
Bam.
Four is a subject that--
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, can we
move [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: But you'll notice
that that's all in
different amounts.
And so it's really that
modular arithmetic.
So 12 will take me once around
on one of them, but
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
on another one.
And you start doing simultaneous
equations to
solve this.
This level's hard.
I think maybe the hardest puzzle
we designed in the
whole game is level three of
this, where every step you've
got to align two bridges.
It's serious work.
AUDIENCE: Are you trying
to avoid that monster?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, you've
got to avoid the monster.
GUEST SPEAKER: Which
isn't always hard.
But you have to keep in mind,
sometimes it needs, instead of
going around once, particularly
one on the nine
thing, maybe you go 10 and
he'll always go on
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
shows up, to make
to show up and [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So this is really the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: As of what?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
GUEST SPEAKER: Anyway, again
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
you can say, hey,
math, school math at all.
There's no school math
in this game.
But I think there are
really interesting
things to think about.
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
said with that character.
If he walks or not.
I think we [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
anyway.
But you have to keep
in mind, there are
two forms of learning.
One is learning the game,
how to play the game.
And the other one is learning--
there's a problem
solving, you've got a
puzzle in the game.
And I think it's sometimes like
special education games.
It's so easy to mix this.
Because sometimes you make the
coolest educational game and
it's really interesting.
But [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
character wouldn't move if you
don't press the mouse button.
So he would always stand there
in the beginning and he would
get attacked.
And I think the mixture of
both forms of learning is
quite interesting to keep in
mind when you're prototyping.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, there's
two answers to that.
One is, I never think.
just because we want people to
think hard, I don't think the
interface should be the
thing that they're
thinking hard about.
It's always tempting to say,
oh, that's a really
hard thing to solve.
How do I make him jump?
But no, I think generally it
should not be hard to figure
out how to make him jump.
Or walk left or right, or
how to open a door.
Unless that's a puzzle, and it's
easy to delude yourself
that by making the
interface hard...
On the other hand, there is this
other challenge, which is
that kids do have different
degrees of
literacy around games.
And it's hard to figure out
where the sweet spot is.
That's one I don't have
an easy answer for.
Because some large percentage
of the audience naturally
knows, try and get to the end.
Knows what winning means.
But there's some
kids who don't.
And the question is, if you
make the game, if you bend
over backwards--
I watched my mother play this,
and it was horrible.
Because she just was totally
clueless about where to go.
But I think if I try to set
up the game to work for my
mother, you can only work with
all this explicit instruction.
So hopefully with kids it's
less of an issue.
There's more, I think, uniform
game literacy.
But it's always a challenge.
No game appeals to everybody.
And you do want--
I don't think those of us who
make learning games have a
good answer to that.
I don't think we can ever make
a game that every kid would
play with equal--
we should never claim
that we're going
to get 100% on that.
PROFESSOR: One thing that I know
that you've noticed is
the amount of tolerance that
kids and adults have for
frustration, when--
I've seen kids say,
I hate this game.
This game is too hard and
they'll just keep going at it.
Whereas the adults have this
tendency to get really
embarrassed when they can't
solve it first time.
GUEST SPEAKER: It happens
when you're 26.
You suddenly sit down and
say, well, I'm not
very good at this.
You may be a gamer all your
life, but it's having another
adult watching you.
There's some point or another
where you suddenly say, I'm
not good at this.
I don't know why it happens.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Can you do
negative numbers?
GUEST SPEAKER: Not
in this one, no.
That's a good idea, though.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: In much of the
arithmetic you could always do
it as put in a larger number
and [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: That's right.
PROFESSOR: I have a question
for [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Because in some of them we were
hearing from you guys
about coming, more or less from
a game design angle into
designing games as a
learning purpose.
And you kind of [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the other way around.
You came in from the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Are there things to keep in
mind when you're working
across disciplines, that
game designers know?
GUEST SPEAKER: So, I think one
more difference that I still
have, or see between the way I
approach games and the way
educational games approach games
design, I'm more focused
on learning as an experience,
more in abstract form.
That doesn't mean that I
wouldn't be invested in that,
but that's not what I've been
working on yet here.
So for instance, after
that it was--
so the research question was
how, how can players overcome
expectations that are wrong.
And so the idea was not to use
educational stuff like numbers
or whatever, but more, can we
develop patterns in games that
players who realize very
quickly, and are they ready to
give them up if they realize
that they think what they've
seen is wrong.
So, for me it was very
interesting because I come at
an abstract theory inside.
And so we were developing
prototypes.
And it's very interesting when
you come from the abstract
idea to prototypes.
But paper prototyping is perfect
because it really made
me as a scientist come
to the ground.
Because of course I can read
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] and all these
people and say, wow, experiences
this and that.
And then you suddenly have pen
and paper and sit there and
think about a game that, is it
a metaphor for your theory.
And so I think my takeaway was
that paper prototyping was
very healthy for me.
And with the team to come down
to the fact, what is really
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] in the game.
What can we really--
I think at the beginning I was
a bit inexperienced in
prototyping.
Wow, we can all do that later.
We can do the cool stuff when
we get to programming.
But then I realized,
no, we can't.
We cannot do it as a paper
prototype, how should we do it
in programming.
But what is changing?
And I think for us it was
very interesting.
So I think one experience we
had is, we had them develop
different prototypes.
And so I think that was healthy
for us not to make one
paper prototype but then think
how we can do it better.
But that's what [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
a lot of prototypes.
And to stay open.
And even if you spend three or
four days on a prototype, if
it doesn't work with others
the moment you show them.
And they go like, what,
these are the rules.
Are you sure?
I don't get it.
If you explain the tenth time,
maybe-- maybe it was a cool
idea back home or with your
friend, maybe, but it just
doesn't work.
And so this experience
in the prototypes was
very healthy for us.
And then coming to the point.
And I realized for me it was
important that somebody coming
in the room, playing a prototype
for five minutes,
kind of understands
the core mechanic.
If this is not happening--
who takes the five minutes to
understand a core mechanic?
Nobody, today.
PROFESSOR: That would be, like
in this game, just walking
onto a [INAUDIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: Right.
That's right.
And so, yeah.
I think, coming from a different
perspective, again,
prototyping is kind of like the
way to get in the game.
Even as the designer.
Because from then on, you know
what you're talking about.
And so I had to lose a
lot of my abstract
thoughts in the process.
And then the playtesting.
So it was interesting sometimes
to see, even if the
prototype is cool, then
you have a prototype.
And then people come in and
say, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
again.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
it's so easy.
But then you can start to stick
with your idea or say
no, maybe I have to go down with
the theoretical aspect
and really look [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
for the players.
GUEST SPEAKER: And another thing
about prototyping, it's
not focus groups.
So it's not a case of, --sure
you want to put it in front of
as many people as possible.
But you really want to, I think,
avoid stuff like what
did you like, what
didn't you like.
Those kind of questions.
Because people want
to be helpful.
And sometimes the piece they
didn't like was actually the
part where they were
working hardest.
So it's like I didn't
like that I had to
jump over the wall.
[INAUDIBLE] jump
over the wall.
And it may not really mean that
if you took that out,
that they would enjoy
the game more.
In fact, they might not
enjoy it at all.
So you have to be really
careful about that.
And people want to please you.
So they'll say oh, it's good,
and stuff like that.
I think it's really important
that what you do with
prototyping is watch
the player.
And then trust yourself
as a designer.
Rather than ask them what you
should do, because they will
try and be helpful and they'll
come up with wrong
suggestions.
Watch them and use your best
judgment as designer as to
what they're reacting to,
and why they're reacting
the way they are.
And try to fix it.
And then you try to get some
questions, try to maybe get
some access to their thinking.
But don't think that they
necessarily know what was
interesting to them, or what
would make them happy.
Don't ask those questions.
Those are focus group questions,
and you shouldn't
ask them because it's not
going to give you
the answers you want.
You've got to trust yourself
at some level
as to what's happening.
GUEST SPEAKER: And something
that I also had to learn was,
if you have the focus test or
the playtest, and then you
realize you have problems.
And it's really healthy to
write all the problems.
And then brainstorm different
solutions.
Don't ever, when you discuss
it, try to come up with a
solution immediately.
Because what happens is, you
quickly develop one solution.
And then you go and end up with
another problem, but you
don't realize that sometimes,
some problems stick together.
Or sometimes you realize,
well, we have so many
problems, just because of this
little aspect of the game.
Why don't we just let
it [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
If you don't do that, you start
to spend two hours in
solving a problem then
realize it was wrong.
Or you never realize it again.
So have [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
problems and quick solutions
where you [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
or not.
Make solution, solution,
solution and then with the
same problem a few weeks
later again.
GUEST SPEAKER: And I just want
to clarify, focus tests and
focus groups are two very
different things.
The kind of resource we're
talking about is focus
testing, which is specifically
identifying individual
problems in the game.
And a focus group is asking them
what they liked, which is
actually very not useful for
most product design in fact.
Games in particular.
GUEST SPEAKER: One piece of
advice that [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
really important if you're a
smart college student, like an
MIT student, is that you've
probably learned in spite of
your education, by having
someone sit in front of a
class and tell you what
was going on.
And you somehow absorbed it.
And that's why you've
got here.
But lots of people
don't learn that.
And it's really hard to avoid
the tendency in the game to
just tell people what
they should know.
Which is, sort of for my money,
like when you meet
someone who speaks a
foreign language.
You don't understand each
other so you both start
speaking slower and louder.
And I think that's what
a lot of education--
it's all a bad education
in general does.
Speaks slower and louder.
And [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
educational games.
So just remember that just
because you got it the first
time someone told you doesn't
mean that everybody else--
it's not just about explaining
it better.
It's about giving them a
different way of learning.
PROFESSOR: Any questions
for our guests?
GUEST SPEAKER: I just want
to say something.
Have you ever heard
of firehose games
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
forum.
So I told them, I know a
guy who works there.
And he said, we've got a focus
group tomorrow night.
They're PS3 set to release
in a few months.
Does anyone want to
go tomorrow night?
Seven o'clock, about an hour
to an hour and a half.
GUEST SPEAKER: That includes
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
are part of Firehose Games.
AUDIENCE: Are they looking for
people who haven't played the
game before?
GUEST SPEAKER: Maybe.
We're going to have
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Can I ask a question,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: So the question
I would have to use is,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
in his play biography,
educational games?
Have you played it, would you
say it was an important
experience to you?
That even, maybe it's
embarrassing now when the
other ones are listening.
But does anybody out there
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Zambonis or whatever
that game was?
GUEST SPEAKER: Best
game of all time.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It was similar
in that you had a
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] you were taking
around and had to solve
little puzzles.
And underlying them was math
and simple math equations.
But--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Pizza.
You divide a pizza, it's cool.
GUEST SPEAKER: We can't
let that slip.
That's Scott's game.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: I think it's
interesting to think about, if
you have any experience like
that, what would make
you like the game.
I think it's very rich, because
of all the people who
have that experience with
educational games, and then
think about them when
you design it.
Think about the influence.
GUEST SPEAKER: There's this
series of games called
Thinking Things.
And one of them had a mode that
basically was kind of
like programming, in that you
could place different types of
units on a grid, and then give
them instructions in a loop.
So, say, go forward then
left then right.
And they could paint a square.
And so what you'd end up doing
is, if it's a starting
configuration, a certain set of
rules, you could get them
to draw patterns and
stuff like that.
And what used to happen is, my
dad would say, can you get two
inverted triangles drawn
on the screen.
And I would sit there and try
to basically program it.
I realized that it
was actually a
programming game, so.
PROFESSOR: LOGO does a lot
of that sort of thing too
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
GUEST SPEAKER: There's a bunch
of games that have done that.
The last puzzle [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
some of that stuff too.
And there's a product out just
now called, that I'm hooked on
right now, called Train
Yard, which is on the
iPad and the iPhone.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: What?
PROFESSOR: I thought that
would be your game.
GUEST SPEAKER: And
it really is a
programming game, basically.
It's kind of cool.
AUDIENCE: Robuzzle.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: I was just going to
say that [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
educational context.
Where--
Dinosaur Discovery, which is an
ancient game, I played it
when I was in kindergarten
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And it was an adventure
text puzzle game.
Which was Band Leader.
And then Where in the World
is Carmen Sandiego.
GUEST SPEAKER: Another
classic game that I
played, back when--
about the time when things
started getting popular, is
Midnight East.
It was a math busters game.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: The Incredible
Machine.
AUDIENCE: That's like the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It's really [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I loved that game.
PROFESSOR:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
back in the good days.
I really enjoyed that game that
sounds like, I think we
all want to add to the
education game.
It's not like, oh my god, I had
to play an education game,
but more in, they could be
really in [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and it came with almanac.
They encouraged you to to
do research, in fact.
It wasn't cheating to
look up the answers.