PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
We've been talking in lecture
about various different
applications of definite
integrals.
And one of them has been that we
can use definite integrals
to find areas of regions that
previously we wouldn't have
been able to.
So, one simple example of that
is that we can use a definite
integral to find the
area of a region
bounded between two curves.
So I have an example of such
a question right here.
So the question is to compute
the area of the region that's
bounded between the curves
y equals x cubed and y
equals 3x minus 2.
So one thing you'll notice is I
haven't given you endpoints
for this region.
So I've just given you
the bound and curves.
So one thing you're going to
have to do right at the
beginning is to figure out what
this looks like and what
region you're going to
be integrating over.
What interval you're going
to be integrating over.
So, this is a kind
of tricky one.
Why don't you pause the video,
think about it for a few
minutes, try and work it out
yourself, and you can come
back and we can try and
work it out together.
All right, welcome back.
So hopefully you've had some
luck figuring out what this
situation looks like and then
computing the integral.
So let's talk about
it for a minute.
So we have these two curves.
And so somewhere--
I'm asking about the region
bounded by them-- so what I'm
telling you is somewhere these
curves intercept and they
surround some bounded region.
And so I'm asking for what the
area of that region is.
So in order to figure that
out, we should figure out
where these curves intercept.
So to find the, in other words,
we need to find the
endpoints of the interval
over which
we're going to integrate.
So in order to that, we have to
solve for where we have the
intersection between y
equals x cubed and y
equals 3x minus 2.
So we have to solve
the equation.
So we need to solve the
equation x cubed
equals 3x minus 2.
Or x cubed minus 3x
plus 2 equals 0.
So this a polynomial equation.
It's not quadratic, right?
It's a cubic equation.
So that means it's hard
to solve in general.
Luckily in this case, it's,
there are some, there's a root
we can recognize
fairly easily.
Which is, it's pretty,
you know,--
one thing you can always do is
check small positive integers
or use the rational root
theorem, if you remember that
from high school math.
So in this case, if you check
x equals 1, it's fairly easy
to see that x equals 1 is
a root of this equation.
So in other words, we can factor
the left-hand side.
We can divide out a factor
of x minus 1.
OK, and so now we have to do
long division or synthetic
division, whatever kind of
division you want to divide
through here.
So we get x squared minus--
so we've got a nope, I lied.
Plus x minus 2 after
you divide.
How's that look?
We can just double-check.
You know, we get an x cubed
minus x squared plus x squared
minus 2x minus x plus 2.
OK.
So that adds up to
the right thing.
So we either have that 1 is a
root or that x squared you
know, rather for the places
where these intersect, we have
either x equals 1 or x squared
plus x minus 2 equals 0.
And now here you can, you know,
again factor or use the
quadratic equation
or what have you.
And you can see so we have
that this actually fully
factors as x minus 1 squared
times x plus 2 equals 0.
Which means that we have
intersections when either x
minus 1 is 0 or when
x plus 2 is 0.
So intersections at x equals
1 and x equals minus 2.
All right.
So you can take that information
and you can, you
know, put it together and
you can make a nice
picture like this.
Or, I suppose, you could have
made the nice picture before
you had that information.
And so we see that we've
got this line, y
equals 3x minus 2 here.
And we have the curve
y equals x cubed.
And they have two intersection
points.
They intersect once.
Down at x equals minus
2, y equals minus 8.
And they intersect again
up at the point 1, 1.
And they're actually
tangent there.
So x cubed, the curve y equals
x cubed stays above the line
at this point.
So one way you can read that off
is here you had a double
root at minus 1, if you like.
But, OK, so then, the
region in question
is this region here.
So it's a region bounded between
those two curves that
we're trying to compute
the area of.
So now that we have the
endpoints this isn't such a
tricky problem at all.
Right?
so we've got the endpoints
and we know--
now that we've drawn this
picture-- we know which curve
is on top and which curve
is on bottom.
Right?
So the height, when we imagine
cutting this region into lots
of little rectangles or
approximate rectangles, the
height is going to be x cubed
minus 3x minus 2.
Minus the quantity 3x minus 2.
Right?
The x cubed is on top and 3x
minus 2 is on the bottom.
So the area is equal
to the integral.
OK, and now we know where we
have to integrate from and to.
So we're integrating from x
equals minus 2 to 1 to get
this whole region of
x cubed minus the
quantity 3x minus 2 dx.
OK?
Because the y equals x cubed
is the top curve.
And y equals 3x minus 2
is the bottom curve.
So this is the height of those
rectangles, which is positive.
OK, and so now, OK, well
now this is pretty
straightforward.
We're integrating a polynomial
at this point.
So this is the integral.
Well, OK, so integrating x
cubed, that gives me x to the
fourth over 4.
Integrating minus 3x gives me
minus 3x squared over 2.
And integrating plus 2 gives
me plus 2x between x equals
minus 2 and 1.
So OK, so now I just
do this difference.
So this is equal to 1/4 minus
3/2 plus 2 minus--
OK, now I put in minus 2 I get
2 to the fourth-- sorry--
minus 2 to the fourth is 16
over 4, so that's minus 4.
OK, minus 3 times
4 over 2 is 6.
And then plus 2 times minus
2 is minus 4 again.
OK, and now we've just
got some arithmetic.
So this all becomes a plus 6.
And I have to add everything
together.
So that's something like, well
I've got a denominator of 4,
so it's, yeah.
All right, so there's a secret
I should tell you.
Which is that mathematicians are
not actually very good at
arithmetic, usually.
So this is minus 6/4 plus
2 plus 6, so plus 8.
So this is 8 minus 5/4,
which is 6 and 3/4.
OK, that's 6 plus 3/4.
So 6 and 3/4.
This was just arithmetic.
Here was the calculus part.
And, in fact, you know, one
feature of a problem like this
is that you have a fair amount
of work sometimes to see the
picture of what you're
working with.
Then the integration here was
pretty straightforward.
Right?
This was a fairly easy
integral to compute.
If you're, say, better at
fraction arithmetic than I am,
at least.
So, there you go.
So, we had this region.
So we found, actually the
endpoints of the interval.
We found which was the
top curve and which
was the bottom curve.
And that led us right
down this integral.
And then that integral was
fairly easy to compute from
that point out.
And then we ended up with
this as our final area.
So I'll end there.