PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
We've been talking about
applications of integration,
including finding the areas
between curves.
So I have here a nice little
region that I like.
I think it's kind of cute.
So it's the region between
y equals sine x and y
equals cosine x.
And, you know, those two curves
cross each other over
and over again.
They wrap around each other.
So I'm just interested in the
region between the two
consecutive points
where they cross.
So here, you know, so at pi over
4 we have sine x equals--
sine pi over 4 equals
cosine pi over 4.
And at 5 pi over 4 they're also
equal again, down in the
third quadrant there.
So, the question is to compute
the area of this region that
they bound between
those two points.
So why don't you take a couple
of minutes, work through that,
come back and we can work
through it together.
All right, welcome back.
So, from this picture it's
pretty easy to see what the
region of integration is.
I mean what the bounds
on x will be.
As we said, x has to go the
left, I mean, you could--
sorry, let me start over.
You could do any two consecutive
intersection
points you want, right?
The area is the same in any case
because of the symmetry
of these two functions.
So, OK.
But the first two that are
easiest for me to find are
this pi over 4 and
this 5 pi over 4.
So I'm going to do those two.
If you wanted, you could have
done it with a different pair
of consecutive points.
But, once we've agreed that sort
of these first two are
the ones I'm going to
do, then it's easy.
I know that they're pi over
4 and 5 pi over 4.
So that's the interval over
which I'm going to be
integrating.
And then, what I want to do is
just view this region as cut
into a lot of little
rectangles.
And I want to integrate the
height of those rectangles in
order to get the area
of the whole region.
So in this case, the upper curve
is y equals sine x and
the lower curve is y
equals cosine of x.
So the height of a little--
you know if I drawn in a
little rectangle here--
the height of that rectangle
is going to be sine x
minus cosine x.
Its width is dx.
And then I add them all
up by integrating.
So the area is just the integral
from pi over 4 to 5
pi over 4 of sine x
minus cosine x dx.
Top minus bottom to
get the height.
If you did it backwards; if you
wrote cosine minus sine,
what you would get is exactly
the negative of the area.
So it's, all right, from pi
over 4 to 5, pi over 4.
So now, we just have
to integrate this.
So integral of sine, the
function whose derivative is
sine is minus cosine x.
And the function whose
derivative is cosine is sine.
So it's minus sine x between
pi over 4, 5 pi over 4.
And OK, so now, we just have
to plug in the values.
So this is equal to minus cosine
5 pi over 4 minus sine
5 pi over 4 minus minus
cosine pi over 4 minus
sine pi over 4.
And I'm sure you can work out
for yourself that this is
equal to 2 times the square root
of 2 if I haven't botched
anything terribly.
So I'll end there.