PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video segment
we're going to look
at the chain rule.
And specifically we're going to
answer a question that I've
placed on the board.
I want you to find two
values for theta.
So that the d d theta of the
function cosine squared theta
to the fourth equals 0.
At this point I should also
point out a few things.
One, theta is a variable
in this case.
And if you haven't seen it
before, frequently we use it
when we're dealing with
trigonometric functions.
Theta often represents the
variable that measures angle.
So if you haven't seen
theta before, this is
what it looks like.
That's how you say it.
And I'm actually doing the same
things we've done before.
I'm taking the derivative with
respect to the variable theta,
of a function of theta.
The other thing I want to point
out, which I think we
know already, but just to be
sure, is it that this squared
here, cosine squared theta to
the fourth, means I'm taking
cosine of theta to the fourth
and I'm actually squaring it.
So with that knowledge I would
like us to use the chain rule
to find two values for
theta where this
derivative is equal to 0.
So I'll give you a moment to
take a stab at finding the
derivative, setting it equal to
0 and finding some values
for theta that make
this equation, the
derivative equal 0.
And we'll come back and then
I'll work it out as well.
OK, so the first thing we
obviously need to do is be
able to take the derivative
of this function on
the left-hand side.
And I should say it's a little
more complicated than an
example you saw in the lecture,
because in the
lecture you were given
an example
with just two functions.
So I want to write it a little
differently just to show very
obviously what the three
functions are we're composing.
So this function I can rewrite
it as cosine theta to the
fourth-- does that look like
a 4, there we go--
and then I square that
whole thing.
That's really what
the function is.
OK?
So we can see what is the
outermost function here?
The outermost function is
actually the quantity of
something squared.
So the outermost function
is x squared.
What's the next function in,
in this composition?
The next function in is
the cosine function.
And then the last function
in is the function taking
something, raising
it to the fourth.
So it's very important you
understand sort of the
composition, which is the
outermost function, which is
the innermost function?
In order to do this
chain rule.
Now as you saw in the
recitation, you were given the
example, you had y as a function
of t-- sorry, not in
recitation--
in the lecture you were given,
you were given y as a function
of t or a function of x and then
you had to put one other
variable in the middle.
Here we're going to have a
composition of three functions.
So we need to have two other
things sort of in the middle.
So let's write this out.
First, the outermost function,
we'll call the whole thing y.
So y is equal to x squared is
the outermost function.
So then this whole
thing is x now.
So then we'll write x is
equal to cosine of w.
And then w is equal to
theta to the fourth.
OK.
Again this is what you saw
before in the lecture.
So you write the outermost
function.
And then that function
is a function of
cosine of another one.
Cosine of w and w
is a function of
theta to the fourth.
So if I put all these back
together, I have theta to the
fourth in here, and then I
square that, and I come back
to the function I wanted.
Now we know from the lecture
what we need to do to find,
essentially, dy d theta.
That's what we're looking for.
So dy d theta, you'll see, you
remember from the lecture,
should be dy dx times dx
dw times dw d theta.
So it's slightly more
complicated than we saw before
because there's one more term.
OK.
So now let's work out
what these are.
Well dy dx is fairly
straightforward.
dy dx is just 2x.
And then dx dw, well what's
the derivative
of the cosine function?
The derivative of cosine
is negative sine.
So this is times negative
sine of w times--
and what's dw d theta?
So w is the function theta
to the fourth.
So dw d theta is 4 theta
to the third.
Now when you look at this you
should remember, x we sort of
inserted into the problem to
make the problem easier, and w
we inserted into the problem to
make the problem easier for
us to follow.
So we don't want all
these x's and w's.
We want everything in terms
of, in terms of theta.
But what is w?
Well w is theta to the fourth.
So I can replace that by
theta to the fourth.
And what is x?
x is cosine w.
But w is theta to the fourth.
So x is actually cosine of
theta to the fourth.
OK?
So I get 2 cosine of
theta to the fourth
times negative sine--
w again is theta
to the fourth--
of theta to the fourth times
4 theta to the third.
Let's make this nicer.
I'll bring the coefficient and
the theta to the third in
front and this minus
sign in front.
I get negative 8 theta to the
third cosine of theta to
fourth sine of theta
to the fourth.
OK, and then the problem asks
to find where the derivative
is equal to 0.
Find two values.
Now why did I ask you
to find two values?
Because one is very easy.
If this thing is set equal to 0,
one value should stand out
right away for theta that
makes this product 0.
And that is theta equals 0.
So theta equals 0 is
our easiest answer.
So if you didn't do that,
then you wanted the more
challenging stuff, you
could have done the
other things also.
So what about cosine theta
to the fourth?
If we want a product of three
things to be 0, then at least
one of them has to be 0.
So I could have set cosine
theta to the
fourth equal to 0.
And for what values of--
an angle I should just say--
for what values of theta to
the fourth is this
going to be zero?
Well this means that theta to
the fourth is equal to either
maybe pi over 2, or you
could add another pi.
OK?
So we could say, well let's just
say that's one example.
Theta to the fourth equals pi
over 2 would work right?
Because it cosine of pi
over 2 is equal to 0.
OK?
And so then we could have said
theta is equal to pi
over 2 to the 1/4.
That's another example there.
We could have also done, we
could have added pi to this
and gotten another answer.
But I only asked for two.
So I guess that I'm allowed
to stop there.