DAVID JORDAN: Hello , welcome
back to recitation.
The problem I'd like to work on
with you now is a long one.
So it's going to be practice
computing line integrals.
So to begin with, we have this
function of two variables.
f is x to the fifth
plus 3xy cubed.
And we have this--
C is the upper semi-circle going
from (1, 0) to (-1, 0).
So it's this upper semi-circle
here that we often consider.
And so the first thing that we
want to do is to just compute
the gradient capital F
to be the gradient of
this function f.
And then parts b through d,
we're going to compute this
line integral of this vector
field f along this curve C.
We're going to compute it
in three different ways.
So first of all, we're going to
compute it directly, just
using the definition.
And then in Part c, we're going
to compute it using the
path independence of line
integrals and we're going to
replace the path C with
a simpler path.
And then finally in Part d,
we're going to use the
fundamental theorem
of line integrals.
Now when you do Part b,
what I want you to do
is set up the integral.
You're going to get a very
complicated integral that I
wouldn't want to
try to compute.
So just set up the integral
completely and then go ahead
and move on to Part c and d.
So why don't you pause the video
and work on that, and
we'll check back in
a few minutes and
we'll solve it together.
Welcome back.
I hope you had some luck working
these problems. So
let's do the easy one first,
computing the gradient.
So for the gradient we just
take the two partial
derivatives.
So we get 5x to the fourth
plus 3y cubed.
That's the partial derivative in
the x-direction, and in the
y-direction, we just
get 9xy squared.
So now for Part b, we're
asked to compute
this integral directly.
So we have to recall
what it means.
So first of all, if we go back
over here, we have this curve
C. And we need to give a
parameterization for it, and
so we're going to introduce
a parameterization r of a
variable t, and we're going
to use that to do our
computations.
So let's set r of t--
so this is our usual circle
that we're used to working
with, so we're just going
to take the usual
parameterization,
cos t and sin t.
And what's important is that the
range is going to be from
t equals 0 to t equals pi.
It's t equals pi because we
don't want to go all the way
around the circle.
We just want to go halfway
around until we get to
negative 1.
So if that is r of t, then
we can compute the
differential dr of t.
And so it's going to be just
taking the derivative.
So we have negative sin
t and cos t dt.
And so now we can just
write out this
line integral directly.
So the integral over C of
F dot dr just becomes--
so we have the integral
from t equals 0 to pi.
Those are the ranges
for our curve.
And now we're going to take the
dot product of F, which
was (5x to the fourth plus
3y cubed, 9xy squared).
We're just going to dot this
with our dr vector, which is
(-sin t, cos t).
All together we have dt.
And so now, notice that here
we've got the variables x and
y, and here we've got the
variables t, but because of
our parameterization, we
actually know that, for
instance, x is cos
t and y is sin t.
So we can write this all out.
So we have 5 cos to the fourth
t plus 3 sin cubed t.
So that's this guy written
out in terms of t.
And then we multiply it
by a negative sin t.
And then to that we add
the other components.
So we have plus a 9.
So we have cos t coming from the
x and another cos t here.
So we have cos squared t, and
we have a sin squared t dt.
OK, so that's what it means to
compute this line integral
directly, and it's not
something that I
look forward to doing.
So let's see if we can use path
independence to make our
lives a little bit simpler.
So that's going to be c.
So what we want to do is we want
to replace our original
curve C with any other curve
that has the same starting
point and the same
ending point.
And the curve that I would like
to use is just a straight
line connecting them.
There's lots of different
choices that you could do, but
to me this one seems
the most natural.
So let's give that a try.
So let's let r of t be
the curve (-t,0).
Negative t because we want it
to run moving to the left.
And then our range is just going
to be from minus 1 to 1.
So when t is minus 1, then we
get minus the negative 1 and
it starts at 1.
And when t is 1 it goes
to negative 1.
And notice that it goes along
the y equals 0 axis.
So now we can do the same
computation that we did before
but we can use this curve.
So the thing that I want to
emphasize is that if we're
computing a line integral
of a gradient function--
so of a function which
is conservative--
then we can use any line and
we can use any path that
connects the two end points.
We can replace our path.
And so that's what we did.
We replaced C1 with C2.
So now this becomes much
easier in two ways.
So we'll see.
So our range now is just t
goes from minus 1 to 1.
And so dr here is
just (-1, 0).
That's dr. And there's a dt.
And let's see.
So now F, we had this value
for F, but notice that the
y-coordinate is always
0 along this curve.
So the y-coordinate being 0
means that we just have 5t to
the fourth and then 0 here.
That's it, because we set y
to be 0 along this curve.
So all together this is a very
nice integral to do.
So just taking this dot product,
all we have is minus
5t to the fourth dt.
That's simplified greatly.
And we just have minus t to the
fifth from 1 to minus 1.
And so we get simply minus 2.
So that was a much, much more
straightforward integral to do
than the one we started with.
Now finally, in d, we're
suggested to use the
fundamental theorem
of line integrals.
So let's remember
what that says.
That says that if we have any
curve and the line integral
that we're taking--
if we know that we're taking the
line integral not of any
vector field, but of a vector
field which is already the
gradient of f, then that tells
us that this is simply f of
the endpoint minus f of the
starting point of our curve.
So really we don't need to
do any integral at all.
And so let's see.
So recall that f was x to the
fifth plus 3xy cubed.
And so the endpoint--
so we just need to take
f of (-1, 0) and
subtract f of (1, 0).
And so plugging this all in
together we get minus 1 minus
a positive 1.
All together we get minus 2.
And, of course, this does agree
with what we did when we
computed using the
line integrals.