The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
OCW.MIT.edu.
So some of my perspective on
what kinds of things you can
do in relation to game mechanics
is kind of like
seeing [INAUDIBLE].
But it's not the be
all and end all.
I'm basically showing you my
perspective but it's not the
only perspective out there.
I have very little that I feel
qualified to say about things
like sports.
Things where we are talking
about athletic competitions.
Faster, higher, stronger,
that sort of thing.
But I'm a little bit more
engaged in games where there's
role-playing.
Where you're taking on a persona
or at least some sort
of behavior that
you aren't just
normally doing in real-life.
It's not just about how fast you
can run or how skilled you
are at hitting the ball.
That sort of thing.
Let's see, and not every single
live-action game needs
to necessarily fit within
role-playing sports.
You've got things like
party games.
This afternoon we'll have the
lead designer for Dance
central coming in to do a
little Q & A about Dance
Central around 4 o'clock,
4:30, in the TV lounge.
You guys are all welcome
to do that.
And that's arguably a
live-action game.
Sure you've got a computer,
you've got a--
how much is the Kinect?
$150 piece of equipment
connected to a $250 Xbox
hooked to a screen that's
probably more than that.
You've got all this technology,
but in the end,
what's that game about?
What's Rock Band about?
It's about the people who
are in the living room.
And what is one of the arguments
that [INAUDIBLE], in
a different chapter in Casual
Revolution, he argues that one
of the big things that's
happened with gaming is this
re-introduction of the space
in front of the screen.
The living room space has
come back into play.
You haven't lost that with board
games or card games, but
for electronic games really it
used to be something that
existed with arcade games.
You've got these giant
motorcycles or steering wheels
and stuff like that.
And you still had it with some
really expensive computer
games like flight
simulators where
people buy the joysticks.
I'm a big train fan, so I've
got a Playstation One train
controller.
It's throttle and brakes.
That's all it is.
No steering when it
comes to trains.
It's a lot of fun.
With arcade games, and of course
[INAUDIBLE], there's
this whole idea that you're
going to be engaging your
entire body.
And you could argue that those
are live-action games.
And you take the technology
out and what you've got is
just this human body playing
with all it's constraints,
beholden to gravity, it can't
move faster than a certain
speed, it's kind of ungamely,
and it's got
roughly a certain size.
Gives you constraints that
you can work with in
terms of game mechanics.
One of the things that we did
last year was we had a
live-action game assignment
in this class.
And the constraint was you had
to be able to play the
game in this room.
Was a newspaper a constant?
GUEST SPEAKER: No.
PROFESSOR: That was one huge
decision to use newspaper as a
constraint.
But they did things like
blindfold people.
They were playing around with
the senses on the body so that
you could hear.
When one person had unlimited
ammunition, in terms of low
vaulted newspaper and the
bucket, but couldn't see where
everybody else was.
And everybody else could
move around the room
on sheets of newspaper.
They had to step on sheets
of newspaper.
So you could always hear where
they were stepping.
And the person with the bucket
was trying to pelt the people
who were stepping
on the ground.
If you got hit you had to go
out of the magic circle and
then start coming in.
The whole idea was to attack
the person who was actually
throwing all these
newspaper balls.
We had a little newspaper
hat that you could grab.
It was pretty awesome,
because what you need
to play that game?
You need one set of rules,
and a chair, a recycle
bin--specifically it
was that bin--
and newspaper.
But there were all these
things in play about
what you can do.
So OK, your target is going to
be roughly the size of a human
body, and roughly the weight
of a human body.
It's going to be able to move at
roughly the same speed of a
human body.
And you cannot have multiple
targets in the
same place at once.
In fact it's hilarious when you
try, because you've got
these [INAUDIBLE].
And because you're playing with
the humans, all five of
the human senses, usually
just like hearing.
I don't know that anyone's
made a smell game.
But you will have the situation
where the people who
are standing on the newspapers
will try to make noise near
the other people who are
playing the game.
So they were drawing attention
away from themselves.
Sometimes it works.
Sometimes it doesn't.
Sometimes it leads to hilarious
collisions --a good
time was had by all.
And those kinds of
party games.
You know, King of the Hill?
Can anyone think of any other
playground type games that are
personal favorites?
AUDIENCE: Freeze tag.
PROFESSOR: Freeze tag?
[?
AUDIENCE: Lava.
PROFESSOR: What's?
[?
AUDIENCE: Lava's where you have
swings and all things you
can climb on.
And you're playing generally
on the little pebble-like
rocky stuff.
And if you step on the pebble
stuff that's like the lava and
you get burnt.
So you have to stay hanging
on the metal part.
And usually there's someone
who's immune to the lava
trying to tag you.
So they can walk over
the lava but they
can't go in the structure.
AUDIENCE: Lava monster.
PROFESSOR: Does the
game ever stop?
Just out of curiosity?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, someone becomes
the next lava monster.
Once you get tagged you switch
roles and keep doing it.
AUDIENCE: But the thing is,
I never played that on my
playground.
I always played in my living
room and throw couch cushions
on the floor and stuff.
AUDIENCE: That sounds
really dangerous.
AUDIENCE: We'd have wheely
chairs and push off and yeah.
PROFESSOR: I used to
have a water bed.
So there was some
unpredictability that I could
have in my bedroom with
my two brothers.
But they were both bigger than
me so I always lost.
I mean, you can think of--
on one hand, these are athletic
games because they do
test your ability to move
and control your body.
Which is why they're so popular
around kids who are
trying to master what their
bodies are capable of.
But on the other hand, they're
also games of mimicry going
back to [INAUDIBLE]
definition.
Because you're pretending that
it's lava, and pretending that
you're a person that cares that
it's lava, or a monster
that's immune to it.
And these games don't
necessarily--
they may have some rules
about, OK you
can tag now we swap.
I've seen games where sure, I've
technically been tagged
out of this game but since this
game really has no end
state that just means
that oh, I lost.
Now I'm back in the
game again.
It's like playing a Doom death
match and you die and you're
just right back in
the game again.
Let's see, anyone play those--
what's the name of the football
variant where you
just have a scarf
attached to you?
AUDIENCE: Flag football.
PROFESSOR: For those of you--
everyone knows what it is?
AUDIENCE: Isn't flag football
where you just have a flag and
instead of being tackled you?
PROFESSOR: Yeah, instead
of tackling you
just grab the flag.
And that's an abstraction.
That's an abstraction of
something that you well could
physically do.
You could grab this person and
pull them to the ground.
AUDIENCE: Does touch
football exist?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR: That's a smaller
level of abstraction because
you can really hit someone
pretty damn
hard with touch football.
But it's an abstraction of,
here's this thing that I
personally, physically,
could do.
But I'm going to introduce
this level
of abstraction for--
I don't know-- safety.
That's usually the reason.
And so you've got the human body
and you've got all of its
values and virtues and
all of its curses.
You've got issues of safety.
You don't want people to hurt
each other, but yet human
beings and their bodies are
extremely capable of hurting
each other with no added
implement at all.
Even worse when it gets to a
game and someone's trying to
win something.
If you don't have a specific
rule that says you can't punch
this person, but you have a
game that's very athletic,
someone's going to try.
That's why you get these sort of
abstractions to pretend in
that military form that all
right, I've grabbed
this thing off you.
Now you have just been tagged.
I've effectively tackled
you [INAUDIBLE].
So, what I'm trying to draw
attention to with these
examples is that with
live-actions games the thing
that you have to keep in mind
all the time is at what point
is the person who's playing
actually the
character who's playing?
It's really, really, hard
to tell when it comes to
live-action games.
If you are playing in sports
it's the same thing.
Any given athlete and their
performance in the sport is
who they are.
It's the same person.
If I'm role-playing then the
person that I'm playing is not
supposed to be the same.
But there needs to be a whole
bunch of rules that basically
specify that the character
that I'm playing is not
actually the person that you're
seeing in front of you.
For that time, the player is not
the Count of Monte Cristo
or something like that.
AUDIENCE: One interesting
exception to that is wrestling.
Not wrestling like actual
high-school wrestling, but
wrestling on TV--
I don't remember what
it's called.
Because everybody puts
on a persona.
They're never the same
person that they are.
I just thought it was
interesting when you said that
any sports person, but
that's one exception.
PROFESSOR: That's true.
And that creates a lot of
discussion about whether
wrestling is a sport.
It's athletic.
Everyone agrees that
it's athletic.
But so are trapeze artists
athletic but you wouldn't call
it a sport.
And in fact, if I understand
correctly, wrestlers are
insured as circus performers,
because they have the same
risks and are playing the same
role as a performance.
But you're right, that's
one of those things
where it's a persona.
The really, really, good
wrestling networks play around
with what's real
and what's not.
Yeah sure, these two people
are putting on these
ridiculous personalities.
Threatening to kill each other
over the most trivial and
made-up of the offenses, and
crazy accents, and costumes,
and everything.
But when they're bleeding
they're actually bleeding.
There's no denying and no doubt
they actually get angry
with each other and people
actually get hurt.
And playing around with that
line is actually some of the
appeal that we get in things
like professional wrestling.
I guess that's what the
terminology that they use.
It's very different from
something like
mixed martial arts.
I don't watch mixed
martial arts.
AUDIENCE: No, I don't think
so, I'm pretty sure
it's just flat out.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] are very
associated with the person.
PROFESSOR: So they
are the persona.
AUDIENCE: They don't have stage
personalities, but they
do have strong personalities.
AUDIENCE: That's definitely
a sport.
I mean, they're actually
fighting.
PROFESSOR: I mean let's
take a look at
Muhammad Ali for instance.
Extremely athletic person but
his personality had a lot to
do with it as well with how
successful that he was.
The way that he taunted people
on TV and on cameras before
the game, so that people would
get all worked up for the
game, made him a star.
Sure he was athletic, but
that was part of it.
So where that line is, and as
designers you get some control
over that through the rules
that you're writing.
And there are a couple of
tactics that you can focus on.
But I want to segue into--
that's the tension.
That is one thing that's
pulling your
design in one direction.
Which is, how am I going to
figure out what the difference
between the person who's playing
this game and the
character that they're playing,
or the role that
they're playing,
is going to be.
In your games, for this next
assignment, if you've got
people playing mental patients
then you've got to figure out
how you're going to
draw that line.
You've got to be clear whether
it's the player who's actually
upset at you or the character
who's actually upset at you.
But if you draw that line too
broadly, then you've got the
situation where both be angry
at you [INAUDIBLE].
Because this is a ridiculous
situation and emotional.
Pretending to be really
emotional can usually make a
lot of people react by laughing
just to release the
tension in space.
In fact, that happened when
Dion was role-playing with
Caesar, right?
Sure, they were laughing.
They were trying to level that
and take it as seriously as
possible, and everybody else in
the room was cracking up.
To release that tension.
And sometimes that's
OK playing games.
In fact, sometimes that's
great for the game.
And sometimes that's
detrimental.
Depends on what you're
playing for.
But you have to understand
that is something that's
pulling the overall design, why
do rules exist, and why
your game mechanics exist, and
why your game mechanic is
pretending a certain way.
That's one of the tensions
that's pulling it
in a certain direction.
And in reality, that's actually
two different tensions.
Because in one sense, they're
trying to make an experience
as aversive, as feeling
like you're
actually doing it as possible.
And on the other hand, you
don't want to make it so
associated with who you are,
and what you're actually
doing, that people start
to think, oh wow.
This person, this player,
is actually mad at me.
Or, this player could actually
hit me at this point.
While as, no the character
[INAUDIBLE].
I call that verisimilitude.
These are just words that I
picked up from dictionaries.
This one, you were in
my masters thesis.
Verisimilitude is basically a
tension when you're designing
a game mechanic.
And that tension is telling
you, I want to make this
experience as immersive and as
true to life as possible.
And the opposite of that is
what I call dissociation.
Which is really hard
to pronounce.
It's not like I just
call it separation.
But, how do you draw that line
between who I am and who my
character is?
And I'll give you a couple
of examples just to
get inside this now.
Who doesn't know what
a live-action
role-playing game is?
Or doesn't have a
good clear idea?
OK.
So maybe, a little bit of
background just so that I can
use the examples.
Do you folks know how a
table-top role-playing game
generally works?
OK.
So, start from scratch.
Imagine improv theatre.
Imagine you have an environment
where you have a
bunch of people who
want to enact some
sort of scene together.
In theatre, a scene is usually
something like five minutes,
maybe half an hour.
In a live-action role-playing
game, that's more like an hour
to 10 days to 30 days long.
A much longer period of time.
But the motivation
is the same.
We're in this space to enact
some sort of shared reality,
shared creative reality,
together.
In a role-playing game
that's done by the
usual addition of rules.
And usually some sort of world
setting and some sort of
character description.
And how these things are told
to you could be as simple as
the game master walks up to
each person and explains
what's going on.
You are all cats in an alley-way
and some of you are
hungry and looking for food.
Some of you are on top of the
pecking order and make sure
you get all of the food.
Here's how you eat food.
Here's how you move
food around.
Go.
That sort of thing.
A game master could just do it
at that level, and you've got
a live-action role-playing
game.
There's usually some sort of end
condition or at least some
sort of time limit to tell
you when the game's over.
When you get a little bit more
detailed, and when you start
mixing and matching it with the
conventions of other kind
of role-playing games--
computer and table-top
role-playing games--
you have things like character
sheets where you're given your
information on a piece of paper,
or you create your
information on a
piece of paper.
And that information is
information that's only
available to you and
the game master.
A secret information for all
intents and purposes.
You will use different means
to convey chunks of the
information to the rest
of the world.
Like I'm actually not
female, but I'm
playing a female character.
So maybe I'll wear a badge
or something that has
my gender on it.
And that tells the rest of the
world treat me like a female.
That's one example.
I may actually be psychic, but
the rest of the world can't
necessarily see that.
Except for maybe other
psychic people.
So maybe I'll have a little
Greek symbol or something--
not Psi, that would
be too obvious--
or maybe my badge is just a
different color or something.
And people who are not psychic
have no idea what that means.
And people who are playing other
psychic characters now
see, [INAUDIBLE] has
a red badge.
I am sensing psychically.
And then there are other game
mechanics that I can do with
that person.
Actually all the psychic people
know each other's cell
phone numbers or something and
can talk to each other.
That's an example.
AUDIENCE: That's awesome.
PROFESSOR: That would be
to your advantage.
So the connection with improv
theatre is actually stronger
than a lot of people may
generally assume.
Because a lot of people think
of live-action role-playing
games and they focus on
the games part of it.
And they think of it as a RPG
in the computer sense.
So your role is your character
in the sense of, I have my
character's stats, my
character's abilities, a lot
of these steps and abilities
don't necessarily need to be
written down.
Because, again, you're dealing
with a human body.
So, how strong is
my character?
I don't know.
How strong are you?
How long a sword do I have?
Well, how long is that piece
of foam over there?
That's your sword now.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
I played a character that
was supposed to
be very, very, strong.
And I am not very,
very, strong.
But I had a disclaimer badge
and the that it manifested
itself in game play was that at
some point they challenged
someone to an arm-wrestling
duel.
And they made sure--
they looked at my stat
and saw, oh I
know what this means.
And so even though they were
about twice my size they
pretended to lose.
It was very entertaining.
PROFESSOR: So the spectrum
of on one hand
there are these games.
The type of games that Jeremy
describes allows you to play
things that are physically
very different from you.
And then there are
some live-action
role-playing games--
AUDIENCE: Where it's just
how strong you are.
PROFESSOR: --Yeah, it's just
A lot of those are
like [INAUDIBLE]
LARPs, where people will dress
up in actual armor that
they've decided to make out
of leather or duct tape.
And they will swing around
swords instead of foam padded.
They'll go out to a
forest somewhere--
typically in New England--
and spend two days, three
days, in the middle of a
forest sleeping in a cabin
somewhere and pretending to
fantasy adventure it.
And every once in awhile there
will be GM controlled
volunteers who will be wearing
[INAUDIBLE] masks.
That's on the other spectrum.
It's a spectrum.
It's not like the [INAUDIBLE]
LARPs where you run around with
sticks and are Assassins
Guild type LARPs where most of
your abilities are governed by
numbers and stats.
Kind of this spectrum.
You can think of assassin guild
type thing as being very
much inspired by what you could
do on a computer or what
you could do on a
table-top LARP.
Because on a table-top LARP, how
strong your character is
has nothing to do with how
strong the player is.
It's what [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Playing a game just
recently, I found out that in
New England there are basically
LARPs which get done
with rifles.
AUDIENCE: They're
military level.
AUDIENCE: But they're
not paintball.
So you shoot people.
AUDIENCE: With plastic
pellets?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Yeah, air-soft is what
they call them.
And so one team will dress up as
US soldiers, and the other
ones are like middle-eastern
soldiers.
It's elaborate and slightly
distasteful.
You can go and look
at their website.
I think it's the New England
Airsoft Association or
something like that.
And they have excerpts of
a video cam of these.
And there's negotiation
between the two sides
and what have you.
They actually take on the roles
of the insurgents or the
[INAUDIBLE].
Sometimes they're just
shooting each other.
Other times they're trying to
find out who in the town who
is the bad guy.
PROFESSOR: Sometimes it
gets more elaborate.
And some of us are actually
going to be [INAUDIBLE] and
some of us are actually going to
be combatants and you have
to figure out who's who.
That one will be really,
really, interesting
[INAUDIBLE] for IEDs.
That's something that annoys
me about games that involve
Middle Eastern combatants.
Is that, they don't have
rules for IEDs.
And that's the primary form of
contact in those states.
That's to the point.
Military exercises a lot of them
are basically live-action
role-playing games.
All the way from I'm actually
running around with a gun full
of blanks or shooting pellets or
shooting a laser beam that
is going to register on some
other soldier's gear.
AUDIENCE: We call
them war games.
PROFESSOR: We call them--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: --Yes, that's
a good thing.
Then you also have the other
end of military simulations
where it's just a bunch
of people in a room
looking at a screen.
Or not even a screen, a white
board with a world map on it,
and they're moving forces around
like a table player.
But those are still considered
live-action action things,
because every person in the room
is representing someone
in the chain of command that
would normally be in a war
room attack.
I am the commander.
You are the lieutenant, or
something like that, and I'm
going to say, get me the status
of Washington D.C. Has
it been nuked yet?
And the lieutenant says we have
three missiles coming in
based on some look up.
The term for that is typically
called creep [INAUDIBLE],
especially when it's
real people playing
against real people.
It's two or more player game
where not everyone is
one the same side.
If it's just on one side then
just the war game terminology
tends to be more a catch all.
But when you have two players on
each side, and are playing
through these things,
how results get
resolved also can vary.
There are obviously digital and
mathematical ways to compute.
OK, I've given an order to fire
a missile at Singapore.
And it's going to take two
hours for it to land.
And there's a percentage
that it might land.
You could do it.
You could do that way.
But traditionally, what's
actually been done is that you
say this is what I'm
going to do.
And someone far more experienced
than you, usually
your instructor or one of
several instructors, takes
that information, goes into
another room, and talks to the
people who are actually doing
the same thing with your
opposing team.
And they're just saying,
OK in this event
what's going to happen?
And then they go back to
each team and they
report, missile missed.
Or, your troops engaged.
You found your opponent's troops
at this location and
you've lost 50% of
your troops.
That sort of thing.
And that's the traditional
[INAUDIBLE].
The nice thing about that is
that takes advantage of the
fact that not just the players
but everybody is a live-action
human being.
Because you have flexibility.
You can do ridiculous things
that programmers or game
designers may not necessarily
have assumed were possible,
but happen to make sense
in the heat of
that particular game.
And you have real people
deciding, this is
what's going to happen.
So we'll make up a
logical solution.
In the military, that's why you
want people who are really
experienced.
In a non-military live-action
role-playing game, like the
kind that's played around MIT,
people will still do that.
So I'm in a game where I have
a steampunk setting.
And I don't have all the
equipment I need to build this
machine of death that I'm
supposed to be completing.
But I could take apart some
of the other machines
that are in the world.
And then the game master
says, wait a minute.
We've got to put rules
about that.
Or, we don't want to start
anyone taking apart
[INAUDIBLE].
But it makes perfect sense
in this world.
So, OK, it's going to take you
two hours and you have to be
in this room.
But after that, you'll have
the parts you need.
The other side of live-action
role-playing is that often the
people who are controlling the
game of live-action say that
wasn't fair.
And again, they can improvise
along with the players.
So you have that bit
of flexibility.
You're limited by how
experienced most people are.
People who don't tend to be
terribly experienced tend to
make rash decisions that
end up hurting the
playability of the game.
Sometimes they get lucky.
Sometimes they don't.
Let me see, one example early
on when I was making
live-action role-playing
games, was I had a game
mechanic where if one of the
police officers in this sort
of detective scenario wanted to
do a background check they
could ask the game master.
Some amount of time--
actually it was fairly
instant.
Because the very molded
kind of system.
The assumption was that they
will find a computer and
they'll look it up.
And we'll give them
information.
And that led to two problems
was that, first of all what
happens if I'm not physically
in the same location as the
person who wants the
information?
And this is weird to think
of a computer with
legs walking around.
It sounds very science
fiction.
And on the other hand, it means
that I needed to have
all the information about
everybody at my
finger tips at all times.
Which often wasn't true.
So someone would come in, I
need the information about
this character.
I'm performing a look up.
And it's like, I'll get back
to you in two hours.
Because I don't have the
information here with me I'm
going to look it up and I'll
give it to you later.
Now I don't make that mistake
anymore, but that was the kind
of mistake I made when
I was a [INAUDIBLE].
Because I hadn't really thought
about what that would
require from me as
a game master.
Now that's a different
tension.
I am actually going to read
a chunk of this--
[INAUDIBLE].
I talked about dissociation
or separation.
And what I'm talking about with
that mistake that I made
is just plain old feasibility.
Something that you probably have
already run into it with
the games that you've
designed.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: And many of the games
that you've designed
[INAUDIBLE] could have thought
of as just plane of scope.
It's like, how big
is this game?
How long is it going
to take us to put
all these bits together?
[INAUDIBLE].
Can we order these
bits in time?
And are they going to
be delivered in
time for the class?
I know multiple teams
had this problem.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Let me see if
I can combine some
of these ideas together.
One thing that the Assassin
Guild likes to have are people
who have locked memories.
They know something, but they
don't know that they know it.
Little memory packets, little
pieces of paper that they
printed out and folded
up and stapled.
Takes you about 20 seconds
to make one of those.
Now imagine a game that
has maybe 60 people.
And each person maybe has five
locked memories because the
GM's really love the idea.
And 5 times 3 is
AUDIENCE: That's only
about an hour.
Only about an hour.
PROFESSOR: Only about an hour.
Does it ever only actually
take an hour to actually
produce that?
You get staple cuts and you
have to write them all.
AUDIENCE: It's a little less
than two hours actually.
AUDIENCE: No way.
AUDIENCE: 20 seconds
per 60 people.
AUDIENCE: But it's not
20 seconds each.
PROFESSOR: And then what happens
is that oh, wow, we
have 300 pieces of paper all
of which are now folded and
almost indistinguishable
from each other.
And we've got to figure
out who gets which.
And these are the concerns.
That's a feasibility issue.
Doing something like that for
one or two players is
extremely feasible.
It takes almost no time
for the game master.
Doing that for your entire
player base, if you have a 60
person game, on the large scale
becomes the majority of
your prep time.
Suddenly you're setting
aside a whole day just
to deal with that.
And a game's only three days
long or something like that.
With that level of effort.
Things to preserve the
game master's sanity.
The MIT janitorial staff,
facility staff, are pretty
ruthless when it comes to
picking up stuff that has
fallen on the floor.
So say that's a really important
piece of paper that
you've taped up on the wall
somewhere's here at MIT.
And there's information that
this is the place that your
players are looking for.
They've combed all of
campus and they need
to find this location.
And that tape that you
used just wasn't that
strong and it fell.
And the janitorial staff
just picks it up
and throws it away.
Now what happens to your game?
Can your game even end?
Are you just going to have a
whole bunch of really tired
players chasing you down
as the game master?
So the way that you resolve
this can be built into the
game mechanics.
You can build things like
multiple redundancy.
Like in addition to a sign there
will usually be this
other thing in this same area.
If you find one and you don't
find the other, it means
something has dropped off.
Involve the game master and the
game master will go and
fix it at some point in
time in the future.
If you have a game that has no
secret locations, and you have
a game that's campus wide, you
could just give people a map
of all the information.
Sure, you still want stuff on
the wall because it's neat to
be able to walk into a classroom
like this and say,
oh mortuary.
That's where I am.
And then suddenly reminded, oh
maybe I should be role-playing
back then and that
sort of thing.
But it's sort of like walking
through a space and you have a
map that told you you're
in a mortuary.
But you weren't looking at your
space, so you just walked
through the space in entry
to the classroom.
Yes, I am going to do my
tutoring in this room.
It's a morgue, why are
you doing tutoring?
So it's neat to be able to
have those things to give
players information about what's
going on in the space.
And to help them make believe,
help them imagine what they
could possibly do
in the space.
Maybe even give them clues about
what they need to be
doing in order to advance
their goals.
But then you also want to be
able to have backup plans for
when those things fail.
That's part of feasibility.
You don't want the game to break
halfway just because
janitorial staff came through or
the wind blew or something
and now your game sucks.
That's another type
of information.
And that's not entirely unlike
the information that we've
discussed in this class back
earlier this semester.
But with live-action games,
especially live-action games
that don't have any kind of
turn based thing, they're
happening in real time and
they're moving in real-time.
Information overload on the
player becomes something that
you have to be very careful of
when you're designing your
game mechanic.
How much is someone expected
to know at any given time?
This is going to be very
applicable for any of the
games that you design for
the third assignment.
If you decide to do a
live-action game, think about
here's somebody who's moving
around in a space.
Maybe it's a hospital or it may
be the doctor's office.
And this person is trying
to remember X numbers of
statistics about their
character.
How agitated I am, the number
that determines how many drugs
are part of me right now,
and that sort of thing.
You've got these stats.
And once again, too high, then
what happens is you've got a
character that's standing there
trying to do all the
math in their head and
not role-playing.
If they're role-playing
anything, they're role-playing
a mathematician or a [INAUDIBLE]
in their minds.
And you're losing the immersion,
you're losing the
[INAUDIBLE] to be I'm supposed
to be an angry person.
But I'm standing here
trying to do math
about how angry I am.
And you've got attention
of information and very
[INAUDIBLE].
There are times when you
actually want that though.
There are ways to take
that and turn
it into your advantage.
In particular, when the
thing that you want
people to be doing--
the kind of activity that you
want people to engage in--
are the things that players
would generally be
uncomfortable doing
with each other.
Physical violence would be
a good example of that.
I want to be able to hurt this
other character, but I don't
want to hurt this
other player.
So what are the things that I
can do to bridge that gap?
AUDIENCE: Insult his mother.
PROFESSOR: Verbally, sure, there
are ways to do that.
But you might need rules or at
least some guidance from the
GM to say, take that
seriously.
Because that can very easily
drift into the realm of, yeah
that's just a joke.
AUDIENCE: Rock, paper,
scissors?
PROFESSOR: Rock, paper,
That could be a mechanic for
a fist fight, for instance.
Or [INAUDIBLE]
that you start see them
avoiding that.
AUDIENCE: Nerf guns.
PROFESSOR: Nerf guns?
Things that shoot little
pieces of plastic.
But odds and evens.
AUDIENCE: How about tokens
like in [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Say what?
AUDIENCE: Health tokens
like in [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Give me
some more detail.
AUDIENCE: Like if someone was a
certain number of flags, and
so you hurt them
by taking one.
PROFESSOR: So the player
might have
multiple flags for instance.
OK, gets them angry.
It's like health bar
almost, actually.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So dice rolling is
under the general term like
things randomizing numbers.
In fact, rock, paper, scissors,
is randomizing
things almost.
And then you have toy
weapons, right?
Probably not so relevant
for the game violence.
But you could imagine setting up
a room full of foam things
which you will be quite happy
to throw at each other.
You know that this cylinder of
foam, of pipe-insulating
material, is not going to hurt
anyone when you throw it.
Which makes it more likely that
I'm going to pick it up
and throw it at someone.
Clearly it's something that's
designed for me to throw that
the GMs put there.
And if you want your players to
be engaging in that kind of
activity that's technically--
you could have put a
real bottle there.
You could have put a real mug
or computer or something.
That's the reason why you as
the GM could have, but they
are deliberately designing to
put something fake there to
clue the player into maybe
there's something I can do
with that I wouldn't necessarily
want to do if it
was the real thing.
I wouldn't want to throw a real
bottle at somebody, but I
would easily throw a foam
bottle at somebody.
Same thing for Nerf guns, dart
guns, this guns, it's like you
put something with a trigger
in somebody's hands that's
going to launch a little cheap
piece of plastic at someone?
They're itching for a chance
to use it, really.
Let's see, what else?
Dice are difficult.
The problem with dice is you
need a flat surface to roll
them on, and you might
not have that.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Still a little bit
risky, because they could end
up going all over the floor.
AUDIENCE: Another thing that
I've seen people do is some
kind of [INAUDIBLE]
style thing.
Where essentially they have
[INAUDIBLE] or something, you
might have created them.
You can beat a challenge by
giving one to the other player
that you're fighting with.
And then [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So it's like the
amount of energy you've got.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, it's like the
And also, if you discard them or
give them to another player
then it's the difference between
these things are just
gone and they circulate
around.
PROFESSOR: [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so if there's
the circulation thing than you
can get whooped a few times.
But after being whooped then
suddenly you get a chance to
whoop back.
And then it becomes
less [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: That was
interesting.
This is the good part that I
want to talk about which is
[INAUDIBLE].
A topic that you guys are
already very familiar with.
But, at what point do your
game mechanics--
are you designing your game
mechanics not necessarily to
enhance the realism or to
encourage certain behaviors or
to give the player enough
information about what they're
allowed to do or what they
should be doing?
And you're just going into the
realm of how do I make this
competitively interesting?
Real fights, if you get
a bunch of blows,
you do not get stronger.
Well, if you're Bruce
[? Bannon ?] maybe.
But from a competitive point of
view, or from a traditional
game play point of view, that
sounds like a great idea.
That gets you back into the
game, whereas any very
realistic fight mechanic is
really probably going to be a
positive feedback mechanic.
You win, you keep winning.
You can think of these five
different things as--its not
like game balance, but these are
decisions that you have to
make either as an individual
designer or as a team about
what any given mechanic in
your game is trying to
accomplish.
It's rarely mutually
exclusive.
It's usually trying to involve
multiple one of these things.
You don't want to fall down on
any of these, especially not
feasibility.
It's like, yes this is the
perfect game mechanic!
And we had two years to be able
to put together all the
things that we had.
And for the games that
have failed to run
because of that idea.
Especially live-action games
that have a hidden computer
component, especially if
they're designed by MIT
students, rapidly designed into
a software engineering
project that never finishes.
The game kind of disappears and
it's all about this damn
website that would have solved
everything else.
It's completely realistic
because of the hacking
mechanic that actually happens
on the computer.
And the skills scale to your
ability as a character which
the computer already knows,
and you don't have to
remember, so you can
feel really neat.
And it's competitive because
you know what the opponents
are doing, but not everything
they're doing, and it's going
to take us five years
to write this code.
The game's never going
to happen.
Let's see, let me think about an
example just to sort of put
some ideas in your head.
Back to the idea of things
that players might be
uncomfortable doing
with each other.
Seduction is one of those
things that's--
if you don't have a game
mechanic for it, it never
happens in the way that
you want it to
that helps the game.
If it happens, it's happening
between the players and that
causes all kinds of problems.
So you come up with a rule, come
up with a game mechanic,
that feels nothing like
real-life seduction.
We're going to play a game of
blackjack now, if I win you're
now in love with me.
And it's like, that's not how
seduction actually works, but
it actually makes it easier
for players to
say, I can do that.
I can play a game
of blackjack.
There's no social
awkwardness in
playing a game of blackjack.
AUDIENCE: You can associate that
with, I win this game so
I slipped inside your glass a
love potion so now you're in
love with me.
Something like that.
PROFESSOR: But see, in that
particular case you're
describing an action that people
might be more actually
willing to do through some
sort of simple mechanic.
Like OK, instead of love potion
we're going to mechanic
that enables you to something.
I'm going to actually
give you a file.
And if you drink something in
the tea, like maple syrup,
talk to the GM.
Because you probably just
drank some magic potion.
But if the goal is, all
right we're playing
a film noire game.
And you're supposed to be
engaging in constant witty
banter, laden with sexual
innuendo, a lot of people have
a lot of difficulty with that.
Sometimes it works.
I made it work in some games.
But it makes it a lot easier if
the success or failure in
that is not going to be
bottlenecked by whether the
players feel comfortable
doing it.
So creating a game mechanic that
actually feels a little
bit less than what activity
you're trying to represent may
make it easier for people to
engage in the activity.
Same thing goes in combat,
playing rock, paper, scissors,
feels nothing like
an actual fight.
But people will be much more
willing to play rock, paper,
scissors with each other than
to punch each other.
So come up a rule, give them a
little plastic gun, give them
something to make it easier,
and they'll be willing to
engage in that activity
more often.
Violence in the rule will
probably be the thing that
comes up a lot in
this setting.
So, let me see what else
we can get into.
It's about 2 o'clock.
How many folks here have played
some variant of Mafia
or Werewolf or?
Who's played Mafia
in particular?
OK, who's played Werewolf?
So those are live-action
games too.
And those are live-action games
that specifically don't
try to draw too sharp a division
between who you are
and who your player is.
You are given a role, a card,
that basically says whether
you're Mafia or whether you're
a villager I think.
AUDIENCE: Civilian.
PROFESSOR: And the whole idea
is that everybody who's--
that's a character sheet that
gives you private, secret,
information about the role that
you're supposed to play.
But in my opinion, these
particular games-- and we're
going to play some variants
of them--
what you are told by the
cards is only what
you're allowed to do.
What actually gives you the role
is what you decide to do.
I play Mafia and I'm going to
say, Patrick needs to die.
And other people in the room
agree with me, and Patrick's
character gets taken
out of the game.
That decision is the decision
that made me Mafia.
And that decision is the
decision that other people are
trying to catch, because they
are trying to find a person
who's actually responsible for
various acts when everybody's
eyes are closed.
The general model for these
games is there are cycles.
For Werewolf it's a day and
night cycle, and for Mafia
it's also day and night.
But the idea is that during the
night everybody who's not
Mafia gets to have
their eyes open.
Everybody who is Mafia--
everybody who's not Mafia
keeps their eyes closed.
Everyone who is Mafia keeps
their eyes open.
And people who are Mafia can
communicate through some GM
mediator, some game master
mediated way, to specify the
player to be taken out of
the game at this point.
It's usually a point.
I see things with blinks.
Because as the GM moves around
sometimes that gives you
clues, because you can hear.
Even with your eyes closed you
can hear where the GM is.
And then that's like
the night cycle.
And during the day cycle
everyone opens their eyes and
whoever's been taken out of
the game informs you.
And everyone knows and everybody
starts discussing
and accusing each other of
being responsible for it.
And the whole point of the game
is for the villagers to
identify who all the Mafia is
before everyone finishes.
It's a live-action game that
doesn't have a lot of action.
I would say, it's one action.
There's closing your
eyes, opening your
eyes, and there's pointing.
There are variants where
sometimes there is a Godfather.
AUDIENCE: I've seen websites
with whole lists of different
roles that are just
ridiculous.
Like there's grave keeper,
there's necromancers.
PROFESSOR: There's people
who can bring characters
back from the dead.
There are people who
can basically do
a background check.
I think that's--
AUDIENCE: Oh, that's
right you told us.
PROFESSOR: -- angels and cops.
And you go from two cycles to
three cycles per round.
Four cycles per round where
different people
have their eyes open.
And you get different bits of
information about what the
world state is like.
The fact that killing somebody
is pointing at them, that's a
dissociation mechanic right?
It's not like you're actually
being asked to engage in
physical combat.
Even though the fiction of
the game is that you're
assassinating this person in
the middle of the night.
The verisimilitude, and
competition, will largely come
down to the discussion phase.
They are trying to put players
in an environment where you've
got a paranoid of villagers, a
paranoid town, and they're all
mutually accusing each other.
And both the act of trying to
not be accused, and trying to
deduce who is the right person
to accuse, is a compelling
competitive experience.
That's what all these games
are really about.
So all the emphasis, all the
time of the game frankly, is
devoted to that phase when
everyone sits down and
discusses with each other
who could be the Mafia.
You want to walk us through
one of the variants maybe?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, do you
want to actually play it?
Or just describe it?
PROFESSOR: We have 1, 2,
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
10, 11, 12, 13, 14.
We could have two groups
or one big group.
GUEST SPEAKER: One big group
may take awhile.
PROFESSOR: Let's do two
groups but how many
different rule variants?
GUEST SPEAKER: I only found one
that I thought was really
interesting, although we can
certainly-- even the Wikipedia
page has a million variants.
AUDIENCE: The one I normally
would play would be one where
there's mafia and
there's cops.
There might be a medic.
AUDIENCE: Inspector, angel,
and prostitute.
AUDIENCE: What's the prostitute
do again?
AUDIENCE: If you sleep
with the mafia
they don't kill anybody.
If you sleep with an inspector
they get incorrect
information.
If you sleep with a nurse
they don't heal.
PROFESSOR: This is it's very
important to make sure you
know what rules that
you're playing with
before the game starts.
So walk us through the roles,
and then what we'll do is
we'll break this into
two groups.
And we'll have two groups play
separately and that's probably
the end of the class activity.
GUEST SPEAKER: I had found a
variant called Thing, which is
based on the John
Carpenter movie.
Which is interesting because it
takes out one of the roles.
The idea is one person is the
shape shifting thing, and at
night they infect someone else
and that person becomes a
thing as well.
So they're not knocked
out, out right.
And then during the day the
group votes and decides on one
person to test.
And if they test a thing that
person is killed and they get
to test another one.
And the idea is that the things
are trying to outnumber
the people.
Which is interesting because
it takes away
that inspector role.
AUDIENCE: Do you know who
gets thinged in the
middle of the night?
GUEST SPEAKER: So, I was
thinking about this.
What you would need is for the
person who is the thing to
indicate to the moderator.
And then maybe the moderator
could tap them or something.
AUDIENCE: Ok, so if you're a
thing you know you're a thing.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
The things are spreading
as opposed to just--
AUDIENCE: And then if there's
two things, do they both just
agree on another?
On a third?
GUEST SPEAKER: Presumably.
So this is really interesting
because apparently this is
played at a conference for
science fiction writers.
So there's little snippets of it
on the web about the rules
from different blogs
and stuff.
And it's not as interesting, but
of course the problem is
how do you Google
for mafia thing?
It's not interesting to me, and
then it seems like there's
[INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So it might be fine
actually to have two groups
figure out how to play that game
just from the description
that you've just been given.
I think [INAUDIBLE]
there's going to be enough
people who've played
traditional Mafia to
know how it works.
And then we'll just reconvene at
the end of it and see what
each version people
came up with.
What were the similarities and
what were the differences.
Again, that's the flexibility
of doing a live-action game
when the people who are actually
coming up the the
rules are actually in the same
room as the players, or are
the players themselves.
You get to make stuff
up on the fly as
long as everyone agrees.
So let's give it a shot.
While Jason is sorting out, any
questions about the stuff?
AUDIENCE: The two biggest
challenges that I've come
across in the block mechanics
have to do with surgical
challenges and intellectual
skill.
So let's go intellectual.
It's easy to play a character
that's stupider than you.
It's really hard to play
a character that's
smarter than you.
In particular, it's really
hard to play a character
that's smarter than you if you
don't have a GM around all the
time to tell you, stop.
So, if you have any ideas about
how to deal with that.
The other one is, I'm creating
social conflicts.
Like, this is harder than any
role-playing game because it
feels like if you want to be
able to persuade a character
or something you just want to
persuade them because you're
role-playing right?
But you're supposed to be
playing a character who is
more persuasive than you.
But it feels really cheap.
If you can just sort of.
PROFESSOR: You believe me now!
AUDIENCE: It also ties into
another area that frequently
pops up in LARP's and
role-playing games in general
which is use of metagame
knowledge.
So frequently if you've been
persuaded to do something then
you've come across players using
their metagame knowledge
that they don't want to do the
thing that they're being
mechanically forced to do.
And they're trying to find
loopholes constantly.
I don't know if you can really
force people to abandon their
metagame knowledge
mechanically?
But I don't know.
PROFESSOR: I have some examples
on how the Assassin's
Guild in particular has
dealt with that.
And in some ways it's cheating,
because we're not
going to try to do some
of those things.
In particular, let's
take persuasion for
one of those things.
The problem with persuasion is
that whatever mechanic you
come to, other than what you
see is what you get--
[INAUDIBLE]--
any other mechanic that you come
up with runs that risk of
the, wait a minute this
is not what I really,
really, want to do.
So the Assassin's Guild
has replaced that with
brainwashing.
Which is the whole idea of,
you're not being persuaded.
You goals are being forcibly
changed, but now you have
other goals.
And that's the big difference.
Your old goals are no longer
your win conditions.
Your new goals are now
You can still win the game by
obeying your new goals.
AUDIENCE: That's cool.
PROFESSOR: The brainwashing
mechanism.
AUDIENCE: So you've aligned the
interests of the player
with the interest of
the character.
PROFESSOR:You want to go with
your new goals now because--
how this came up, typically in
the Assassin's Guild, the
Assassin's Guild actually
grew out from
circle of death games.
Which is, getting to know you.
I have the name of somebody, and
I need to shoot them with
this water gun.
Who is this person again?
I don't know.
I'm a freshman.
I haven't met everyone
on campus.
I'm going to figure out
who this person is.
That's where those
games came from.
The Assassin's Guild kind
of grew up from that.
Then it became teams.
And brainwashing was basically
the set of game mechanics that
was used for recruiting
people to your team.
So it's like, all right
everyone's got one target.
But there are a few people out
there who's job is destroying
everybody on this opposing
faction.
And there's only one person
in that opposing
faction right now.
There's only one of me.
But I have this brainwashing
mechanic that recruits more
and more people.
So what you thought was one,
I'm just against another
individual, becomes my group
is against that group.
And it feels pretty
awesome, actually.
Because what it actually
feels--
it's a weird game mechanic way
of making your character have
some sort of development
in the game.
If you think about a
role-playing game, character
development means your goals
now change somehow.
But it's really difficult to
give players a means of doing
that themselves.
Brainwashing was one of the
few ways that seems to
actually have worked.
I'm actively going to knock out
this character, put this
blinky helmet on them for five
seconds, and if nobody catches
me in this process I give
them new goals.
And the person who's
[INAUDIBLE], dude this is way
more exciting than anything
[INAUDIBLE].
And you also avoid the metagame
problem of loyalty.
It's like, I got this
information from this other
group but I've been brainwashed
and I don't want
to tell you.
It's like, no you want to tell
me now because it'll actually
help you win.
But metagaming in all
kinds of live-action
games is a big thing.
You know things about the player
or you know things
about the game state
that you're not
really supposed to know.
If a person is supposed to be
able to teleport from one end
of campus to the other end of
campus, the character may be
able to do that.
But the damn player's got to
walk all the way in between.
And you have to drive the player
halfway to the, I now
know that player is probably
on this side of campus.
Even though your character
really had no idea how
to deal with that.
That's just one of those--
there are ways to design game
mechanics to avoid those
situations.
But in many, many, live-action
role playing there is a honor
system that really
has to kick in.
The nice thing about it is that
if everyone decides to go
by the honor system, and agrees
that this honor system
is necessary for the world to
be reinforced, it actually
helps reinforce that mutual
illusion that
this world is real.
By saying, I know that I'm not
supposed to know those things.
But I am going to play this game
as hard as I can in a way
that's [INAUDIBLE].
Actually reinforces the world
for everybody else.
It's the same for
improv theatre.
Anyone here involved in improv
theatre or improv comedy?
So, you know yes, and?
AUDIENCE: Sure.
PROFESSOR: What would be the
concept behind that?
AUDIENCE: Yes, and, is an idea
where if you give someone an
offer they'll take your offer.
So if I say, man we're
all out of tomatoes.
Someone will say, yes and the
big tomato cook-off is
tomorrow or something
like this.
PROFESSOR: You cannot contradict
what was said.
AUDIENCE: Not only do you not
contradict, you always add
information.
Every line, at least at the
beginning of the scene, should
be adding information
to the scene.
And then after a few lines you
have a very, very, elaborate
set up that's kind
of ridiculous.
PROFESSOR: But, mutually
shared?
AUDIENCE: Exactly.
PROFESSOR: So, in that
same situation.
Metagaming is one of those
things that's actively working
to destroy the reality
of your world.
And if all the players agree to
try their damn hardest to
not let it interfere with
the world [INAUDIBLE].
The illusion in a way that it
strengthens the scene for
improv theatre.
PROFESSOR: Hold on, just one
sec, the other concern that
you had before persuasion
issue which was?
AUDIENCE: Characters who, in
particular this comes up a lot
in this [INAUDIBLE] type
situations or what have you,
where you have somebody's who
either a super genius.
AUDIENCE: Oh, so someone who's
better than you at something.
AUDIENCE: Much better
than you.
How do you mechanic that?
PROFESSOR: The best way that you
can do that is to cast the
right person.
But what I have generally found
is that old role-playing
game chestnut of separating
intelligence from wisdom makes
it a little bit easier.
There's intelligence, which is
the ability to think on the
feet, and there's wisdom
which is how much you
know about the world.
And you as the game master
designing a game can figure
out, when I say someone's really
smart, what do I mean?
Intelligence or wisdom?
It helps you a little bit on
thinking how I can use game
mechanics or game writing
to fix that problem.
So if it's intelligence it's
just like, oh I have the
ability to do stuff that
other people can't do
because I'm so smart.
And you can literally just give
them abilities to act on
things that other people
do not have.
I'm able to build a telephone
out of this Coke because I'm a
professor of Gilligan's
Island.
I'm smart.
It doesn't mean I have to
act terribly smart.
I'm capable of doing things
that other people can't
because I've been told
specifically
I have these abilities.
But that's the intelligence
side of it.
The wisdom side of it is
a little bit harder.
Which is basically, you
dump a whole bunch of
information on somebody.
And you hope that they are
capable of making associations
between what's happening in
game and what they read.
That's a lot harder.
It is a problem, but I find that
by separating those two
it makes it an easier problem.
Patrick?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, this is a bit
of a noobish question.
Are LARPs usually played
in real time?
PROFESSOR: Typically, they have
rules about when to hit
the pause button.
Basically at MIT those are
usually enacted when safety
becomes an issue.
People are running too fast.
Somebody just fell down and you
want to be able to stop
everyone from running, and
so they shout halt.
Typically they're happening in
real time because it's really
hard to do turn based stuff that
doesn't quickly feel like
a board game.
AUDIENCE: I mean like, when you
say someone would want to
do a background check and you'd
say I don't know, come
back in two hours.
You'd literally wait
two hours?
PROFESSOR: So, yeah,
often that really
means just two hours.
And that's an interesting thing
of that it's real time
but it's kind of a time delay
at the same time.
So as a game master you can
build in game mechanics that
take advantage of real time
delays to be able to give you
as game master some
time to breathe.
Typically they're happening
in real time.
I wrote a game where the clock
stopped somewhere between
midnight and 8:00 AM.
The game world literally froze,
well not literally
figuratively froze, as well.
And one minute after 8:00 the
clock would practically, in
game terms, have moved one
minute even though there were
eight intervening hours in
between so that people could
go and take a break.
Which would be great
for an Army of
Darkness type of scenario.
[INAUDIBLE].
But those three films as opposed
to it all happened
within 48 hours.
So Andrew?
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: So I guess
two things, one
is in terms of wisdom.
Could you possibly have little
note cards that are flipped
over everywhere?
And then the wisdom person, the
person with high wisdom,
could read about information
in there?
PROFESSOR: You could certainly
have taken advantage of a
piece of paper taped on
the wall just put
in the back, right?
Some people can arguably be able
to read off the back of
the paper, some people aren't.
Which will be a little bit
easier than trying to keep it
all in your head at once.
You can also give very limited
wisdom, like the whole psychic
example, right?
I am sensitive in some way.
I can tell when certain
things are cursed.
By giving them clues on printed
pieces of paper that
nobody else knows how
to interpret.
I see there is a number
associated with each one of
these rooms.
That number happens
to be even.
This is not a place that any
sane person would want to be.
And there are people who have
the wisdom to tell that and
there are some people
who don't.
That's another way to put those
environmental clues.
Particularly in MIT, hiding
clues in plain sight, and
every single way that
you can possibly do
that, is really exploited.
So the numbers for instance.
I've seen games where
everyone has five
digits on their badge.
And every single one of those
digits means something.
If you happen to have the
ability to interpret them, but
each one of the digits means
something different.
So that's an example.
AUDIENCE: And just
really quickly.
In terms of space, how much
space do Assassin's Guild
games take?
PROFESSOR: MIT Assassin's Guild
has the advantage of the
MIT campus.
So it can go anywhere from main
campus mounted by Mass
Ave. and Main Street,
to all over campus.
But players hate that.
Players hate walking
all over campus.
It kills their feet.
So often it just turns out to
be the few rooms that they
could get room reservations for,
the MIT campus activities
complex, and the sort of general
vicinity around there.
Outdoors is really not used
much, because MIT Assassin's
Guild loves shooting little
plastic things at each other.
And when the wind blows
that just sucks.
Jeremy?
AUDIENCE: Do those eight
story [INAUDIBLE]
games that have gone way
horribly, fallen apart.
PROFESSOR: Oh, absolutely.
How much time have we got?
AUDIENCE: Can you highlight
what are the mistakes that
have made--
everyone who's doing these,
especially on my team, they're
all smart people.
And they're written
by smart people.
So what hazard mistakes do smart
people still make that
results in these games
falling apart?
Or bad things happen?
PROFESSOR: Well, the most common
thing that happens is
not even an issue of how smart
the game writers were but how
much experience they've
had in seeing
things go horribly wrong.
AUDIENCE: Right, which
is why I'm asking.
PROFESSOR: Just like this class
has given you experience
making games, you've seen how
some projects can go wrong.
A lot of it is just system
dynamics, right?
I put together a
bunch of rules.
I didn't expect those rules
to interact in that way.
But because a live-action game
is difficult to run multiple
times, the first
time you see--
AUDIENCE: How do you play
a live-action game
that lasts to a month?
PROFESSOR: That actually came
up in the forums I believe.
Somebody was asking
about this.
You can at best to a test--
AUDIENCE: Give them mechanics?
PROFESSOR: --You can play the
sort of game mechanics.
Write down the stripped down
version which takes out all of
the plot motivations and
just has the combat.
This is how combat plays.
I did that for a Matrix
game once.
And it's like, I'm writing
a game of a Matrix.
Combat is really freaking
important.
So I just made an entire game
where all it was, you want to
go in and get this thing
and get out.
That was the whole rule.
And here's your three pages
of contact notes.
And people were like holy shit,
this is a lot to remember.
And that showed me the
problems that I had.
Unfortunately, it wasn't so
catastrophic that I would use
it as a catastrophic
game example.
AUDIENCE: Tell us about
a catastrophic.
PROFESSOR: Catastrophic
game examples.
OK.
AUDIENCE: Tell us someone
tripped and hurt themselves.
[INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: No, that's not what
you're looking for I
understand.
It was a game where everyone
was playing undead.
I think they were vampires.
So they could get knocked down
if they got shot, and they
would get up again
in five minutes
because they were immortal.
Unless they got staked
or something they
would get up again.
Unfortunately, there were a lot
of vampires in the game.
Often many of them were
in different factions.
So they were going after
each other with guns.
So when two people who were
obviously against each other
shot each other, fell over,
they would get up in five
minutes and shoot each
other again.
Repeatedly begging for someone
to show up and do something to
break this deadlock.
And that's one of those things
where it's like game
mechanically you know
what's supposed to
happen, and it sucks.
So that's one example.
AUDIENCE: Do we have to
wait five minutes?
Can we just continue to
shoot each other?
PROFESSOR: But the issue is,
again, these games are
happening in real time.
So the five minute rule is there
possibly for a reason.
While you are down for five
minutes those five minutes
become very valuable for someone
who wants you down for
those five minutes.
You can kill me.
I can kill you.
But both of us can knock each
other down for five minutes.
And that's a great
delaying tactic.
And I can send one of my friends
and do something that
I don't want you interfering
with.
And if that's the case
then that's great.
But often it was just, oh
crap there's no way
to break the deadlock.
AUDIENCE: You'd figure the
limiting factor would be
ammunition though.
PROFESSOR: I think that game
actually let you pick up your
ammunition all you want.
Because it can be a really
annoying limitation to run out
of ammunition.
Especially if you are playing
with the little rubber dart
guns because carrying
a whole pile of
them is really annoying.
So if the rule is, I get to pick
them up, then you have
the allusion of having a lot of
ammunition without having
to carry a lot of ammunition.
So that's one example of
a catastrophic failure.
There's a really funny quote
regarding brainwashing
actually, which is
where were you?
I was not being brainwashed.
Who were you with?
Not with the people who
were brainwashing me.
Back to the problem with
the persuasion, right?
It's like, I want to tell you
something because my goals
haven't changed far enough
to want to align
me to my new goals.
So I'm going to do everything
that I can without
breaking the rules.
I'm not allowed to tell you that
I was being brainwashed.
So I can say that I wasn't
being brainwashed.
Other catastrophic?
How long do you think the thing
will take probably?
GUEST SPEAKER: I don't know.
Probably about as long
as a game of Mafia.
PROFESSOR: OK, so like
half an hour?
GUEST SPEAKER: Depends
on the people.
AUDIENCE: If you put a time
limit on discussions then,
because I've played in the past
where it's lasted hours.
Because there's no cap and
people just went into these
long discussions in
between rounds.
So if you put a cap like OK,
it's going to be this long a
discussion and then we're going
to kill someone off.
PROFESSOR: Let's see, I
had wanted to read.
AUDIENCE: Played online Mafia?
It's a totally different
experience.
PROFESSOR: Chat involved
or something?
AUDIENCE: Forums usually.
So basically, when you can look
at the history of what
people have said and who they've
accused and what order
they did it in, it completely
changes how
Mafia turns out, right?
Because all of a sudden, people
start going, back in
the history and compiling
statistics [INAUDIBLE].
And who said what and then who
must be on their side if
that's the case.
But there's this kind of meta
knowledge that you can use
with this if you are Mafia
because you can tell
[INAUDIBLE].
We were able to communicate
at the Mafia privately.
That meant we could for instance
do things like, make
sure we were never the first
people to accuse anyone.
So that's a Mafia truth,
never do that.
Because it immediately makes you
look suspicious later on
if somebody turns out
to be the Mafia.
There's no way that you can be
the first person who accuses.
But bandwagoning somebody who's
not in the Mafia is
always great.
So you can coordinate to do the
sort of thing to try and
defeat the statistical
analysis that
somebody else is doing.
PROFESSOR: You've
got this whole
shadow governance theory.
AUDIENCE: That's a great
[INAUDIBLE] tactic to try and
get you away from my team
is to actually accuse
someone on your team.
And hope that they don't
actually vote them off.
I've definitely been in a game
where we purposely killed off
one of the people on our
team just so that
we wouldn't be accused.
Oh, he cannot be on Mafia
because he killed off a Mafia.
OK, and then we end up winning
because no one
figured that out.
PROFESSOR: I mean, that's one
of the best things about all
kinds of live-action games is
that it almost encourages
people to look for
these slightly
out of the box illusions.
These sort of emergent I'm not
really going to expect that
but it still fits within
the rules.
Because we are dealing with real
people for the most part
and you're not limited to the
cards you're allowed to play
or the turns you're
allowed to take.
So taking advantage of that.
I have one more disaster
story.
AUDIENCE: I want to hear it.
PROFESSOR: I'll limit
it to just one for
the people who don't.
This was a game where
there was a
virus that was spreading.
People who are in Assassin's
Guild might have
already heard this one.
The whole basic idea is that
there was a explosive
nano-virus.
People who got infected after a
certain amount of time would
explode and anybody in
the room with them
would now be infected.
Of course this was a game--
a game set in science fiction
kind of thing--
and we've got doctors
who are capable.
Who have mechanics to be
able to research cures.
However when the doctor happened
to be one of the
first people to die, what
rapidly happens is that what
should have been a one night
game turned out to be a one
hour game and everybody
exploded.
I guess that might come
down to feasibility.
But you can think about it as
you need a certain amount of
redundancy when you're designing
any game, but
particularly live-actions
games.
Because shit happens.
And you've got to expect
that to happen.
There's always this fear about,
oh I put in too many
resources into this game and the
players are going to find
it too easy.
And more often than not, yeah,
there's some players that that
are going to say we breezed
through that.
But, rarely do people get
terribly upset in a
live-action game when something
is really too easy.
They get really upset when it
comes to the end and it seems
to be impossible.
Oh, so the GMs only made it
possible for one person to fix
this problem?
And they didn't think about that
person just dying in the
beginning of the game?
So that was another example.
That [INAUDIBLE], I'm sorry.
I feel really bad about bringing
up examples from my
games, but I don't know which
ones are the ones that I
genuinely--
Oh, I do have one more.
So, this was after The
Sims came out.
And people should really
be worried about that.
I thought having a bladder stat
would be a really good
idea for a game.
This was a game that
was set in a train
that was steam pumped.
So tea was the game.
Tea was in fact the
combat drug.
If you drank tea, your combat
status would increase but so
would your bladder stat.
Once your bladder stat was
passed a certain point all
your combat stats went down and
you really had to go to
the restroom.
Which was really interesting,
most people just
reviled that game.
Because there was one more
number they had to hit that
was stupid annoying and really
didn't do terribly much for
the immersion of the game.
I was thinking, it's a game
about travelling on the train.
So you use the restroom
all the time.
That's the only thing I do
when I'm travelling.
I use the restroom.
[INAUDIBLE].
But that led to some interesting
emergent
situations.
Because when this train gets
attacked, and everybody needs
to find a safe place to hide,
what they all do is they head
into the washroom, barricade
it, and drink tea until all
their combat stats go out the
roof and then win the fight.
Because they were right there
in the restroom they could
afford to do that.
It was hilarious.
AUDIENCE: Some of these people
come up with exploits.
PROFESSOR: They may hate the
rules, but once they
understand how the systems work
they're going to come up
with ways to use it to
their advantage.
And that can be some of the
most enjoyable moments.
AUDIENCE: I saw a squirrel
this past weekend, and he
figured out if he stood under a
bird feeding thing up in the
tree it could just get free food
because when the birds
ate it once every two to three
minutes they would drop a
grain inevitably.
And there was this really fat
squirrel just sitting there.
He spent the entire day sitting
right [INAUDIBLE].
So it's like it's so natural
to try and find exploits of
everything and work it
to your advantage.
PROFESSOR: There is a moral--
AUDIENCE: It doesn't work
for [INAUDIBLE] but
you still do it anyway.
PROFESSOR: There is
a moral to that.
Is that the live-action games,
especially if you're playing
in the live-action game
community, there is whatever
you write down as a rule we put
it up on the wall and they
put it on a piece of paper.
Someone's going to
try to do it.
And you have to think of, I'm
going to put in a rule that's
so ridiculous that people are
not going to want to try and
do it because it's going to
hurt them or something.
Like jump on this spot
100 times and you
will unlock this door.
Or you could find someone with
lock picking, and you'll just
assume that person's
going to find
someone with lock picking.
No, someone's going to jump on
the spot 100 times and they're
going to hate you for
it because you
put the rule in there.
So try not to hurt your players,
would be the moral,
because they will do what
you tell them to do.
AUDIENCE: Do you guys sign
disclosure forms?
PROFESSOR: All right, that's
a [INAUDIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: Before we go,
I want to just clarify this
version of the investigation
mechanic.
So, the group of scientists
gets to test two people.
If you catch the thing then
they're dead and out.
If you catch them on the second
time-- this is what
I've read-- if you catch them
on second guess you get
another guess.
I'm not sure if that
means you can have
infinite guesses or not.
So that's something to
play around with.
AUDIENCE: If you test the wrong
person who's not the
thing they don't die?
GUEST SPEAKER: No.
AUDIENCE: So I test someone the
first time, they're the
thing, then they're out.
But I test someone the second
time, regardless of whether or
not I tested a thing
the first time.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes.
So you always get at
least two guesses.
AUDIENCE: But if you test
someone on the second
one they don't die?
GUEST SPEAKER: If they're
the thing they're dead.
AUDIENCE: The thing dies.
If you test someone on the first
time and they're the
thing you don't get
an extra guess?
AUDIENCE: Well, not
necessarily.
GUEST SPEAKER: You get two.
AUDIENCE: You always get two.
AUDIENCE: So if you guess
any time [INAUDIBLE]
but if you guess a thing
and then not a
thing you get a player.
AUDIENCE: I think you
can catch the
thing really quickly.
AUDIENCE: I think you can
catch the thing without
actually doing anything sort of
like making a system where
you automatically
catch the thing.
You're getting two guesses so
in the ratio of randomly
guessing you'll--
GUEST SPEAKER: And you can
certainly change it right?
This is just what I've found.
And it seemed like an
interesting thing, the whole
point of the part was.
AUDIENCE: Which thing
do you start with?
AUDIENCE: No, you're
not [INAUDIBLE].
Because as I recall you would
infect someone first.
AUDIENCE: Because you're going
to have two unprescribed.
AUDIENCE: This seems really
like biased towards
non-infected.
AUDIENCE: Well we'll find out.