PROFESSOR: Hi, and welcome.
Today we're going to do a
problem about least squares
approximations.
Here's the question.
Find the quadratic equation
through the origin that is a
best fit for these three
points (1, 1), (2,
5), and (-1, -2).
I'll give you a minute to work
that out on your own.
You can hit the pause button
now, and we'll be back in a
minute to work the problem
out together.
OK and we're back.
So what's the first step
in a problem like this?
The first step is figuring out
what our equation looks like,
the one that we're
going to find.
So our equation is going
to look like ct plus dt
squared equals y.
So that's what we're
looking for.
We're looking for a quadratic
equation through the origin.
Now if it were just any
quadratic equation, then we
would have a constant term, but
through the origin just
means that the constant
term is 0.
Now what's the next step?
Next we need to set up
a matrix equation.
So we need an A, a matrix
A. And which matrix is
that going to be?
Well, let me start with the
first coordinate of these
three points.
And I'm going to put them in
the first column of this
matrix, 1, 2, -1.
And then my second column is
going to be the squares of
these coordinates,
1, 4, and 1.
And my x hat--
that's just c and d.
And my b--
this is going to be the second
coordinate, 1, 5, and -2.
OK, why did I set this
problem up like that?
Well, multiply A times x hat.
The first coordinate of A
times x hat is 1 times c
plus 1 times d.
It's just the same as plugging
in this first point into the
left hand side of
this equation.
And similarly, if I took the
second point and plugged it in
here, I would just get 2 times
c plus 4 times d, which is
just the same as the second
coordinate in the
multiplication A times x hat.
2 times c plus 4 times d.
OK and where did the
b come from?
Well, b came from plugging
in these points to
the right hand side.
So 1, 5, and -2 are just
the y-coordinates
of these three points.
So it would be great if we could
solve A x hat equals b.
But we can't solve A x hat
equals b, because there isn't
a quadratic equation through the
origin that contains these
three points.
But we need to find the best
approximation to that, so
that's the same as solving A x
hat equals the projection of b
onto the column space of A.
Because we only have a chance
of solving A x hat equals
something if it's in the
column space of A. And remember
from our projections
part of the class that this
is the same as solving A
transpose A x hat equals
A transpose b.
So that's what we're
really going to do.
We're really going to solve A
transpose A x hat equals A
transpose b.
And now all we have to do
is just the computation.
So let's do it.
So what is A transpose A?
I'm going to do this kind of
quickly, because you should be
good at multiplying
matrices by now.
Oh this--
I have the negative in the
wrong place, thank you.
Thanks for that correction.
I have the negative
backwards there.
And what do I get when
I multiply these?
I'll let you check.
This is 6, 8, 8, and 10.
And what is A transpose b?
Well, if you multiply this out,
I'll let you check that
you get 13 and 19.
So this is just some
computation.
And so what we're solving here
is 6, 8, 8, 10 times x hat
equals 13, 19.
And we remember how to do this
just by using elimination.
We replace the second row by 3
times the second row minus 4
times the first row.
Again, I'm going to do this
quickly because you know this
from other parts of the class.
You similarly change the b
vector, and we back solve to
get d is -5/2 and c equals--
let's plug that in and see--
think you're going
to get 11 over 2.
So what's our final equation?
Our final equation is y equals
11/2 t minus 5/2 t squared.
OK.
So this is our best
fit quadratic
equation through the origin.
Now before I end, let me
do a couple things.
First, let me go back
and review what
the key steps were.
Whenever you're faced with
such a best fit equation,
first, you want to see what
the general form of the
equation is.
Next you want to write it
in terms of matrices.
Write down your matrix
A and your vector b.
And lastly, you set up your
projection equation.
And then all you have to do
is just a computation.
But it might also be worth
noting that these three points
certainly aren't on this
quadratic equation.
For instance, if I plug in 1
here, I don't get (1, 1), I
get (1, 3).
But that's OK.
This is as close as we can do.
Thanks.