PROFESSOR: The phase lines
mathlet helps us to understand
the behavior of nonlinear
autonomous equations.
The large graphing window
shows a direction field.
The horizontal axis is t, and
the vertical axis is y.
As you see, the direction field
is independent of t.
This is the significance of
an autonomous equation.
The applet opens with the
equation 1 minus y times y
minus a, but I want to talk
to you about a different
equation, namely this one, which
can be written as the
quantity a minus y, times
y, minus 1/4.
This is a logistic equation
with harvesting.
Specifically, this is a model
of the oryx population in a
certain game preserve in
Kenya, measured in
kilooryx and years.
The Kenyan government wants to
sell permits to kill 1/4
kilooryx per year, and it wants
to know how large a game
preserve it should create to
guarantee a stable oryx
population.
The size of the preserve
determines what would be the
limiting population of oryx
which is the number a.
We can use this applet to
explore the options to
recommend to the Kenyan
government.
We can control the parameter a
using this slider down here.
Right now, it's set to a equals
0, so the equation is y
prime equals minus 1/4 minus y
squared, always negative, so
all the solutions decrease.
With a game preserve of zero
area, the population is
guaranteed to collapse.
We can draw some solution
curves by
clicking on this window.
You'll notice that any
horizontal translate of the
solution is another solution to
this differential equation.
Is another consequence of the
fact that it's an autonomous
differential equation.
We can increase the value
of a using this slider.
And when I do, notice
that the change in
the direction field--
it starts to flatten out,
especially in an area just
above the t-axis.
And when a takes on the value
1, a solution appears, a
constant solution in blue.
This is an equilibrium
solution.
We can measure the value
of y along it.
There's a readout below
the screen.
It seems that y is about 1/2.
And if we take a equals 1 and
y equals 1/2, and plug those
values into this equation, you
will get y prime equals 0.
In other words, you get
a constant solution.
Now notice this parabola in the
lower left of the screen.
As I change a, it moves.
That parabola is the graph of
y prime as a function of y.
So it depends upon a.
When a moves up to the value a
equals 1, the parabola moves
up and touches the y-axis at
the value y equals 1/2.
Now this blue curve represents
a steady state solution, but
the Kenyan government would be
ill-advised to use a preserve
only this big.
Because random fluctuations will
occasionally drive the
population of oryx below y
equals 1/2, and as soon as
that happens, disaster ensues.
The population is guaranteed
to collapse.
So let's take a bigger game
preserve, make a larger, and
when you do that, the parabola
moves up, the blue double root
splits into two roots, and
the equilibrium solution
bifurcates into two equilibrium
solutions.
The red equilibrium
is unstable.
Solutions near to it
diverge from it.
In fact, solutions below
it approach infinity.
These curves become asymptotic
to vertical straight lines.
They blow up in finite time.
Solutions between the two
equilibria move from the lower
equilibrium up to the green,
upper equilibrium, and
solutions above the green
equilibrium decay towards it.
The green solution is a
stable equilibrium.
You can see this behavior
by looking at
the parabola as well.
If the value of y is less than
the red zero, the value of the
parabola is negative.
Solutions are falling.
Between the two roots, the value
of y prime is positive.
Solutions are growing.
And to the right of this
equilibrium, the value of y
prime is negative.
Solutions are falling again.
You can see all this very neatly
using the phase line,
which I can invoke using
this key here.
The phase line carries all the
information present in the
direction field, but in a
much more compact form.
You can see the two equilibria
marked, and below this
equilibrium, all the solutions
are decaying.
Between the two, the solutions
are all increasing, and above
the upper equilibrium, the
solutions are all decaying.
These are indicated by
these yellow arrows.
Now the Kenyan government
has some leeway.
It may predict an accidental
variation
of, say, 1/2 kilooryx.
In that case, it should arrange
a game preserve large
enough so that the distance
between the two critical
points is at least 1/2.
Then, assuming that the initial
population is close to
this equilibrium, a deviation
of 1/2 won't be a disaster,
because the population will
recover and return to the
stable equilibrium.
Well, we've come a long way.
We're now looking at a family
of differential equations,
when indexed by the
parameter a.
Each value of a has its own
direction field, its own set
of critical points, it's
own solutions, and
its own phase line.
But as we see, for practical
policy reasons, it's important
to be able to consider them
all simultaneously.
The bifurcation diagram lets
you do exactly that.
Let's invoke it with
this check box.
The diagram has appeared
above the a slider.
In it is marked a curve.
This curve consists of all the
critical points for these
differential equations for
all values of a, marked
simultaneously.
The critical points for a given
value of a appear above
that value of a in the slider.
So here's the phase line for
this value of a containing an
unstable critical point and
a stable critical point.
And when I change the value
of a, that phase
line changes and moves.
And as the value of a decreases
to a equals 1, those
two critical points collide and
form a single semi-stable
critical point.
For smaller values of a, there
are no critical points, until
you reach the value a equals
minus 1, when a single
semi-stable critical point
appears and then bifurcates
into two critical points for
smaller values of a.
The critical curve is color
coded according to the type of
critical point that
it represents.
The bifurcation diagram takes
place in the a/y plane.
It's the curve defined by the
equation y prime equals 0.
In this case, that's minus 1/4
plus ay minus y squared.