PROFESSOR: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So in this problem, I'd like to
take a look at autonomous
equations and phase lines.
And specifically, we're going
to take a look at the simple
equation x dot equals ax plus
1, which models birth and
death rates and a fixed
replenishment rate for a
population.
So in this case, the variable
a represents births minus
deaths In a population.
And 1 represents the constant
input of new creatures.
So for part A, we're asked to
find intervals of the variable
a which determines the long
time stability of the
population.
And then secondly, for each
typical case of a in the first
part of the problem, we're asked
to sketch a phase line
and then also to sketch the
solution x of t versus t.
So I'll let you take a look at
this problem, and I'll be back
in a moment.
Hi Everyone.
Welcome back.
So the problem we're looking
at is x dot equals ax.
And as mentioned in the title
of the problem, this is an
autonomous equation which means
that the right-hand side
is not a function of time.
The right-hand side
only depends on x.
And for these types of problems,
the critical points
or the points at which the
right-hand side vanish tend to
determine the longtime
characteristics of the solution.
So we can kind of get a handle
on what intervals of a
determine the longtime stability
by sketching what x
dot versus x might look like.
And we see that if a is
positive, this represents a
line with a positive slope a.
So on the right-hand side of the
intercept with the x-axis,
x dot is positive, which means
that when the line goes
through the point x dot equals
0, the term ax plus 1 is going
to be positive.
I'll just point out that this
point right here is when x dot
is equal to 0.
And this happens when x is equal
to negative 1 over a.
So this point right here
is negative 1 over a.
And when x is below negative 1
over a, x dot is negative,
which means that solutions will
want to move away from
the point negative 1 over a.
What other qualitative behavior
could we have?
Well, when a is below 0, when a
is less than 0, the slope of
this curve is going
to be negative.
So I'll plot again
x dot versus x.
And again, the intercept
is going to be at
negative 1 over a.
However, when x is above
the critical
point, x dot is negative.
So solutions will want to tend
to move back towards
negative 1 over a.
And when x is below the critical
point, we see that x
dot is in the upper plane, which
means it's positive.
So solutions will
want to grow.
So we have two cases
right now.
One is when a is
bigger than 0.
One is when a is less than 0.
And then, of course, there's
going to be an intermediate
point, which is when
a is equal to 0.
And in this case, the curve x
dot versus x, it's just going
to be a straight line
hat goes through 1.
So this gives us three regions
that will determine the
longtime behavior.
So the three regions are a
equals 0, a less than 0, and
then a bigger than 0.
So this concludes part A. And
for part B, we're asked to
investigate the behavior of each
of these three regions by
constructing a phase line, and
then, secondly, by sketching a
solution or several solutions.
So for part B, let's take a
look at the case when a is
bigger than 0 first. And
I'm just going to pick
one value of a.
I'll just pick a is equal to 1
to work things out concretely.
And we're asked to sketch
a phase line.
So plot the phase line x here.
And we know from the ODE that
the critical point occurs at
negative 1 over a.
So in this case, there's going
to be one critical point, and
It's going to be
at negative 1.
Now when x is bigger than
negative 1, we've already seen
that x dot is going
to be positive.
So when x is bigger than
negative 1, in this region, x
dot is positive.
So above negative 1, x dot is
positive, which means that if
a solution starts at a point
above negative 1, it's going
to constantly increase
forever.
And likewise, if it's below
negative 1, it's going to
decrease forever.
So this is x dot is negative
in this region.
And of course, x dot is 0 at
the critical point, which
means if we start at the
critical point, we stay there
for all time.
So let's sketch some
solutions.
So whenever I have to sketch
solutions for a phase line,
the first solution I always
plot is going to be the
critical point.
So note that x equals negative
1 solves the
differential equation.
So x equals a critical point
always solves the
differential equation.
So that means when x is equal
to negative 1, we solve the
differential equation.
When x is bigger than
negative 1, we
attain exponential growth.
And when x is less than
negative 1, we have
exponential growth in the
opposite direction.
So this is sometimes said to be
an unstable critical point,
because any small perturbation
away from negative 1 will make
the solution diverge.
Also note that once I have one
of these curves, I can
generate all the others by
just picking it up and
shifting it over.
And the reason this works is
because the original equation
is autonomous, meaning that
the right-hand side didn't
depend on time.
So whenever you have an
autonomous equation, when you
sketch one solution, you can
always get the others by just
picking, or you can always get
a family of others by picking
up that solution and just
shifting it to the right and
to the left.
Now when a is below 0, I'll
just pick the value of a
equals negative 1, we have
a critical point at 1.
And in this case, the arrows
are going to point
towards 1 like this.
And again, I can sketch
some curves.
So I'll first draw the solution
when x is equal to 1.
And in this case, solutions are
going to converge towards
the critical point.
And in this case, we say
that the critical point
x equals 1 is stable.
And that's because any small
perturbation in the solution
will eventually just come
back to the critical
point at x equals 1.
And now lastly, we have the
third case which is
when a equals 0.
And in this case, there are
no critical points.
In fact, x dot was equal to 1.
So x dot is positive for
all values of x.
So our phase line is just
a line with arrows.
And in this case, if I were to
sketch some solutions, I'll
just draw my axes, x and t,
there are no critical points.
X is just increasing.
So the solutions are going to
look something like this.
They're just going to be a
family of straight lines.
So we've just sketched some
phase lines, and we sketched
several solutions for
each phase line.
We've seen how the critical
points and the arrows around
the critical points affect
the long time
behavior of the solutions.
And this is typically the
process that you go through
when looking at autonomous
equations.
You always first, A, find the
critical points, then B, find
the regions between the critical
points and figure out
if x dot is either positive
or negative.
And then that automatically
gives you the phase line.
Once you have the phase line,
you can always just sketch a
family of solutions.
So I'd like to conclude here.
And I'll see you next time.