DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
The problem I'd like to work
with you now is simply to
compute some partial derivatives
using the
definitions we learned
today in lecture.
So first we're going to compute
the partial derivative
in the x-direction, this
function xy squared
plus x squared y.
Then we're going to compute
its derivative in the
y-direction, and then finally
we're going to evaluate the
partial derivative in the
x-direction at a particular
point 1, 2 for the first
problem, and in the second
problem, we're going to
compute second partial
derivatives.
Now these we just compute by
taking the derivative of the
derivative, just as we do in
one-variable calculus.
So why don't you work on these,
pause the tape, and
I'll check back in a
moment, and we'll
see how I solve these.
OK, welcome back.
Let's get started.
So we have x squared y--
excuse me, xy squared
plus x squared y.
That's our f.
So when we take the partial
derivative in the
x-direction--
remember, this just means that
we treat y as if it were a
constant, and we just take an
ordinary derivative in the
x-direction as we would do
in one-variable calculus.
So the derivative of this in
the x-direction is just y
squared, because we only
differentiate the x here.
Similarly here, the derivative
of x squared is 2x, and y just
comes along for the ride as
if it were a constant.
For the partial derivative in
the y-direction, we do the
same thing, except now, x is a
constant, and we're taking an
ordinary derivative in
the y-direction.
So we have 2xy plus x squared.
And then the final thing that
we need to do is we want to
evaluate partial f, partial
x at the point 1, 2.
And so all that means is that we
have to plug in x equals 1
and y equals 2 into our previous
computation, and so
we get 2 squared plus
2 times 1 times 2.
So altogether, we get 8.
So that's computing partial
derivatives.
Now let's move on and compute
the second partial
derivatives.
So, for instance, we want to
compute the second partial
derivative both times
in the x-direction.
So all this means is that when
we took the first partial, we
got a function of x and
y, and now we just
need to take its partial.
So we just need to take the
derivative of this again in
the x-direction.
So now, the derivative
of y squared--
be careful-- the derivative of
y squared in the x-direction
is just zero, because y is
a constant relative to x.
And so, then altogether,
we just get 2y.
When we take the derivative to
this x, we just get one.
So that's our second partial
derivative in the x-direction.
And now you can also take
mixed partials.
So here, we take a
derivative of f.
First we take the derivative in
the y-direction and then we
take a derivative of that
in the x-direction.
So we can look at our derivative
here, partial f,
partial y, and we need to
take its partial in the
x-direction.
And so we get 2y plus 2x.
Now let's see what happens if
we switch the order here and
we take, instead, the partial
derivative in
the opposite order.
So now let's go back to our
partial derivative of f in the
x-direction and let's take
its derivative now in the
y-direction.
So the first term there, y
squared, gives us a 2y and the
second term gives us a 2x.
I want to just note that
these are equal.
In fact, the mixed partial
derivatives, whether you take
them in the xy order or the
yx order for the sorts of
functions that we're going to be
considering in this class,
for instance, all polynomial
functions and all
differentiable functions of
several variables, these mixed
partials are going
to be equal.
In your textbook, there are
some examples of sort of
pathological functions where
these are not equal, but
certainly for any polynomial
functions, these are always
going to be equal.
And I think I'll leave
it at that.