So we have now problem number
five, which is 24, 61.
It's a coaxial cable.
This is the outer part of the
cable, which has radius b.
And this is the inner part of
the cable, which has radius a.
And this is metal, is a
conductor, and the outer
sleeve is also a conductor,
and this is a vacuum.
So inside here is a cylinder
inside a cylinder.
We have, on the inner cylinder,
which must be on the
outer surface of it, we have a
charge plus lambda coulomb per
meter, and we have on the outer
shell of the cylinder,
which will be undoubtedly on
the inside, minus lambda
coulomb per meter.
So the next charge on the
whole thing will be 0.
Because we have here the same
amount plus per meter as we
have here minus per meter.
And you're being asked, what is
the potential anywhere in
space, here, here, and there.
The trick always
is as follows.
First you calculate what the
electric field is at any
location r.
And then the second thing you do
is, you say v at position 1
minus v at position 2.
The integral in going from 1 to
2 of e dot dr. And if you
prefer the definition in going
from 2 to 1 with a minus sign
of e dot er, that will give
you, of course, the same
answer, whatever you prefer.
Very well.
Let's now first look at
r is smaller than a.
It's very clear that
e equals 0 there.
But let's go for r larger
than b, that
is outside the cylinder.
It's clear that if you apply
Gauss's law, that you will
also find that e equals 0.
And I will leave
you with that.
You will make a Gaussian
cylinder with a
radius larger than b.
You give it any random
length you want to
give, I don't care.
And you apply Gauss's law.
And you will find, since there
is no charge inside that
cylinder, that the electric
field will be 0.
So outside 0, and here
in the core 0.
What now is the electric
field between a and b?
That's really the only part
where you have to do some
calculations.
Well I, now inside this vacuum,
produce a Gaussian
cylinder coaxial it has radius
r, and the radius is larger
than a and smaller then b.
It is clear that the electric
field everywhere on the bent
surface will be pointing
radially outward.
There's a positive
charge here.
I don't even have to
worry about whether
it's inward or outward.
It will shortly be outward.
So let's draw it just
here, outwards.
And if you can see this
here, the idea
is that it is outwards.
Perpendicular to the surface.
And the ds values themselves
are of course also
perpendicular to the
curved surface.
So e and the s are in
the same direction.
So if you were to look from
above, this is the radius b,
and this is the radius a, then
the electric field will be in
this direction, even though it
will be stronger here, as you
will see, than it
will be there.
Now I will apply Gauss's law.
The e field everywhere on the
cylinder must be the same, for
reasons of symmetry.
I take the length of the
cylinder arbitrarily l.
And so the flux through that
cylinder equals 2 pi r times
l, that's the surface of
the cylinder, times e.
The dot product becomes a plus
1, because ds and e are in the
same direction.
And that now must be the total
charge inside which is lambda
times l divided by epsilon 0,
because l was the length of
this cylinder.
And the l cancels, the l beta
cancels, because it would be
absurd if the e field depended
upon the length
of my Gaussian box.
And I find that e equals
lambda divided by
epsilon 0 2 pi r.
A very famous result, inversely
proportional to 1 over r.
With a sphere, we had an
electric field falling off as
1 over 4 squared.
With a cylinder, we have an
electric field falling
of as 1 over r.
Now, you can imagine what you
might have if you have two
very long, infinitely
big plates.
Maybe the electric field doesn't
fall off at all.
Because think about it.
The sphere, electric field falls
off as 1 over 4 squared.
The cylinder, it falls
off as 1 over r.
So maybe two parallel plates,
the electric field doesn't
fall of at all.
Maybe it's constant in size.
We'll get to that.
All right.
Let's now talk about
potentials.
The potential at point b, at the
surface, call that point
b, is 0, because the potential
at infinity is also 0, and so
there's no e field all
the way from the
outer shell to infinity.
So if this potential is 0, then
that potential is also 0.
Now this is the outer radius
b, and this is the
inner radius a.
What, now, is the potential here
at this radius r where r
is smaller then b and
larger than a?
Well, if I go from here to
there, and I use my shorthand
notation, vr minus vb, b is
any point, then, on this
cylinder, that equals the
integral in going from r to b
of e dot dr. The dot becomes a
plus 1, because the cosine
between, the angle between e
and the r is plus 1, so I
don't have to worry
about that.
And so that becomes the integral
in going from r to b
of lambda divided by 2 pi
epsilon 0 dr over r.
We just calculated.
Now, this integral is the
logarithm of r, taken between
the value b and r.
So this becomes lambda over
2 pi epsilon 0 times the
logarithm of b minus the
logarithm of r, which is the
logarithm of b over r.
So that's the way that
the potential changes
from here to here.
And if you want to know what it
is at r equals b, well, you
put in r equals b, and
what do you find?
No surprise.
The logarithm of 1 is 0.
It's exactly what's we had.
If you want to know what the
potential is at r equals a,
then you put in r equals a,
and you here b over a.
And so I would like to make a
drawing now of the potential
as a function of r.
Here is b.
Here is a.
I know that right
at the center--
well, let's start at infinity.
So right at infinity,
all the way.
Potential is 0.
And then it will climb up to
a certain value in this
logarithmic fashion that
we just calculated.
And then, since the inner core
is metallic, there is no e
field in that inner core, and
if there is no e field,
there's an e field with an equal
potential, and so it
will stay there.
And the value here, everywhere
inside that inner core, the
potential is lambda 2 pi divided
by epsilon 0, times
the logarithm of b over a, and
all of this, then, is correct,
because v at infinity
equals 0.
That's why we talk about v
potential, rather than
potential difference.