ANA RITA PIRES: Hi there.
Welcome to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about vector spaces
whose vectors are actually
matrices or functions, and
this is what our problem
today is about.
We have a set of 2 by 3 matrices
whose null space
contains the vector 2, 1, 1.
And I want you to show that this
set is actually a vector
subspace of the space of
all 2 by 3 matrices.
And then, I want you to
find a basis for it.
When you're done, here is
an additional question.
What about the set of those 2
by 3 matrices whose column
space contains the
vector 2, 1?
All right.
Hit pause.
And work on it yourself, and
when you're ready, I'll come
back and show you
how I did it.
Hi.
I hope you managed
to solve it.
Let's do it.
So, how do we show that
something is a vector subspace?
Well, there are only two things
that we need to check.
One is that if two vectors, in
this case two matrices, are in
that space, then their
sum is in that space.
And if you take a vector, in
this case a matrix, and you
multiply by a scalar you'll
still be in the space.
So, suppose that the matrices
A and B are in this set that
we want to prove
is a subspace.
So that means that A times the
vector 2, 1, 1 is equal to the
vector 0, 0.
Notice that the dimensions
I write, A is 2 by 3,
so this 3 by 1.
I should get a 2 by 1.
Suppose that 2, 1, 1 is in the
null space of A, and that 2,
1, 1 is also in the null space
of B. Then what is A plus B
times 2, 1, 1?
Is 2, 1, 1 in the null
space of A plus B?
Well, if you think about what
this means, you're just adding
entry by entry.
And you can do it slowly on your
own and just check that
this is what happens.
But by now you are familiar
enough with matrices that this
should not be a surprise.
Well, this is 0, 0, and this is
0, 0, so their sum is 0, 0.
So, indeed, 2, 1, 1, is in the
null space of A plus B. So if
A and B are in the set, A plus
B is in the set, as well.
Let's check the other thing.
The other thing is A times
2, 1, 1 is 0, 0.
So A is in the set, because 2,
1, 1 is in the null space of
A. And also, let's let
c be a scalar.
That just means that
c is a number.
Then we want to check that 2,
1, 1 is in the null space of
the matrix cA.
That matrix is just the matrix
A except every entry is
multiplied by the number c.
Well, again, this is
how matrices work.
You can just pull out the
constant and do A times 2, 1,
1 first. Now this is
the vector 0, 0.
So, this will simply be c times
0, 0, which is 0, 0.
So the matrix cA is also
contained in this set.
So the set is closed under
addition and other
multiplication by scalar,
so the set is,
indeed, a vector subspace.
Well that takes care of the
first part of the question.
The second part was find a
basis for the subspace.
So let's work on that now.
So the condition for a matrix to
be in this subspace is that
the vector 2, 1, 1 is
in the null space.
So I must have A times 2,
1, 1 is equal to 0, 0.
So what is happening?
Well A is a 2 by 3 matrix.
So you can actually think about
what happens in each row
separately.
You'll have the first row of A
times 2, 1, 1 is equal to 0.
And the second row of A times
2, 1, 1 is equal to 0.
So let's see what that means.
Each row of the matrix A in this
vector subspace must be
a, b, c, 2, 1, 1 equal to 0.
This is not really a good
sentence, but you understand.
Which means that--
well let's see--
2 a plus b plus c
is equal to 0.
So I can actually write
it in this format.
It must be of the form a, b,
and then c must be equal to
-2a minus b.
Right?
So, furthermore, we
can say that it--
well, one thing that you can
do-- let me write this
here to help you.
It will be a, 0, -2a,
plus 0, b, -b.
See?
So what I'm doing is I'm
splitting this into the linear
combination of two vectors.
I can pull out the a out of this
one, and pull the b out
of this one, and it must be
a linear combination--
that's what this means,
linear combination--
of the following--
1, 0, -2, and 0, 1, -1.
Does that make sense?
So this is what each row
of a must satisfy.
So we can now put everything
together into what a basis for
the vector space has to be.
The basis will be, well it's 2
by 3 matrix, and each row must
be a linear combination
of these two vectors.
So let's write that--
1, 0, -2.
I'll keep the second
row with zeros--
0, 1, -1, and I'll keep the
second row of zeros.
And now the same, but keeping
the first row with zeros, I'm
taking these vectors
on the second row.
So this is a basis for
my vector space.
1, 2, 3, 4 that also means
that the dimension of the
subspace is 4.
There was one further question,
which was what can
you say about the set of those
matrices that contain the
vector 2, 1 in their
column space?
What about the set of those 2
by 3 matrices whose column
space contains the
vector 2, 1.
Is that a vector subspace?
Well one quick check that you
can always do is check that
the 0 vector, in this case the
0 matrix, belongs to the set.
Does the 0, 2 by 3 matrix,
0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0.
Does this matrix belong
to this set?
Does this matrix contain
the vector 2, 1
in its column space?
It does not, so this set cannot
be a vector subspace.
If you want to think about how
this 0 belonging in the set
has anything to do with the two
conditions being closed
under sum and closed under
multiplication by scalar,
simply think that you should
always be able to multiply a
matrix by the scalar 0 and have
it still be in the set.
That will be your 0 matrix.
Well the zero matrix is not in
the set, so the set is not a
vector subspace.
All right?
We're done.
Thank you.