DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
I'd like to work on a problem
with you, which is to compute
the volume of a parallelepiped
using 3 by 3 determinants.
So here we've got the
parallelepiped drawn.
It has, one of its vertices
is at the origin--
0, 0, 0--
and the other three edges are
given to us with these
coordinates here.
So why don't you take some time
to work out this problem,
pause the video, and check back
with me and I'll show you
how I solved it.
OK, welcome back.
Let's get started.
So the first thing that we
need to do is we need to
remember that computing volumes
of parallelepipeds is
the same thing as computing
3 by 3 determinants.
So the volume is just equal to
the determinant, which is
built out of the vectors,
the row vectors
determining the edges.
So we have-- well, that's
almost true.
This determinant will be either
a positive or negative
number and we always want to
take the positive number.
So I'm going to write plus or
minus here, and we'll have to
remember at the end that we
want a positive number.
So we can compute this
determinant using Laplace
expansion as we did
in the last video.
So for Laplace expansion, we
take, can do Laplace expansion
on the first row.
And that will again be nice,
because this 0 here will make
our computation simpler.
And so, remember what we do is
we take the first entry in the
row, and then we need to
multiply by the minor that we
get by covering up that
row and that column.
So we have this little 2
by 2 determinant, which
looks like minus 1.
And now we need to subtract
the next entry in the row
times its minor, which is now
this matrix 1, 1, 0, 1.
So taking that determinant,
we get 1 minus 0.
So altogether, we get 1.
So what that tells us is that
our determinant is minus 4.
But then that tells us that
our volume is plus 4.
And I'll leave it at that.