DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
As a warm up, let's get started
by computing some
determinants for 2 by 2
and 3 by 3 matrices.
Why don't you take some time to
work on computing these two
determinants, and when you're
finished, check back with me
and I'll show you
how I solved it.
Welcome back.
So why don't we get started with
the 2 by 2 matrix first.
So remember, when we compute
a 2 by 2 determinant, we
multiply the entries in the main
diagonal and we subtract
from that the product of the
entries in the off diagonal.
So in this case, we have 3 times
minus 2, minus, minus 4
times minus 1.
So we have minus 6 minus
4 is minus 10.
OK, now, the 3 by 3 matrix,
we're going to use a Laplace
expansion, which means that
we're going to need to choose
a row or a column
in the matrix.
We can choose any row or column,
but as I look at this
matrix, I'd like to choose the
first row, because I see this
0 here, which is going to mean
we have less work to do.
So let's do Laplace expansion
across the first row.
So what that means is we take
the very first entry, minus 1,
and now we need to multiply it
by a 2 by 2 determinant, which
we get by covering up the row
and the column corresponding
to our first entry.
So our first entry was minus 1,
and what we need to do is
cover up the row and column
containing that, and we have
this little 2 by
2 matrix here.
And so we get 2,
2, minus 2, 1.
OK.
The next entry, we have to take
negative of this entry,
but this entry is 0.
So minus 0 times--
just for practice, why
don't I put in this
cofactor here anyways.
So again, we cover up the row
and the column containing the
0, and we have this
matrix 1, 2, 3, 1.
Now finally, we have to walk
over here, and we have to take
4 times the minor--
which we get by covering
up the row and
column containing 4--
1, 2, 3, minus 2.
And now notice that these are
just 2 by 2 determinants and
we can just compute those the
same way we did earlier.
Altogether, we get minus 1,
times 2 minus another 2--
excuse me--
2 minus, 2 minus a negative
4, so we get 6.
OK, this one goes away.
And then we have plus 4, times,
we have minus 2 minus
another 6, so it looks
to me like minus 8.
Altogether, we have minus 38.
Now let's just take a moment
to see what we did
on the 3 by 3 matrix.
We needed to do a Laplace
expansion, which means that we
needed to choose a
row or a column.
And we needed to take the
entries of the row and add
these up, multiplied by the
cofactor matrix we got by
covering up the row and
column containing
our highlighted entry.
And we needed to do that
alternating the signs.
So we got minus 1 times this
cofactor, minus 0 times this
cofactor, and then finally, plus
4 times this cofactor.
Altogether, we got minus 38.
OK, I'll leave it at that.
Thank you.