PROFESSOR: Welcome.
In this session, we're going to
examine pole diagrams. So
let's consider a pole diagram
for the linear time
independent systems of the
form bdy equals f.
So here, we have a few pole
diagrams to examine with the
poles marked with
the red crosses.
The axes are imaginary axis
and the real axis.
And the questions are list all
the stable systems. Choose the
systems with the
fastest decay.
And last, choose fastest decay
without oscillation.
So you have to think of how to
interpret these diagrams and
what are the meanings of the
position of the different
poles to address these
questions.
So pause the video.
Take a few minutes.
And I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So the first question asks
us to list all the stable
systems. So if you recall, all
the stable systems would be
the ones for which the
real part of the
pole are all negative.
So if we have all the poles with
real part negative, we
would have a stable system for
which the solution after a
long time would decay,
basically.
It would be transient.
So here, if we look at our pole
diagrams, we have diagram
B for which the real part
of the two poles are
minus 3 and minus 2.
So this would definitely
generate a decaying
exponential, exponential minus
2t, exponential minus 3t type
function at large time
for this system.
In A, we have a minus
1 and a 1.
So the real part here would
give us a decay, an
exponential decay, exponential
minus t.
But we would have here a term
that will diverge with
exponential t.
So this would have basically
behavior a long time that
diverges and doesn't go to 0.
So this would not basically
be a stable system.
For C, we have all the
real parts negative.
So we're in the stable case.
For D, we also have the same.
All the real parts
are negative.
So these are imaginary,
3i minus 2 plus 3i.
So both of them have also
negative real parts.
Everything is on the left
side of the plane.
Same thing for E. And for F,
we're right on the imaginary
axis, which means that we can't
tell if it's going to be
an exponential.
It's not going to be an
exponential decay or growth at
this point.
So to answer the first question,
the stable systems
would be B, C, D, E,
and that's it.
So now, for the second part,
choose the system with the
fastest decay.
So here, again, as we just
saw, the real part of the
poles gives us the speed
at which the
system is going to decay.
And so we have to look for a
system that has its pole on
the rightmost part
of the plane.
So for example, if we restrict
ourselves here, the fastest
decay here is going to be
governed by the rightmost
pole, so exponential minus 2t
that we need to examine.
Here, we have an exponential
minus 3t decay time.
Here, we would have an
exponential minus t decay.
Here, we would have something
a little bit--
minus 0.5t.
And here, again, this is
not stable system.
We did decay at large time.
So which of the system has
the fastest decay?
We would need to select the one
with the rightmost pole
that is the most on the left.
So we would need to compare this
minus 2, with this minus
3, with this minus 1,
with this minus 0.5.
And from all these poles, the
one that has the minus 3 here
would be the one that would
be decaying the fastest.
So we would have system
C decaying as
exponential minus 3t.
And I'm going to just write
down the others.
And these would be the dominant
terms that would
basically subscribe the
behavior at large t.
So this is the fastest. For our
system B, which is not the
fastest, I'm just going to write
it, it's going to be
dominated by a minus 2t.
For the system D, it would be
dominated by a minus 1t.
For the system E, it would be
dominated by the minus 0.5t.
So the fastest decay would
definitely be system C.
So the last question, choose
the fastest decay without
oscillations.
So now, we need to pay attention
to whether the poles
are on the imaginary axis, on
the real axis, or somewhere in
the middle.
So let's again, examine
only the stable cases.
So here, the two poles
are in the real axis.
So it's going to give us a
behavior that is only pure
decay, exponential decay,
exponential minus 2t,
exponential minus 3t with
no oscillation.
Because basically, these two
people don't have any
imaginary parts.
Here, we have a term in
exponential minus 3t.
But we would have a term that
would show oscillations with
the circular frequencies of 3.
So you would have an exponential
minus 3t cosine 3t
plus exponential minus 3t
sine 3t, for example.
So here, we would have a system
that shows oscillation.
So we don't want that.
For this case, that
would be similar.
So you see the pattern.
Here, we have an exponential
decay.
Here, we would have decaying
oscillations.
So there is oscillations.
Same thing here.
And so we're left with only
system B, which basically does
not show any oscillation but
only an exponential decay.
Pure decay.
And it's dominated by the
exponential minus 2t without
oscillations.
So that ends this first
part of the problem.
I'm just going to take a minute
and come back to show
you the second part
of the problem.
Welcome back for the second
part of the problem.
So here, another pole diagram
that we're going to label J
for this system.
And the poles are basically
here, 0.5 plus
4i, 0.5 minus 4i.
And then here, we have
almost a minus 3.
And here, it would
be a minus 4.
So the question is to consider
now the previous system we
had, p of dy equals f of t.
But now, with f of t equals f0
cos omega t, and omega, the
circular frequency going
between one and five.
And the question is for which
values of omega do we have the
largest response from
the system G?
So basically, we're looking at
phenomenon of resonance where
we want to find the frequency
omega for which the response
of the system is going to be
the biggest. So I give you
just a few minutes, and
we'll be right back.
Welcome back for this
second part.
So here, if you recall, the
amplitude response from the
previous recitations, the
amplitude is governed by 1
over the characteristic
polynomial
evaluated at i omega.
Where does i omega come from?
If you recall, it
comes from the
exponential response formula.
Because on the right-hand side
here, we have a cosine omega
t, then we complexify
exponential and we get, et
cetera, to get the amplitude
response.
So the amplitude is going to be
the largest for basically
values of i omega that are the
closest to the poles of the
polynomial to the poles
of this function.
Basically, the poles of the 1
over characteristic polynomial
is going to give us the 1 over
0, which will give an
amplitude response that
goes to infinity,
so the largest response.
So we want to choose our
frequency, i omega.
Basically, we want to look at
this diagram and look at the
poles that are the closest to
the values that are going to
give us p of s equals to 0.
And this is basically diagrammed
that gives us the
pole of this 1 over p.
And so we want to choose a value
for i omega, which will
be on the imaginary axis, that
is the closest to one
of these two poles.
Given that we work with positive
frequencies, we would
want, for example, to choose
i omega equals i4.
So it would be here, or just
omega equals to 4.
And this value of omega would
get us very close to this
pole, which would mean then
that we are 1 over a very
small number, which means that
the amplitude response will be
the biggest. So that's the look
behind the resonance and
looking at, again, the
phenomenon of the resonance
from the pole diagram
perspective and with the idea
of the use of the laplace
transform
behind the whole technique.
So that ends this session.
And the goal was really to learn
to interpret the meaning
of the poles in the pole diagram
and how do the polls
give us an idea inside on
the behavior of the
system on the long term.