PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
Today what we're going to do
is use what we know about
first and second derivatives
and what we know about
functions from way back in
algebra and precalculus, to
sketch a curve.
So I want you to sketch
the curve y equals x
over 1 plus x squared.
Doesn't have to be perfect, but
try and use what you know
about these derivatives, first
and second derivatives of this
function, and what you've talked
about in the lecture to
get a, get a pretty good
sketch of this.
I'll give you a little time to
work on it and then I'll be
back and I'll work
on it for you.
Welcome back.
So hopefully you feel good about
the sketch you've drawn.
But just to check everything, we
can go through it together.
And what I'm going to do, just
to keep track of things, is
I'm going to put an axis in this
region and then I'm going
to do all my work sort
of off to the side
and come back slowly.
So we'll try and keep track
of everything that way.
So before I do anything else I'm
just going to draw myself
a nice axis here.
And I'll give myself even
a little bit of--
oops, that's maybe a
little off, but--
so we'll assume every hash
mark is one unit.
I'll just put a 1 there so we
know every hash mark here is
going to represent one unit.
And I won't write the
rest of them.
Now one of the things you always
do first, is you want
to make sure that you understand
where the function
is defined.
So we have to check right away,
are there any values of
x for which this function
is not defined?
Well, how can that happen?
If it were a logarithm or if it
were a square root function
we would have problems in the
domain where would have to
check and make sure that
the input was positive.
In this case, because we have
a rational function, we have
to make sure that the
denominator is
never equal to 0.
But if you notice, the
denominator is 1 plus x squared.
Well, x squared is always bigger
than or equal to 0, and
once I add 1, I'm
in the clear.
I'm always positive in
the denominator.
So the denominator is always
positive, so I don't have to
put any vertical asymptotes.
Some other things we think about
before we even start
taking derivatives, or anything
I can find out about
this function, like
end behavior.
When we say end behavior we
mean, what happens as x goes
to positive infinity and as x
goes to negative infinity?
And from what you've seen
before, as x goes to positive
infinity, because this is a
rational function, the higher
power is going to win out.
The higher power always
wins out.
So the higher power here is in
the denominator so as x goes
to positive infinity this
whole expression is
going to head to 0.
For large values of x the x
squared is significantly
bigger than the x.
And so the denominator
is significantly
bigger than the numerator.
That's how we can think
about this.
So when x goes to plus or minus
infinity we know that
our function is going to be
headed to 0, so it has a
horizontal asymptote.
OK.
And then another thing we would,
we should notice is the
sign of the graph.
Notice where the sign
will change.
This denominator is always
positive so the sign of the
function depends completely
on the numerator.
And so when the numerator
is positive this
function will be positive.
When the numerator
is negative this
function will be negative.
So that's a little bit that
we should keep in mind.
And now let's go to using our
derivatives to figure out a
little bit more.
So obviously, first I should
take some derivatives and then
we'll look at what we
can get out of them.
So let's let f of x equal
x over 1 plus x squared.
So then f prime of x,
what do we get?
We get 1 plus x squared minus
x times 2x over 1 plus x
squared squared.
So I'm just going to continue
that straight below.
Let's see.
I can keep this x squared minus
2x squared, gives me a 1
minus x squared--
in the numerator--
over 1 plus x squared
quantity squared.
OK.
I'm going to keep
that right here.
We're going to do a little bit
of calculation below in a
moment, but I'm going to record
the second derivative
just to the right.
So the second derivative,
remember, is the derivative of
the first derivative.
So now I'm going to take this
derivative, again using the
quotient rule, which
I used here.
So the derivative of the top is
minus 2x and then times 1
plus x squared squared and then
I subtract the derivative
of the bottom times the top.
So I'll keep the top here,
1 minus x squared.
And then the derivative of the
bottom has a little chain rule
on it, so I'm going to get
a times 2 times 1 plus x
squared times 2x.
And then this whole thing
is over 1 plus-- whoa--
x plus 1.
We'll write x squared plus
1 for the fourth.
Sorry to switch the direction
or the order of those.
OK.
Now I'm going to pull out a
1 plus x squared from the
numerator to simplify it.
And then I'm going to see
what I have left.
Here I have a 1 plus x squared
times a negative 2x.
That's going to be negative
2x minus 2x cubed.
Here I'm going to have
2 times 2 is 4x times
this 1 minus x squared.
So I have a minus 4x
plus 4x squared--
cubed, sorry.
Let's make sure.
So I should have a 4x here and
then an x squared times 4x,
which is 4x cubed.
And that sign should
be positive.
And then I still have to divide
by 1 plus x squared to
the fourth.
To make this much simpler I'm
just going to divide out one
of the 1 plus x squared's,
simplify what's inside, and
we'll leave it that way.
Actually, let me move
this down so there's
a little more room.
So the numerator will now be 2x
cubed minus 6x over 1 plus
x squared to the third.
So these were some tools
that we needed.
Now we're going to
try and use them.
So let's recall what we know.
We know that when the derivative
is equal to 0, we
have a maximum or minimum
for the function.
And we know that when the second
derivative is equal to
0, we have changes
in concavity.
So let's find those places.
Let's find where the first
derivative is 0 and let's find
where the second derivative
is 0.
So I'm going to work under
each individual
function to do that.
So where is f prime
equal to 0?
Well, f prime is only
equal to 0 when the
numerator is equal to 0.
So let's solve 1 minus
x squared equals 0.
Well that's--
there's a couple ways you
can think about that.
You could factor it and then
solve, or you could see right
away this is going to be
x is plus or minus 1.
You get the same thing
if you factor.
But we see x is equal
to plus or minus 1.
So those are our maximum values
or minimum values for
the function.
OK.
So we know that this is an
important spot for the x value
and that's an important
spot for the x value.
Now let's just come over here
and look at, when is the
second derivative equal to 0?
So the second derivative is
equal to 0, again, when the
numerator is equal to 0.
So let's look at what we get.
Well, if we factor that we
get 2x times x squared
minus 3 equals 0.
So this has three places it's
going to be equal to 0.
It's going to be equal to 0 at
0, x equals 0, and it's going
to be equal to 0 at plus or
minus root 3, which is sort of
unfortunate that we don't know
exactly where that is, but we
know it's between 1 and 2.
I think it's about 1.7 or
something like this.
So we know we're interested in
the point x equals 0 and the
points x equal plus or minus
square root of 3.
So these are our places of
interest. And so let's
evaluate at least a couple
of these places and see
what's going on.
Let's go back to the
graph to do this.
Now I want to point out
something I didn't say
earlier, which is, if you know
the function is defined
everywhere, what you might want
to do is evaluate the
function at x equals
0 right away.
It's an easy place
to evaluate it.
It gives you sort of
a launching point.
So if I evaluate this at
x equals 0 I get 0.
So I know the point 0,
0 is on the graph.
So I know that's one point.
And now what I'm interested
in-- if you think about we
know where max's or min's occur
we know a max or min
occurs at x equals
plus or minus 1.
Or we have a hope for
a max or min there.
It's a critical point,
at least.
So I can evaluate the
function-- sorry--
I can evaluate the function at
1 and at negative 1 and I can
then plot those points.
So when x is 1, I get 1 over 1
plus 1 squared, so I get 1/2.
So with input 1 I
get output 1/2.
I'm going to erase that 1 now
so we don't lose track of
what's happening.
That looks potentially like it
could be a maximum, given sort
of what's happening
here, to the left.
So let's plug in negative
1 for x.
I get a negative 1 over 1 plus
quantity negative 1 squared.
So I get negative 1 over 2,
so I get negative 1/2.
So at x equals negative
1, I get negative 1/2.
And let's recall what we know
about the end behavior, which
we said at the beginning.
The end behavior of this is as
x goes to positive infinity,
the function's outputs
go to 0.
Which tells you that, in fact,
this has to be a maximum.
There are the only two places
where the function can change
direction from going up to going
down, or from going down
to going up.
So it has to be that
this is a maximum.
It has to be that this
is a minimum.
So, and also notice 0, based
on what we know about the
second derivative, is one of
the inflection points.
So that's also representing a
place where the derivative is
changing sign.
So maybe the derivative was
increasing and then it's going
to start decreasing.
So let's look--
I think I might have said
something a little off there,
so I'm going to maybe come back
and see if I have to fix
anything in a moment--
but let me draw a rough sketch
of what's happening.
Very rough, very roughly we know
we're going up and then
we're going down.
We're going down here and then
we have to go back up because
the end behavior.
So we have three inflection
points-- this is what I want
to point out-- we have three
inflection points.
We have an inflection point at 0
and at plus or minus root 3.
So we said root 3 is bigger
than 1, it's less than 2.
So I know somewhere in here I
have an inflection point,
which represents a change
in the concavity.
Right?
Which represents how the
derivative is going to change
the direction, whether it's
continuing to get more
negative and then getting more
positive than it was
previously.
So yeah, that's where we're
looking at where the
derivative changes sign.
As I said before.
So let me point out-- this
is a change in concavity.
Maybe right about in this x
region we want to change
concavity, and then
this x region we
want to change concavity.
So the graph will look something
like going up, going
down, going down.
And then I've tried to represent
the change in
concavity changing that
direction there.
And I'm doing something that
I didn't tell you yet.
But if you notice, this looks
highly symmetric, doesn't it?
And in fact, one thing I didn't
tell you about this
function-- that maybe you
picked up on already--
is that when I take the right
hand side and I rotate it
about the origin I get
the left hand side.
Why is that?
That's because this is
an odd function.
Why is it an odd function?
Because the numerator is
an odd function and the
denominator is an
even function.
And so the quotient is
an odd function.
So this is, I would say, a
fairly good sketch of the
curve y equals x over
1 plus x squared.
So hopefully yours looked
something like this.
And that's where we'll stop.