PROFESSOR: Welcome back.
So in this session, we're going
to look at unit step and
impulse responses.
So in this question, we ask you
to find the unit impulse
response to these two equations,
x dot plus 2x
equals f of t, and 2x dot, dot
plus 27 x dot-- oops, it
should be a 7--
plus 7x dot plus 3x
equals f of t.
In the second part, you're asked
to find the unit step
response for the
first equation.
So here, the key points are
really to remember what do we
mean by unit impulse and
unit step response.
Which initial condition
correspond to these responses?
And what functions of f of t
do you choose in each case?
So why don't you pause
the video and work
through this problem?
And I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So let's look at the equation
A. So the unit impulse
response is simply--
I'm going to write this down,
unit impulse response--
is simply the solution to the
following problem to our
differential equation, x dot
plus 2x that we're given, with
the forcing in a delta function
of magnitude 1 with
rest initial conditions, which
means in this case, that x of
0 is equal to 0.
So 0 minus is equal to 0.
So how do we go about solving
this equation?
So here, first of all, let's
look at what this means.
This equation could be modeling,
for example, the
quantity of radioactive
chemical in a tank.
And delta t here means that we
are giving a high disturbance
on a very short time
on this system.
So for example, dumping a huge
amount of chemical in that
tank, and then, just letting
the system evolve after
dumping all that chemical
in a tank.
So really, what we could see
is that the delta can be
identified to x dot, which
is the highest
derivative in the system.
And that would then mean that
we have a jump in the second
highest derivative, which
would be an x.
So delta t introduces
a jump in x.
And what do I mean by that is
that we had rest initial
conditions initially.
Now, we have to go into a jump
where the quantity of the tank
was raised to 1, which is
basically the magnitude on the
right-hand side and the fact
that we have no coefficients
for the highest derivative
in the system.
So basically, we can solve this
equation by solving the
equivalent problem, x dot
plus 2x equals to 0.
This is just the homogeneous
part with our new initial
conditions, x of 0 minus
equals to 1.
And so here, clearly from
before, we saw that the
solution would be a decaying
exponential.
We would have a constant
integration here, which would
be just 1 given our new
initial condition.
So this would be valid
for t larger than 0.
And given that we started from
rest initial conditions prior
to this perturbance introduced
by the delta, we could also
write this with a u of t step
function if we were to
consider t in r.
So if you want to look at how
the solution looks like, we
would have basically rest
initial conditions, and then,
a jump introduced by our
forcing, and after that, just
a decaying exponential, and a
jump here to a new initial
condition of 1.
So let's move to the
second problem.
Now, we're dealing with
a second order
differential equation.
2x dot, dot plus 7x dot
plus 3x equals f of t.
And we are asked again to seek
the unit impulse response to
this problem.
So the unit impulse response is
simply the solution of 2x
dot, dot plus 7x dot plus 3x
equals, again, the unit
impulse means that we're just
kicking the system with an
impulse of delta function.
And we're starting from rest
initial conditions.
So here, let's just look at what
could this be modeling.
So this could be just basically
Newton's Second Law
with acceleration and forces
applied to the system.
For example, it could be a mass
hanged on a spring with
certain damping due
to this term.
And this delta here would
have basically the units
corresponding to a force that
would be felt by the highest
order of term in the integral
which could correspond to the
acceleration multiplied, for
example, by a mass of 2.
So really, the delta can be
identified to the highest
order derivative, which means
that we would have a
discontinuity from 0 to 1 on
the derivative one degree
lower, so in x dot.
And so the delta introduces
the discontinuity on the
second highest derivative.
And what I mean by that is that
we have a jump from our
original initial conditions of
x dot 0 minus equals to 0 to
new initial conditions, x dot
of 0 minus equals one half.
Where did this one
half come from?
It came from the fact that I
have a factor of 2 in front of
the highest order derivative.
So If I'm identifying this with
delta, then integration
of this term would give me an x
dot that corresponds to the
jump from 0 to 1 over
2, so one half.
That's where it comes from.
And each time that you would
have a coefficient in front of
your highest order derivative
associated with the delta on
the right, you would have
a jump of 1 over that
coefficient.
So from this point, what
are we solving?
What do we need to solve to get
the unit impulse response?
It's equivalent to solving our
new system where we can then
get rid of the delta with our
new initial conditions, dot
equals one half.
And of course, here, I did
mentioned by the initial
condition on x0 minus 1, because
we need two initial
conditions for the second order
derivative, would still
be 0 as the discontinuity
would not be felt by the
function x itself.
So we can go ahead and
solve this problem.
So we use the characteristic
polynomial as we did before.
This characteristic polynomial
would have a discriminate of
25, which gives us simple roots
that we can compute, so
minus 7 plus or minus the
square root of the
discriminant over 4.
So we have two roots, minus 7
minus 5 over 4 minus 12 over
4, which is minus 3, minus 7
plus 5 over 4, which just
gives us minus one half.
So we can write down the
solution to this problem as C1
exponential the root that we
just found minus 3t plus C2
exponential the other root,
minus one half of t.
Now, to get C1, C2, we need to
take into account the initial
conditions.
So the first one tells
us that x at 0 is 0.
So that will give us C1 plus C2
equals to 0, so basically,
C2 equals minus C1.
And the second initial condition
tells us that the
derivative is 0.
So that gives us minus 3C1 minus
one half C2 equals to 0.
Here, we have that C2 is
equal to minus C1.
So we can just factor
out everything.
And we end up with 3 minus
one half-- whoops, sorry.
Here it should be one half,
our new modified initial
condition, equals to one half.
And here, you would have
5/2 equal to 1/2.
So C2 equals 1/5 equals
minus C1.
And so plugging in C1 and C2 in
this formula would give us
the general solution with C2
exponential minus one half t
minus exponential minus 3t.
And all of this, remember, we're
solving for t larger
than 0 in our modified system
with our new initial
conditions.
So this is for t
larger than 0.
And again, here, if we wanted
to just write it for t or r,
then we could just add the step
function u of t dot to
signify that we took rest
initial conditions before x
equals 0 minus.
So that ends the first part.
So now quickly, for the second
part, we're asked to find the
unit step response to
the first system.
So the unit step response is
just the solution to our
original ODE problem,
x dot plus 2x.
But now, f of t is the step
function, hence, the step
here, with still rest
initial conditions.
So really, the step
function is just 0
everywhere before 0 minus.
And it takes the value
of 1 after.
And so basically, we can just
solve again for t positive,
the modified differential
equation with u taking just
the value of 1.
And here, we just get
similar roots.
So it would be a minus 2t.
But then, we would
have a constant
integration to worry about.
And a new particular solution,
a lucky guess
would just be a constant.
And that would give us the
one half from 1 or 2.
So then, we just need to seek
the C1 that would give us x of
t equals to 0 at 0.
Because in this case, we don't
need to modify the initial
conditions.
They still remain the same,
rest initial conditions.
And so we would get here just
C1 equals minus one half.
So we have 1 minus exponential
of minus 2t.
So just here, something I forgot
to mention, what could
this be modeling?
So this could be modeling, if I
go back to my analogy of the
radioactive chemical in the
tank, this would be telling me
that after a certain time, I
start inputting at a steady
rate at a constant rate of u of
t of one per unit of time
the amount in the tank and then
looking at how the system
evolves to that.
So there's no abrupt change
that introduces a
discontinuity.
So just to conclude, I just want
to sketch the solution
just so that you see the
difference between the two.
And here, what we have, again,
I could have introduced my u
of t here if I want t in R. So
here, we have again a solution
that is 0 before.
There is no discontinuity.
It's still 0 at 0 minus.
And then, we have basically a
solution that is growing until
it reaches an asymptote
of one half when this
exponential goes to 0.
And so you can see that it's a
smooth transition because I
just started inputting the
amount of the chemical in the
tank in a non-abrupt way.
So this concludes
this session.
And the key here was to really
remember what do we mean by
the unit step response.
What type of f of t are
we talking about?
What initial conditions
do we need?
And same thing for the unit
impulse response.