Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
I, today I wanted to teach
you a variation on trig
substitution.
So this is called hyperbolic
trigonometric substitution.
And I'm going to teach you it
just by going through a nice
example of a question where
it turns out to be useful.
So the question is
the following.
Compute the area of
the region below.
So what's the region?
Well, I have here the hyperbola,
x squared minus y
squared equals 1.
And I've chosen a point on the
hyperbola whose coordinates
are cosh t sinh t.
So remember that cosh t is a
hyperbolic cosine, and sinh t
is the hyperbolic sine.
And they're given by the
formulas cosh t equals e to
the t plus e to the minus t over
2, and sinh t equals e to
the t minus e to the
minus t over 2.
So and we saw in an earlier
recitation video that this
point, cosh t, sinh t, is a
point on the right branch of
this hyperbola.
So I've got a region.
So I've got the hyperbola,
I've got that point.
I've drawn a straight
line between the
origin and that point.
So the region that I want you
to find the area of is this
region here.
So it's the region below that
line segment, above the
x-axis, and to the left of this
branch of the hyperbola.
Now, I'm not going to, I'm not
going to just ask you to do
that alone, because there's
this technique that
I want you to use.
So let's start setting up the
integral together, and then
I'll describe the technique and
give you a chance to work
it out yourself, to work out
the problem yourself.
So from looking at this
region--so let's think about
computing the area
of this region.
There are two ways we could
split it up, right?
We could cut it up into vertical
rectangles and
integrate with respect to x,
or we could cut it up into
horizontal rectangles and
integrate with respect to y.
Now, if we cut it up into
vertical rectangles, our life
is a little complicated, because
we have to cut the
region into 2 pieces here.
Right?
There's the, so this is the
point 1, 0, where the
hyperbola crosses x-axis.
So over here, you know, the top
part is the line segment
and the bottom part is the
x-axis, and then over here,
the top part is the line segment
and the bottom part is
the hyperbola.
So life is complicated if we
use vertical rectangles.
It's a little bit simpler if we
use horizontal rectangles,
so let's go with that.
You know, the amount of work
will be similar either way,
but I like this way, lets you
right down in one integral.
So the area--
OK.
So if we use horizontal
rectangles to compute the area
of a region, then the area is,
we need to integrate from the
bottom to the top, whatever
the, you know,
the bounds on y are.
And then the thing we have to
integrate has to be the area
of one of those little
rectangles.
So the area of the little
rectangle, its height is dy,
and its length, or width, I
guess, is the x-coordinate of
its rightmost point, minus
the x coordinate of
its leftmost point.
So OK.
So we need to integrate from the
lowest value of y to the
highest value.
So we start at the bottom at y
equals 0, and we need to go
all the way up to the
top here, which is
y equals sinh t.
So it's an integral
from 0 to sinh t.
OK.
And so we need the x-coordinate
on the right
here, minus the x-coordinate
on the left.
So what's the x-coordinate
on the right?
Well, we need to solve this
equation for x in terms of y.
Right?
This is going to be an integral
with respect to y.
So that if we solve for this
point, we get x is equal to
the square root of
y squared plus 1.
So the right coordinate is
the square root of y
squared plus 1.
And the left coordinate, this
is just a straight line
passing through the origin, so
its equation is y equals sinh
t over cosh t times x, or
x equals cosh t over
sinh t times y.
So this is minus cosh t
over sinh t times y.
And we're integrating
with respect to y.
OK.
So this is the integral that
we're interested in.
This integral gives
us the area.
And just a couple of things
to notice about it.
So t is a constant.
It's just fixed.
So cosh t over sinh t, which
we could also, if we wanted
to, this is the hyperbolic
cotangent.
But that's really not
important at all.
But we could call it that,
if we wanted to.
So this is just a constant.
So we have a minus a constant
times y dy.
So this part's easy
to integrate.
So the hard part is going
to be integrating this y
squared plus 1.
Now, one thing you've seen
is that when you have a y
squared, a square-root of, when
you have a y squared plus
1, one substitution that
sometimes works is a tangent
substitution.
And the reason a tangent
substitution works, is that
you have a trig identity,
tan squared plus 1
equals secant squared.
In this case, I'd like to
suggest a different
substitution.
All right?
So this integral is the integral
that you want.
And I'd like to suggest a
substitution, which is that
you use a hyperbolic trig
function as the thing that you
substitute.
So in particular, instead of
using, instead of relying on
the trig identity, tan squared
plus 1 equals secant squared,
you can use the hyperbolic trig
identity, which is that
sinh squared u plus 1 equals
cosh squared u.
So this identity--
so here we have a something
squared plus 1 equals
something squared.
So the identity this suggests
is to try the substitution y
equals sinh u.
All right?
So this is a hyperbolic
trig substitution.
So why don't you take that
hint, try it out on this
integral, see how it goes.
Take some time, pause the video,
work it out, come back
and we can work it
out together.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you had some luck
solving this integral using a
hyperbolic trig substitution.
Let's work it out together, see
if my answer matches the
one that you came up with.
So as I said before, this
integral comes in two parts.
There's the hard part, the
square root of y squared plus
1 part, and there's the easy
part, this y part.
So before I make the
substitution, let me just deal
with the easy part.
So I'll do that over here.
So we have the one part of the
area, or one part of the
integral, really, is the
integral from 0 to sinh t of
minus cosh t over sinh
t times y dy.
OK.
So this is just a constant, so
it's a constant times y.
So this is equal to--
well, it's the same constant
comes along, minus cosh t over
sinh t, times y squared over
2, for y between 0 and this
upper bound, sinh t.
So that's equal--OK.
So when y is 0, this
is just 0.
So this equals minus cosh
t sinh t over 2.
So that's the easy
part of integral.
So in order to compute the total
area, we need to add
this expression that we just
computed to the integral of
this first part.
So that's what we need
to compete next.
And that's what we're going
to use the hyperbolic trig
substitution on.
So we're going to complete the
integral from 0 to sinh t of
the square root of y
squared plus 1 dy.
And we're going to use the
substitution sinh u equals y,
or y equals sinh u.
OK.
So we need, what do I need?
I need what dy is, and I need
to change the bounds.
So dy--
I'm sorry, I'm going to flip
this around to take the-- so
dy is, I need the differential
of sine u, sorry of sinh u.
And so we saw in the earlier
hyperbolic trig function
recitation that that's cosh u
du, or if you like, you could
just differentiate using the
formulas that we know
for sinh and cosh.
And we need bounds.
So when y is 0, we need sinh
of something is 0.
And so it happens that
that value is 0.
So if you remember the graph
of the function, or you can
just check in the formula, when
sinh is 0, when t is 0,
that's when you get sinh is 0.
It's the only time e to the
t equals e to the minus t.
OK.
So when y is 0, then u is
0, and when y is sinh
t, then u is t.
Right?
Because sinh u is sinh t.
So under the substitution, this
becomes the integral from
0 to t now, from u equals
0 to t, of--
well, OK.
So this becomes the square root
of sinh squared u plus 1,
and then dy is times
cosh u du.
OK.
Now the reason we made this
substitution in the first
place is that this, we
can use a hyperbolic
trig identity here.
So sinh squared u plus 1 is
just cosh squared u, and
square root of cosh squared
u is cosh u.
Remember that cosh u is
positive, so we don't have to
worry about an absolute
value here.
So this is the integral from 0
to t of cosh squared u du.
OK.
So at this point, there are
a couple of different
things you can do.
One is that you can, just like
when we have certain trig
identities, we have
corresponding hyperbolic trig
identities that we could
try out here.
So we could try something
like that.
Another thing you can do, is
you can just go back to the
formula, right?
Cosh t has a simple formula in
terms of exponentials, so you
can go back to this formula
and you can plug in.
So let's just try that quickly,
because that's a sort
of easy way to handle this.
So this is cosh squared u du.
So I'm going to write--
OK.
Carry that all the
way up here.
So this is the integral
from 0 to t.
Well, if you take the formula
for hyperbolic cosine and
square it, what you get, I'm
going to do this all in one
step, is you e to the 2u
plus 2 plus e to the
minus 2u over 4 du.
OK.
And so now this is, once you've
replaced everything
with exponentials, this
is easy to integrate.
This is so e to the 2u, the
integral is e to the 2u over
2, so that comes over 8.
2 over 4, you integrate that,
and that's just 2u over 4,
which is u over 2.
And now the last one is minus
e to the minus 2u over 8
between 0 and t.
OK.
So now we take the
difference here.
At t, we get e to the 2t over 8
plus t over 2 minus e to the
minus 2t over 8.
Minus--
OK.
And when u is equal, so that
was at u equals t.
At u equals 0, we get 1/8
plus 0 minus 1/8.
So that's just 0.
OK.
So this is what we got for that
part of the integral.
So OK, so we've now split the
integral into two pieces.
We computed one piece, because
it was just easy, we're
integrating a polynomial.
We computed the other piece,
which was more complicated,
using a hyperbolic trig
substitution.
The whole integral is the
sum of those two pieces.
So now the whole integral, I
have to take this piece, and I
have to add it to the thing that
I computed for the other
piece before, which
was somewhere--
where did it go?
Here it is, right here.
Which was minus cosh
t sinh t over 2.
OK.
So I'm going to save you a
little arithmetic, and I'm
going to observe that minus
cosh t sinh t over 2 is
exactly equal to the minus e
to the 2t over 8, plus e to
the minus 2t over 8.
So adding these two expressions
together gives us--
so the first expression, minus
cosh t sinh t over 2, is minus
e to the 2t over 8 plus e to
the minus 2t over 8, plus--
OK.
Plus what we've got right here,
which is e to the 2t
over 8 minus e to the minus
2t over 8 plus t over 2.
And that's exactly equal
to t over 2.
OK.
So this is the area of that sort
of hyperbolic triangle
thing that we started out
with at the beginning.
So let me just walk back over
there for a second.
So we used this hyperbolic trig
substitution in order to
compute that the area of this
triangle is t over 2.
And I just want to--
first of all, I want to observe
that that's a really
nice answer.
So that's kind of cool.
The other thing that I want to
observe is that this is a very
close analogy with something
that happens in the case of
regular circle trigonometric
functions.
Which is, if you look at a
regular circle, and you take
the point cosine theta comma
sine theta, then the area of
this little triangle here
is theta over 2.
So in this case, u doesn't
measure an angle, but it does
measure an area in exactly
the same way that
theta measures an area.
So there's a really cool
relationship there between the
hyperbolic trig function and
the regular trig function.
So that's just a kind
of cool fact.
The useful piece of knowledge
that you can extract from what
we've just done, though, is
that you can use this
hyperbolic trig substitution in
integrals of certain forms.
So in the same way that trig
substitutions are suggested by
certain forms of the integrand,
hyperbolic trig
substitutions are also suggested
by certain forms of
the integrand, and often
you have a choice about
which one to use.
And in this particular instance,
a hyperbolic trig
substitution worked
out quite nicely.
Much more nicely than
a trig substitution
would have worked out.
So it's just another tool
for your toolbox.
I'll end with that.