CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video I want to explain
to you where the
coefficients we saw
in Simpson's rule
actually come from.
So what I'm going to do is take
this curve that I have
and show you what the picture
of Simpson's rule does.
And then I'm actually going to
determine explicitly where the
coefficients come from.
So let's look at this picture
first. The picture I have
here, the white curve
is going to be my y
equals f of x function.
And so, if you remember, what
Simpson's rule is saying, you
have to have two delta x's.
So in this case h is
equal to delta x.
So what Simpson's rule is
saying is I can find,
approximate, the area under this
curve from minus h to h
by a certain expression.
And the expression is, I said
delta x is equal to h, so let
me write h over 3 times y0 plus
4 y1 plus y2-- oh, y2.
So that's what you got, that's
what you saw in the lecture,
that this is what the
coefficients are.
So I want to explain why this
is a 1, why that's a 4, why
that's a 1, and where
that 3 comes from.
The picture is not going to
explain it, but the picture
will help us understand
how to go.
So what Simpson's rule does is
it takes those three points,
so the x0, y0, the x1, y1 and
x2, y2 that are on the curve y
equals f of x.
And it finds a parabola through
those three points.
So I'm going to do my best
to draw what looks like a
parabola through those
three points.
Something--
I'll draw it lightly first
and then I'll fill it in.
Something along these lines.
Something like that.
That's a sort of looks
like a parabola.
And os the idea is Simpson's
rule is saying I can find the
area under the blue curve.
So I can find the area
under the blue curve.
So this is a function, we'll
call this y equal P of x.
And that's what you
were actually
told about in lecture.
That you're approximating your
function y equals f of x by a
quadratic function that goes
through the values x0, y0, x1,
y1, and x2, y2.
And then you find the area
under that parabola.
Between minus h and h.
Now this picture, you might
say, Christine, this looks
really like a bad estimate.
This looks kind of stupid.
Maybe you should have
picked a different
function to estimate this.
And I did this one because I
wanted to be zoomed out far
and to show you, to give you a
little intuition about what
happens when we make
h smaller.
Notice that if I cut the size of
h in half, so if I started
with here was minus h to h, what
would my three points be?
My three points would be this
point, y1, and y2 would be
right here.
Well the quadratic through those
points is much closer to
the actual function.
And if I cut that in half again,
I'd have points here,
here, and here.
Something like that, and that
starts to look almost exactly
like a quadratic.
So if I found the area
under this--
or if I wanted to estimate the
area under this piece of the
curve using a quadratic through
those three points,
they would be very close.
So don't be alarmed by
Simpson's rule as an
approximation based on
this large picture.
So now, what do we have to do?
Remember, what's our goal?
Our goal is to figure
out where the
coefficients come from.
So what I actually need to do
is I need to evaluate a
certain integral.
Or I need to integrate
a certain function.
I need to integrate P of x.
So what I'm going to be finding
through the rest of
this video, is the integral
from minus h
to h of P of x dx.
And my goal is to show that this
integral is equal to this
expression.
I want to show that
these are equal.
That's my goal.
So let's get down to it.
What do I know?
What's the only thing I know
right away about P of x?
I know I'm choosing it to be a
quadratic function and I know
it goes through three
certain points.
Right?
I'll write down what the three
points are when we need them.
But first let's just say, in
general, let's take this
integral for a general quadratic
and see how much
information we actually need.
So let me come over here.
Actually, let me say
first, what do I
mean my general quadratic?
I mean something of the form big
A, capital Ax squared plus
Bx plus C. So I'm not filling
in values for these
coefficients yet.
Those coefficients are coming
exactly from my three points.
x0, y0, x1, y1 and x2, y2.
So let's just integrate that
from minus h to h first and
see what kind of information
we need.
So if I come over here.
So what do I get when I actually
integrate this?
Well, I get Ax to the third over
3, plus Bx squared over
2, plus Cx, and then I have to
evaluate for minus h to h.
Well, if you were thinking about
this, it shouldn't be
surprising that when I
do this, there's not
going to be a B term.
Why is that?
Well, these two functions
are even.
Ax squared and C are
even functions.
And I'm integrating over
something that's symmetric
about the y-axis.
I'm going from minus h to h.
So if you think about Ax
squared, and I'm going from
minus h to h, I'm finding the
area under a quadratic, from
minus h to h, it's going to be
twice the area from 0 to h.
But Bx, that's a line with
slope B. If I wanted to
integrate Bx from minus h to h,
that's the area, the signed
area under the curve of a line
Bx, from minus h to h.
If I just draw a quick
picture, what
does that look like?
It's symmetric with respect
to a rotation there.
I'd have this signed area.
This is the curve y equals Bx.
From minus h to h, I get this
area is negative and this are
is positive and they're equal.
So, what I'm about to do, you
shouldn't be surprised there
won't be a B term.
So what do we actually get
when we evaluate this?
We get 2A h cubed, over
3, plus 2C h.
That's what we get.
You can actually work it all,
put in and all the h's and see
that, but I knew I was going to
have double what was here
when I evaluated at h, and
nothing from the B term.
So we're getting closer.
We're getting closer.
We might not look like we're
getting closer, but we're
getting closer.
So let's simplify this
expression a little bit.
Actually, what I ultimately need
to do is I need to figure
out C and I need to figure
out something over here.
I need to actually figure
out Ah squared.
And let me explain why I need
to figure out Ah squared.
In the end, if I come over back
to what I want to show--
let me even box it,
so we see it--
I want to show that this
integral, which I've started
to calculate, is equal to h over
3 times this quantity.
So I want to keep one around,
but I want the other, any
other powers of h to not
be there when I'm done.
Right?
I need one power of h there.
In fact I need an
h over 3 there.
So I think what I'll do is I'll
start off and I'll pull
out an h over 3, and then I'll
try and figure out if I can
get the rest of my expression
to look like what's in the
parentheses.
That's really, ultimately,
what I'd like to do.
So let's come back over here.
I'm going to pull out an h over
3 from both of these and
we're going to see what
we end up with.
OK so if I pull out an h over 3
here, what do I end up with?
This is easy.
That's 2A h squared.
And this one's a little
bit trickier.
But I have to multiply by 3
over 3 to get a 3 there.
So I end up with 6C.
OK.
Let's make sure I didn't
make any mistakes.
If I multiply through here
I get 2A h cubed over 3.
If I multiply through here I get
2h C. Looking good so far.
Now I have to figure out A and
C, or Ah squared and C. Well,
C is pretty easy to find.
Let's think about why that is.
I have this polynomial.
The polynomial was equal to--
if we come over here and we
look again, it's Ax squared
plus Bx plus C. And the
polynomial has to go through
those three points I had.
So when x is 0, P of 0 is C. So
let's come back and look at
our picture.
When x is 0, what's the output
on the white curve?
It's y1.
So C is exactly y1.
How am I going to
find Ah squared?
Well, what I need to do is use
these other two points.
I'm going to evaluate the
function P of x at minus h.
And it's output has to be y0.
And I'm going to evaluate the
function P of x at h and it's
output has to be y2.
So we're going to come over to
the other side, but that's
really what we're doing next.
So let's come over here and
let's evaluate P of h
and P of minus h.
So P of h is Ah squared plus Bh
plus C. And P of minus h is
Ah squared minus
Bh plus C. OK.
What else?
Again we said this one has to
be y2, the output, and this
one has to be y0.
Because the output at h has to
agree with the output of the
function f of x.
And its output at h was y2.
The output at minus h of P has
to be the same as the output
at minus h of f.
And that was y0.
Now this might not look fun yet
but what if I add these
two things together.
What happens?
I get 2A h squared.
These drop out.
And then I get plus 2C is
equal to y0 plus y2.
I'm getting closer.
I'm getting much closer.
Because now notice what I have.
I have 2A h squared, I
can isolate that.
And that's something that
I want to figure out.
I want to figure 2A h squared.
So let's figure out
what that is.
2A h squared is equal to y0 plus
y2 minus, well what did
we say C was?
C was the output
at x equals 0.
Which is y1.
So it's minus 2C, which
is minus 2 y1.
So now we're very close,
we're very close to
getting what we want.
And that's good, because
I'm almost out of room.
So let's take that expression,
we were working on this
expression right here,
and let's start to
fill in what we get.
We get h over 3 times 2A h
squared which is y0 plus y2
minus 2 y1, and then
I have to add 6C.
Now what's C?
C is y1.
So I'm going to add 6 y1.
And if I simplify
that, I get y0--
bingo--
plus 4 y1 plus y2.
And that's what we wanted.
So let me take us through kind
of where all this came from
again, what the big pieces
were and we'll see now we
understand how we do Simpson's
rule, and these small chunks
of Simpson's rule.
So let's come back to
the very beginning.
OK, in the very beginning, what
we had was a function f
of x, that was the white curve.
y equals f of x was the
white curve.
And then I found a quadratic
that went through minus h, y0,
0, y1, and h, y2.
Went through those
three points.
And I called that quadratic
P of x.
And then what I was doing, we
know Simpson's rule says find
the area under the curve of P
of x between minus h and h.
So what I did was I came over
here and I said OK, P of x,
integral of P of x from
minus h to h.
I wrote P of x in a
very general form.
And then I actually
found an integral.
I came through and after writing
it out, calculating
the integral, I got to
this expression.
This is actually the integral
of P of x from minus h to h.
So it's the area under the curve
of P of x from minus h
to h is that.
And now I had to figure this
out, how to write this in
terms of the outputs
of f of x.
Which were y0, y1, and y2.
Those were the ones we
were interested in.
So I ultimately knew I wanted
an h over three in front.
I knew I wanted my integral in
my quadratic to be h over 3
times something, so I pulled
out an h over 3, and then I
looked at what this
expression was.
And if I could get this
expression to look like the
inside of what I wanted, which
was y0 plus 4 y1 plus y2, I
was in business.
And so then I used outputs that
I knew for p of x to find
2A h squared and to find C. I
know P of h is the output of
the f of x function at the
far right, which was y2.
And I knew P of minus h was
the output of the f of x
function at the far left.
That's y0.
I actually then evaluate P at h
and minus h, and when I add
those together, I get my
2Ah squared in terms
of y0, y1, and y2.
Let me do this in terms
Because I also knew C was y1.
We talked about that as well.
C had to be y1.
So I can then do the
substitution I need right here
and show where the
coefficients in
Simpson's rule come from.
So hopefully that was
informative for you.
And I think I'll stop there.