PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video I'd like us
to practice some of the
approximation techniques we've
learned in the lectures.
so in this one specifically,
what I'd like us to do is
estimate the integral from 0 to
pi of sin x dx using these
two approximation methods.
a is going to be using the
trapezoid rule, and b is going
to be using Simpson's rule.
In both cases, I'd like you to
do this for n equal 4, and to
get you started I have drawn a
little sketch of what y equals
sin x looks on the interval
from 0 to pi.
So I'll give you a while to
work on this and then when
you're finished you can come
back and I'll show
you how I do it.
OK.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you were
able to get an
approximation for both of these.
Now I'll show you how I do it
and make sure that you're
doing it in the correct way.
So I've done a little bit of
work ahead of time, because I
didn't want to have to write
everything down in the video.
So if you come over here to the
right a little bit, we'll
see that I've actually made
myself a table of the
important x-values
and y-values.
And if you recall, what I said
is we're going to approximate
the integral from 0 to pi using
four sub-intervals.
So we're interested in i going
from 0 to 4, and then we need
to subdivide that interval from
0 to pi into four equal
sub-intervals.
So that will be length
pi over 4.
So x0 is just 0,
x1 is pi over4.
x2 is pi over 2, you
get the idea.
x sub 4 is pi.
And then what I've done, is to
make it really easy on myself,
is I've determined what the
y-values are associated to
that x-value, given that
my function is sin x.
So I filled in a table of values
for myself right away,
and then when I want to use the
two rules, I can simply
come back and look
at this table.
So the first thing I'm going to
do is the trapezoid rule.
So I'll come back over
here a little bit.
So using the trapezoid rule,
let's remember what the
trapezoid rule is.
The trapezoid rule is delta x
times, in this case, we're
going to have y0 over 2 plus
y1 plus y2 plus y3
plus y4 over 2.
So let me actually move that.
So remember, what you get is
you get essentially you're
averaging the right and the
left hand end point ones.
So you end up with the furthest
left has a 1/2
coefficient, the furthest rights
has a 1/2, all the
other coefficients
are equal to 1.
So what do we get when we
actually evaluate this?
When we plug in what we
have for delta x and
for all these values.
Delta x, we know again, it
should be the length of the
interval divided by n.
We're sub-dividing
equally here.
So we get pi over 4.
And then let's look
at our values.
Well, y0 and y4 are both
0, so I'm going to not
even put those in.
You'll see 0 there, 0 there,
so these two are both 0.
So I just have to substitute
in these values.
y1, y2, and y3.
So y sub 1 is root 2 over 2, y
sub 2 is 1, and y sub 3 is
root 2 over 2.
So I should get root 2 over 2
plus 1 plus root 2 over 2.
And if you want to simplify a
little bit, you can do that.
Root 2 over 2 plus root
2 over 2, is root 2.
Hopefully you got something
that looked like this.
And I gotta tell you at this
point, I'm stopping.
Because I don't want to
bother to simplify
any more than this.
But the main point is, I want
to make sure we understand,
once we have this method how to
substitute everything in.
So this first one was just using
the trapezoid rule to
approximate the integral.
Now, what does that actually
mean in terms of the graph?
Let's go back to the graph and
let's look at what that
actually means.
I'm going to get another
color for this.
So in the case of the trapezoid
rule, what that
means, I'm sub-dividing the
interval like this and the
trapezoid rule, remember,
connects the two y-values.
Consecutive y-values here.
And it's giving you the
area of each of those.
So we found the blue, we found
the blue shaded area with the
trapezoid rule.
So just to recall, that's
actually what we did.
This is a fairly good
approximation, looks like in
this case, of what the
actual integral is.
So now let's do Simpson's
rule.
And I'll come over to the
right of the table to do
Simpson's rule.
Now notice I can do Simpson's
rule because
n is an even number.
I have to have n even in order
to do Simpson's rule.
So just to remind us what
Simpson's rule is, Simpson't
rule is delta x over 3 and
then I have these funny
coefficients, which at some
point we will explain.
I have a 1 in front of y0, a 4
in front of y1, 2 in front of
y2, a 4 in front of y3, and a
1 in front of the y sub 4.
So that's exactly
the coefficients
for Simpson's rule.
And you saw in class
why this is a 2.
You'll see in another recitation
video why we end up
getting the 1, 4, 1.
And those two things add
up, 1, 4, 1, 1, 4, 1.
And where the 3 comes from.
We'll show all of that
in another video.
So let's fill in what we have.
Well delta x is pi over 4 so I
get pi over 4 times 1/3,
so I get pi over 12.
y0 is again 0.
y1, come back here, it
was root 2 over 2.
Root 2 over 2 times
4 is 2 root 2.
y2, if you remember, was 1.
So I get 2 times 1 is 2.
And then I have the
same two values.
Because this is a, this is
symmetric about the y2 value.
So I get another 2 root
2, and another 0.
So if I simplify all this,
I get pi over 12-- oops--
pi over 12 and then I
get 4 root 2 plus 2.
And so that we can maybe see a
little bit more what it, how
it compares, we can simplify
this a little bit.
I'm going to put the 1 in
front, 1 plus 2 root 2.
Now, if you wanted to actually
do a comparison of those two
values, and then compare that to
the actual integral, you'd
want to evaluate the actual
integral and then maybe look
at what these two are
on a calculator.
But, I just wanted to make sure
we knew how to plug in
the y-values, and the
appropriate delta x to the
appropriate formula.
So, again, what we were trying
to do is estimate the integral
for one that we actually know,
so we could do some comparison
if we wanted.
And see how these numerical
methods, or these
approximations actually work.
So we did trapezoid rule, we
had the formal up there.
We did Simpson's rule and the
formula's right here.
And when we were doing this, the
thing that made it simpler
is at the very beginning I made
a nice table of values.
So when you're solving these
types of problems that might
be something you want to think
about doing right at the very
beginning to make things a
little simpler for yourself.
And I think I'll stop there.