PROFESSOR: Welcome back.
So today we're going to take a
look at a problem with partial
fractions, and specifically
how to use these partial
fractions to compute
Laplace inverses.
So just as a warm-up, we're
asked to recall what the
formula is for the Laplace
transform of f prime, in terms
of the Laplace transform of f.
In the second part, we're asked
to find the inverse
Laplace transform for three
different functions.
The first one is 1 over s
squared minus 4, s squared
divided by s squared plus 4, e
to the minus 5s divided by s
square minus 4.
And notice how none of these
functions appear in the
look-up table for Laplace
transform.
So in each case, we have to
use partial fractions to
convert it or massage these
functions into something which
we do know the Laplace transform
inverse for.
And then lastly, for the third
problem we're asked to write
down the partial fraction
decomposition of this
function, 1 over s squared times
s squared plus 4 times s
plus 1 times s plus 3.
And specifically, when we
do the partial fraction
decomposition, we're just
going to leave the
undetermined coefficients
unknown.
We're not actually going
to solve for them.
OK?
So I'll let you think
about this problem.
And I'll be back in a moment.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
OK.
So for part one, we're just
asked to recall the Laplace
transform of f prime in terms of
the Laplace transform of f.
So the Laplace transform of f
prime we can write down as s
times the Laplace transform of
F, which I'll use capital F,
minus f evaluated at the lower
bound of the Laplace transform
integral, which in this case
is just zero minus.
OK.
So this is just part one.
This is a warm-up problem.
For part two, we're asked to
find the inverse Laplace
transform for three different
functions.
The first one is 1 over
s squared minus 4.
And we see here that we can
factor the denominator into
one over s minus 2 times 1 over
s plus 2, which means
that we can use a partial
fraction decomposition which
has the form of A divided
by s minus 2 plus B
divided by s plus 2.
And then we need to solve for
the coefficients A and B.
So one way to solve for the
coefficients A and B is just
to multiply both sides of this
equation through by the
factors s minus 2
and s plus 2.
We can then plug in values of
s and solve for A and B.
There's another way, which is
sometimes referred to a
cover-up method.
And in this case, what we do is
we pick, for example, say
one of the places where the
denominator blows out.
So for example, if we look at
this factor s minus 2, this
factor diverges when
s approaches 2.
So then what we do is we go back
to our original function,
we cover up the term s minus 2
where it diverges, and then in
the remaining term, we plug in
the value of s, which causes
the factor s minus
2 to diverge.
So in this case, s minus
2 diverges at 2.
So we would cover this factor
up and then plug in
s is equal to 2.
And this would give us the
value of A. So for this
problem, A is equal to 1 over
2 plus 2, which is just 1/4.
For B, we look at plugging
in s equals negative 2.
So we cover up the factor
that diverges in
the original function.
Plugging in s equals negative
2 gives me negative 2 minus
negative 2.
So B is just negative 4.
So this function is 1/4 1
over s minus 2 minus 1/4
1 over s plus 2.
And when we take the inverse
Laplace transform, so the
inverse Laplace transform of
1 over s squared minus 4 is
going to be 1/4.
The inverse Laplace transform
of s minus 2 is
e to the plus 2t.
The second factor is negative
1/4 e to the negative 2t.
And this concludes the
first problem.
For the second function, we have
s squared divided by s
squared plus 4.
So again, this function's not
in the correct form to use a
Laplace transform
look-up table.
But what we can do is we can
divide long division of
polynomials the numerator
out by the denominator.
So when we do that we end up
with 1 minus 4 divided by s
squared plus 4.
So when we take the inverse
Laplace transform of s squared
divided by s squared plus 4,
we're left with the inverse
Laplace transform of 1 minus the
inverse Laplace transform
of 4 divided by s
squared plus 4.
And if we use our look-up
table, we know that the
inverse Laplace transform of
1 is the delta function.
Meanwhile, the inverse Laplace
transform of some number
divided by s squared plus
4 looks like, in this
case, sine of 2t.
Now we need a 2 upstairs, so
this is going to give us 2
times sine of 2t.
And I obtain this by noting that
the Laplace transform of
sine omega t is equal to omega
divided by s squared plus
omega squared.
So that's how I went from this
function, this Laplace
transform inverse,
to 2 sine 2t.
Lastly, for part three, the
third problem, we're asked for
the inverse Laplace transform
of e to the minus 5s divided
by s squared minus 4.
Now note that we already know
the inverse Laplace transform
to 1 over s squared minus 4.
In this case, we're just
multiplying 1 over s squared
minus 4 by e to the minus 5s.
So we can use the shift formula
in addition to what we
already computed, the inverse
Laplace transform to 1 over s
squared minus 4,
to compute this
inverse Laplace transform.
So the shift formula says that
we need to multiply by the
step function t minus 5.
So we're shifting with
the step function.
And then what we do is we want
to shift the inverse Laplace
transform of 1 over
s squared minus 4.
So the inverse Laplace transform
to 1 over s squared
minus 4 is 2 t minus 5.
So if we shift t by 5, we end up
with 1/4 e to the 2 t minus
5 minus 1/4 e to the
minus 2 t minus 5.
So again, just to reiterate,
when we have an exponential e
to the minus, say, 5s and we
already know the inverse
Laplace transform of everything
else, we just
multiply by the step function
u t minus 5, the same shift.
And then wherever we see the
t in the inverse Laplace
transform, we just replace it
with t minus 5, in this case.
OK?
And now lastly, for part three
we're just asked to write down
the decomposition for this
very large function, the
partial fraction decomposition
of this large function.
So it's s squared times s
squared plus 1 times s plus 1
times s plus 3.
Let me just double check.
s squared plus 4.
OK?
And unfortunately this
function's going to be a
little ugly.
We're going to have a constant,
A, divided by s plus
B divided by s squared.
So these first two terms come
from this term right here.
For the squared plus 4 term,
we're going to seek a C
times s plus D--
so we need both factors,
Cs plus D--
divided by s squared plus 4.
We have E divided by s plus 1.
And then plus F divided
by s plus 3.
So just to associate each factor
in the partial fraction
decomposition with the original
function, I've just
drawn some arrows.
OK?
And then lastly although I
didn't state this in the
original problem, we can also
just write down the inverse
Laplace transform of this entire
mess without actually
determining the constants.
We can just keep the
constants in.
So if we wanted to compute the
inverse Laplace transform,
well, it would just be A--
because inverse Laplace
transform of 1 over s is 1--
plus B--
inverse Laplace transform
of s squared is t--
plus, now this part has two
terms, Cs divided by s
squared plus 4.
That's going to give us
C times cosine of 2t.
The D divided by s squared plus
4 is going to give us,
well, we need to multiply
upstairs by 2 and divide
downstairs by 2.
So we get D divided
by 2 of sine 2t.
This term, E, is going to give
us e times the exponential of
negative t.
And then the last term is going
to give us F times e to
the minus 3t.
OK?
So just as a quick wrap-up, in
this problem we've computed
partial fraction
decompositions of several functions.
And the reason we've done this
is because we often end up in
a situation when we want to
solve an ODE using Laplace
transforms where we have some
complicated function and we
need to use partial fraction
decomposition to write down
simpler functions, in which
case we can then use the
Laplace inverse formula on each
of the simpler functions.
OK?
So I'll just conclude here, and
I'll see you next time.