PROFESSOR: Welcome back.
So in this session we're going
to look at Laplace transform.
And we'll start with asking you
to recall the definition
that you saw in class, then to
use the definition to compute
the Laplace transform of the
function 1, exponential At,
and the delta function.
For each one of these, give the
domain of definition or
convergence of the
od integral.
For the last question, you're
asked to use the results of
question 2 to give the Laplace
transform of this linear
combination of functions.
In the last part, you're asked
to compute Laplace transform,
cosine and sine.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a few minutes, and
work through that.
Welcome back.
So let's start with
the definition.
Laplace transform of the
function s was defined as the
integral from 0 minus to
infinity of the function f of
t exponential minus st dt.
So note here, the interval
of integration
is 0 minus to infinity.
So using this definition, we can
go ahead and compute our
first Laplace transform,
L of 1.
So I'm just going to substitute
1 in that integral,
which gives me basically
exponential minus st dt, which
is just the integral of the
exponential minus st over
minus s from 0 minus
to infinity.
And if I expend this, basically,
I end up with 1/s.
The minus reverses the order
of integration, so I start
with 0, which is 1, minus the
limit when t goes to infinity,
my exponential minus st.
So here the sign of s
becomes important.
If s was positive, then this
term would go to 0 as t goes
to infinity.
If s is negative, then this term
diverges, and so we're
not anymore in the domain
of convergence
of the Laplace integral.
But really, s could
be also complex.
So what we're interested in
is really the sign of the
real part of s.
So if the real part of s is
positive, this term is goes to
0, and the Laplace transform
of 1 is just 1/s.
And if the real part
of s is negative,
then the Laplace diverges.
So the domain of convergence in
which you want to be on is
the one where the real part
of s is positive.
OK.
So let's move to
the second one.
The second one is a Laplace
of exponential at.
So we can move a bit faster now,
and just merge the two
exponentials.
Exponential minus 0 to infinity
to 0 to infinity of
this exponential.
Clearly this is just, again,
a case of exponential
integration between
the two bounds.
And here again we're going to
hint a problem with the domain
of convergence where we need--
so let me just write
these again.
So we're going to have
here a minus--
so we have our a minus s.
So we have the limit again when
t goes to infinity of
exponential minus s plus
a capital T minus 1.
And here, again, we need to
impose the condition that the
real part of a minus s be
negative to have the domain of
convergence of the integral.
And then we're left with the
Laplace interval being over 1
over s minus a.
If the real part is positive,
then we have divergence.
So the domain of convergence
of this Laplace is the one
defined by the real part of a
less than the real part of s.
OK.
So let's do the last one.
The last one is the Laplace
transform of the delta
function that we saw before.
That's 0 minus to infinity delta
exponential minus st dt.
So from the previous
recitations, we saw that on
this domain, from 0 minus to
infinity, the delta is 0
everywhere except at 0, where we
basically assigned a value
of this function at
t equal to 0.
So basically we're
just left with
exponential 0, which is 1.
And this computation was
really easy, due to the
properties of the
delta function.
So that ends roughly this first
part, except that you
can also notice here that the
domain of convergence for the
Laplace for delta is all s.
There's no condition.
So the last part, next question,
asked us to compute
the Laplace transform
of a linear
combination of functions.
So this one is 7 plus 8
exponential 2t plus 9
exponential minus 3t.
So here I've used solely Laplace
as an integral, and so
the Laplace transform of this
linear combination of
functions is the linear
combination of the Laplace
transform of the functions
individually.
And so we can just rewrite this
as 7 Laplace of 1 plus 8
Laplace of exponential
2t plus 9 Laplace
exponential minus 3t.
And here we can see how we can
recycle the results from the
previous part, as we computed
the Laplace transform of 1,
and we computed the Laplace
transform exponential at,
which we're going to be able to
apply in these two cases.
So we can write the results
directly here.
And I'm just going to not
rewrite everything, just
include it.
So the Laplace of 1, we found
it earlier to be 1/s.
The Laplace of exponential 2t we
just found here, and would
be s minus 2.
The Laplace of exponential
minus 3t would be s minus
minus 3, so it's s plus
3 with the 9.
And we're done.
So for the last part, you're
asked to compute the Laplace
transfer of cosine and
sine, and you should
know these by heart.
But just a trick to
remember it--
I just want to remind you,
again, of the linearity and
the fact that you could
also use the formula.
Given what we just derived,
you could also write this,
again due to the linearity of
the integral as a linear
combination of Laplace of
cosine and sine here.
And we know that the Laplace of
the exponential at is just
what we computed here.
So that would be s minus i
omega, which you can just
rewrite like this.
And then identify just the real
part with the real part,
the imaginary part with the
imaginary part, which finishes
our problem.
And this is a quick way
of checking that
you have that, right?
To give you the Laplace
transforms of cosine and sine.
So that ends the problem
for today.
The key point was just
remembering the definition of
the Laplace transform, and then
learning how to use it
for different cases, and
identify the domains of
convergence.