PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
You've been talking about
differentials.
And one of the things that
you've shown is that some of
the stuff that we've been doing
with derivatives can
also be phrased in terms
of differentials.
That for many purposes they
form a just a different
language to compute
the same things.
So in particular one example
of that is linear
approximation.
So I have a problem here that's
a linear approximation
problem, but I'd like you to
do it using the method of
differentials.
So in particular I'd like
you to approximate the
square root of 21.
And the way I'd like you to do
that is by using a linear
approximation to the function f
of x equals the square root
of 10x minus x squared based at
the point 2, x0 equals 2.
Note that, you know, why are
we using this function to
approximate square root of 21?
Well because at 3, the function
value at 3, f of 3,
is exactly equal to the
square root of 21.
So to approximate the square
root 21 means approximate the
function value at 3.
And so, you know, this function
has a nice value at x
equals 2, so we can use linear
approximation at 2 to try and
compute an approximation to the
function at x equals 3.
So why don't you take a couple
of minutes, work this out,
come back and we can work
it out together.
All right, welcome back.
So we're doing linear
approximation here.
And we're doing it with
differentials.
So, in general, when we use the
method of differentials to
compute a linear approximation,
what we have is
that if y equals f of x, so if y
is given as a function of x,
then we have that so if we want
to change x a little bit
and figure out what the change
in y is, we have this formula,
which is that f of x plus dx--
so the function value
at a nearby point--
is approximately equal
to y plus dy.
So this is our formula for
linear approximation in terms
of differentials.
So in our case we have that our,
that the point we want is
x equals 2 and y equals 4.
And so we have, we know was dx
is also, because we want the
approximation at the point 3.
So we want dx to be equal to
1 for this approximation.
And so the question is, what
is dy going to be?
So that's the value
that we're after.
That tells us how much the
function value changes.
So to compute dy,
well dy is the
differential of the function.
So this is d of the
square root of 10x
minus x squared, quantity.
OK, so to compute this
differential now, we just use
our straight-forward rules
for doing this.
So we take a derivative
and then we
have dx's where necessary.
So this is d of square root
of 10x minus x squared.
So the outermost function is
the square root function.
So this is going to be 1/2 times
10x minus x squared to
the minus 1/2.
So that's 1 over the square root
of 10x minus x squared.
And now I need to multiply by
the derivative of the inside
function, which is
10 minus 2x dx.
So really it's 10dx minus 2xdx
but I just, you know, pulled
that dx out in front.
So we have a differential
equal to a differential.
OK, and so, but we want this
value at this particular point
in question.
So at this particular point in
question we have x equals 2
and dx is equal to 1.
So the value of dy that we want
is equal to 1/2 times--
well this is again, OK, 10
times 2 minus 2 squared.
That's 16 to the minus
1/2 times--
so here x equals 2.
10 minus 4 is 6.
Times dx is just this 1 that
we're interested in.
OK so 16 to the minus 1/2, 16 to
the 1/2 is 4, so 16 to the
minus 1/2 is 1/4.
So this is 1/2 times
1/4 times 6.
So that's 6/8, which is 3/4.
So our dy is 3/4.
So that means our linear
approximation that we're after
is just f of 3, f of x plus dx
is approximately equal to our
value y that we, at our original
point, which was 4
plus the dy.
So plus 3/4.
So the linear approximation that
we get from this method
of differentials is exactly the
same approximation that we
would get if we did this
the other way.
But I think it's kind of
nice to do it in this
differential form.
Somehow it seems a little more
straightforward sometimes.
And OK, andso the answer
that we get out of
it is 4 plus 3/4.
All right, so that's that.