JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've
been learning
about Stoke's Theorem.
And I have a nice question
here for you that can put
Stoke's Theorem to the test.
So what I'd like you to do is
I'd like you to consider this
field F. So its components
are 2z, x, and y.
And the surface S that is the
top half of the unit sphere.
So it's the sphere of radius 1
centered at the origin, but
only its top half.
Only the part where z is greater
than or equal to 0.
So what I'd like you to do is to
verify Stoke's Theorem for
this surface.
So that is, I'd like you to
compute the surface integral
that comes from Stoke's Theorem
for this surface, and
the line integral that comes
from Stoke's Theorem for the
surface, and check that
they're really
equal to each other.
Now, before we start, we should
just say one brief
thing about compatible
orientation.
So I didn't give you any
orientations, but of course,
it doesn't matter as long as
you choose ones that are
compatible.
So if you think about your
rules that you have for
finding them.
So if you imagine yourself
walking along this boundary
circle with your left hand
out over that sphere.
So you'll be walking in this
counterclockwise direction
when your head is sticking
out of the sphere.
All right?
So in other words, the outward
orientation on the sphere is
compatible with the
counterclockwise orientation
on the circle that
is the boundary.
So let's actually put in a
little arrow here to just
indicate that is our orientation
for the circle.
And our normal is an
outward-pointing normal.
And let's call our circle
C, and our S is our
sphere is our surface.
OK.
So just so we have the
same notation.
Good.
So why don't you work this
out, compute the line
integral, compute the surface
integral, come back, and we
can work them out together.
Hopefully you had some luck
working on this problem.
We have two things to compute.
I think I'm going to start
with the line integral.
So let me write that down:
line integral.
So what I need to do to compute
the line integral is I
need to compute the integral
over the curve C of F dot dr.
And so I know what F
is on that circle.
So I need to know what dr is.
So I need to know what r is.
I need a parametrization
of circle.
Well, you know, that is a
pretty easy circle to
parametrize.
It's the unit circle
in the xy plane.
So we have C. And we're
wandering around it
counterclockwise.
So it's our usual
parametrization.
It's the one we like.
So we have x equals cosine
t, y equals sine t--
where t goes from 0 to 2 pi--
and this is in three dimensions,
so the other part
of the parametrization
is z equals 0.
So this is my parametrization
of this circle.
OK, so let's go ahead
and put that in.
So the integral over C
of F dot dr is the
integral from 0 to 2 pi.
So we've got three parts.
So F is 2z, x, y.
So it's 2z dx plus
x dy plus y dz.
But z is 0 on this
whole circle.
So that piece just dies.
And dz is also 0, so that
piece just dies.
So we're just left with x dy.
So this is equal to
the integral x dy.
Oh.
So I guess this is not
from 0 to 2 pi.
This is still over C.
Sorry about that.
OK.
And now I change to my
parametrization.
OK.
Yes.
Right.
So this is still in dx dy dz
form, so it's still over C.
Now we switch to the dt
form, so now t is
going from 0 to 2 pi.
OK, so now we have x dy.
So x is cosine t, and dy--
so y is sine t--
so dy is cosine t dt.
So this is cosine t times cosine
t is cosine squared t.
dt, gosh.
So now you have to remember
way back in 18.01 when you
learned how to compute trig
integrals like this.
So I think the thing that we
do when we have a cosine
squared t is we use a
half-angle formula.
So let me come back down
here just to finish
this off in one board.
OK, so cosine squared t is the
integral from 0 to 2 pi.
So cosine squared t is 1 plus
cosine 2t over 2, dt.
And now cosine 2t--
as t goes between 0 and 2 pi--
well, that's two whole
loops of it.
Right?
Two whole periods
of cosine 2t.
And it's a trig function.
It's a nice cosine function.
So the positive parts and the
negative parts cancel.
The cosine 2t part, when we
integrate it from 0 to 2 pi,
that gives us 0.
So we're left with 1/2
integrated from 0 to 2 pi, and
that's just going to give us
1/2 of 2 pi, so that's pi.
All right.
So good.
So that was the line integral.
A very straightforward thing.
We had our circle back here.
We had our field.
So we parametrized the
curve that is the
circle that is the boundary.
And then we just computed the
line integral, and it was a
nice, easy one to do.
You had to remember one
little trig identity
in order to do it.
All right.
That's the first one.
So let's go on to the
surface integral.
So the surface integral that you
have to compute in Stoke's
Theorem is you have to compute
the double integral over your
surface of the curl of F dot n
with respect to surface area.
So this is the integral we
want to compute here.
So OK.
So the first thing we're going
to need is we're going to need
to find the curl of F. Let me
just write it here so we don't
have to walk all the way
back over there.
So F is 2z, x, y.
So curl of F--
OK, you should have
lots of experience
computing curls by now--
is going to be--
I always think of it as these
little 2 by 2 determinants
with the partial derivatives in
them, but most of those are
going to be 0.
We've got a dx x term that's
coming up in k, and a dy y
term that's coming up in i,
and a dz 2z term that's
coming up in j.
So OK.
So almost half the
terms are 0.
The others are really
easy to compute.
I trust that you can also
compute and get that the curl
is 1, 2, 1 here.
OK, so this is F. This
is curl of F. Great.
So OK.
So that's curl of F.
So now we need n.
Well, let's think.
So we need the unit normal
to our surface.
So back at the beginning before
we started, we said it
was the outward-pointing
normal.
So we need the outward-pointing
Well, this is a sphere, right?
So the normal is parallel
to the position vector.
So that means n should
be parallel to the
vector x, y, z.
So n should be parallel to this
vector x, y, z, but in
fact, we're even better
than that.
We're on a unit sphere.
So the position vector
has length of 1.
So n should be pointing in the
same direction as this vector,
and they both have length 1, so
they had better be equal to
each other.
Great.
So this unit normal n is
just this very simple
vector x, y, z.
If it had been a bigger sphere,
then you would have to
divide this by the radius to
scale it appropriately.
All right.
So we've got curl
F. We've got n.
So the integral that we want is
this double integral over
the surface of curl F dot n.
So that's x plus 2y plus z, with
respect to surface area.
OK.
Well, now we've just got
a surface integral.
It's over a hemisphere.
Not a terrible thing
to parametrize.
So that's what we should do.
We should go in, we should
parametrize it, and then we
should just compute it like
a surface integral, like
we know how to do.
So before we start though,
I want to make one little
observation.
Well, maybe two little
observations.
We can simplify this.
All right?
x.
We're integrating x over the
surface of a hemisphere
centered at the origin.
This hemisphere is
really symmetric.
And on the back side-- the part
where x is negative--
we're getting negative
contributions from x.
And on the front side--
where x is positive--
we're getting positive
contributions from x.
And because this sphere is
totally symmetric, those just
cancel out completely.
So when we integrate x over the
whole hemisphere, it just
kills itself.
I mean, the negative parts
kill the positive parts.
We just get 0.
Similarly, this hemisphere is
symmetric between its left
side and its right side, and
so the parts where y are
negative cancel out exactly the
parts where y are positive.
So as a simplifying step, we
can realize right at the
beginning, that this is actually
just the integral
over S of z with respect
to surface area.
Now, if you didn't realize
that, that's OK.
What you would have done is
you would have done the
parametrization that
we're about to do.
And in doing that
parametrization, you would
have found that you were
integrating something like
cosine theta between 0 and 2
pi, or something like this.
And that would have
given you 0.
So you would have found this
symmetry even if you don't
realize it right now.
You would have found it in the
process of computing this
integral, but it's a little
bit easier on us if we can
recognize that symmetry first.
Now, notice that z doesn't
cancel, because this is just
the top hemisphere, so it
doesn't have a bottom half to
cancel out with.
Right?
So the z part we can't use
this easy analysis on.
If we integrated this z over
the whole sphere--
if we had the other half of the
sphere-- well, then that
would also give us 0.
But we only have the top
half of the sphere.
So it's going to give us
something positive, because z
is always positive up there.
OK, so let's actually set
about parametrizing it.
We want to parametrize
the unit sphere.
Well, OK.
So we have our standard
parametrization that comes
from spherical coordinates.
So rho is just 1.
Right?
You know what?
I always get a little confused,
so I'm just going to
check carefully that I'm doing
this perfectly right.
x is going to be cosine
theta sine phi.
Good.
y is going to be sine
theta sine phi.
And z is going to
be cosine phi.
So that's our parametrization.
But we need bounds, of course,
on theta and phi in order to
properly describe just
this hemisphere.
So let's think.
So for phi, we want the
hemisphere that goes from the
z-axis down to the xy plane.
So that means we want 0 to be
less than or equal to phi to
be less than or equal
to pi over 2.
Right?
That will give us just
that top half.
And we want the whole thing.
We want to go all
the way around.
So we want 0 less than or equal
to theta less than or
equal to 2 pi.
OK, so this is what
x, y, and z are.
These are the bounds for our
parameters phi and theta.
Now, the only other thing
we need is we need to
know what dS is.
So in spherical coordinates,
we know that dS--
I'll put it right above here--
so dS is equal to sine
phi d phi d theta.
Let me again just double-check
that I'm not
doing anything silly.
So dS is equal to sine
phi d phi d theta.
So we've got our
parametrization.
We've got our bounds
on our parameters.
We know what dS is.
And we have the integral that
we want to compute.
So now we just have to
substitute everything in and
actually compute it as
an iterated integral.
Great.
So let's do that.
So, this integral that we want,
I'm going to write a big
equal sign that's going to carry
me all the way up here.
That's an equal sign.
All right.
So our integral.
The integral over S of z with
respect to surface area.
So z becomes cosine phi.
So we've got our
double integral
becomes an iterated integral.
z becomes cosine phi.
dS becomes sine phi
d phi d theta.
And our bounds.
So let's see: phi we said is
going from 0 to pi over 2.
And theta is going
from 0 to 2 pi.
OK.
So now we just have a nice,
straightforward iterated
integral here to compute.
So let's do the inner one first.
So we're computing.
The inner integral is the
integral from 0 to pi over 2,
of cosine phi sine phi d phi.
And OK.
So there are a bunch
of different ways
you could do this.
If you wanted to get fancy, you
could do a double-angle
formula here, but that's
really more
fancy than you need.
Because this is like sine phi
times d sine phi, right?
Another way of saying that is
you can make the substitution
u equals sine phi.
Anyhow, this is all CALC I stuff
that hopefully you're
pretty familiar with.
So OK.
So this is equal to--
in the end-- we get sine squared
phi over 2, between 0
and pi over 2.
OK.
So we plug this in.
So sine squared pi over
2, that's 1/2, minus--
sine squared 0 over
2 is 0 over 2.
So it's just 1/2.
So the inner integral is 1/2.
So let's see about
the outer one.
The outer integral is just the
integral from 0 to 2 pi d
theta of whatever the
inner integral was.
Well, the inner integral
was 1/2.
So the integral from 0
to 2 pi of 1/2 is pi.
Straightforward.
Good.
So OK.
So that's what the surface
integral gives us.
So let's go back here
and compare.
So way back at the beginning of
this recitation, we did the
line integral for this circle
that's the boundary of this
hemisphere, and we got pi.
And just now what we did is we
had the surface integral--
the associated surface integral
that we get from
Stoke's Theorem-- this
curl F dot n dS.
So we computed F and
curl F and n.
And then we'd noticed a little
nice symmetry here.
Although if you didn't notice
it, you should have had no
trouble computing the extra
terms in the integral that you
actually ended up with it.
It would've been another couple
of trig terms there
after you made the
substitution.
So we parametrized our
surface nicely.
Because it's a sphere,
it's easy to do.
And then we computed the double
integral and we also
came out with pi.
And we had better of also come
out with pi, because Stoke's
Theorem tells us that the line
integral and the surface
integral have to give
us the same value.
So that's great.
So that's exactly what we were
hoping would happen.
And now we've sort of
convinced ourselves,
hopefully, that through an
example now, we have a feel
for what sorts of things Stoke's
Theorem can do for us.
I'll end there.