The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Anyway, today we
have a guest speaker.
His name is Abe Stein.
He's the audio director for the
Singapore MIT Initiative.
And he's going to run through
brainstorming exercises.
We're not actually planning out
the game that you're going
to be doing for your first
assignment in this class.
This is a-- you're
doing other--
ABE STEIN: Yeah, these will
just be practice.
PROFESSOR: So basically, there
will be a group activity
involved in this, but the things
that you're working on,
those have to be the same
groups that you will
eventually be using for
your first assignment.
The idea is just to get
used to the process of
brainstorming and some of the
general rules of thumb.
And before I spoil
the entire talk--
GUEST SPEAKER: That's OK.
So my name is Abe Stein.
A little bit of background
on myself.
I am the audio director here.
I've been working in sound
design officially for a number
of years now, five
some odd years.
Unofficially, way longer than
that doing TV and video game
sound design.
And then before that, I was
a high school teacher.
And so I think to the extent
that talking about creative
collaboration, I have a fair
amount of experience ranging
even back to when I was teaching
high school, for
trying to encourage what we
might call organized ideation.
I guess first off, I'll thank
you guys for reading the text.
It is funny.
It does have these I guess now
a little antiquated, 1950s
references.
And some of his scientific
evidence for why brainstorming
is good is not particularly
well-supported.
He's like, we got 95 ideas.
And it's like, well how many
ideas did you get doing
it the other way?
He doesn't tell you.
But hey, 95, that's
a big number.
So a little bit of background
about Alex Osborn.
He was an advertising
executive.
And so you can see where
brainstorming and advertising
is a creative industry,
as a design industry.
And so getting multiple people
in interdisciplinary different
skills working together on a
creative project, it could be
a challenge.
And so you can see how
brainstorming came out of the
work he was doing
in advertising
So just to get started, I would
say you've read-- and so
you have a sense-- but forget
what you think you know
brainstorming is.
Some of what you think
it is will apply.
Some of the most fundamental
principles to brainstorming
maybe you don't realize, or you
didn't realize until you
did the reading.
And that's a little bit of what
I want to talk about.
I think the foundation for his
brainstorming ideas is
actually really solid.
It's something that we
should explore today.
Why brainstorming for
video game design is
an interesting question.
But I touched on that a little
bit with its relation to
advertizing, right?
I mean we're talking about a
creative industry where you
have people with various skill
sets, whether they're artists
or sound designers
or game designers
explicitly or producers.
All of these people
existing in a
collaborative environment together.
They're bringing different
things to the table.
How do you get them to
work together and be
collaboratively creative?
And so this is a first
step in that process.
And so this is why brainstorming
is particularly
useful for game design.
And then the other thing that
I think is important to
understand--
and we'll talk about
it a bit more--
is the social pressures that
are created in professional
creative environments, even
non-professional actually.
I mean it would exist in an
educational environment too.
You guys are all at MIT.
It's one of the most prestigious
universities in
the world, right?
And so you're probably no
stranger to the idea of social
pressure in the process
of ideation, right?
You sit there and you say, if I
say this idea, am I going to
look like an idiot?
And usually the outcome from
that is, if I don't say
anything, maybe I don't get the
gain of presenting a good
idea, but I don't get the hit
of making a bad idea.
So it's self-preservation.
Why take the risk if
it's not worth it.
And so I think MIT is an
interesting place to talk
about brainstorming and this
kind of organized ideation
because there is social and
academic pressure here too,
pressure to be right, pressure
to not say something that
would seem wrong.
And that sort of pressure is
completely antithetical to the
idea of a brainstorming
session.
And so that's a basis for why
not only it's good for video
games, but why it's also good
to talk about here at MIT.
So there are four basic
principles of brainstorming.
These were outlined
by Alex Osborn.
He was an ad agent, and he says
it was 1938 when he first
started using it.
People started talking
about it since then.
And I like when he said that
it spiraled out of control,
that people ran away with it.
They were like, oh, this
is a great idea.
But then they were practicing
it wrong.
And so in applied imaginations,
which is the
text you guys read, it's
him reflecting on this
brainstorming idea and saying
this is really how it should
be exercised.
The first principle is
single-handedly the most
important principle, and
that's no criticism.
That's a blanket way of saying
it, but really in a more broad
sense, it's saying judgement
needs to be excluded.
In some sense, it's both
positive and negative, but
especially you don't want to
criticize each other's work.
You also don't want to spend
time during a brainstorming
session talking about how
good an idea is, right?
If someone throws out an idea,
and someone's like, oh, this
is the best idea.
We don't even need to
keep going anymore.
Then it's like, whoa, no.
Wait, now we're not
brainstorming anymore.
And so really judgement is
absolutely supposed to be
excluded from the process.
I think that this is the primary
principle that goes
against that social
pressure, right?
Because the social pressure of
judgment, the people who are
saying what you have, an
executive who's in charge of
you, a boss who's saying whether
or not the ideas are
good or bad, or whether you
have colleagues that are
saying whether or not ideas are
good or bad, that sort of
social pressure that forces
people to stay quiet and maybe
hold onto good ideas or
throw away good ideas.
If everybody's on board with a
lack of criticism, then you
have more freedom to
express yourself.
Just pulling back to the text
a little bit, there was this
great quote from this vice
president I'll read to you
guys again.
He said, "It was hard to get
through my head what you were
trying to do with us.
My 15 years of conference after
conference in my company
have conditioned me against
shooting wild.
Almost all of us officers
rate each other on
the basis of judgment.
We are far more apt to look up
to the other fellow if he
makes no mistakes than if he
suggests lots of ideas." That
is something that may sound
familiar to you.
"So I've always kept myself from
spouting any suggestions
which could be sneered at.
I wish our people would feel
free to shoot ideas the way we
have been doing in these
brainstorm sessions.
And so really, this lack of
criticism, this creating a
safe environment for ideation,
is the most fundamental
principle in this
brainstorming.
And it really goes right at
those social pressures which
can stop creativity and really
hamper creativity.
Any questions about that?
That makes sense right, this
principle of no criticism.
Cool.
Principle #2, freewheeling, as
Mr. Osborn likes to call it.
The wilder idea the better.
This is also hard
to get used to.
Again, it was like the guy
said in that quote.
You resist the urge to throw
out something that's
absolutely crazy and absolutely
wild for fear of ridicule.
Well, if we eliminate the fear
of ridicule, and we understand
that we're just trying to get
every idea that we can, then
freewheeling is absolutely
encouraged.
And you need to get passed that
oh, this will never work.
Or nobody would ever
like this.
And I put up a katamari up here
because that's the sort
of idea that someone throws
out at a meeting, and if
there's criticism, someone
will be like, that's the
dumbest thing I ever heard.
You can't just roll around
picking up stuff for the king
of the cosmos.
That's insane.
And it probably was a synthesis
of a lot of
different ideas that created
that game, which we'll talk
about later.
But really, having these wild,
crazy ideas, you may think
it's over the edge.
And it might be over the edge.
But it is way easier to make
something feasible than it is
to take something that's pretty
normal and make it
innovative and interesting.
It's much easier to go in
that backward direction.
So really the wilder the
idea you can come
up with, the stronger.
Any questions about
principle #2?
Making sense?
On board?
Cool.
Quantity.
This is really the goal of
a brainstorming session.
Come up with as many ideas
as you can, right?
It stands to reason that if
you have lots of ideas,
there's a greater likelihood
that you'll have a useful one.
That if, say, you have two,
your choices are limited.
You're going to pick the better
of the two, I suppose,
but it might not be the
best idea you have.
And so really, this adds onto
that wild idea, throw
everything out you can.
You need to just get everything
out and everything
on the page in order to even be
able to start judging it.
And that's the important thing
too that needs to be clarified
is that brainstorming
is a first step
in a creative process.
It's not the whole process.
It's not like, oh, we have this
creative problem that we
need to solve.
We'll have a brainstorming
session, then we'll have it.
And actually, that's something
that hampers
brainstorming a lot.
You have a brainstorming
session.
You come up with these
great ideas.
And then everybody leaves, and
you never return to it or you
never reflect on which these
ideas is going to be best, or
you just end up picking one.
And so the judgment needs to
happen as well, but not now.
In the brainstorm session, it's
just get everything out
that you can.
And really it just
stands to reason.
And I made fun of Alex Osborn
when he was saying, well, in
this instance in the government,
they had 95 ideas.
And we came up with eight
new [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
How many did you come
up with before?
But it's true.
The more you have, the better
you're going to do.
Cool.
And then this one is related to
that, which is the idea of
synthesis, or building
on ideas.
Which is that oftentimes the
best idea, the best creative
idea, is not going to be
something that's just a unique
idea that stands alone in this
corpus of ideas that you've
collected over the brainstorming
It's going to be
an idea that is a synthesis
of one idea an another.
Or someone suggests an idea, and
then that makes you think
of something else that's
related to it.
And you build on that.
And you can see, in really
positive, good brainstorming
sessions, there's a momentum.
And one of the things that can
really hurt that momentum is
when people are starting to
riff on an idea, and then
someone is like, oh, but in
other news, we could do this.
And so it's really encouraged
that you synthesize ideas.
If you have that other
left field idea,
don't throw it away.
Jot it down so that you can
bring it up later, but don't
kill the momentum of the
synthesis if that's happening.
It's really important
that you start--
it's the collaborative part
of this creative ideation.
It's this combining of
ideas that's going
to create good ideas.
And I think we can take that
as a given, that if you
collect a bunch of skilled,
thoughtful, creative people
together, combining their
ideas is going to create
something that's better than
just any one idea that one
creative professional
is going to have.
Or at least just a different
solution that might be more
ideal given the problem.
And so you can think of things
like, Lego is pretty awesome.
Star Wars is also
pretty awesome.
But Lego Star Wars [INAUDIBLE]
is also awesome.
Similarly, Marvel is dope.
Capcom is also pretty dope.
Marvel Versus Capcom is
tremendously dope.
So building on ideas can
create obviously really
interesting things.
And it's a good idea to keep
working on that in your
brainstorming sessions, what
can you put together?
So how is it organized?
We talked about the
basic principles.
Any questions about those
four principles?
Did they all make sense?
Did they all seem to
be grounded in--
you're nodding yes.
It's the greatest thing
I've ever heard.
OK, cool.
So the question then becomes,
how do you organize your
brainstorm.
One of the points that Alex
Osborn makes is that it needs
to have a casual spirit or
a casual atmosphere.
He refers to it as a
picnic, which is
another one of those--
I haven't been on a picnic
in a really long time.
But it's like, we brought out
lunches in, and then we talked
afterwards.
We call those lunch
meetings now.
But he has a good point that
if a large part of the
brainstorming session is
intended to combat social
pressures that stop you from
being creative and inhibit
your creativity, then it would
stand to reason that creating
a casual spirit, a casual
environment for this process
is important.
And so most video game processes
and most video game
companies have a pretty casual
spirit and environment because
of the nature of the
work in general.
So sometimes this might
not be that hard.
But things to consider
are, what is the
makeup of your team?
If your president of the company
does a really bad job
of putting himself or herself
on the same level as all the
people, you might want to
exclude that person from the
brainstorming session.
Because then everybody is going
to feel the pressure of
the president.
And oh, do we need to
make an idea that
makes that person happiest.
You have to think to think these
things through in terms
of what the environment is
going to be for your
brainstorming session
and who's involved.
So it is an important point
and an important step.
Starting with a bad or a
worthless idea encourages that
freewheeling sense.
A lot of times, people
will contribute
ideas that feel safe.
Again, you want to come
up with the most
ideas that you can.
So having someone with the
courage, or even bringing to
the beginning of it a crazy,
worthless, bad, freewheeling
idea can help encourage people
to keep doing that.
So either starting with some who
has a crazy idea or even
bringing it to the brainstorm at
the very beginning can be a
really good thing as well.
This is a key one.
Don't interrupt anyone.
It's really important in an
brainstorming session to
encourage that every
voice is heard.
Let me see if I can find that
quote from that one guy.
Yeah, here we go.
It's great.
AUDIENCE: Think up or shut up.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, there's that
one too, which is a good one.
But it's talking about "the
spirit of a brainstorm session
is important.
Self-encouragement is needed
almost as much as mutual
encouragement.
A perfectionism complex will
throttle effort and abort
ideas." He says, "One of the
ablest members kept mum
throughout one of
our sessions.
I button-holed him"--
never heard that expression--
"afterward and begged him to
spout whatever ideas might
come to his mind in
our next meeting."
And this is where
it gets good.
This is the really able member
of this ad team.
He says, all right, I'll try.
But here's what happened.
"After our first meeting, I
jotted down about 15 ideas
with the thought that
I would bring
them to our next session.
When I looked them over, I
decided that they were
worthless, so I just
tore up the list."
And Alex goes on to to say it
took awhile to encourage this
guy to understand that there's
no such thing as a worthless
idea, that it can either be
expanded upon or revised.
And that's that synthesis
thing, that
having a wild idea.
And getting back to this idea
of the interruption, nothing
will stop a person from wanting
to contribute more
than not being to even have
their voice be heard.
They're trying to say something,
and then they just
get cut out by somebody else
who is like, oh, this is
better, especially for a shy
person or a person who is
otherwise feeling like my
ideas are worthless.
They won't be able to
get it out because
they've been cut short.
So some of this responsibility
falls on what we might call
the leader, which I'll talk
about later, of the group.
But it's a collective
responsibility that everybody
makes sure that as someone is
expressing an idea, that it's
[INAUDIBLE].
And to that, keep
the description
of your idea short.
If people are sitting here, and
you've now hijacked the
30-minute brainstorming session
with your one idea
that took five minutes
to explain, that can
also hamper it, right?
Part of it is not only don't
interrupt people, but also
make sure that when you are
contributing, you are allowing
for other people to contribute
as well, something that maybe
is not considered as much.
For the organization, it
does need a leader.
I hate that term, but that's
what he used in the book.
I tend to use the term clerk,
which is a Quaker idea, which
I grab onto.
A clerk being more
of a facilitator
than an actual leader.
Leader suggests boss, which is
not great for everyone's even
brainstorming session.
And then of course the
secretary, or as he calls it,
an associate leader, this is
someone who writes stuff down.
There's some of that good,
old-fashioned hierarchy going
on in this text.
But obviously, we'll talk a
little bit more about what the
roles of these people are, but
having those roles defined
early is important.
And then this is something to
talk about a bit, explaining
the process and the principle
question at the
start of the session.
How many of you had heard of
these four principles of
brainstorming explicitly prior
to reading this text?
Anybody?
Well.
I know.
You heard from me.
But the process is something
that needs to be clear.
Otherwise, people won't
remember to do it.
You'll see when we do the
exercise, it's even hard
sometimes to curb your
criticism, especially when
you're comfortable
with people.
And you may not mean it in a
malicious way, or your may not
mean it in a way to stop the
brainstorming session.
But you'd just be like,
Oh, that's nuts.
You're laughing, and everybody
is having a good time.
And then when you think back,
you're like, wait.
That was me passing judgment
on an idea and possibly
inhibiting the kind of ideation
that we're trying to
get across.
So explaining the process at
the beginning regardless of
the group is really important.
And that is usually a
responsibility that falls on
the leader or the secretary,
whoever is
organizing the session.
They even suggest in the
text, have it posted.
Have the four principles up so
that everybody can remind
themselves through the
process what these
four principles are.
But explaining the process
is really important.
And then this is so important.
Having the principal question
and the goal of the
brainstorming session
clear at the start.
Obviously, it's encouraging
freewheeling.
It's encouraging free thought.
It's encouraging all kinds
of wide open creativity.
And at the same time, if you do
that in an unbounded sort
of way, you might end up with
things that really in the end,
you don't have too many
useful ideas.
You have useful ideas for
something else, not for the
actually creative problem
that you have.
So if you take it from an ad
concept, you have a vodka
company that's like, oh, we need
an advertisement for our
awesome vodka or whatever.
And so you're like, all right.
We're going to have a
brainstorm session.
And a bunch of people
come up with ideas.
Now you're selling
dryers because it
was wide open, right?
It's like, oh, we've got these
great ad ideas for dryers, but
they're just really not going
to work for vodka.
Bringing it back to the video
game contract, you've got a
contract with a producer to make
a first person shooter,
and in your brainstorming
session, you've designed a
cool new platform.
Neat, but that's not where the
money is coming from, right?
So bounding the brainstorm
session is important too.
And you'll see that in the
exercises that we do today,
how it's important
to bound that.
Oh, and write down everything.
Sorry, I forgot about that.
This is an important point.
This happens to all of us, but
you have this great idea, and
then you don't write it down.
And then you go to bed, and
then the next day, you're
like, oh, I had this great
idea and you can't
remember it, right?
So writing down everything
is absolutely essential.
You'd be amazed the number of
times that a week later,
you're like, oh, we could put
these two ideas together as
long as you can remember
what those ideas were.
And so what you think, it's
hard to not mentally pass
judgment on things during the
brainstorm session, and what
you think might be great
now, may be a week
later not be as great.
And what you didn't
think will be.
And so making sure to have
everything written down is
really important.
And they even suggest having two
secretaries if you need it
if you have a large group with
lot of ideas and they're each
writing every other one.
That can be helpful to make sure
that you get everything.
Next is the question of what
sort of problems are suitable
to a brainstorming session.
The great example that Alex
Osborn gives is setting up a
brainstorm session on whether or
not to get married is not a
particularly suitable
question.
And that was an interesting
concept.
He's like, well, to decide to
get married, you apparently
list the pros and cons.
That's not exactly the process
I went through
before I got married.
I was like, well honey,
I'm going to have
to write this down.
But, fair or not, that was the
suggestion that he came up.
And he had a good
point, right?
The question of whether
or not to get married
is a judgment call.
It is not a creative
ideation process.
And so that's not a particularly
useful problem
that's suitable to the
brainstorming process.
You want a problem that is
going to be benefited by
having a large, selection,
a large corpus of ideas.
And so those are the kind of
problems that are more useful.
And you'll see when we do our
example exercise what some of
those might be.
I also put here that having a
clear definition of the aim is
really essential.
It's what we talked
about before.
You need to make sure that
everybody understands and
everybody's on the same page.
Otherwise, you'll end up with
stuff that might be useful for
something, but not useful for
what you're particularly
trying to do.
And so making that clear for
everybody is really important.
Keeping the problem as
simple as possible
is also really important.
Trying to keep simple language
for the problem.
Keep it constrained in a way
that is simple enough so that
people can work on it as
opposed to just feeling
limited by it, if that
makes any sense.
If something is overly
complicated and overly
constrained, then it becomes,
well, how do I fit
everything into this?
How do I match every single
one of these things?
If its' simpler, then it's a
little bit easier to work on
and try to be creative with.
So keeping problems simple.
Which isn't to say that complex
problems couldn't be
dealt with, but just divide
them into sub-problems.
Divide them into little
sections.
So there might be something
like, how could we
deal with the UI?
How could it look
in this game?
So rather than say, well how
are we going to design our
first person shooter, you've
got a brainstorming session
about what the UI could look
like for the first person
shooting game.
You have maybe a brainstorming
session for what the fiction
for this first person
shooter might be.
You're dividing it into
sub-problems rather than
having it be this gigantic
monolith of a thing.
And you can see how that would
be a problem, right?
Because if you just brainstorm
on what's our first person
shooter going to be,
you're going to get
ideas about the UI.
You're going to get ideas
about the fiction.
You're going to get ideas about
what sort of guns you
should use or what they
should sound like.
And it'll just be lots of
interesting ideas but
all over the place.
And yeah, the problem should
be clearly and simply
articulated.
I think that's what I said
by the shooting example.
Make sure that they're
articulated in a simple way.
Sometimes you can have a simple
problem that's not
articulated particularly
clearly.
So it's just something
to consider.
Responsibilities of the leader,
or whatever, the first
being to understand and explain
the problem and the
aim of the brainstorm session.
I mean a lot of times, people
maybe will write a memo
beforehand.
As the facilitator of the thing,
there's a person who
perhaps wants to see the
brainstorm be a success.
But mostly, having a clear
understanding of the problem.
And explaining that to the group
is an important job for
the leader.
I use this term facilitating
the session, encouraging
ideation, discouraging
criticism.
You are the watch guard for the
process, not necessarily--
you can sometimes be a
contributor and a watchdog for
the process.
But most important
is that you are a
watchdog for the process.
You'll see as we do it, it's
just so easy to slip into
these conversational habits
that are contrary to the
brainstorming process.
And so having someone who's
making sure people don't
criticize and encouraging people
like oh, I haven't
heard from this person.
Do you have ideas?
Even pulling people
out is important.
And that comes down to ensuring
that no voices are
lost during the discussion,
right?
I mean we had that ablest member
who had 15 ideas that
he wrote down, and he's like,
they're worthless.
Well, in some ways it's the
part of the leader, either
during the session or after
the session to try to
encourage those able members
to contribute.
Yeah, some of the most crack
pot ideas become the best
ones, so you really want to make
sure ever voice is heard.
And then encouraging the
synthesis, encouraging people
to riff on other ideas, trying
to find ways for people to
build on each other.
Even offering synthesis towards
the directives.
So maybe you have
a couple ideas.
And you're like, oh, 1
and 10 are similar.
Is there any way we could
combine this?
And somebody is like, yeah, we
could give him a helmet.
Awesome.
So it's simple.
I don't know what two
things you can
combine to get a helmet.
Can't get shot in the head.
How about a helmet?
All right, so responsibilities
for the secretary.
Most obviously, record
every and all ideas.
Write it all down.
You have to write it all down.
This is so important.
This one is often overlooked,
monitoring the schedule and
the duration of the session.
Something I learned a long,
long, long, time ago is one of
the worst things that can happen
is meetings that run
over or meetings that start late
or meetings that don't
adhere to a schedule.
No better way to lose your
employees or lose your staff
than to bite into their time.
And so making sure that it's
constrained and that it meets
the duration is really
important.
So, they seem simple, but
timing's a thing.
And then of course, they look
like participating in the
brainstorming.
Like I said, all voices should
be heard, and that oftentimes
will mean that the secretary
is a creative
professional as well.
And so making sure that you
participate [INAUDIBLE].
So we've got a few exercises now
to get you acclimated to
the idea of brainstorming.
The first one is an actual
individual brainstorm.
So if you have paper,
grab some paper at
the top of the pile.
AUDIENCE: If anyone is lacking
either writing
equipment or paper?
ABE STEIN: You could use
a note card too.
Really just something to write
on other than the table.
Note cards are totally fine.
As you guys are getting ready,
I'll continue to talk.
This is actually something that
I didn't mention in the
process but is actually
very useful to the
brainstorming process.
I think doing warm ups
before you actually
brainstorm is useful.
You know how people show up just
from lunch, especially if
it's one of those
picnic meetings.
People sometimes are tired.
People just might have other
things on the brain.
So getting into the habit,
getting warmed up to being
creative is important.
I tend to find it's a rare kind
of person who you just
give a blank piece of
paper to, and you're
like, oh, make something.
Go, be creative.
And they're like, vroom.
They just whip something out.
You have to get warmed up.
Visual artists sketch
constantly,
and that makes sense.
And then they build
on sketches.
I just make dumb pieces of music
that I'll maybe never
use for anything, but
maybe I will.
Who knows?
I make stupid sound effects
in the shower.
I consider that warming
up for work actually.
So you have to get warmed up.
And so this is just a really
quick, five-minute warm up.
And the idea is, write anything
that comes to your
mind for this specific
problem, and
I'll show you a picture.
Brainstorm possible uses-- it's
not really a brainstorm.
It's more just that you
individually come up with
creative ideas, creative uses,
for the following items.
And I'll give you five
minutes starting now.
All right.
Hopefully it was good
for a warm up.
Quick question by
a show of hand.
Be honest.
This is a safe environment.
How many of you had an idea that
you did not write down?
How many of you self-censored
yourself with an idea?
Yeah, Tommy, you were like,
oh, that's dumb.
See, it's hard to get out of
the habit of doing that.
It's hard to get out of this
habit of self-judgement.
And it's really important.
That dumb idea that you
think was worthless
might be a good one.
Does anyone who raised their
hand want to share what their
censored idea was just
to exorcise the
demons, so to speak?
No, no one?
All right, who wants to
share some ideas that
they did write down?
AUDIENCE: See, I have a lot.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, well
throw us a couple
that are your favorites.
AUDIENCE: C, lock pick,
MacGyver, connecting circuits.
ABE STEIN: There you go.
AUDIENCE: Caring hurts, a
knife, clothes hanger,
chopsticks, dowser, stirrer,
connect batteries, let air out
of tires, emo tool,
nose picker.
ABE STEIN: Sure.
AUDIENCE: Staple.
And a paper weight.
I have a lot of things.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, good,
that's awesome.
Try it out?
AUDIENCE: All right, I got,
let's see, fingernail cleaner,
an eyelash straightener,
basically rail gun ammo, a
balloon annihilator,
and an official
Tamagotchi TM resetter.
ABE STEIN: It resets a lot
of things actually.
Over to this side.
Owen, go ahead.
AUDIENCE: I had [INAUDIBLE].
I had scratch messaging tool.
I had used as a key ring,
conducted electricity with it.
Made it into jewelry.
Fixed umbrellas and what
have you with it,
which I've done before.
A money clip.
Use it as a screw for cooking.
Put it on top of the door, and
so when people open it and it
falls on the ground, you
know that somebody has
been in your room.
Lance boils, poke eyes out.
Hair accessory.
[INAUDIBLE].
ABE STEIN: That was
a good question.
Did you have a whole paper?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I had hairstyling
accessory, projectile,
something you could melt down
for metal and other stuff.
Something you could bend and
then put on chairs, and then
when people sit down,
it pokes them.
Modern art.
I thought you could get a bunch
and fill a dorm room
with it as a prank
or something.
Toothpick.
Hold stuff open for
emergency surgery.
ABE STEIN: Cool.
Some other ideas?
AUDIENCE: I thought you could
bend it into an interesting
flat shape, and then put it in
ink and use it as a stamp.
ABE STEIN: Very nice,
very good.
Cool, yeah, go ahead.
AUDIENCE: Game bits
and tokens.
Holder for dipping something
into liquids.
Tie clips and keeping small
boards together.
ABE STEIN: Very good.
Sure, yes?
AUDIENCE: A mini rock
garden rake.
Also a [INAUDIBLE].
ABE STEIN: That is very good.
Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: Heat generator.
If you work hard on it by
bending it and unbending it,
then it gets hots.
ABE STEIN: Very nice.
AUDIENCE: As long as
it doesn't break.
ABE STEIN: Yes?
AUDIENCE: I think about a
souvenir as a bulletin for a
lost robot.
ABE STEIN: That's good.
Say that again.
AUDIENCE: I was going to say
that it's a robot that is made
by humans, but it's
lost in space.
Then we have this thing that
reminded us of [INAUDIBLE]
a secret thing.
ABE STEIN: My favorite use for
a paper clip is cleaning the
lint out of my iPhone ear
jack, which drives me
absolutely crazy.
So I'm running on reserve
battery power, and my slide
show has been suspended.
In my office, there's a air
powered connector thing.
So yeah, how did we feel
about that exercise?
It got you to loosen
up a little bit?
It got you thinking
about some ideas?
It got you feeling the creative
juices flowing?
We have three more exercises
that we're going to do.
So much brainstorming.
This is the hardest work
I've ever done at MIT.
No, so we have a few more
exercises to get you guys
comfortable, to get you
guys relaxed with this
brainstorming process.
The next one is going to
be a group exercise.
I'm going to wait to describe
it until I can get
my slide show up.
Anybody else have
any particularly
choice paper clip ideas?
AUDIENCE: Oh, I just
thought of one.
ABE STEIN: What?
AUDIENCE: A sine
wave generator.
ABE STEIN: Oh, very good.
AUDIENCE: Wire frame doll.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] shaker.
ABE STEIN: Oh yeah, totally.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ABE STEIN: Hold up
a second guys.
AUDIENCE: If we stop looking at
it as an [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Take it apart like an Army man
and use it as a spear.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, like Man Vs.
Wild catching fish with it.
Bear Grylls.
Something
AUDIENCE: To chew on.
AUDIENCE: You could use it
as a catapult if you
bend the top part.
AUDIENCE: Rubber
band launcher.
AUDIENCE: Letting air
out of tires.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ABE STEIN: There we go.
AUDIENCE: Do you remember that
guy who had an oversized red
paper clip and ended up trading
it for a house?
Currency towards a house.
ABE STEIN: Cool, so hopefully
that got you loosened up.
I do want to just emphasize
again, for those of you who
raised your hand, and even
though of you who did not
raise your hand because you
were censoring the truth
because you were afraid,
try not to self-censor.
Really, it's important
to brainstorming.
AUDIENCE: It sounds
like the military.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, stop
self-censoring.
I bet those crappy ideas that
you didn't write down are
actually really awesome.
So activity #2, we're going to
work as one large group.
This is our conch shell.
It doesn't look like
one, I know.
But the principle
still applies.
This is just to get us in the
habit, in the shape of
speaking one at a time, not
interrupting each other.
And in some senses building on
each other's ideas too, right?
There's something in the
physical passing of the ball
after you've heard someone's
idea that might encourage that
sort of synthesis of ideas
as you're going.
I will be your fearless
leader.
All that means is that I just
make sure you're not
interrupting each other.
And we're going to brainstorm
solutions to a design problem.
This one I think is actually
a lot of fun.
So, I will show you the
design problem.
I will maybe throw out an idea,
and then I will toss the
conch shell to the first
person who wants it.
And then it doesn't have
to go back to me.
Just anyone who wants it,
throw up your hand.
And we'll keep moving around.
Please close the lids
on your drinks.
Put away your crystal stuff that
you don't want shattered.
So we'll take approximately
15 minutes on this.
We'll see how our
momentum goes.
So you've just finished
updating Tetris
for Xbox Live Arcade.
Awesome.
I don't know how you got the
rights, but that's great.
Microsoft is demanding a set of
achievement for integrating
the game into their online
service, because unless you
have achievements, it's
not a real game.
So, we are going to brainstorm
possible player achievements
for your new version
of Tetris.
You know what achievements
are, right?
Those little things that pop up
on your Xbox every time you
do anything?
So that is our idea for
Tetris achievements.
And I'll start.
How about for actually getting
four lines, you get a Tetris
achievement.
Who wants to be next?
AUDIENCE: You get an achievement
for losing as
quickly as possibly, which
they think will be like,
really obvious.
AUDIENCE: Getting three
lines with an S-piece.
AUDIENCE: Drawing some sort of
unique little picture with the
Tetris blocks, like something
new perhaps.
AUDIENCE: Putting one
of each block down.
AUDIENCE: Lasting for a certain
amount of time without
ever getting above
a certain height.
ABE STEIN: Very cool.
AUDIENCE: Lasting a certain
amount of time without ever
locating a piece.
AUDIENCE: Modern Tetris games
have a system where you can
rotate indefinitely when
your piece is down.
So you rotate indefinitely for
a minute or two or three.
AUDIENCE: Lasting a certain
amount of time without ever
clearing a line with
a straight piece.
AUDIENCE: Putting your piece
down underneath another piece
into a little hole.
ABE STEIN: Sliding it in?
AUDIENCE: The T-spin.
AUDIENCE: Spelling USSR
with your pieces.
That was a bad throw.
AUDIENCE: Making a
conglomeration of all pieces
into a shape of a
regular piece.
So the whole board
is one L-shape.
ABE STEIN: Very cool.
AUDIENCE: Basically only moving
the pieces in beat to
the music that's playing.
AUDIENCE: Spelling USA with
your pieces, but doing it.
ABE STEIN: Capitalist
centered.
AUDIENCE: High score and high
score without pairing lines.
AUDIENCE: Managing to clear
the entire board in a game
that has already reached the
top line, but not quite
overflowed.
AUDIENCE: Putting a piece down
without actually looking at
the piece at all.
AUDIENCE: Most pieces per
time, so [INAUDIBLE].
ABE STEIN: Sure.
AUDIENCE: One day of continuous
Tetris play.
ABE STEIN: Marathon challenge.
AUDIENCE: Breaking the
previous high score.
AUDIENCE: Only ever shifting the
pieces either to the right
or to the left the
entire game.
ABE STEIN: Ah.
AUDIENCE: Doing the marathon
challenge but only listening
to one piece of music
the entire time.
AUDIENCE: Clearing a level by
dropping pieces before they
fall five spaces.
ABE STEIN: Oh, all
right, cool.
AUDIENCE: Rotating every single
piece that you play.
ABE STEIN: Oh, very good.
AUDIENCE: Never going above a
certain line for a certain
amount of time.
ABE STEIN: Ooh, a sustaining
effort.
AUDIENCE: All of the
above, but on
different difficulty levels.
AUDIENCE: Clearing three lines
with a T, I guess.
ABE STEIN: There you go.
Sure.
AUDIENCE: Starting
up the game.
AUDIENCE: Clearing
an entire screen.
AUDIENCE: Using the L-block.
It doesn't matter how.
AUDIENCE: [? Turning ?] a
box a different color.
So clearing lines always
with the same color.
AUDIENCE: Rotating a
piece 720 degrees.
AUDIENCE: Only matching pieces
such that the U-blocks that
fall down are touching blocks
of the same color.
ABE STEIN: Cool.
AUDIENCE: Clear two, four
block segments with two
consecutive lines.
AUDIENCE: Clearing a level
using only tetrices.
AUDIENCE: Sorry, you
can't talk anymore.
AUDIENCE: Challenging somebody
on your friends
list to beat the score.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
someone on your friends
list to lose faster.
AUDIENCE: Having no holes in the
golf course at all times.
ABE STEIN: Oh cool.
AUDIENCE: Inviting one of
your Xbox Live friends
to play with you.
AUDIENCE: Five consecutive
line clears.
AUDIENCE: Beating one of your
friends on Xbox Live when you
play with them.
AUDIENCE: Losing to a
friend on Xbox Live.
AUDIENCE: Playing with
a friend for one hour
continuously.
Plus one day.
AUDIENCE: Beating a
score set by the
original creator of Tetris.
AUDIENCE: Clearing a line
somewhere above the first line
when the first line only has
one block filled in.
AUDIENCE: I think
it's possible.
It definitely is.
You get the flat ones.
ABE STEIN: Someone has
to have ideas.
There's an idea.
AUDIENCE: Lose more than
10 levels to a friend.
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Play the original
creator of
Tetris on Xbox Live.
AUDIENCE: Losing 100 times.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, there you go.
AUDIENCE: Playing on
increasingly ridiculous
difficulties with achievements
for each.
Or speeds, increasingly
difficult speeds.
AUDIENCE: Completing the Tetris
challenge, which is
presumably some kind of game
where you have to throw a box
in the right sequence in order
to clear all the lines.
AUDIENCE: Clearing
1,000 lines.
AUDIENCE: Playing
invisible mode.
AUDIENCE: Playing for a certain
amount of time while
holding down the Down
key continuously.
ABE STEIN: Only rotating in
one direction, always.
I don't know if someone
said that already.
AUDIENCE: Getting 10
achievements in Tetris.
AUDIENCE: Getting every
achievement in Tetris.
ABE STEIN: Oh no, how
can you get it?
AUDIENCE: It's a paradox.
It's impossible.
AUDIENCE: Always have lost on
the far left and on the far
right column.
Oh yeah, sure.
ABE STEIN: Cool, I think that
had some decent momentum, but
I think our mission
was accomplished.
We were really only giving one
idea at a time because it was
only the person who had the
ball that was talking.
That, probably with a little bit
more speed and momentum,
but it was nice.
We had a little building
on ideas.
We're starting to get
this brainstorm.
There was still some
shyness, which is--
people have different
personalities,
but stop being shy.
You're allowed to
have different
personalities, but stop it.
No, so that's activity #2.
Any questions about
that process?
How did we feel about it?
Any thoughts on it before we
go on to the next activity?
All right.
Next activity.
Actually, this is our
last activity.
Sorry, I said there were four,
but there are only three.
[INAUDIBLE]
I screwed up.
OK, so this one is a more
formal brainstorm.
And actually, I screwed
up that last one.
We didn't have a secretary, so
all of those great Tetris
ideas are now lost because I
can't remember any of them.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ABE STEIN: Oh yes.
Did we not have that?
Let me just get these
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So what we're going to do is
we're going to separate into
two design teams.
So it will just totally
be by location.
We'll just get half of
you over here and
half of you over there.
I want the two to designate
one leader.
That's going to be the person
who's responsible--
clerk--
for facilitating it.
Did I say clerk there?
A leader and a secretary.
It's supposed to a clerk
leader and a secretary.
So one person to write
everything down, and one
person to obviously
facilitate.
And we're going to do
20 or so minute
brainstorm for a game pitch.
What do I mean by game pitch?
Think of the, you're in an
elevator with Miyamoto or
you're in an elevator with
[? Philip Haas ?], and you
have this game idea that
you need to pitch.
But you're only going to
the 10th floor or so.
And so really, you have 30
seconds, a minute, two
minutes, to get the
core information
about this game out.
So that can be something like
a title, maybe a tagline for
it, any main features you
might have for it.
Of course, it would be way too
easy, or way actually crazy
for me to be like, any game at
all, because there are lots of
different types of
games obviously.
So it's going to be a game
based on the following
constraint.
So what I'd like to do first
before I give you the
constraint is let's divide
ourselves in half.
We can draw this imaginary line
diagonally dividing the
two of you back there, and we'll
just get one half here,
one half there.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ABE STEIN: And once I give you
the constraints, we'll
actually find a separate room
for the other team.
AUDIENCE: You're stuck
on that wire.
That's an achievement there.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ABE STEIN: If someone has a
piece of paper, they can jot
down their ideas.
Just write on a piece
of paper.
So these are your teams.
You guys will go in that room.
You guys stay out here.
As soon as I give you the
constraint, designate a
clerk/leader, a fearless leader,
and a secretary,
someone to write everything
down.
Because our groups are
relatively small, right, we
can have the leader and the
secretary involved in the
brainstorming process.
Please don't be afraid
of contributing.
But if you are designated as the
leader, keep in mind your
primary responsibility is
facilitating the brainstorm.
You want to make sure
it runs smoothly.
You want to make sure people
are not criticizing ideas.
You want to make sure
that it's going OK.
Any questions on this before I
give you your constraints?
Everything makes sense?
All good?
OK.
Here are the constraints
for the game.
It must have zombies.
It must have a love story.
It must be massively
multiplayer.
So those are the constraints
for the game.
That's what the publisher is
going to give you money for.
So you need to develop a pitch
for this game idea.
Title, tagline, what have you.
All right, so you guys,
we'll take you into
this room over here.
You guys stay here.
Designate a leader and a
secretary, and then start
brainstorming.
Oh, I love this.
It's like, I don't want
to be the leader.
I don't want to be
the secretary.
AUDIENCE: I said I'll do it.
AUDIENCE: But you wanted
to be the secretary.
AUDIENCE: One of you
is secretary.
One of you is leader.
Be a leader then.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and you lost.
AUDIENCE: It brings up
the age-old question.
If they're both vampires or
they're both zombies, does it
count as necrophilia?
AUDIENCE: Fun, let's see.
AUDIENCE: Pride and Prejudice
and Zombies manages to have--
AUDIENCE: It encompasses all
of those except the massive
and multiplayer part.
Licensed title right there.
AUDIENCE: Make it
Nazi zombies.
Two Nazi zombies.
No, a forbidden love.
A Nazi zombie is in love
with an Allied zombie.
AUDIENCE: Jewish.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
AUDIENCE: Yes, and then so
there are two factions.
Well, they are all
people online.
One group-- there are
two factions.
There's the Allied group
and the Axis group.
AUDIENCE: What if there
are two factions.
There are the zombies and the
humans, and they're drawn into
war because there's a love story
between a zombie and a
human, and and the leaders
get pissed over this.
And so we're at war because
of Romeo and
Juliet-esque zombie human--
AUDIENCE: So what you're
saying is we're having
intelligent zombies.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, intelligent
zombies.
AUDIENCE: So clearly they're
Nazi zombies.
AUDIENCE: Semi-intelligent
zombies.
AUDIENCE: The zombies should
decide to become Nazis.
AUDIENCE: We need a tagline.
AUDIENCE: Title.
AUDIENCE: We have to somehow
bring Hitler into this though.
Because if Nazis, there must
be a zombie Hitler.
AUDIENCE: What is your name?
AUDIENCE: Jason.
AUDIENCE: I'm Brian.
On Jason's idea of is it
necrophilia, I think we could
do a love story.
The title could be
Necrophilia?
AUDIENCE: Is it necrophlia?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I like
it as a title.
AUDIENCE: They say it
is a love story,
but is it a sex story.
AUDIENCE: How about this?
Or maybe even zombies
strippers that fall
in love with them.
AUDIENCE: Have you seen
Zombie Strippers?
AUDIENCE: No, I haven't.
AUDIENCE: It's a terrible,
wonderful, terrible movie.
AUDIENCE: Well, I'll
watch it then.
AUDIENCE: You should,
not, should.
Actually, how about we have the
zombies as the good guys.
That way, the Allies are trying
to make a weapon that
will destroy half the world, and
the zombies are like, no,
that would be bad.
Let's make everyone
else zombies so
they can be with us.
AUDIENCE: What if you're just
a zombie, and everyone is
trying to kill you.
So you want to make everyone
zombies so that the world will
be peaceful and happy.
AUDIENCE: And you want
everyone to love you.
AUDIENCE: I like that a lot.
AUDIENCE: And then it'd
be a love story.
AUDIENCE: Even better,
love zombies.
Who says they have
to be in bed?
They can be infected
by emotions.
That's the tagline right there,
"Infected by Emotions."
AUDIENCE: Nudist zombies.
AUDIENCE: What if 95% of the
world is zombie, and so then
the weird creatures that are
scary are the humans.
And they're sentient and they
do weird things, but the
zombies all are happy
and love each other.
AUDIENCE: Maybe the humans
have the love disease.
AUDIENCE: They're trying
to hump zombies?
AUDIENCE: Like they're infecting
zombies with love.
AUDIENCE: So then each person
would either start as a zombie
or a human.
They'd have to complete a bunch
of little taks so they
can come [INAUDIBLE].
They challenge each other, so
it'd be like, zombie against
zombie, and one of the is
infected and one isn't.
AUDIENCE: So humans can infect
zombies with love that makes
them not zombies?
AUDIENCE: No, they are
just love zombies.
AUDIENCE: What is the dynamic
between-- so there are the two
factions, obviously humans.
And every player is
given a match.
And in this massive multiplayer
world, one of
their main objectives is to find
their match who's in the
opposing faction very deep among
hostile hoards of either
humans or zombies.
Find them and live happily
ever after together.
AUDIENCE: And become either
zombies or humans together.
AUDIENCE: Correct.
AUDIENCE: But love zombies.
AUDIENCE: Find a cure
or just get bitten.
AUDIENCE: And become
love zombies.
AUDIENCE: Love zombies.
AUDIENCE: And so that's
the question.
Is there truly a difference
between in
love and being undead?
AUDIENCE: That's a
great tagline.
AUDIENCE: [ZOMBIE VOICE]
Love.
AUDIENCE: Maybe some
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: What can make
you more blind?
Having your eyes go dead by
a zombie or being in love?
PROFESSOR: So then we can draw
it into the actual Nazi zombie
game, maybe the Nazis
zombie is from the
other point of view.
So they're just trying to have
love, and the humans are
trying to kill them.
AUDIENCE: What?
Wait, are we having Nazis?
AUDIENCE: We can.
AUDIENCE: Most of the ideas can
include Nazis, and some
can't, and we can
decide later.
AUDIENCE: Phil, should we get
into the point of judgement
towards the end of thing so
we can finalize a pitch?
PHIL: No, just be
brainstorming.
AUDIENCE: Just brainstorming?
That's awesome.
Yeah, this is fun.
AUDIENCE: How about the player
is a human fighting against
the zombies, and you have
some kind of companion--
may or not be a cube--
but accompanies you on your
journey to defeat the zombies.
AUDIENCE: So a companion.
I like companion cube better.
That has a heart.
It's like a love story between
you and your cube.
AUDIENCE: But can the cube
become a zombie?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
I mean it could be a person
left for dead.
AUDIENCE: Four people against
all the zombies [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Then we need
spitters and stuff.
AUDIENCE: Or witches.
Maybe you're trying to get--
the love story is you and the
witch, considering the scene.
AUDIENCE: What if all players
play zombies, and most
missions are stuff like you have
to infect a city, and you
run around biting people through
the entire city that
you conquer and try
to zombify.
But your ultimate goal is that
your girlfriend from back when
you were human, or your
boyfriend from back when you
were human is at someplace.
And you want to infect all
cities until you can get
there, and then infect her so
that you guys can live happily
ever after.
AUDIENCE: Ahh.
How sweet.
AUDIENCE: Also, building on the
idea of being zombies--
AUDIENCE: We're not done yet.
AUDIENCE: You are zombies with
Cupid's love arrows trying to
infect the entire city with
love, at which productivity is
all gone in the city.
AUDIENCE: A zombie with love
arrows infecting people.
It could be set in the 1950s
where everyone is trying to be
productive and not
love each other.
AUDIENCE: What if you build
along the lines of having to
infect the city, but one zombie
can't infect the entire
city, right?
So you have to ally with
other zombies.
But there are different factions
of zombies, like two
zombie mob families that
are trying to infect.
They have two different
varieties of this love--
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Can it be
a drug trade?
So they have to infect people
with a certain drug, so it's a
drug war as well?
And there should be swords
because swords are cool.
AUDIENCE: Zombie Mafia?
AUDIENCE: What if when you have
a zombie virus, instead
of going in to eat people, you
are overcome with an urge to
passionately make
out with them.
And then if you make out with
somebody, then they turn into
a love zombie too.
And so there's no decomposition
going on so much
as there are hordes of people
running through streets trying
to passionately make out
with each other.
AUDIENCE: Decaying and decrepit
love zombies suddenly
become very attractive.
AUDIENCE: And they start
taking care of their
appearance and stuff.
AUDIENCE: After the zombie
make out, what's next?
AUDIENCE: Well, we make
it [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: What if we just make
it like a World of Warcraft
type MMO, but every player
plays a human.
You have a zombie companion.
AUDIENCE: Pet zombie?
AUDIENCE: You have to raise
your zombie from a little
zombie kit.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Shaun of the Dead?
AUDIENCE: No, but they had
a pet as a pet zombie.
AUDIENCE: I think it's
called Fido.
It's a movie called Fido.
AUDIENCE: No, it's
not that one.
AUDIENCE: I've not seen it,
but I've seen a trailer.
AUDIENCE: So what if you have to
fight with Pokemon zombies.
Get their power-up
[INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I like that.
AUDIENCE: Different kinds of
zombies like Left for Dead.
There are the big fat
ones that vomit.
AUDIENCE: Spitters, I
hate the spitters.
AUDIENCE: The smokers.
The smokers are the worst.
AUDIENCE: Instead of power-ups,
you have love potions.
AUDIENCE: When we said smokers
are the worst, that sounds
like a dating site.
AUDIENCE: Wait, I like
the Pokemon idea.
So you're human, but you just
have to capture all the
different types of zombies.
And then you fight other people
that are zombies.
And it's a match, zombie
versus zombie.
AUDIENCE: What if the love story
is not for the player
but is in the story of the game
in that the reason that
you're waging war at the moment
is because you're
trying to steal a cure to
zombyism because your fearless
leader, 20 ranks up, your
president's girlfriend has
been zombified or his wife
has been zombified.
And so the whole game, you're
the only means in a quest to
try to find this cure.
But you don't realize that
you're not trying to find a
cure for your use or your
girlfriend's use or
for people you love.
It's for your leader's.
AUDIENCE: And what if
she is actually the
leader of the zombies.
Oh crap.
AUDIENCE: What if the
zombies are aliens?
AUDIENCE: Zombie Aliens?
AUDIENCE: The flood.
AUDIENCE: What if the
zombies are ninjas?
AUDIENCE: Combine the zombie
Pokemon idea with the Sims,
where you have a zombie that's
under your control, and you're
trying to teach your
zombie to love.
And maybe you're a
different avatar.
You're a human avatar.
And you go through quests where
you take your zombie
places and teach your
zombie things.
AUDIENCE: Like not
to bite people.
AUDIENCE: Yeah exactly.
I don't know.
Train your zombie.
AUDIENCE: So the whole thing
with the ninja zombies, why
not have pirates as well,
pirate zombies.
AUDIENCE: Pirate versus
ninja zombies.
AUDIENCE: Zombie edition.
Special edition.
AUDIENCE: In space
wrapped in bacon.
AUDIENCE: Chtulu, but time
traveling zombies.
AUDIENCE: It would be a great
game to make, just pirate
zombies versus ninja zombies
in space wrapped in bacon.
And just make that game.
AUDIENCE: So, is
it necrophilia?
Probably.
Pirate edition.
AUDIENCE: So maybe we should
divide it into little
sub-brainstorms for a name,
tagline, all that.
As a name, do we have any
more brainstorming?
AUDIENCE: I think we
should figure out a
mechanic that works.
So far we have a lot of ideas
about what the game world is.
We have no idea how you
play with game.
AUDIENCE: So maybe more
brainstorming on that then?
AUDIENCE: It's massive
multiplayer.
AUDIENCE: Ones working such
as typical WoW-style RPGs,
typical massive multiplayer
IPS.
Pokemon style RPG.
AUDIENCE: Pokemon FPS.
AUDIENCE: Or, as we were saying
before, we could get
The Sims online.
AUDIENCE: The Sims online was
so good back in the day.
AUDIENCE: Did you play
the Pokemon?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, we could play
the Pokemon, but it's a first
person shooter.
But you still have
an RPG, first
person shooter as Pokemon.
AUDIENCE: It could entirely
text-based.
AUDIENCE: You have to fight--
you have battles with words
like Monkey Island.
AUDIENCE: I like that,
text-based zombie love.
AUDIENCE: Text-based
zombie love.
AUDIENCE: And then he sticks his
really, really long tongue
down your throat.
AUDIENCE: Zombie make
out disease.
AUDIENCE: I thought
of a title.
AUDIENCE: If it's massively
multiplayer, what if you
randomly get paired with five
other players who are playing
this game, and you
all have some
task you have to complete.
And you are given these
particular zombie Pokemon that
you can use this particular
task.
So you'd be working with
those five, six people.
AUDIENCE: Wait, will you
have zombie Pokeballs?
AUDIENCE: What?
AUDIENCE: We have a title.
AUDIENCE: So Necrofeelia
with F-E-E-L.
AUDIENCE: The first
zombie sex game.
AUDIENCE: Exactly.
AUDIENCE: And this can be
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], you have to
be tentacles somewhere.
AUDIENCE: What if you
are a zombie.
And all the players
are zombies.
And the NPCs are the humans, and
you try to go on quests to
make yourself more attractive
and learn human customs.
And you get points for
seducing humans.
AUDIENCE: You have to make sure
your brains meter doesn't
get too low.
AUDIENCE: So you have
to eat them.
AUDIENCE: Use them and
then eat them.
AUDIENCE: And then if you eat
them with certain qualities--
AUDIENCE: That actually sounds
like a fun vampire game.
You're a vampire.
You have to seduce a human
female to bring back to drink.
AUDIENCE: It's like Prototype.
AUDIENCE: Or that you have to
seduce a human because you
want to seduce a human.
But at the same time, you
have to eat humans.
So you have to hide the fact
that you're eating from the
human you're trying to seduce.
AUDIENCE: Oh, I see.
So you have a human girlfriend,
and then you eat
other humans.
AUDIENCE: While she's
not looking.
AUDIENCE: Have you been eating
other girlfriends without me?
Where's my stepdad?
Uh, about that.
AUDIENCE: Oh, that's
who that guy is.
I thought he was the
delivery guy.
AUDIENCE: Let's see.
Zombies meets American Psycho.
You've never seen
American Psycho?
He goes around killing random
people, but he has a
girlfriend on the side.
But he's crazy.
It's fun.
AUDIENCE: So it's like Psycho.
AUDIENCE: But better.
AUDIENCE: So Necrofeelia.
AUDIENCE: Get infected
with emotion.
AUDIENCE: Necrofeelia,
infected with love.
AUDIENCE: Brains, love,
it's the perfect game.
AUDIENCE: All right guys, I'm
going to have you stop.
We're going to bring
the other group in.
AUDIENCE: Love after Life?
AUDIENCE: I like it.
AUDIENCE: That's really good.
AUDIENCE: All right guys.
AUDIENCE: Our publisher
is going to
give us so much money.
AUDIENCE: It may seem odd to
have you do this brainstorm,
and then what I actually want
to talk about is rather than
give [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
because I'm sure
they're all really good.
AUDIENCE: Ahh.
ABE STEIN: I know, so sad.
But what really matters is the
process, because the point of
brainstorming is to
withhold judgment.
Judging which of your ideas is
best shouldn't have even been
happening at this stage.
And so one kind of question--
we'll come back to
what went well--
but what sort of stumbling
blocks did you guys run into
in this process as you
were doing it?
Did it all go perfectly?
I highly doubt it.
AUDIENCE: I would say we were
trying to design this whole
game, so sometimes we
would say features.
And then we [INAUDIBLE].
ABE STEIN: Yeah, in some senses,
it may have been
constrained in one area.
Sure, zombies and
a love story.
But then it was asking for a
whole lot, and so it could
have been, can we just
brainstorm a title.
Or could we just brainstorm
this or brainstorm that.
What about you?
AUDIENCE: We very briefly got
sidetracked on Pokemon.
For a second, it was Pokemon
only, Pokemon
first person shooter.
ABE STEIN: Any other thoughts?
I mean you can talk about
the whole group.
You can talk about your own
difficulty you had personally,
whether you had any
challenges with--
AUDIENCE: So I feel like if
somebody says a really good
idea, then everybody is stuck on
that idea. and you have to
get through that whole
idea before any other
ideas can come out.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, that's true.
AUDIENCE: We had a
stumbling block.
What other MMOs are
there out there?
So [INAUDIBLE] a
few other ones.
That was a dead spot in
the brainstorming.
ABE STEIN: Sure.
AUDIENCE: I was the scribe.
It was hard to jump in and
talk about your own ideas
because I was so busy writing
everyone else's.
ABE STEIN: It was really hard
with brainstorming.
You guys actually-- both
groups-- but I
stopped in with you guys.
You guys had this interesting
momentum going, and I was
watching you try to
write it all down.
It was way hard because the
ideas were coming in as you
were finishing the last idea.
So if a group has really good
momentum, I actually really
like the idea of having two
people where each person is
writing every other one.
Of course the difficulty is then
you pull two people out
of contributing.
So the organization of the
actual group is important.
AUDIENCE: Do you ever recommend
using a tape recorder?
ABE STEIN: Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean it certainly
makes sense.
One of the things that Osborn
says which I think is--
AUDIENCE: You can't put
a tape recorder down.
I remember that.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, but he also
says that one of the most
important things for the
secretary scribe is to number
things so that you know
how many you have.
Is that just to support
your work?
Look, we came up
with 110 ideas.
Amazing.
How many doesn't seem to
matter as much as the
qualities of the ideas.
So I thought it was weird
that he said it.
But yeah, tape recording,
video recording.
Any way of documenting the
process is I think the most
important part.
And actually, he does make a
good point of saying that one
of the problems with
brainstorming as it evolved
from when he first introduced it
at this one place and then
people started running with it
without thinking about the
principles is they would
brainstorm, and then that was
sort of it.
And you really have to
look back at what
you had come up with.
It's really important to reflect
on what you've done as
a second step.
And so that's important too.
How about the judgement thing?
I didn't notice a whole
lot of criticism.
It was really good.
Nobody was like, that's
a terrible idea.
But did you find it hard to not
pass judgment on ideas as
they were coming out?
Even your idea?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I mean I
definitely let more than one,
"I like that" slips.
ABE STEIN: That's OK.
What you want to avoid is like
the, oh my god, we've got to
do this one.
That will derail everything
because then it's just a loud
voice that proclaims
that we're done
because we got the idea.
But nothing encourages a person
who is shy more than
feeling like their idea
actually was good or
meritorious.
And so that sort of
stuff is fine.
You want to avoid the
stop the process.
AUDIENCE: I think I did say at
some point, ah, we've got our
title, which is probably
not good.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, it's
just a hard thing to
train yourself to do.
AUDIENCE: Is it Necrophilia?
A great title.
ABE STEIN: Are there
self-censors still out there?
Were there a lot of people who
thought of ideas but then just
didn't contribute?
Good, you didn't.
It's great if everybody
felt free.
Cool, that's really good.
So I would say that's one
thing that went well.
What other things went
well for you guys?
AUDIENCE: The tagline.
ABE STEIN: Specifically, just
coming up with taglines?
AUDIENCE: Infected by the--
Is it love after life.
ABE STEIN: That's cool.
Did you guys feel like
you had momentum?
It seemed to me watching that
there was momentum building.
AUDIENCE: I think we did a
really good job of taking a
lot of different ideas that we
had and synthesizing into
different things.
Saying, oh, that idea would
work well if we did this.
Oh, and then we could
use that name, and
that would fit there.
ABE STEIN: Yeah.
Who were the two leaders for
the two groups, the clerks?
Did you guys feel like you had
to do much facilitating.
AUDIENCE: Not really, the hard
part was really at the
beginning, where it was,
how do we want to
approach this thing?
And so I guess we decided
to start with the title.
It was either the titles
or the main features.
And we were just like, let's
come up with a whole bunch of
titles and go from there.
ABE STEIN: Sure.
AUDIENCE: I forgot
I was the leader.
I didn't lead anything.
ABE STEIN: If you don't have a
whole lot of facilitating to
do, it generally means that
the group is running OK.
I do think you have
a good point.
A lot of the facilitator's work
comes at the beginning of
the process, or even before the
process began, making sure
the constraints are clear.
And then you guys know
what you are going
to be working on.
OK, so bringing this back--
this is a game
design class, right?--
I touched on it earlier.
How do you guys see this as
being a useful mechanic or a
useful tool You know what?
It's funny I called
it a mechanic.
Did any of you catch that
paragraph in Alex Osborn where
the guy was saying, "When my
team feels like they're
playing, it's a way more
productive brainstorm than
when not." And I thought that
was really interesting because
there are elements of gaminess
to this, which I think is
interesting.
So how do you guys this could
improve the general game
design process?
AUDIENCE: I feel like after
you have a game and you're
testing it, and there's a major
flaw that is taking too
long or something like that.
And everyone sits down in a
brainstorm and says, this is
exactly what our problem is.
How can we fix it?
ABE STEIN: Yeah, overcoming
road blocks.
AUDIENCE: We never would have
come up with half the cool
ideas that we came up
during the process.
Just me thinking alone never
would have come up with
Pokemon zombies.
ABE STEIN: Sure, anyone else?
AUDIENCE: Well, this is good
just in general just
to think up a game.
Because maybe it's like,
oh, every single
game has been decided.
People make games
of all types.
How am I going to make
a unique game.
This brainstorm is like,
hmm, those two things.
I've never seen that before.
That could be interesting.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, and
that's a really
important good point actually.
The synthesis thing is actually
I think something
that is really important because
we tend to see a lot
of recycled mechanics.
And what becomes the interesting
thing in a game
oftentimes is not that it's a
completely new rule, right?
It's the way that rule interacts
with the other rules
in the system.
And in some instances, it's also
how that rule is read and
interpreted by the player, or
perhaps tends to be better in
terms of other players.
So yeah, I think the synthesis
is actually an interesting
part of this where people can
bring a lot of different ideas
from a lot of different
experiences with
games to fuse ideas.
AUDIENCE: When it comes to
coming up with ideas for
games, the nice thing about
brainstorming is that it gets
past the good idea that everyone
happens to make,
which is the problem that we
sometimes have in the classes.
The people will find one idea
that they like, and they will
never think past it because they
were happy to find one
that everybody agreed with.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, and so you guys
are divided into design
teams, and one of the things
I would encourage--
I don't know how it's set up
schedule-wise, but try to
divide the brainstorming process
from the judgment,
like I said.
It's true.
Even if you do the brainstorm,
it can help you get over.
But a lot of times, whatever
had momentum during that
brainstorm or whatever got
the most yuks during that
brainstorm is going to be the
popular, strong idea.
And then when you come back to
it with a little space, you
might be like, oh, that it
is a really good idea.
But there was this other thing
that got mentioned half an
hour earlier that's really
interesting.
Maybe we can incorporate
that somehow.
And so making the judgment
happen in a separate phase can
be really important.
Because it's true, creativity is
a little bit more organic.
It's not necessarily a strictly
logical process, right?
So applying logic later can be
a good thing, I think, to the
creative process.
Cool, any questions about
brainstorming at all?
You are incredibly enlightened
by Alex Osborn?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
using things like Google Wave
or Google Docs where things
are automatically recorded
because everyone is basically
typing in their ideas
as it's happening.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, and I think
it's interesting.
I don't have a whole lot
of experience with--
well, I should rephrase.
I don't have a lot of experience
with remote
brainstorming, but I one of
the games I worked on this
summer was this game called
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
where you were asked a lot
of personal questions.
And so we had to think of
personal questions.
So we were like, well, if you
have ideas, write them down in
Google Docs.
And at one point, myself and
two of the other designers
were all on the Google
Doc at the same time.
And you could actually
see that that sort of
brainstorming would happen.
Someone would type
something in.
And then someone would type next
to it, ha ha, that's so
funny, and then write an idea
that's related to that.
And you're seeing it happen
in this digital space.
So I think we've gotten so
accustomed to having these
digital personalities or these
digital personas in IMing and
text messaging and all that
other stuff that I think we've
gotten pretty adept at typing
fast enough to get ideas out
that I think it could
totally work.
There's something to be said
for the momentum that gets
generated in person.
But yeah--
AUDIENCE: You could
try both ways.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, I mean
it's so funny.
I was going to say, no that's
a terrible idea.
You have to be around
each other.
And I was like, actually,
it works.
I think it all depends
a little bit on the
personalities of the people
that were involved.
Certainly for a prolonged
brainstorm--
one of the thing Alex Osborn
says is time box it.
If you don't time box it, it's
going to be a problem.
I think for in person,
that's true.
It's so easy to get onto a
Google document now whenever
you have an idea that actually
having a long form brainstorm
where anytime someone has an
idea over a week or something
like that, write it down.
That's also useful too because
then you separated the process
into collecting and--
But you still should do that,
building on ideas.
AUDIENCE: It's probably easier
just to do this [INAUDIBLE]
when you're simultaneously
online or in the same room.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, and to
see the ideas come out
as they come out.
Because it's a little uncommon
to just read something and be
like, oh yeah, what about this
when it first shows up.
Or when it first comes into
existence as you're trying to
think of things that
can spur ideas.
AUDIENCE: The other danger about
doing it like, OK, this
document is open for the next 24
hours, everyone throw your
ideas in, is that then people
start spending too
long on any one idea.
They start thinking about what
they're going to write down
before they write it down.
No, that's not the point.
ABE STEIN: Yeah, think of the
paper clip experience, and
those of you that raised your
hand for saying that you were
self-censoring.
On your own--
I wasn't going to make you all
hand in those paper clip ideas
you were self-censoring.
So the same sort of
thing applies.
You might censor yourself or
spend a long time on ideas.
Any other thoughts, questions?
Cool, well I hope this
was helpful.
I hope it'll be helpful for
your game design stuff.
Email me if you do have any
questions about this stuff.
I can try to help out.
Other than than, good luck on
your game design on this class
and for the rest of
the semester.
Cool.
[APPLAUSE]
ABE STEIN: I do like that of
the keynote things it says,
"End of show."
PROFESSOR: Let's see now.
We're going to play
some card games.
But before that, just a
little bit of admin.
On Monday, you'll notice that
we have two readings, one of
which you've already done.
As for the other reading,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], it's a
little bit dry.
Tough it out caffeinate
yourselves before reading it.
Tough it out.
It is worth it.
It's a translation.
Let's see now.
There's at least one person who
hasn't filled a form that
you need to fill out.
So just come up here
and fill that out.
Is Courtney in class today?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Yeah, I'm not sure if
we have enough time to get
through all of them.
But most of them are
pretty short.
A lot of them today are going
to be set up, which is why
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] is first
because that takes a
while to set up.
That being said, if you do get
a chance to look at the rules
and study the cards,
even [INAUDIBLE]
a bunch of smart things
[INAUDIBLE]
easier to set up.
And you really want to pay
attention to that.
But the name of the game today
is pretty much variety.
We have all fairly different
games that use cards in a very
different way.
And if you don't get a chance
necessarily to play all of
them, at least get a chance
to look at other
people playing them.
And if you wanted to check them
out over the middle of
the week, we'll keep them
around the office.
But there'll be time to come
back here next week and
[INAUDIBLE].
But that's basically it.
It we can clear the tables
because that's for the cards.