PROFESSOR: Hi, welcome
back to recitation.
Today we are going to talk about
some, an infinite series
and discuss it's convergence.
So in particular I have
this infinite series.
The sum from n equals 1 to
infinity of 1 divided by the
product n times n plus 1.
So what I'd like you to do is to
compute a few terms of the
series, compute a few partial
sums, and use that to get a
sense for what you think
the series is doing.
Is it converging?
Is it diverging?
If it's converging, can you
figure out what value it's
converging to?
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to try
that out, see what you
get, come back and
we can do it together.
So this is a nice series.
It has terms that are
easy to compute.
And I've taken the liberty of
computing a few of them in
advance, and I've put
them up over here.
So for n from 1 to 5, the terms
that we're adding up are
1 over n times n plus 1.
So that's when n equals
1, that's 1 over 1
times 2, which is 1/2.
When it is 2, it's 1 over
2 times 3, which is 1/6.
Then we've got 1/12, 1/20,
1/30, and so on.
So those are the things
we're adding up.
And then the partial sums, the
nth partial sums. Well, the
first one is just the first
term, which is 1/2.
The second one, we take the
first term and the second term
and we add them together.
So 1/2 plus 1/6 is 2/3.
The third one, we take the first
three terms and add them
together and that
gives us 3/4.
And OK, so I computed the
first five partial
sums here as well.
Now, if you look at this column,
so remember that the
limit, that the value of an
infinite series is defined to
be the limit of its partial
sums. So if we want to know
what is the value of this
infinite series that we
started with, does it converge,
does it diverge,
what we have to do to figure
that out is we have to take
its partial sums and we have
to compute their limit.
And if we, if their
limit doesn't
exist, then it diverges.
If their limit does exist, then
the sum of the series is
equal to what that value
of that limit is.
And if you look at these terms
here, you'll see that they,
there's a little bit of
a pattern here, right?
So these, this is 1/2,
2/3, 3/4, 4/5, 5/6.
That's a pretty nice sequence
of numbers.
It's, you know, we could
probably guess at this point
that the next one is going to
be 6/7 then 7/8 and so on.
So that would be a guess.
One way we can actually
prove this is, so we
have this guess that--
let me write it down.
Guess is that Sn is equal
to n over n plus 1.
Now if you wanted to confirm
this guess, what you'd have to
do is you have to just figure
out how could you prove that.
Well, one thing you can do is
you can say, well, Sn plus 1
is equal to Sn plus the
next term, right?
So in our case, Sn plus 1 is
equal to Sn plus the next
term, the n plus first term,
which in our case is 1 over n
plus 1 times n plus 2.
So, all right, so that's not
maybe obvious what to do with
this, but you could split this
up, really you can split it up
by partial fractions.
And you can write this as say Sn
plus, so if you split this
up by partial fractions what
you'll get is that it's
exactly equal to 1 over n plus
1 minus 1 over n plus 2.
And from here it's easy to see
that, well, if Sn is equal to
n over n plus 1, then this will
be equal to 1 minus 1
over n plus 2, which is n
plus 1 over n plus 2.
And so using the process known
as mathematical induction, you
have that it follows for
all values of n.
So because of this nice
expression for the term, it's
easy to see that this pattern
will continue forever.
OK, and so that, you know,
that's just a sketch of how
you would prove this.
Now once you've proven this,
it's easy to see, that the,
once you know that this is true,
it's easy to see what
this limit is right?
As n goes to infinity, this
just approaches 1 and that
means the series converges and
the limit of the series is 1.
So here we have a nice example
of a series that converges and
where it actually is possible
to compute the
limit of this series.
This isn't possible for most,
for all series or even for
most series.
Even ones with fairly nice
terms, it's often very
difficult to figure out what
their limit is, but in this
case it's not hard to do and
we have precisely that the
value of the series is 1.
So I'll end there.