LINAN CHEN: Hi everyone.
I'm Linan.
Welcome back to recitation.
In recent lectures, we have
studied the properties of the
determinant.
And we also derived the
formula to compute it.
Today we're going to put what
we learned into practice by
considering these
two examples.
So we want to find out the
determinants of these two 5 by
5 matrices.
And as you can see, matrix A has
x along this diagonal, and
in the first four rows, y to
the right of x, except
for the last row.
And 0 entries everywhere else.
And matrix B also has x along
this diagonal and
y everywhere else.
Before starting, let me help you
review what you can do to
compute determinants.
Of course, you can carry out
elimination to transform your
original matrix into upper
triangular matrix.
Or you can use this big
summation formula.
Another choice would be you
can do it by cofactors.
Namely, you can expand your
original matrix along any row
or any column, and then the
determinant is simply given by
the dot product of
that row or that
column with its cofactors.
Why don't you pause the
video now and try to
work on them yourself.
Whenever you're ready, I'll come
back and show you my way.
I hope you just had some fun
with these two problems. Now
let's look at them together.
Let's look at matrix A first.
As you can see, there are a
lot of 0 entries in matrix A.
So perhaps you don't need
elimination to introduce
more 0s.
Furthermore, we observe this
pattern of A, and you notice
that if I cover the last row
and the first column, so if
this column and this row and not
here, what is left over is
simply a 4 by 4 lower
triangular matrix.
And similarly, if you cover the
first column and the first
row, what is left over here
is simply a 4 by 4 upper
triangular matrix.
This is telling us that we
should calculate the
determinant of A by
the third method.
So we should expand along the
first column of A, and we
calculate the cofactors.
Let's do it now.
So determinant of A, is equal
to the 1 1 entry of A, which
is x times the cofactor of
that spot, which is the
determinant of the leftover
4 by 4 matrix.
And its upper triangular, so
its determinant is simply
given by x to the power 4.
Plus, the only other non-0 entry
in that column is the y
at the very bottom.
So you put y here.
And you multiply y by the
cofactor of that spot, which
is the determinant of the
leftover 4 by 4 matrix again.
In this case, it's lower
triangular and its determinant
is y to the power 4.
So I have a y to the power 4.
But not quite.
In principle, there should
be another factor here
indicating the sign.
And the sign in this case,
well because the y is the
entry in the fifth row
and the first column.
So this factor should
be negative 1 to the
power 5 plus 1.
And of course, is just 1.
So the determinant of A is
simply equal to x to the fifth
power plus y to the
fifth power.
Did you get the correct
answer?
Well the determinant of A is
not too bad because A has a
lot of 0 entries.
Now let's look at the
determinant of matrix B.
I have another copy of B here.
So B also has a very
clear structure.
It has x along its diagonal,
and y everywhere else.
But in general, B does
not have an 0 entry.
So perhaps our first step
should be carrying out
elimination to introduce 0
entries into matrix B.
Of course, you can do it
by the regular routine.
You start with the first row,
find a pivot, and eliminate
the second row and the third
row and so on and so forth.
But in this case, there's
a shortcut.
If you compare two rows that
are next to each other, for
example, if we compare the
fourth row and the fifth row,
you notice that they have a
lot of entries in common.
And they're only different
at these two spots.
So imagine if I subtract the
fourth row from the fifth row.
So if I do the following
operation.
So I subtract this row
from the last row.
Then the new fifth row should
become the following.
So this row will become 0 0
0, y minus x, x minus y.
You see, just by the simple
operation, I have introduced
three 0 entries at once.
And it's similarly with the
fourth row and the third row.
They have common entries
here, here, and here.
So you subtract the third
row from the fourth row.
You update the fourth row to 0
0, y minus x, x minus y, 0.
Again, three 0 entries.
And same thing happened to the
second row and the third row.
So you subtract the second row
from the third row and your
new third row will become 0,
y minus x, x minus y, 0 0.
Finally, you subtract the first
row from the second row,
and then you update the second
row to y minus x, x
minus y, 0 0 0.
Let's keep the first
row unchanged.
So I'm going to copy here.
All right.
By row elimination, we have
introduced many 0 entries to
matrix B. Is there anything
else that I can
take advantage of?
Let's observe the pattern
of this new matrix.
As you can see, in each row,
you have two non-0 entries,
except the first row.
And they're only different
by a sign.
So if somehow you can figure out
a way to sum them up, you
will get even more 0 entries.
So let's do it.
That's going to involve the
operations on column.
So here is how I do it.
I'm going to keep the last
column unchanged.
So the last column is
y 0 0 0 x minus y.
What I will do is I will add a
copy of the last column to the
fourth column.
So this is what I'm
going to do.
Add one copy of the last column
to the fourth column.
Now the new fourth column will
become 2y 0 0 x minus y 0.
As you can see by doing this,
I have killed the spot.
So I have introduced one more 0
entry into my fourth column.
If you continue, you may want
to add the fourth column to
the third column.
Let's see what will happen
if you do that.
So if you add the fourth column
to the third column,
now what should appear here is
2y 0 x minus y 0 y minus x.
But in this new third column,
you still have two 0 entries,
which is the same as the
original third column.
So although you've killed this
spot, but you've introduced a
new non-0 entry.
So is there a way that we
can kill this spot too?
You may have noticed that if
you add a copy of the fifth
column to this column again,
then that spot
will have been killed.
So let's do it.
If I add this column to
this one, I'm going to
just update it here.
Then the first entry
should become 3y.
These are unchanged.
And the last spot becomes 0.
It reflects here as you are
adding a copy of the fourth
column and a copy of the fifth
column to the third column.
Now you've got the idea.
And you continue.
What do you do with
the second column?
This time you will have to add
a copy of the third column, a
copy of the fourth column, and
the copy of the fifth column.
So you update the second
column to be 4y
x minus y 0 0 0.
Eventually, what you will do to
the first column would be
you add everything to
the first column.
So a copy of each.
Then the first column
will become--
so I don't have in that spot
here, so we'll make it here--
x plus 4y.
Then everything else is 0.
This is fun.
And the result's really nice.
This is wonderful because
this is simply
upper triangular matrix.
Now you tell me what is the
determinant of B. The
determinant of B is the
determinant of this upper
triangular matrix.
So you simply multiply
everything together, that's x
plus 4y times x minus y
to the fourth power.
So I hope you enjoyed
these two examples.
Maybe your method is different
from mine, but at least these
two examples teach us that you
can be flexible in combining
methods in calculating
determinants.
Thanks for watching,
and I'm looking
forward to see you soon.