All of you have looked at
rainbows, but very few of you
have ever seen one.
Looking at something is very
different from seeing it.
And today I will make you see
the rainbow in a way that goes
way beyond the beauty that we
can all experience,
a way that you will always
remember.
And I would like to start
asking you fifteen perhaps
simple questions about the
rainbow.
The first question then is
would any one of you remember if
you see a bow whether the red
color is outside or whether the
-- the red color is inside?
And then I wonder about the
radius of the bow.
If this is a bow in the sky,
something like this,
here is the horizon,
it's clearly a perfect circle,
and so the perfect circle has
somewhere a center.
And so that means there must be
a radius R.
You can measure that
radius in terms of how many
degrees and so what is roughly
that radius.
You've never measured it but is
it ten degrees,
is it twenty,
thirty, fifty,
sixty?
The length of the bow.
Is there a difference,
do you sometimes see a very
long bow, sometimes a very short
one?
What is the width of the bow?
You see colors here.
How wide is that strip of
colors in degrees?
Perhaps some of you have
noticed that there is a
difference in light intensity
between inside the bow and
outside the bow.
Maybe you've never seen it,
and if there is a difference
where is it brighter,
inside the bow or outside the
bow?
What time of the day would you
see bows?
Would you see rainbows in the
north, east, south or west?
Is there perhaps a second bow
in the sky?
And if there is a second one,
where should you look for the
second bow?
And if there is a second one
what is the color sequence of
the second bow?
Is the red on the outside or is
the red on the inside?
And then you can ask the same
question, what would be the
radius
of the second bow?
And what would be the width of
the second bow?
All these first twelve
questions in principle you
should have been able to answer
if you really have seen a
rainbow.
The last three is more
difficult.
The question is are the bows
polarized?
In what direction are they
And are they weakly polarized
or are they strongly polarized?
Who knows the answer to twelve
questions, to the first twelve
questions?
Who knows the answer to more
than
ten?
Who knows the answer to nine?
Eight?
Seven?
Six?
Five?
Four?
Do I see a hand at four?
Good for you.
Five, four, three?
Three, good,
that's already good.
Two?
One?
And who knows the answer to
zero?
Most of you,
right?
I haven't seen a lot of hands
though.
All right.
So I've made my point.
You've looked at rainbows but
you've really never seen them.
And I'm going to make you see
them today.
What you see here on the
blackboard is one drop of water.
I put the sun for simplicity at
the horizon.
Later I will put it a little
bit higher in the sky.
Light from the sun hits this
raindrop.
I've only drawn one narrow beam
which hits the raindrop right
there.
And you see here the angle of
incidence, which with Snell's
law we call theta one.
I call it I here because it's
nicer for me,
more descriptive,
it means incidence angle.
Right at that point A some of
the light will be reflected and
some of the light will go into
the water.
We call that refraction.
And Snell's law will tell me
this angle R.
Whatever goes in there reaches
point B where there is a
transition back to air and so
some of that light will come out
here and some of that light will
be reflected inside.
And then when it reaches point
C again there is a transition
from water to air.
Some of that light will be
reflected inside the water.
And some of it will come out.
And as far as the geometry is
concerned, if this angle is R,
then this angle is also R,
this is also R,
and this is also R.
And the angle here is I.
That follows from Snell's law,
and I'll leave you with that.
Notice that the light came in
like
this but it comes back like
this.
So the direction has changed
over the angle delta.
And the angle delta is very
easy to calculate in terms of I
and R.
Delta is a hundred eighty
degrees plus two I minus four R.
I want you to check that at
home.
The four Rs come in here.
One, two, three,
four, and the two I's come in
here and
there.
If now I think of all possible
narrow beams of light that can
strike this raindrop,
one that would strike it here
would have an I of zero degrees.
And then here would be ten
degrees and twenty degrees and
thirty and forty.
And the largest value for I is
when the light strikes here,
would be ninety degrees.
And so I can calculate for all
these values of I,
which obviously all of them
occur, sunlight strikes this
raindrop, and all these angles
for I are present.
So I can calculate now for all
these angles of I what the value
is for R and then I can
calculate what delta is.
R follows from Snell's law and
delta follows from this
geometric relationship.
And what you will find now very
much to your surprise,
that there is a minimum value
for delta which is about hundred
and thirty-eight degrees.
That means this angle phi here
has a maximum value which is
very roughly about forty-two
degrees.
And I will show you some
numbers.
You can download this,
by the way, this is on the Web,
under lecture supplements.
Here all I have done I've taken
I to be from zero to ninety
degrees, all these angles are
possible, with Snell's law,
using an index of refraction of
one point
three three six,
that you see at the bottom,
I calculate R and then in the
last column using that
relationship I calculate delta.
And indeed you see that delta
starts at a hundred eighty
degrees when I is zero.
And then goes to a minimum of
roughly a hundred thirty-eight,
after which it increases again.
And this now is crucial,
is key to
an understanding of the
rainbow.
Imagine now that I have one
drop of water here.
And sunlight comes in at all
angles of I, not just at one,
but all angles of I.
Whatever you see here has of
course axial symmetry.
It is a spherical drop.
And the light comes in like
this.
So light can go this way but it
can also go this way.
And it can also go this way and
this way, so there's complete
axial symmetry,
so this whole drawing you can
rotate about this line here.
And everything holds then in
axial symmetry.
So therefore if phi maximum,
if this angle phi maximum is
forty-two degrees,
then the light that will go
back in the direction of the
sun,
the light that goes through the
journey A B C and then comes out
of the raindrop,
that's all I'm talking about,
now, I'm not talking about this
light that sneaks out here,
it is this journey,
A, refraction at A,
reflection at B,
and then coming out at C.
That light comes out in the
form of a cone.
And the half -- top angle of
the cone must be roughly
forty-two degrees.
And so I will go --
I'm going to draw that cone for
you.
Like so.
And like so.
And you have to think of this
as a cone.
It's completely symmetric,
axial symmetric,
about this line.
And this angle here then is
roughly forty-two degrees.
No light can go here.
Because that would mean that
phi would be larger than
forty-two
degrees and that's not allowed.
Now comes something very
important.
The index of refraction of red
light for water is about one
point three three one.
And that translates into an
angle for phi max which I can
calculate now -- it translates
into an angle of phi max which
is about forty-two point four
degrees.
But blue light has a slightly
different index of
refraction, therefore has a
slightly different angle for phi
max, and the blue light has an
index of refraction of something
like one point three four three.
Notice I have blue light and I
don't use violet light.
Violet is much harder to see
with our eyes.
So I always refer to it as blue
light.
And that has a value for phi
max which is approximately forty
point seven degrees.
A different index of refraction
means of course that if you know
I that R is slightly different,
using Snell's law,
so you get slightly different
values for R,
and so you get slightly
different values for delta,
so you get a slightly different
value for delta minimum,
you get a slightly different
value for phi max.
What does this mean now?
That means if you look at this
cone of light that goes back
into the direction of the sun,
that the outer edge,
the outer
surface of that cone,
which has the largest possible
angle, this angle is now
forty-two point four degrees,
must be red light,
because blue light cannot come
out in that direction.
Because the maximum angle for
blue is forty point seven,
is not forty-two point four.
So it's only red light that can
come out when the angle -- the
half angle of the cone is
forty-two point four degrees.
And the blue light is not going
to make it until this
angle here -- I'll put it in
here -- is forty point seven
degrees.
If you look inside the cone
with an half top angle of forty
point seven degrees all colors
can come back.
All this is saying is that for
red light phi maximum is
forty-two point four.
It can also therefore be forty
point seven.
It can be thirty.
It can be twenty.
It can be ten.
It can be zero.
Light that comes
in here at I equals zero
reaches point P,
comes straight back.
That's allowed.
Phi would be zero then.
If all the colors can make it
back inside this cone that I
have given here a blue color,
that would mean that your
brains will tell you that it is
white light.
Because you see red light,
you see blue light,
you see green light,
you see yellow light,
and so your brains will tell
you that that is white light.
If I had a screen here with a
small opening to let the
sunlight in and I asked you what
would you see on this screen
having only one water drop,
then you would see the
intersection of this cone of
light with this screen.
And it would look as follows.
The outer edge,
the outer circle,
which is the intersection of
the cone with your screen,
would be red.
And then there would be an
inner portion whereby all colors
can come back.
So that would be white light.
And then as you go further in
from the red,
until you reach that white
portion, then the last color
that will be added is the blue.
And you can already of course
sense that all the action about
the rainbow occurs here.
And here there is no light.
It's
going to be dark because there
is no way that phi can be larger
than forty-two point four
degrees.
And if light would appear on
the screen outside the red it
means that phi would be larger
than forty-two point four
degrees and that's not allowed.
So it's dark here.
It's white light here.
It's red light here.
Then as you go further in you
will finally see the other
colors.
And this really is now the key
to
the geometry of the -- of the
rainbow.
I'm going to put you here,
so here you're standing,
and let the sun again be near
the horizon.
It's always nice when you make
a picture.
The easy reference that you
have.
You're standing here.
Sunlight is coming in in this
direction.
And there is rain here.
If it's also raining here you
won't
see a rainbow.
Because the sun will not be
able to hit these raindrops.
So it's essential that it's
raining in the direction away
from the sun but that you can
still see the sun.
So here are these raindrops.
All right.
You're looking in this
direction in the sky.
You're looking up in the sky
like so.
And I pick here one raindrop
and only one but what I'm
telling you holds for all the
raindrops in that direction.
What will that raindrop do?
That raindrop will produce a
cone of light which goes back in
the direction of the sun whereby
the edge of the cone is red
light and this angle is
forty-two degrees,
forty-two point four,
whatever.
What do you see?
Nothing.
Because there is no light that
can come from
this raindrop in your
direction.
There is no light because that
would mean that phi is larger
than forty-two degrees and
that's not allowed.
So you look high up in the sky,
you will not see any light
coming back from that raindrop.
And think of the whole thing as
axial symmetric,
right?
Not only there,
but there and there you will
not see any light.
Now I am looking say at some
raindrops which are here.
I pick one.
It holds for any one in that
direction.
And so now I draw a line to
this point.
This is what I'm looking.
I look in this direction.
I take this raindrop.
I could have picked this
raindrop.
I could have picked this one.
Would have made no difference.
What is that raindrop doing?
Well, that raindrop is throwing
back at the sun light in the
form of a cone and the cone has
this angle forty-two degrees,
forty-two degrees.
What do you see now?
Look.
You're looking straight into
that cone.
You're nowhere near the edge.
So you see white light.
Because green light comes back
at you, red light comes back at
you, everything comes back at
you.
So you will say ha,
I see white light.
Not only there,
low on the horizon,
but the whole thing is axial
symmetric, also there and there.
So you haven't seen a rainbow
yet.
But now suppose I ask you to
look
up in the sky at a very
specific angle and we'll make
the angle forty-two point four
degrees.
So you're looking at the sky in
the direction somewhere here,
I'm not quite sure that I have
the angle just right.
So I'm looking in the sky here.
Pick one raindrop.
But you could pick any one,
any other other one.
There's nothing special about
that one.
So the sunlight comes in like
so.
What is that raindrop doing?
Well, it's throwing a cone of
light back to the sun.
And it just so happens that you
are only looking at the outer
surface of the cone where only
red light can go because this is
the famous angle of forty-two
point four degrees.
And so you see red light.
And since the whole problem is
axial symmetric,
you would see red light if you
look forty-two point four
degrees in this direction but
also forty-two degrees in this
direction, away from this
direction to the sun.
And so now you see how the bow
is being formed by zillions and
zillions of small water drops
which each of them in their own
way contribute to your rainbow.
And we'll now put the sun a
little higher in the sky.
So I'll put you here now.
And let's say the sun is now
like
so.
So, you look at your shadow
here on the ground.
The sun is there.
There's your shadow.
Here's your shadow.
Here's your head -- your
shadow.
And this is the reference line
that we're talking about.
That is this line.
That was this line.
And so where would you see a
rainbow?
You have to look now forty-two
degrees away from that line.
Forty-two degrees away from
that line.
That would be red then and a
little lower would be your your
blue.
And so if I sketch in there the
bow, it would be sort of like
this and then the blue would be
on the inside and here you would
have white light and this would
then be the red.
It's always relative to this
reference line.
This would be roughly -- I call
it forty-two degrees,
but according to my
calculation, there it would be
be forty-two point four.
So whenever you know where
the sun is, you look at the
shadow of your own head and you
have to go forty-two point four
degrees away from that direction
from your eye to the shadow.
And so what you're seeing now
is that if the sun is low in the
horizon then the bow will be
high above the horizon and when
the sun is rising then the bow
goes down and goes down and goes
down and by the time that the
sun is forty-two degrees above
the horizon, you're not going to
see a rainbow anymore unless the
water is right where you are.
If the water is at a distance,
you won't see a rainbow.
So the higher the sun in the
sky, the less likely it is that
you will ever see a rainbow.
Before I show you some -- some
slides and before we're going to
answer some of the questions,
uh, I want to mention to you
that what I went through here is
refraction at A,
reflection at B -- reflection
at B and coming out at C.
You can go through the same
geometry and allow for one more
reflection at C and then let
the light come out,
so it would come out at point D
and if you did that,
you can convince yourself that
there is indeed a second rainbow
and we call that the secondary.
We call this the primary.
And the secondary has a radius
-- this one of course has a
radius of forty-two point four
degrees for the red and the blue
would have a
smaller radius.
The secondary has a radius for
the red of fifty point four
degrees.
So in the red,
it's fifty point four degrees,
and in the blue,
it's larger.
So the blue is outside
fifty-two point five degrees.
Is that what it is?
Fifty-three point five.
The secondary bow is fainter
and it is also wider because you
see this separation in terms of
angle is larger than the
separation there.
That's only one point seven
degrees
and this is,
uh, more than three degrees.
And so there is a secondary bow
and the secondary bow is only
about roughly ten degrees above
the primary.
So if you see your primary at
forty-two degree angles away
from your shadow there and there
and there, go another ten
degrees and you should see a
second bow.
And you should see the colors
reversed.
Red is there on the outside and
blue is on the inside.
Red is on the outside and blue
is on the inside.
is on the inside,
but here it is reversed.
The secondary bow,
the red is on the inside and
the blue is on the outside.
So let's answer some questions
now.
We'll put the questions back up
again and you will see that you
can now without any difficulty
already answer twelve questions.
The first twelve.
Red is outside.
That is non-negotiable,
right?
That follows immediately from
what we'd talked about,
but that's not an issue
anymore.
The radius is about forty-two
degrees and the length of the
bow, well that depends on if the
sun is high in the sky then the
length will be very small
because this whole s- arc will
then go down and there will only
be a little bit left.
It could also be that it's only
raining here and it's not
raining there.
So depending upon where there
is rain and how high the sun is
in the sky, that will determine
the length of the bow.
The width of the bow,
you would think,
perhaps naively,
that if you subtract the
forty-two
from the forty -- forty point
seven from the forty two point
four that that would give you
the width of the bow which would
then be one point seven degrees
in angle.
However, you would overlook
then that the sun is not a
point, but that the sun in the
sky has a dimension of half a
degree and each point of the
sun, of course,
makes its own little rainbow,
so you really have to add
roughly half a degree.
So, the width of the bow is
more like, something like two
degrees rather than the one
point seven, maybe two -- two
point two degrees.
It's a little wider than what
you would think.
It has to do with the finite
size of the sun.
A comparison of the light
inside and outside,
clearly inside the bow,
there must be a lot of white
light which you don't see
outside the bow -- big
difference.
You will see a slide shortly.
The time of the day -- well the
sun has to be a little bit low,
so you don't expect it at
midday and you want rain as
well, so late afternoon,
early morning would be ideal
and you can figure out uh in
what direction to look.
If it's early morning,
the sun rises in the east,
you would see the bows in the
west and late in
the afternoon when the sun is
in the west, you would see the
bows in the east.
Yes there is a second bow.
It is about ten degrees higher
in the sky than the primary.
And the colors are reversed.
The blue is outside and the red
is inside.
And the radius is about
fifty-two degrees.
And the width of the bow is
again the difference between
these two numbers which you have
to add about half a degree.
So you would think on the basis
of this that it is more like
three degrees and you have to
add roughly the half a degree,
so it's about three --
three-and-a-half degrees.
So let's now look at some
slides.
And the first slide that you
will see is a -- is a drawing
that I made.
Which uh is meant to repeat
some of what I told you.
So you see a person standing
there and here you see the
direction to the sun.
Your shadow would be this
long.
This would be your head of the
shadow, here would be your feet.
And if there are water drops
here and if there's no
interference between the
sunlight and the water drops
then in this direction forty-two
degrees you would see this water
drop red.
And then the water drops which
were here you would see white
light from those water drops and
maybe from this one you would
see red as well as blue.
And if you have water near your
feet there's no reason why you
can't see the rainbow there
either but of course you would
have to lead some
garden hose to produce water
there.
The next slide then.
This is a drawing made by the
maestro himself,
Newton, who was the first to
fully understand the workings of
the rainbow.
You see here the primary bow
and for those of you who are
sitting close you can see the
direction of the sunlight going
in at A, reflects at B,
coming out at C.
Which he calls E,
but that's a detail.
And here you see then the
secondary whereby the light
comes in, one reflection,
two reflections,
and now it comes back at you
and that gives you the
secondary.
And so this is red and this is
blue whereas here this is blue
and this is red.
The next slide.
So if the sun is high in the
sky, I've done this many times
when I was uh watering my
garden, you get this for free,
you might as well do this,
it's great fun,
you're standing there,
gives you an immense feeling of
power, and is completely clear,
there's not a -- not a cloud in
the sky, there's no rain
anywhere, but you spray water
around you and you see a
beautiful rainbow
encircling your feet.
And always what matters is this
forty-two degree angle relative
to the direction from the sun to
you and this is where the shadow
of my head would be.
Very easy to do and I would
recommend that you try that when
you get a chance.
The next slide is a painting
from the eighth century,
Turkey, I see a hand here --
probably makes reference to the
Bible, but I think it reads in
the Bible I do set my bow in the
clouds, it's very nice and very
dandy, the fact that the colors
are wrong,
the sequence of the colors,
that's a detail,
it's a nice picture,
but red has to be on the
outside and blue has to be on
the inside.
Small detail.
Next slide.
Ah yeah.
A -- a few years ago,
actually it's more than a few,
when I was first lecturing
eight oh three I knew I was
going to talk about the rainbow,
ideal for eight oh three.
And so I wanted to make some
rainbows myself in my backyard
in Winchester.
And so there is water coming
out of a um water hose and the
sun was behind me
and I took this picture and you
see indeed all the ingredients
that we just discussed.
Notice the red is on the
outside and the blue is on the
inside.
You see all this white light.
That is that light that comes
back from the water drop but if
you go here where the angle of
phi would be larger than
forty-two degrees,
which is not allowed,
you don't see any light coming
back at you, so you look
straight through and see the
forest without any white light.
So you really see already here
sky so to speak is bright here
and darker there.
I needed help from my daughter.
And the next slide will show
you that.
The poor darling was suffering
badly.
It was January,
it was freezing cold,
she was crying.
She was really crying and I
felt guilty but I said look,
you know I really need these
slides for my eight oh three
class, it'll only take you
half-an-hour or so,
and she still remembers it,
I had email exchange with her
yesterday and she said dad I was
crying, it was an awful thing
what you did to me.
But look, but look.
You know, you got to do
something, and when you're
daughter of a
scientist occasionally you have
to suffer a little bit.
And so she's holding here the
-- the water hose and you see
the same thing red outside blue
inside, and clearly the white
light, you see this is that
white light that I discussed
with you earlier.
The next slide will show you
then a real rainbow -- oh no,
this is the um this is the
artificial one I made uh over my
driveway, if you want to see the
secondary, you need a real dark
background, because the
secondary is quite faint.
And so that's why I did it over
my driveway and you see here the
primary, red on the outside,
blue on the inside,
and here you see the colors
reversed.
You can also see perhaps that
it's a little wider.
But it's always much s- it's
much fainter,
so it's -- it's hard to tell.
And then the next slide is one
that's a wonderful slide made by
Doug Johnson in New Mexico,
Socorro, it is where the radio
telescopes are,
the very large array,
now look, red on the outside,
blue on the inside.
The sky you got to admit is a
hell
of a lot brighter here than it
is there.
And you may never have noticed
that, you've -- you've looked at
it but you've never seen it and
then here you see the secondary
red on the inside blue on the
outside.
There is a phenomenon that we
have never discussed uh in eight
oh two yet, it's coming up I
think next week.
And that phenomenon we call
diffraction.
Snell's law cannot deal with
That occurs when water drops
are very very small,
say, smaller than a tenth of a
millimeter.
What you then get over and
above the bow you get areas in
the bow whereby you get as we
call that destructive
interference,
the waves begin to kill each
other and you get dark bands and
you can actually see that here.
With a little bit of
imagination you see here a dark
band.
And when that is the case the
water is always extremely small
in size and we give this a name,
we call this supernumerary
bows.
It's not so uncommon.
If the water drops become
exceedingly small,
let's say, smaller even than
fifty microns,
then this diffraction
phenomenon becomes so important
that in addition to the dark
bands all the colors are
beginning to wash out over each
other, and that creates then a
white rainbow.
Plus the dark bands.
And a student of mine who was
in my eight oh three lecture
sent me years later the next
slide when he was -- his name
was Carl Wales,
this picture he took,
it's three hundred forty miles
from the North Pole,
he was at Fletcher Island at
the time, this picture was taken
at two AM at night in July when
the sun is above the horizon.
And so this must be the result
of very fine water drops which
somehow are there in the
atmosphere.
Doesn't look like it's raining
but there must have been small
water drops.
Fifty microns or less.
And here you see the
white-colored rainbow and you
also see beautifully the
supernumerary bows,
you see the -- the dark bands
in there and the next slide is a
close-up of that.
So you see here the white
rainbow plus the dark bands
which is the phenomenon the
result of uh of diffraction.
Now before I will discuss the
polarization of the bows,
because I still owe you answers
to the last three questions,
now that I'm at it,
I want to show you some
phenomenon which are quite
common which you may never have
seen
even though they're quite
common and they're rather
spectacular.
The first slide that comes now
shows you what we call the
twenty-two degree halo.
It's very common around the
sun, it's very common around the
moon.
The red is inside.
It has nothing to do with
water.
It is the result of ice
crystals way up in the
atmosphere.
You can see it both in the
summer as well as in the winter
because it's very cold way up
there also in the summer.
This is very common.
The reason why you and I don't
see
it that often,
because who wants to look in
the direction of the sun.
This angle is only twenty-two
degrees, it's not so far.
But I would advise you to at
least keep an eye on the moon.
Because the moon also has this
twenty-two degree halo.
And of course it's much easier
to look in the direction of the
moon.
That doesn't uh -- any no
problems for your eyes.
This is very common that I see
this at least three or four
times per month and I always
look for it of
course.
The next um slide shows you
both the twenty-two degree halo
as well as the forty-six degree
halo which is way more -- way
way less common,
it's very rare to see the
forty-six degree -- I've seen it
only a few times.
It's very rare.
In addition to the twenty-two
degree halo and the forty-six
degree halo you sometimes see
bright spots here.
You see them here and you see
them here.
They're really not circles.
They are arcs.
And they have names,
they call them uh sun dogs,
mock suns, they have various
names.
I've seen this often in in
Boston, the forty-six degree
halo is rare.
All of this as the result by
the way of um ice crystals.
Ice crystals way up in the
earth atmosphere.
And there is a phenomenon that
many of you may have seen from
an airplane.
Uh if your airplane flies over
clouds and you look at the
shadow of your airplane onto the
cloud you may have noticed
colorful rings
around the shadow of your
airplane.
And the next slide is such an
example.
I took this picture several
years ago.
You are always right at the
center of the circle.
So you can see that I was
sitting just behind the wings.
This is the result of
diffraction.
Got nothing to do with Snell's
law.
It is the result though of very
very fine water drops but not in
the sense of refraction and
reflection the way that we
discussed it with the rainbow.
This is the result of
diffraction.
It's extremely difficult,
the explanation of the glory.
And even ten years ago,
I read an enormous article
about it, I think it was in
Scientific American.
Which made an utter attempt to
be very quantitative about the
explanation, which is not easy.
The radius of this bow,
if you want to call it a bow,
depends on the size of the
water drops.
If the water drops are very
small the radius is
substantially larger.
So as you fly over clouds you
may fly over different clouds
with different size of water
drops and on a very short time
scale will you see the radius of
this glory change.
It can be very rapidly.
It could be on a time scale of
seconds to minutes.
It's very dramatic.
It's very clear.
And these rings can extend,
there's just not one ring,
but you can have several rings.
And so this is the result of
what we call diffraction.
Now I want to mention to you
another phenomenon which is um
also the result of diffraction.
And that you can see when there
is fog.
If you have fog fog consists of
extremely small water drops,
just like the ones in clouds.
I mean fog is a cloud,
let's face it.
Then if you for instance had
the headlights of a car you
could see your own shadow onto
the fog away from the direction
of the car.
And that means you could see
then
around your head the same kind
of stuff that you saw here.
A glory.
We call this a fogbow.
That's just a name.
The Germans have a much better
name for that,
they call it Heiligenschein.
And heilige person is someone
who is a saint and so you see
this around your head,
so it is sort of the -- the
radiation that you would expect
from a saint.
Quite a few years ago I was
invited to visit the Soviet
Union.
And they took me to the
Caucasus, to show me the
six-meter telescope which was at
the time the largest telescope
on earth.
And I went there for a few
days.
And I noticed much to my
surprise that every night at
five o'clock there would be fog
coming out of the valley
overtaking the telescope so you
could make no observations at
night but that was a detail and
what I realized is that the fog
was coming up,
the sun was there,
that was the west,
and the valley was at the east,
and so I said to myself my
goodness if only at the right
moment of time I am there then
the sun is my light beam and my
shadow will fall onto this wall
of fog coming towards me,
this is my chance to make a
wonderful picture of this
Heiligenschein.
And I'll show you that I
succeeded.
I will first show you a picture
of this bizarre observatory.
This is the six-meter telescope
in the Caucasus.
And this is indeed you could
every night around five-thirty
really like a wall
the fog will just coming
towards you overtake you.
You can see the timing of my
picture was extremely crucial.
If you wait a little bit too
long then the fog overtakes you
and then the sun would obviously
not be effective anymore.
I wouldn't see my shadow on the
fog.
So I only had a small time
window, maybe thirty seconds,
maybe one minute.
But I succeeded and you will
see w- Saint Walter coming up.
There is Saint Walter.
You can see here my arm and you
can see here my
camera.
The camera must be exactly at
the center of the glory.
And that's where it is.
I have the camera right here
and here you see the rest of my
body, isn't that terrific?
This can be used as proof
sooner or later.
OK.
Back to our last three
questions.
The last three questions deal
with
the polarization of the bow.
Are the bows polarized?
And the answer is yes,
they are enormously polarized.
Why are they polarized?
You can answer that question.
But I will answer it for you.
The light that contributes to
the rainbow is the light whereby
the minimum angle for delta is
about a hundred thirty-eight
degrees and if you go back to
that
first transparency you will see
that that's the case when the
angle of incidence is about
sixty degrees.
You can download that again.
And that means that the angle
of refraction is about forty
degrees.
Forty degrees is very close to
the Brewster angle.
The Brewster angle if you go
from water to air you -- medium
where you are is water and
you bounce it off this medium,
so you go from water to air,
the tangent of the Brewster
angle is N two divided by N one.
N two is where you're going.
That's air.
So this is one.
N one is where you are.
That's the water.
Let's just call that the index
of refraction one point three
three.
If you calculate now what the
Brewster angle is you will find
that the Brewster angle theta
Brewster
is about thirty-seven degrees.
That is only three degrees
different from this angle which
is the crucial one which
contributes to the rainbow.
So you're only three degrees
away from the Brewster angle.
So what happens as this light
comes in i will make a a
separate drawing