magnetic flux that is produced
by the circuits themselves.
If you have a circuit and you
run a current through the
circuit, then you create some
magnetic fields,
and if the currents are
changing then the magnetic
fields are changing.
And so there will be an induced
EMF in that circuit that fights
the
change, and we express that in
terms of a self-inductance:
L self-inductance ,
and the word self speaks for
itself.
It's doing it to itself.
Magnetic flux that is produced
by the circuit is always
proportional to the current.
You double the current,
the magnetic flux doubles.
And so it is the
proportionality constant that we
call L that is the
self-inductance,
and so therefore the induced
EMF equals minus D five ET,
that is Faraday's Law.
And so that becomes minus L DI
DT.
L is only a matter of geometry.
L is not a function of the
current itself.
I will calculate for you a very
simple case of the
self-inductance
of a solenoid.
yes, there you see this,
Let this be a solenoid and this
is a closed circuit,
and we want a current I through
the solenoid,
and the radius of these
windings is little R.
Let's say they're N windings
and the length of the solenoid
is little L.
Perhaps you'll remember that we
earlier derived,
using *Empea's* Law,
that the magnetic field inside
the
solenoids is new zero times I
times capital N divided by L.
This is the number of windings
per meter.
If we attach an open surface to
this closed loop,
very difficult to imagine what
that open surface looks like --
we discussed that many times --
inside this solenoid you have
sort of a staircase-like of
surface.
That magnetic field penetrates
that surface N times because you
have N loops.
And so the magnetic flux,
file B, is simply the area by
little R squared,
which is the surface area of
one loop, because I assume that
the magnetic field is constant
inside the solenoid,
and I assume that it is zero
outside, which is a very good
approximation.
So we get pi little R squared
surface area of one loop,
then we have N loops and then
we have to multiply it by that
constant magnetic field.
So we get an N squared because
we have an N here,
new zero I divided by L.
And this we call L times I.
That's our definition for
self-inductors.
And so the self-inductions L is
purely geometry.
It's pi level R squared,
capital N squared divided by L
times new zero.
yes, there you see this,
Let me check this.
Pi little R squared,
I have a capital N squared,
new zero, that's correct,
divided by little L.
And so we can calculate,
for instance,
what this self-inductance is
for a solenoid that we have used
in class several times.
We had one whereby we had
twenty eight hundred windings.
R I think was something like
five centimeters -- you have to
work SI of course,
be careful -- and we had a
length,
was 0 point six meters.
We had it several times out
here, and if you substitute
those numbers in there,
you will find that the
self-inductance of that solenoid
is 0 point 1 in SI units and we
call the SI units Henry,
capital H.
It would be the same as volt
seconds or ampere,
but no one would ever use that.
We call that Henry.
Every circuit has a finite
value for
the self-inductance,
however small that may be.
Sometimes it's so small that we
ignore it, but if you take a
simple loop, a sum-,
simple current,
just one wire that goes around
-- whether it's this,a rectangle
or whether it is a circle it
doesn't make any difference --
it always produces a magnetic
field.
It always produces a magnetic
flux to the surface,
and so it always has a finite
self-inductance.
Maybe only nine nano Henrys,
maybe only micro Henrys,
but it's never zero.
yes, there you see this,
And so now what I want to do is
to show you the remarkable
consequences of the presence of
a self-inductor in a circuit,
and I start very simple.
I have here a battery which has
EMFV.
I have here a switch,
and here are the self-inductor.
We always draw a self-inductor
in a circuit with these coils,
and we also have in series a
resistor, which we always
indicate with this,
these teeth.
And I close this switch when
there is no current running.
In other words,
a time T equals zero when I
close the switch,
there is no current.
When I close the switch the
current wants to increase,
but the self-inductance says
uh-huh, uh-huh,
take it easy,
land slow, I don't like the
change of such occurrence.
So the self-inductance is
fighting the current that wants
to go through it.
There comes a time that the
self-inductance loses the fight,
if you wait long enough,
and then of course the current
has reached a maximum volume,
which you can find with Ohm's
Law, because the self-inductance
itself
has no resistor.
Think of the self-inductance as
made of super conducting
material.
There's no resistance.
And so without knowing much
about physics,
you can make a plot about the
current that is going to flow as
a function of time.
You start out with zero and
then ultimately,
if you wait long enough,
you reach a maximum current
which is
given by Ohm's Law,
which is simply V divided by R.
And you slowly approach that
value.
And how slowly depends on the
value of the self-inductance.
If the self-inductance is very
high, it might climb up like
this, so this is a high value
for L.
If the self-inductance is very
low, then there's a low value
for L.
If the self-inductance were
zero, it would come up
instantaneously,
but I just convinced you that
there I no such thing as zero
self-inductance.
There's always something
finite, no matter how small.
And so this is qualitatively
what you would expect if you use
your stomach and if you don't
use your brains yet.
There's nothing wrong with
using your stomach occasionally,
but now I want to do this in a
move civilized way,
and I want to use my brains,
and when I use my brains I have
to set up an equation for the
circuit.
And if you read your book,
you will find that Mister John
*Coley* tells you to use
*Kipshof's* Loop Rule.
But Mister John *Coley* doesn't
understand Faraday's Law,
and he's not the only one.
Almost every college book that
you read on physics do this
wrong.
They advise you to use
*Kipshof's* Loop Rule,
which says that the closed loop
integral around the circuit is
zero.
That, of course,
is utter nonsense.
How can it be zero?
Because there is a change in
magnetic flux,
and so it can only be minus D
five ET.
I advise you to go to the eight
0 two website and download a
lecture supplement that you will
find in which I address this
issue and hit it very hard.
So the closed loop integral of
E dot EL, if you go around the
circuit, is not zero,
is minus D five ET -- Faraday's
Law -- so it's minus L the IDT.
So we have to go around to
circuits
and we have to apply Faraday's
law and not *Kipshof's* Loop
Rule, which doesn't apply here.
This is the plus side of the
battery and this is the minus
side, so the electric field in
the battery is in this
direction.
The electric field in the
self-inductance is zero because
the self-inductance has no
resistance, it's super
conducting material,
and so the electric fields in
the resistor -- if the current
is in this direction,
which it will be -- then the
electric field in the resistor
will be in this direction.
So now I am equipped to write
down the closed loop integral of
E dot VL.
I start here and I always go in
the direction of the current,
and I advise you to do the
same.
I don't care if you guess the
wrong direction for the current.
That's fine.
Later, minus signs will correct
that,
they will tell you that you
really guessed the wrong
direction, but always go around
the loop in the direction of the
current, because then the EMF is
always minus LVIDT.
If you go in the direction
opposed to the current,
then it is plus LVIDT and that
could become confusing.
So I always go in the direction
of the current,
and so I first go through the
self-inductance.
There is no electric field in
the self-inductance,
so the integral E dot EL -- in
going from here to here -- is
zero.
This is where the books are
wrong.
It is zero.
Now, I go through the resistor,
and so now I get plus IR E and
the L are in the same direction.
Ohm's Law tells me it's IR.
In the battery,
I go against the electric
fields, and so I get minus V.
That now equals minus L,
DIDT, and this is the only
thing and the only correct way
to apply
Faraday's Law in this circuit.
You can write it a little
differently, which may give you
some insight.
For instance,
you could write that I can
bring V and the L,
and L, to one side -- so I can
write down that V minus LDIDT
equals IR.
It's the same equation when you
look, and the nice thing about
writing it this way is that
since the IDT is positive here
-- it's growing in time -- the
induced EMF, which is this value
-- notice it's always opposing
the voltage of my battery -- and
that's what *Land's* Law is all
about.
It's not until the IDT has
become zero that V equals IR,
and that happens,
of course, if you wait long
enough.
And so we have to solve the
differential equation,
and what is often done that you
bring all the terms to the left
side and that you get an,
zero on the right side.
And so what you often see is
that LVIDT plus IR minus V
equals zero.
And because we have a zero
here, some physicist thinks that
this is an application of
*Kipshof's* Rule.
This is nonsense.
You can always make it zero
here by bringing all the terms
to this side.
The closed loop integral of E
DEL TL is not zero,
the closed loop integral of E
DEL TL is minus LDIDT,
but when I shift minus LDIDT to
this side I get zero here.
And of course the people who
write these books know that this
is the right answer and so they
manipulate it so they get this
equation and they call that
*Kipshof's* Rule.
Sad, and also embarrassing.
So, this is the equation that
you have to solve.
Some of you may have solved
this equation in eight 0 one
already.
Surely you didn't have an I
here.
You may have had an X here for
the position,
but you probably solved it or
you had friction.
Maybe you didn't.
I will give you the solution to
that differential equation.
It's a very easy solution.
The current as a function of
time is a maximum value times
one minus E to the minus R
divided by L times T,
and IMX -- that is the maximum
current -- is V divided by R.
And let's look at this in a
little bit more detail.
First, notice that when T
equals zero that indeed you find
I equals zero.
Substituting here T equals
zero, you get one minus one.
So you find,
indeed, that I equals zero.
Substituting there T goes to
infinity, then you find that I
indeed becomes V divided by R,
which is exactly what you
expect.
If T becomes infinity,
then clearly the
self-inductance has lost all
it's power, so to speak,
and the current is simply V
divided by R,
the maximum current that you
can have.
And so that's a must,
that's a requirement.
If you wait L over R seconds --
and believe it or not,
if you have some time,
convince yourself that L over R
indeed, as a unit,
is seconds -- then the current
I is about sixty three percent
of IMX, because if T is L over
R, then you get one minus one
divided by E,
and that is about 0 point six
three.
And if you wait double this
time, then you have about eighty
six percent of the maximum
current.
In other words,
right here -- if I wait L over
R
seconds -- this value here is
about 0 point six three times
the maximum value possible,
and it's very,
it's climbing up and
asymptotically approaches then,
ultimately, the maximum current
which is V divided by R.
Make sure you download that
lecture supplement that you'll
find on the Web.
Now, what I'm going to do is
all of a sudden I'm going to
make this voltage zero.
The way I could do that is by
simply shorting it out.
Of course on the blackboard,
I can simply remove it.
So it's not there.
The current is still running
and all of a sudden at a new
time -- T zero,
I define the time T zero again
-- the voltage is zero.
And now comes the question what
is
now going to happen?
Well, the self-inductance
doesn't like the fact that the
current is going down,
so it's going to fight that
change, and so you expect that
the current is not going to die
off right away,
but you expect that the current
is going to go down sort of like
so.
And you want,
when you wait long enough,
you want that,
at T goes to infinity,
where T equals zero the current
is still maximum,
so it's still V over R,
but when you go to infinity --
if you wait long enough -- then,
of course, the current has to
become zero.
And as the current dies out,
heat is being produced in that
resistor at a rate of I square R
joules per second,
and then there comes a time
that the current becomes almost
zero and then the whole show is
over.
And so we can also calculate
the exact time behavior by going
back to our differential
equation and make V zero.
Where is that differential
equation?
yes, there you see this,
Is it hiding?
Oh, there it is.
So I solved this differential
equation, but this is now zero.
And the solution to that
differential equation is that I
as a function of time is IMX
times E to
the minus R over L times T,
and that exactly has all the
quantities that you want it to
have, because notice that at T
equals zero -- when you put in T
equals zero -- the current is
indeed maximum,
and that's what you require.
That's the moment that you make
that capital V zero,
the current was still running.
But notice that when T goes to
infinity --
if you wait long enough -- that
indeed the current goes to zero.
And if you wait L over R
seconds, then you are down to
about thirty seven percent of
your maximum current.
So if you now go to I,
I re-define T equals zero here,
so if now I wait L over R
seconds then this value here is
about thirty seven percent of
that value.
So you've lost sixty three
percent.
And so you see,
this is the consequence of the
fact that the circuit is capable
of fighting its own magnetic
flux that it is creating.
When the current was running
happily here,
with the battery in place,
the current was,
let's say, all the time IMX --
at least very close to that
value -- V over R.
And so all the time,
there was heat produced in the
resistor.
I square R joules per second.
Who was providing that,
uh, energy?
Well, of course,
the
battery.
But now, when I take the
battery out, there is still
current running,
and that means while the
current is dying there is still
heat produced in that resistor,
and that heat slowly comes out
until the current ultimately
becomes zero.
Now where does that energy come
from?
Well that energy must come from
the magnetic field that is
present in the solenoid,
and this idea -- that we have
energy that comes out in the
form of heat,
which really was there ear-,
earlier in the form of a
magnetic field -- allows us to
evaluate what we call the
magnetic energy field density.
Let me first calculate how much
heat is produced as the current
goes from a maximum value down
to zero.
Hmmmm, I'll have to erase
something.
I'll erase this part here.
So at any moment in time,
the current is producing heat
in the resistor,
and so if I,
if my voltage becomes zero at
time T equals zero,
then this is the amount of
heat, uh-uh, no square here.
I square RDT,
integrated from zero to
infinity, is the total heat that
is produced
as the current dies out,
but I know what this current
was -- I just erased it,
if I still remember it -- so I
can bring IMX outside and I can
bring the resistance outside and
the I get the integral from zero
to infinity of E to the minus R
over L times TDT.
And this is a trivial integral.
This integral is,
uhm, L divided by two R.
Oh, by the way,
it is I squared,
so I have a two here.
It's very important.
Don't forget the two.
And so that integral is L
divided by two R,
and so if now I look at the
product of I square maximum R L
divided by two R,
I get one half L times I
maximum squared.
So this comes out in the form
of heat, and IMX is then the
maximum current that we had when
the current
was flowing after a long time.
I can now by,
by manipulating numbers,
I can now calculate how much
energy there was in that field
per cubic meter,
because the magnetic field was
exclusively inside that
solenoid.
And if I know that the energy
that is ultimately coming out is
one half LI squared,
then I have here I,
and so I can replace that I
there by B divided by new zero
times L divided by N and here I
have L.
And so if I substitute in here
the value for L that we have on
the blackboard there,
and we substitute for I the
value that we have here -- you
can drop the maximum now -- this
simply tells you,
then, that any moment in time
that I have a current I running
through a solenoid,
that the energy that is
available in the solenoid in the
forms of magnetic energy is one
half LR squared.
And so when you do that,
you substitute capital L and
capital I, you will find that
one half LI squared then becomes
B squared over two new zero
times pi little R squared times
L.
You check that at home.
It's simply a substitution.
But this is the volume of the
solenoid where the magnetic
field exists,
and we have assumed that the
magnetic field is zero
everywhere outside.
And if you accept that,
then you see that we now have a
result for the magnetic field
energy density -- that is how
much energy there is per cubic
meter -- that is,
of course, this value.
Because this is the total
energy of the magnetic field,
if we know the current,
and this is the volume of the
magnetic field.
So the magne-,
magnetic field energy density
is then B squared divided by two
new zero, and this is in joules
per cubic meter.
So in principle,
if you knew the magnetic field
everywhere in space,
then you can integrate over all
space and you can then calculate
how much energy is,
uhm, present in the magnetic
field.
And earlier in this course,
we did something similar for
electric fields.
We calculated the electric
field energy density.
Perhaps you remember whatit
was.
It was one half epsilon zero
kappa times E squared.
It was also in joules per cubic
meter.
Now in the case of an electric
field, this represents the work
that I had to do to arrange the
charges in a certain
configuration.
In the case of a magnetic
field, it represents the work
that I have to do to get a
current going inside
a pure self-inductor.
That means the resistance of
the self-inductor is zero,
and it takes work because the
solenoid will oppose the
building up of the current,
and so I have to do work.
So there's a parallel between
the two.
I can make you see,
in a quite dramatic way,
how strong self-inductances can
fight their own current,
and the way I'm going to do
that is
with in-, inside of there,
whereby I have a twelve volt
car battery and I have two light
bulbs.
I have here an enormous
self-inductance L,
thirty Henry.
We will learn later in the
course how you make such a high
self-inductance,
and then here is a light bulb.
The light bulb has a resistance
of six ohm.
This self-inductance,
there is nothing we can do
about it.
It happens to have four ohm
resistance.
We don't have a self,
we don't have s-,
superconducting wires here,
so it also has a resistance of
four ohms.
Forgive me for that but there
is nothing I can do about it.
I have here another resistance
of our ohms and a light bulb,
which is the same one as that
one -- also six ohms -- and then
here is my car battery plus a
switch.
And the car battery is twelve
volts, and I'm going to throw
the switch, turn it on.
You will see that this light
bulb comes on almost
instantaneously.
There is no self-inductance in
this loop -- well,
maybe a few micro Henry or even
less -- but in this loop here
there is this huge
self-inductance,
and so the self-inductance says
take it easy to the current,
take it easy,
just wait, and you will very
slowly see that
light bulb come on.
And we can calculate how long
it takes, because we have here
ten ohms -- six ohms and four
ohms, so L divided by R,
we have thirty divided by ten
-- so that is three seconds.
So what that means is that even
after six seconds,
which is twice this time,
even then the current through
this light bulb is only eighty
six percentof it's maximum.
But that means since the light,
of course, is proportional to I
square R in the light bulb,
that the light is only seventy
five percent of maximum,
and even if you wait nine
seconds, then the light that
comes out here is still only
ninety percent of it's maximum,
whereas this one comes on
immediately.
The reason why we put the four
ohm here, we want this part to
be -- from an ohmic resistance
point of view -- to be identical
as this part.
So that's why you artificially
added here the four ohm,
because the four ohm is always
there in the self-inductance,
there is nothing we can do
about it.
And so you are going to see a
remarkable example.
This is one light bulb.
That is the one that is here,
and this is the light bulb that
is there, and the
self-inductance is in this
incredible monster,
here.
I'll make the lights,
change the light setting a
little bit so that we can see
the lights of the bulb.
The bulbs are only eight-watt
bulbs, they're not very,
very strong,
not
very bright bulbs,
but the effect will be very
clear.
So if you're ready for this --
so this is the one that I think
comes on immediately,
and this is the one that takes
it's time -- three,
two, one, zero.
One, two, three,
four, five, six,
you see how slow?
It's still not very bright,
it's still getting brighter.
It's still not as bright as
this one.
It's getting there,
you can actually do some timing
by
counting.
By the way, the values of the
resistance that I gave you are
when the light bulbs are hot.
Three, two, one,
zero, one, two,
three, four,
five, six, seven,
eight, nine,
ten, eleven,
twelve, I'm still seeing it
getting brighter.
What you're seeing here is a
remarkable example that the
self-inductance is fighting
itself.
That's why the name
self-inductance
is so nice.
Now I want to go one step
further and I want to power the
LR circuit with a AC power
supply.
If you have an AC power supply
-- so it's changing all the
time, the voltage -- now,
of course, the self-inductance
is
fighting back all the time,
not just only in the beginning
as you saw in this circuit,
but now, of course,
it is active almost all the
time.
So we can do away with this,
and so now we replace the
battery by a AC power supply,
which we normally put just a
wiggle there,
and here is the self-inductance
L, and here is the resistor R.
And let the voltage provided by
this power supply be V zero
times the cosine of omega T,
omega being the angular
frequency.
And now, I have to apply
Faraday's Law,
not *Kipshof's* Rule --
Faraday's Law -- when I go
around this circuit and I set up
the differential equation.
And of course the differential
equation is going to be exactly
like this, except that V,
now, is V zero times the cosine
of omega T.
And now I have to solve for
this differential equation.
That's the only difference,
so I don't have to start from
ground zero.
And the solution to this
differential equation is quite
remarkable and not so intuitive.
The current -- as a function of
time, now -- is V zero divided
by the square root of R squared
plus omega
L squared times the cosine of
omega T minus phi,
and the tangent of phi,
that angle phi,
is omega L divided by R.
And of course we need some time
to digest this.
The first thing that you notice
is that there is a phase lag
between the current and the
driving voltage.
If phi, as you're going to see,
is, uhm, ninety degrees,
then the current is delayed by
one quarter of a cycle,
though the fact that the
current comes later than the
driving voltage perhaps is
intuitive, because the
self-inductance is fighting the
change in the current.
So it's perhaps not so
surprising that there's going to
be a delay, that the current
comes a little later.
If you look at this equation
here, then what you have in
front of the cosine term is
obviously the maximum
possible current,
because the cosine term is just
oscillating between plus one and
minus one, and so this here is
the maximum current that you can
ever get.
In one full cycle you get
positive and you get negative
net value.
And notice here the role of
omega L really plays the role of
a resistance,
and in fact the dimension of
omega L is ome-,
is, is, is ohms.
It really plays the role of a
resistance, and if omega is
very high then the resistance
here becomes very high and so
your current becomes very low.
Well, that's intuitively
pleasing because if omega is
high, then the changes -- the
DIDT's -- are very,
very high, and therefore if
there are very fast changes the
induced EMF is going to be high,
and so the current will be low.
Also, if L is very high,
then the system also is capable
of fighting back very hard,
and so it puts up a large
resistance.
So it's also pleasing that you
see the L there,
downstairs.
If omega is very low,
in your mind you can make omega
zero.
You don't even have alternating
current when omega is zero,
then you have DC which is
direct current.
So when you make omega zero,
you simply get I is V zero
divided by R.
That's Ohm's Law,
that's obvious that you get
that.
Let's now look at the phase
angle.
The tangent of phi is omega L
divided by R.
If the self-inductor is very
large,
then the system has a strong
ability to fight back,
so it can delay that current by
a large amount,
and the same is true is omega
is high.
If omega is high then the time
changes are very,
changes occur on a very small
time scale, and so the system
can fight back.
Because remember,
you always have the EMF
proportion to the IDT.
And so it's also pleasing to
see that omega and L are
upstairs here.
Either one of being large it
can
fight back and it can hold back
the, the current.
yes, there you see this,
I have worked out a situation
whereby we have an LR circuit --
this is on the Web,
you can download that so you
don't have to copy it -- and the
reason why I have these values
is because directly coupled to a
demonstration that I will do
shortly.
You see, an L in series with an
R, the L is ten *milli-Henry*
and the R
is ten ohms,
and let V zero be ten volts.
And here you see three
frequencies hundred hertz,
thousand and ten thousand
hertz, and here you see the
values for omega.
You have to multiply hertz with
two pi.
And look now at omega L.
At low frequency -- a hundred
hertz -- omega L is six point
three ohms.
Compare that with the ten ohms.
They'd be comparable,
but now look for instance at
ten thousand hertz.
The omega L is huge.
It's six
hundred and thirty ohms.
So it entirely determines -- so
to speak -- the resistance of
that circuit.
And so the current that is
going to run -- at least this is
the maximum current is this
value, which we also saw here on
the blackboard -- that current
at high frequently is enormously
reduced.
It's fifty times lower than
this current at low frequency,
even though they have the same
value for P zero.
And then you see here the phase
angles.
And the reason why you have
these
values is that I can make you
listen to this,
I can make you hear this,
because your hearing is very
good at hundred hertz,
and since all of you are young
you can probably hear even ten
thousand hertz,
maybe some of you can even hear
twenty kilohertz.
When you get older you lose
your high frequencies.
In fact, my frequency cut off
is somewhere near four thousand
hertz.
I'm going to make you listen to
music, and there will be violins
which produce probably three,
four, five thousand hertz,
and then
I will turn on,
all of a sudden,
the ten *milli-Henry*.
So first I will make you listen
to music whereby there is no ten
*milli-Henry* in there,
and then I will turn on the ten
*milli-Henry*,
and what you will hear,
that the violins disappear
because the current reduction is
now huge on the high frequency
but is very little on the low
frequency, and that's the idea
of what a self-inductor can do
for you.
So if you listen to this
[playback
of classical music with violin]
there's no self-inductor in now.
There's no music either
[laughter] OK.
[Playback of classical music
continues, without violin
notes.] OK.
It's different music.
No self-inductor.
[Click] Self-inductor.
The high frequencies are gone.
[Playback of classical music
continues, again with violin
notes] No self-inductor.
[Click] You can turn a violin
concerto into a cello concerto.
[laughter].
You just cut the violins out.
OK.
I cannot make you listen to the
phase shift, not even in the
case of the ninety degree phase
shift,
and that is quite obvious
because what does it mean that
there is a ninety degree phase
shift?
It means that during one cycle
of ten thousand hertz -- which
takes only one ten-thousandth of
a second -- that the high
frequencies are shifted by only
twenty-five microseconds,
and there's no way that your
ears, your ears can hear that.
The fact that the composer
wanted those violins to come in
twenty-five microseconds earlier
than, than they do of course is
something you cannot hear.
So I cannot make you listen to
the phase shift,
but for the phase shift I have
something else.
And for that something else,
I'm going to return to the,
to my last lecture,
in which we levitated a woman
-- magnetic levitation.
And so I'm going to return to
that idea and grind a little
deeper than we did when I gave
that lecture,
just before spring break.
I had a coil and I was driving
that coal, coil with sixty hertz
AC.
And let's assume that looking
from above that the current was
running in clockwise direction,
which is exactly what I assumed
when I discussed with you,
and so the magnetic field is
coming down like this --
magnetic dipole field --
produced by this coil.
And then we have here,
we had a conducting place under
there, and I said to you when
this magnetic field is
increasing in strength,
then there's going to be an
induced EMF here,
which tries to imp-,
oppose that change,
and so the induced current that
is going to run,
which we call eddy currents,
is going to run in this
direction.
If this is clockwise,
this current is going to be
counter clockwise,
so it's going to produce a
magnetic field in this
direction.
It opposes the change of the
increase in magnetic field:
*Lendz* Law.
And since the two currents are
in opposite direction,
the two repel each other.
And you bought off on that,
and we levitated a woman.
However, no one asked me the
question, what happens a little
later in time when the magnetic
field is still in the downward
direction but it is decreasing,
since it is an AC current,
there comes a time that the
magnetic field will be
decreasing in time.
Now the EMF here must flip over
because Lendz says sorry,
we don't like the decrease.
The moment that the EMF flips
over, this current will flip
over.
The two currents are now in the
same
direction, and they will
attract each other,
and so there goes your magnetic
levitation.
Half the time attraction,
half the time they repel each
other.
But yet we did elev- levitate a
woman, and the secret lies in
the self-inductance.
This current that runs here
runs over a pass -- which is
very difficult for me to
anticipate -- which has a
certain resistance,
R; and it has a certain
self-inductance,
L.
We know what omega is;
that's about three hundred
sixty.
And so we do get in this
conductor, we get the current,
the induced current here,
is delayed by a phase angle
driven by this equation,
is delayed over the induced
EMF.
The EMF immediately coupled to
what this coil is doing,
but the induced current is
delayed.
And I have something that will
allow
that, allow you to see that,
perhaps in even more detail.
This *raf* curve is the
current for the coil,
the coil that you see there
above.
And when the current is above
the black line it's clockwise
and when it is below the black
line it's counter clockwise.
The vertical scales are
arbitrary.
The green curve is the EMF,
which is induced in the
conductor.
Notice when the magnetic field
increases, when the current goes
up in the coil,
that the EMF in the conductor
is in such a direction that it
opposes the change of that
magnetic field.
But now when the magnetic
fields go down,
when the current in the coil
goes down, immediately the EMF
flips over, which is what I just
mentioned to you,
and therefore if the induced
current and the induced EMF were
in
phase with each other,
half the time you would have
attraction and half the time you
would have that the two repel
each other, and that won't give
you magnetic levitation.
Here, what you see is a blue
curve which represents the
induced current.
I call it the eddy current.
If there is no phase shift
between the induced EMF and the
induced current,
notice that half the time
the blue curve and the red
curve are in opposite direction.
When they are in opposite
direction they repel each other.
When they are in the same
direction they attract each
other.
But now, if I have a phase
delay so that the induced
current comes later than the EMF
-- and I'm going to do something
dramatic, I'm going to shift it
by ninety degrees so the current
is now ninety degrees delayed
relative to the induced EMF --
look now that the red curve and
the blue curve are always in
opposite direction.
And so now there is hundred
percent of the time a repelling
force.
The coil repels the conductor
and the conductor repels the
coil.
Now in the case when we
levitated the woman,
I am sure that the phase delay
was not ninety degrees but maybe
it was only thirty or forty
degrees, but the net result is
here the shift is not ninety
degrees, the net result is that
you get, on average,
a repelling force.
And so, the secret of the
repelling force,
in the case of the levitation
of this coil and therefore of
the levitation of the woman,
lies in the effect that there
is a finite self-inductance
[tapping noise] in here.
If R is zero,
then of course we have a super
conductor, then *phi* is always
ninety degrees.
When R is zero,
this is infinitely high,
so now we get a ninety-degree
phase shift, and I did a
demonstration whereby I
had a little magnet floating
above a super conductor.
That was an ideal case.
Phi was then ninety degrees,
so they always repel each
other.
Today I want to do a more
controlled demonstration,
whereby I can actually
calculate the self-inductance
and I also can calculate the
resistance.
And what I will do today is I
will have a coil which is
stationary, and I will have a
conductor which is not
stationary.
Here is my coil.
AC, sixty hertz.
There's the coil.
And I have a ring,
and the ring is made of
aluminum, and I know exactly the
dimensions of this ring.
I know the radius -- it's about
five centimeters -- I know the
thickness, I know everything.
It's an aluminum ring and has a
radius of about five
centimeters.
Since I know all the
dimensions,
I can calculate the resistance
of that ring.
You should be able to do that,
too, if I gave you the
dimensions.
And so the resistance of that
ring very roughly is about seven
times ten to the minus five
ohms.
It's very small.
I can all-, this is at room
temperature, by the way,
the lower temperature the
resistance is lower.
I can also calculate very
roughly what the self-inductance
is of that ring.
Now that's not so easy,
because here when I calculated
the self-inductance,
the magnetic
field was constant.
I assumed it was constant,
uniform inside.
That's not the case when you
have a ring.
You have a dipole field.
However, I just assumed that
the magnetic field was the same
everywhere at the surface of the
ring -- and with that assumption
admittedly I could be off maybe
by twenty or thirty percent --
with that assumption I find that
the self-inductance is ten to
the minus seven Henry.
I know what the omega is.
It's three hundred sixty,
roughly, and so I find that
omega L over R
for this ring is about one
half, run at that frequency
omega.
And that gives me a phase angle
phi of twenty five degrees,
and therefore the ring is going
to be repelled by the coil and
of course the coil is going to
be repelled by the ring.
I'll put the ring here,
and the ring is supported by
this, so this ring cannot fall
over.
The only difference between
this
experiment and that one is
first of all I can be very
quantitative there,
I can actually calculate the
phase angle, where here that's
almost impossible.
Here, it is the conductor that
I'm going to make levitate and
the coil is stationary.
In here it was the conductor
that was stationary,
and the coil is floating,
but of course the idea is
exactly the same.
And so what I want to do now is
make you see there,
actually, hmmmm,
and we'll have to  ...
it should come up there .
yes, there you see this,
this ring.
Maybe I should first show you
the whole set up.
So this ring goes over here --
this is an aluminum ring -- and
I'm going to make it levitate by
simply running sixty hertz under
ten volts through this coil and
I hope I do nothing wrong.
Oh no, I have to turn on my AC.
Oh my God, that was not,
gee, that
was not my intention.
A good thing we don't have a
woman sitting on the ring now.
My idea was to have it
levitate.
By the way, you did see that it
was repelled,
that was quite clear.
I had the current too high.
[laughter] I had the current
too high so we'll have it a
little lower,
and I will make the current
come up very slowly and then I
want you to see that it
levitates.
There it is,
levitating.
Oh, oh, off the screen.
There it is.
And I can turn it over and it's
still levitating,
of course.
And the secret is this phase
delay introduced by the
self-inductance.
I have another ring here which
has a, a slot -- also aluminum
-- same ring,
but it has a slot.
Well, the EMF in this ring is
going to be identical.
There's no difference.
In fact, the self-inductance of
this ring is identical,
but the resistance of this ring
is huge because there's a slot
in there and the resistance is
almost infinitely high.
And so if the resistance is
infinitely high,
no matter what L is and what
omega is, phi is going to be
zero.
It won't repel.
Half the time it attracts,
half the time it repels.
[metallic clanking sound] That
means nothing happens,
no magnetic levitation.
Same EMF, same self-inductance,
but an infinite resistance and
here you see magnetic
levitation.
Since the induced current in
the ring is extremely small
because of it's very high
resistance, the force on the
ring -- whether it's repelling
or attracting
-- in any case is practically
zero.
So that alone is enough reason
for the ring not to move at all.
All right, I hope to see all of
you tomorrow during our exciting
testing of the motors.