So today no new concepts,
no new ideas,
you can release a little bit
and I want to discuss with you
the connection between electric
potential and electric fields.
Imagine you have an electric
field here in space and that I
take a charge Q in my pocket,
I start at position A and I
walk
around and I return at that
point A.
Since these forces are
conservative forces,
if the electric field is a
static electric field,
there are no moving charges,
but that becomes more
difficult, then the forces are
conservative forces and so the
work that I do when I march
around and coming back at point
A must be zero.
It's clear when you uh look at
the equation number three that
the potential difference
between point A and point A is
obviously zero.
I g- start at point A and I end
at point A and that is the
integral in going from A back to
point A of E dot DL and that
then has to be zero.
And we normally indicate such
an integral with a circle which
means you end up where you
started.
This is a line now this is not
a closed surface
as we had in equation one.
This is a closed line.
And so whenever we deal with
static electric fields we can
add now another equation if we
like that.
And that is if we have a closed
line of E dot DL so we end up
where we started that then has
to become zero.
Later in the course we will see
that there are special
situations where we don't deal
with static
fields when we don't have
conservative E fields,
that that is not the case
anymore.
But for now it is.
So if we know the electric
field everywhere then we -- we
can see equation number two then
we know the potential
everywhere.
And so if we turn it the other
way around if we knew the
potential everywhere you want to
know what the electric field is
and that of course is possible.
If you look at equation two and
three you see that the
potential is the integral of the
electric field.
So it is obvious that the field
must be the derivative of the
potential.
Now when you have fields being
derivative of potentials you
always have to worry about plus
and minus signs,
whether um you have to pay MIT
twenty-seven thousand dollars
tuition to be here or whether
MIT pays you twenty-seven
thousand dollars tuition for
coming here is
only a difference of a minus
sign but it's a big difference
of course.
And so let's work this out in
some detail.
I have here a charge plus Q.
And at a distance R at that
location P we know what the
electric field is,
we've done that a zillion
times.
This is the unit vector in the
direction from Q to that point
and we know that the electric
field is pointing away from that
charge
and we know that the electric
field E we have seen that
already the first lecture is Q
divided by four pi epsilon zero
R squared in the direction of R
roof.
And last lecture we derived
what the electric potential is
at that location.
The electric potential is Q
divided by four pi epsilon zero
R.
This is a vector.
This is a scalar.
So the um potential is the
integral of the electric field
along a line and now I want to
try whether the electric field
can be written as the derivative
of the potential.
So let us take DV DR and let's
see what we get.
If I take this DV DR I get a
minus Q divided by four pi
epsilon
zero R squared.
Of course if I want to know
what the electric field is I
need a vector so I will multiply
both sides, which is completely
legal, there's nothing illegal
about that, with unit vector in
the direction R so that turns
them into vectors.
And now you see that I'm almost
there, this is almost the same,
except for a minus sign.
And so the derivative of the
potential is minus E,
not plus E.
And so I will write
that down here,
that E equals minus DV DR.
So they are closely related if
you know what the -- oh I want
-- I want this to be a vector so
I put here R roof.
Vector on the left side,
you must have a vector on the
right side.
And so if you know the
potential everywhere in space,
then you can retrieve the
electric field.
I mentioned last time that the
electric field vectors -- e-
electric field lines,
are always perpendicular to the
equipotential surfaces.
And that's obvious why that has
to be the case.
Imagine that you are in an --
in space and that you move with
a charge in your pocket
perpendicular to electric field
lines.
So you purposely move only
perpendicular to electric field
lines.
So that means that the force on
you and the direction in which
you move are always at
ninety-degree angles.
So you'll only move
perpendicular to the field
lines.
These are the field lines,
you move like this.
So you never do any work.
Because the dot product between
DL and E is zero and if you
don't do any work the potential
remains the same,
that's the definition.
And so you can see that
therefore equipotential surfaces
must always be perpendicular to
field lines and field lines must
always be perpendicular to the
equipotentials.
And I will show you again the
-- the viewgraph,
the overhead projection of uh
the nice drawing by Maxwell.
With the plus four charge and
the minus one charge.
The same one we saw last time.
Only to point out again this
ninety-degree angle.
I discussed this in great
detail last lecture so I will
not do that.
R- the red lines are really
surfaces.
This is three-dimensional,
you have to rotate the whole
thing about the vertical.
So these are surfaces.
And the red ones are positive
potential surfaces and the blue
ones are negative potential
surfaces.
That is not important.
But the green lines are field
lines.
And notice if I take for
instance this field line,
it's perpendicular here to the
red, perpendicular there,
perpendicular there,
perpendicular there.
Perpendicular here.
Coming in here,
perpendicular,
perpendicular.
Everywhere where you look on
this graph you will see that the
field lines are perpendicular to
the
equipotentials.
And that is something that we
now fully understand.
The situation means then that
if you release a charge at zero
speed that it would always start
to move perpendicular to an
equipotential surface because it
always starts to move in the
direction of a field line,
a plus charge in the direction
of the field line,
minus charge in the opposite
direction.
So if you're in space and you
release a charge at zero speed
it always takes off
perpendicular to
equipotentials.
You have something similar with
gravity.
If you look at maps of
mountaineers,
contours of equal altitude,
equal height,
if you started skiing and you
started at that point,
and you started with zero
speed, you would always take off
perpendicular to the
equipotentials.
So this is the direction in
which
you start to move.
If you start off with zero
speed.
I now want to give you some
deeper feeling of the connection
between potential and electric
fields and I want you to follow
me very closely.
Each step that I make I want
you to follow me.
So imagine that I am somewhere
in space at p- position P.
At that position P there is a
potential, one unique potential,
V of P.
That's a given.
And there is an electric field
at that location where I am.
And now what I'm going to do,
I'm going to make an extremely
small step only in the X
direction.
Not in Y, not in Z.
Only in the X direction.
If I measure no change in the
potential over that little step
it means that the component of
the electric field in the
direction X is zero.
If I do measure a difference in
potential then the component,
the X component of the electric
field, the magnitude of that,
would be that little sidestep
that I have made,
delta X, it would be the
potential difference that I
measure divided by that little
sidestep.
And I keep Y and Z constant.
And these are magnitudes.
But that's why I put these
vertical bars here.
Equally if I made a small
sidestep in the Y direction and
I measured a potential
difference delta V keeping X and
Z constant, that would then be
the component of the electric
field in the Y direction.
Earlier we wrote down for E as
a unit new- newtons per
coulombs.
From now on we almost always
will
write down for the unit of
electric field volts per meter.
It is exactly the same thing as
newtons over coulombs,
there is no difference,
but this gives you a little bit
more insight.
You make a little sidestep in
meters and you measure how much
the potential changes,
it's volts per meters.
It is a potential change over a
distance.
So now I can write down the
connection between electric
field and potential in
Cartesian coordinates.
It looks much more scary than
the nice way that I could write
it down up there.
When I had only a function of
distance R.
And so in Cartesian coordinates
we now get E equals minus,
that minus sign we discussed at
length, and now we get DV DX
times X roof plus DV DY times Y
roof plus
DV DZ times Z roof.
And what you see here,
this first term here,
including of course the minus
sign, that is E of X.
And this term including the
minus sign, that is E of Y.
And so on.
And the fact that you see these
curled Ds it means partial
derivatives.
That means when you do this
derivative you keep Z and Y
constant.
When you do this derivative you
do X and Z constant and so on.
And so this is the Cartesian
notation for which in eighteen
oh two you will learn or maybe
you already have learned we
would write this E equals minus
the gradient of G.
This is a vector function.
This is a scalar function.
And this is just a s- a
different notation,
just a matter of words,
for this mathematical recipe.
And you'll get that with
eighteen in eighteen oh two if
you haven't seen that yet.
So I now want a straightforward
example whereby we assume a
certain dependence on X and I
give you it is a given that V,
the potential,
is ten to the fifth
times X.
So that is a given.
And this holds between X equals
zero and say ten to the minus
two meters.
So it holds over a space of one
centimeter.
So the potential changes
linearly with distance.
What now is the electric field?
In that space?
Well, the electric field I go
back to my description there.
There's only a component in the
X direction.
So the first derivative becomes
minus ten to the fifth times X
roof and the others are zero.
So EY is zero and EZ is zero.
So you may say well yeah whoa
nice mathematics but we don't
see any physics.
This is more physical than you
think.
Imagine that I have here a
plate
which is charged,
it's positive charge.
And the plate is at location X
and I have another plate here,
it's say at location zero.
I call this plate A and I call
this plate B and this plate is
charged negatively.
So X goes into this direction.
So I can put the electric field
inside here according to the
recipe minus ten to the fifth
and it is in the direction of
minus X roof so e- X roof is in
this direction,
the electric field is in the
opposite direction,
and it's the same everywhere
and that is very physical.
We discussed that.
When we discussed the electric
field near very large planes,
that the electric field inside
was a
constant, remember,
and the electric field inside
was sigma divided by epsilon
zero if sigma is the surface
charge density on each of these
plates.
And we argued that the electric
field outside was about zero and
that the electric field outside
here was about zero.
So it's extremely physical.
This is exactly what you see
here.
The electric field minus ten to
the fifth times e- so the
magnitude of this electric field
here, the magnitude,
is ten to the fifth volts per
meter.
What now is the potential
difference?
Well, VA minus VB minus VB is
the integral in going from A to
B of E dot DL.
Well I go from here to here so
I write down for DL I wrote down
DX of course.
Because I called that the X
direction now.
So I will write down here dot
DX.
And so this is minus ten to the
fifth times the integral in
going from A to B of X roof dot
DX.
It looks scary but it is
trivial, the X roof is the unit
vector in this direction.
And DX is a little vector DX in
this direction.
So they're both in the same
direction.
So the cosine,
the angle between the two is
one.
So I can forget about vectors,
I can forget about the dot.
And so this becomes minus ten
to the fifth times the integral
in going from A to B of DX and
that is trivial.
That is minus ten to the fifth
times the location.
I have to do the integral
between A and B.
So I get here X of B minus X of
A.
And if this is ten to the minus
two meters, to go from here to
here is one centimeter,
I must multiply this by ten to
the minus two,
so I get that this is minus one
thousand volts.
So A is a thousand volts lower
than B.
That's what it means.
And that's something that's
very physical.
Notice that if you go from left
to right that the potential
grows linearly,
this is lower than that,
and if you in your head use
planes like this parallel to the
other planes,
each one of those planes would
be equipotentials,
they everywhere have the same
potential.
And gradually when you move it
up your potential increases,
but notice the electric field
goes
from plus to minus in the
opposite direction.
That's always the reason that's
behind that -- that minus sign.
Well clearly I'm always free to
choose where I choose my zero
potential.
We discussed that last time.
You don't always have to choose
infinitely far zero.
So I could choose this
arbitrarily to be zero
potential.
This would then be plus a
thousand.
And so you then find that the
potential V is then simply ten
to the fifth times X,
when X is zero you find the
potential to be zero,
and when X is one centimeter
you find the potential to be a
thousand volts and that then
goes together with the electric
field equals minus ten to the
fifth in this direction.
And so this is extremely
physical.
This is something that you
would have whenever we deal with
parallel plates.
As long as there's no charge
moving,
and we're dealing with solid
conductors, so we have static
electric fields,
the charges are not heavily
moving, then the field inside
the conductor is always zero.
Not the case in a nonconductor.
It's only in a conductor
because conductors have free
electrons to move and if these
free electrons see electric
fields inside which they may
they start to move until they
experience no longer a force,
thereby they kill the electric
field
inside.
So the charge in a conductor
always rearranges itself so that
the electric field becomes zero.
If the field is a static field,
not rapidly changing.
And so now I want to evaluate
with you the situation that I'm
going to charge a solid
conductor and ask myself the
question where does the charge
go.
In honor of um Valentine's Day
let's take a solid heart,
steel heart,
it's solid all the way
throughout.
So this is a solid conductor
and I bring on this conductor
charge from the outside.
Plus or minus,
let's just take plus for now.
And so the question that I'm
asking you now,
this is a conductor,
this is not an insulator,
the story for insulators is
totally different,
this has free moving electrons
inside, I'm asking you now if I
touch this conducting heart --
by the way, your heart is a very
good conductor -- um if you
touch this conducting heart
where would this charge end up?
Where would it go to?
And I leave you with three
choices.
And we'll have a vote on that.
The first choice is that the
plus charges would uniformly
distribute for throughout.
A possibility.
The second possibility,
less likely,
I think, that all the charge
will go to one place there.
I don't know which place that
would be, but maybe.
And then the third possibility
is that maybe the charge will
uniformly distribute itself only
on the outer surface and then
the fourth possibility is none
of the above.
All these suggestions I made
were wrong.
Who think that the charge
might uniformly distribute it
throughout the conductor?
I see one or two hands.
That's good.
Don't feel ashamed of raising
your hands, in the worst case
you're wrong,
I've been so many times wrong
when it comes to this.
Don't feel bad about that.
Who thinks that the charge will
all go to one point in the
heart?
You have the courage?
You think it will go to one
point?
Charge repels each other,
right, so
that doesn't seem likely.
Who thinks that it will
uniformly distribute itself on
the outer surface?
Who thinks none of the above?
Very good.
Well, those who suggested that
it might be uniform on the
outside I would still give them
a B but it's not uniform,
as you will see.
But it will go exclusively to
the outside.
And I will prove that now to
you.
Let us first look for that
ridiculous possibility that the
charge would somehow end up in
the conductor itself.
I take here a Gaussian surface
which is a closed surface.
I know inside the conductor if
we have electrostatic fields,
not fastly moving charges,
but it's a static field,
I know that the E field
everywhere must be zero on the
surface, this is a closed
surface, so the integral of E
dot DA equation one is zero.
That means the charge inside my
sphere is zero and so there
cannot be any charge.
So Gauss's law immediately
kills the possibility that there
would be any charge inside this
conductor.
So that's out of the question.
So that leaves you only with
one choice, that is on the -- at
the surface.
So the charge must be at the
surface.
And later in a later lecture I
will discuss with you the
details why that charge is not
uniformly distributed.
It would be uniformly
distributed at the surface if
this were a sphere.
But not if it has this funny
shape.
But it will be at the surface.
Now I'm going to make this
heart a very special heart,
more like a real heart,
it's open here,
but it is solid here,
so this is a conducting,
the heart muscle,
and here it's open,
there's nothing here.
And again I'm going to charge
it.
Bring charge on the outside.
So now it's obvious that we
don't expect that there is any
charge that will be inside the
conductor.
That's clear,
the same argument
holds with the Gauss's law
argument.
But now is it perhaps possible
that some of the positive charge
will go on the inside of this
surface and some on the outside?
Who thinks that maybe some will
now go on the inside,
because now the situation is
different, right,
there is now,
it's now a hollow conductor.
Anyone in favor of some of that
charge maybe going on the
inside?
I see one hand,
two hands, who says no it's not
possible,
it will not go to the inside?
It will still go to the
outside.
Well, most of you are very
careful now, you don't want to
vote anymore.
It cannot go to the inside.
Why can it not go to the
inside?
Let this be my Gauss surface.
Closed surface.
Think of this as
three-dimensional.
Everywhere on that line the
electric field is zero because
you're inside the conductor.
So the surface integral is also
zero.
So Gauss's law says there
cannot be any charge inside that
box.
And so again the charge has to
go
to the outer surface and
nothing will go to the inner
surface.
And so the conclusion then is
that the electric field is zero
in the conductor but the
electric field is also zero in
this opening.
There's never any charge there.
And so the whole heart
including the cavity is an
equipotential.
There is never any electric
field anywhere.
The only electric field's
outside the heart.
And there are field lines and
these field lines everywhere are
perpendicular to the surface of
the
heart because the heart is an
equipotential.
So here you get very funny
field lines that go like this.
They have to be perpendicular
locally where they reach the
heart wall.
Earlier in my lectures I showed
that a uniformly solid sphere
has electric field zero inside
and I even showed to you that a
hollow conducting sphere also
has zero
electric field inside.
Today I have demonstrated that
it doesn't have to be a sphere.
You don't need spherical
symmetry.
That any shape provided that
it's a hollow conductor,
it has to be a conductor,
any shape will give you an
electric field of zero inside.
And I first want to demonstrate
that.
I have here something that is
not a sphere.
It's a paint can.
It has some aluminum on top.
It has an opening there.
It's not
perfect.
It's not really closed like
this is.
So the electric field inside
will not be exactly zero.
But it will be very close.
I must have an opening because
I want to get in.
I want to get charge,
see whether there is any charge
on the inside.
So I must be able to get
through.
So I'm going to charge this one
and then I will take some charge
off the outside and take some
charge off the inside and use
the electroscope and see whether
we can demonstrate that indeed
there is charge on the outside
but there is nothing on the
inside.
I will use the same method that
I used last time when I
challenged you to figure out how
this works.
This is this crazy method which
we call electrophorus elec-
electrophorus,
it's difficult to pronounce.
Electrophorus.
We have here a glass plate.
I rub it with cat fur.
Think about it again.
It's a
little problem inside the
problem.
Metal plate.
I put it on top.
I touch it.
I get a shock.
I touch it here.
I touch it again.
I get again a shock.
And I charge this up.
I touch it again.
I get another shock.
And I touch it again.
Let's get a little bit more on
it.
The charge on this plate is
positive by the way.
That I create on the glass.
I touch it.
The charge on here is negative.
Not positive.
Put it on again.
Touch it.
OK.
So I should have negative
charge on there now.
Here is little test sphere.
It's a conductor.
I'll take some charge off from
this side.
Touch it.
Boy.
There's charge.
There's no question.
We agree, right?
There's charge.
OK.
Now I touch the inside,
let's hope that no sparks fly
over.
I touch it.
Nothing.
See that?
Absolutely nothing.
So there's no charge inside,
the charge is on the outside.
Which is what I've just
demonstrated.
You see it in front of your own
eyes.
All the charge goes to the
outside.
Not so intuitive but an
immediate consequence of the
fact that it's a conductor that
the electrons will move freely
so that the electric
field in the conductor itself
is zero and we have argued that
no charge can ever go on the
inside of the surface.
It all stays on the outside.
So when I touch the inside
there was no charge.
So if you are inside that
conductor, if your house is a
conducting house,
and someone in the outside
world charges your house up when
you're inside,
you have no knowledge of that.
It's quite amazing,
isn't it?
You are electrically shielded
from the outside world.
Now I'm going to make the
situation even more complicated.
I now take a conducting object,
doesn't have to be a sphere.
And I bring that conducting
object hollow in an external
electric field.
So someone outside your house
is turning on a VandeGraaff
creating an electric field.
What now is going to happen?
Well, due to induction,
you're going to get some charge
polarization in the conductor.
One side may end up negative
and the other side may end up
positive.
But what happens on the inside?
Nothing.
The electric field in the
conductor must stay everywhere
zero if it is a static electric
field.
And so no charge will -- can
accumulate here and no charge
can accumulate on the inside.
And so as you bring this
electric
field on the outside you may
get negative and positive charge
on the outside,
maybe negative here and
positive there,
but inside nothing.
You are inside electrically
shielded from the outside world
in the same way that you were
when someone was trying to put
charge onto your house,
now someone is trying to zap
you with electric fields,
nothing will happen inside.
You will never see an electric
field inside.
I will show you a interesting
drawing, interesting figure,
which is a conducting box.
It's closed.
The cup that you see open is
just to allow you to look inside
but it is closed from all sides.
And there are some negative
charges here and there are
positive charges in the
foreground which you don't see.
The red field lines come from
positive charges,
end up on the box,
and the negative field lines go
from the box to the negative
charges.
There is clear polarization.
The box itself is neutral.
I started with a neutral box.
But because of this electric
field I get polarization.
I end up with negative charge
on the box here,
only on the outside,
positive charge on the box
here, only on the outside.
Inside electric field is zero.
No charge anywhere inside.
Due to this crazy electric
field the free moving charges in
the conductor will rearrange
themselves in such a way that
the electric field is zero
everywhere in the conductor,
is zero inside the cavity,
and that the closed loop
integral of E dot DL is zero
everywhere if these are static
fields.
And it is clearly impossible
for us to ever calculate how
that charge configuration at the
surface will
have to be in order to meet all
those conditions.
But nature can do this
effortlessly.
And it can do it extremely
fast, obeying all the laws of
physics.
It puts very quickly plus
charge here and minus charge
there.
Make sure that there is no
charge on the inside of the
surface.
It makes sure that the electric
field is everywhere zero inside
and in the box and it also makes
sure that the integral E dot DL
is zero everywhere in space.
And therefore the box and
everything inside becomes an
equipotential so it also
arranges matters so that the
field lines wherever they
intersect with the box are
always perpendicular to the box.
And all of that is done in
almost no time at all by nature.
It is an amazing thing that
this happens and something that
as I said would be impossible
for us to calculate because the
field configurations are
extraordinarily difficult.
So if you were inside this
metal box, no matter what
happens
on the outside,
you would be electrically
isolated from the outside world.
You would not notice that there
is a strong electric field
outside, nor would you notice
that people are trying to charge
up your house.
We call that electrostatic
shielding and we give that a
name, that house of yours would
be called a Faraday cage.
It's called after the great
physicist Faraday.
You will learn a lot more about
him during this course.
Before I demonstrate this I
want to address an issue which
is related to problem two-one.
Which is your next assignment.
And I want to urge you,
I make myself no illusion,
but I want to urge you to start
working on that assignment this
weekend, not next week.
These assignments are not just
baby assignments.
These are MIT assignments and
you got to put in a lot of work
to do them, so please start this
weekend not to do me a favor but
to do yourself that favor.
But let's talk about problem
two-one.
In other words I will help you
with that problem two-one.
I said several times that it is
not possible to get an electric
field inside a hollow conductor.
Well, suppose I go inside the
conductor.
I go inside there.
And I put sneakily a charge in
my pocket.
And I sit inside there and you
close it.
Then there is a charge inside,
there's nothing you can do
about it.
And if there is a charge
inside, there is an electric
field.
So now we have a situation and
since it is post Valentine's Day
my heart has evolved into a
sphere again.
So now we take a spherical
conductor, solid,
this is solid material,
and somehow I'm sitting inside
here with a charge plus Q.
Can make it minus if you want
to.
That's exactly the problem
two-one is about.
Now clearly there is positive
charge inside.
So clearly there has to be an
electric field.
But the electric field inside
the conductor,
that means the electric field
anywhere here,
must be zero.
If it's not zero the electrons
will keep moving until it is
zero.
So the conducting material
itself has no electric field.
What does that mean now with
respect to any charge on the
inside surface?
Now there must be charge on the
inside surface.
Because now if I made this my
Gaussian surface,
which is now a spherical
surface, a closed surface,
Mr.
Gauss says that the closed
surface integral of E dot DA
over this surface must be zero
because the electric field is
zero anywhere.
That's the same as all the
charge inside divided by epsilon
zero.
So this -- the charge inside
must be zero.
Since there can be no charge in
the conductor itself,
negative charge must now
accumulate on the inside of that
surface.
So that the net charge inside
this surface is zero.
So now we do get charge on the
inside, and how much charge do
you get on the inside?
Exactly minus Q.
So that the sum of the two is
zero.
Now this conductor originally
was neutral.
It had no net charge.
So therefore on the surface of
the conductor we must now see
charge plus Q.
Because the minus charge on
the inside came from the
induct- conductor itself,
and so the sum must be zero.
So now you get a peculiar
situation that the plus Q charge
inside which creates an E field
inside creates negative charge
on the inside,
the same in magnitude,
opposite in sign,
and plus Q charge on the
outside.
And the electric fields,
they're very complicated.
The electric fields,
let me try to put them in,
I would imagine that if this
charge Q is closer to this wall
than to this wall that the
negative charge here will be
larger in density than there.
It's really an induction
effect.
The negative charge wants to go
to this plus.
That's really what's happening.
And so since this charge is
closer to this wall than to that
wall it will be able to attract
more electrons and so it's clear
that the density of charge here
should be higher than there and
so the field lines always
perpendicular to the
equipotential,
so they must be always
perpendicular to the wall,
sort of like this.
So I put in a few field lines.
But here the field will be
stronger than there.
So there is a field inside.
What now is the charge
distribution on the outside?
That is the hardest of all.
And by no means so obvious.
It turns out that the charge on
the outside on this sphere,
because it is a sphere,
will be uniformly distributed.
And it is not intuitive and it
is not obvious.
Nature must obey all laws of
physics.
The conductor must become an
equipotential.
There can be no electric field
inside the conductor.
Electric field lines have to be
everywhere perpendicular to the
surface.
The closed loop integral of E
dot DL must be zero everywhere.
And the only way that nature
can do that is by making the
charge distribution on the
surface uniform.
And that is amazing when you
think
of that.
It's independent of the
position of that charge plus Q
inside.
So if you start to move around
with that charge plus Q inside,
the outside world will not
know.
The outside world only knows
that there is a charge plus Q
uniformly distributed on the
outside because it is a sphere.
That would not be the case if
it were a heart.
But the outside world has no
way of knowing that you are
moving that charge inside
around.
So I'm sitting inside there and
suppose I crawl inside there
with a rubber rod and with a
cat.
And I use the rubber rod on the
cat creating positive and
negative charge,
same amount.
The outside world will not know
because I don't change the
charge inside.
Only if there's plus Q in my
pocket.
The fact that I create plus on
the cat and maybe minus on
myself, the outside world will
never know because the sum of
the charges is still Q.
They may hear the cat scream,
that's all they can hear.
But they have no way of knowing
that I'm fooling around there
with charges.
And so the outside world has no
way of knowing what happens on
the inside.
And we call that electrostatic
shielding.
That's the effect of a Faraday
cage.
I want to demonstrate when I
bring this can in the electric
field, it's a conducting hollow
object, I bring it in an
electric field of the
VandeGraaff, the thing is a
conductor,
I will show you that because of
the induction you're going to
get like you see on that figure
you're going to get negative
charge on one side,
positive charge on the other
side, and zero charge on the
inside.
That's quite amazing,
isn't it?
If this were positive,
let's assume it is,
then this side becomes
negative, this side becomes
positive, the whole thing is an
equipotential,
no charge inside.
Quite amazing.
So let's turn on this,
the VandeGraaff.
So we create that electric
field.
We turn on the electroscope.
Here is my little Ping Pong
ball conducting and I'm going to
touch first the can on your
side, on your left side,
there we go,
and I bring this charge on the
electroscope.
Boy, nice charge.
I now touch the other side,
and I will approach the -- I
heard a
spark, sparks are always bad.
I approach that electroscope,
and if the reading of the
electroscope,
if the deflection becomes less,
as we discussed earlier,
it means that the polarity that
I have on here is different from
the polarity on the electroscope
and you clearly see that.
The deflection becomes less.
So the charge that I took off
from this side has a different
polarity than the charge that I
took on from that side.
But yet, it's an equipotential.
All that strange polarization
of
charges takes place at the
surface.
And now I will try to get
inside.
To see whether I can get some
charge from the inside,
and there shouldn't be any,
ooh, I have to take this charge
off of course,
and I touch this and you see no
charge.
So you've seen three things,
which is quite amazing.
That the charge on this side
has a different polarity from
the charge on that side,
and that everything happens on
the surface, nothing happens on
the inside.
I could not get any charge
from the inside.
Now we're going to experiment
with more dangerous stuff and
that is with the VandeGraaff.
Here you see a Faraday cage
with hat -- has some openings,
it's not solid conductor,
but it has small openings,
which doesn't change the
situation too much,
maybe only a little,
and I'm going to go inside that
cage, this would also be a nice
Faraday
cage but it's very hard for me
to crawl in there.
And if I go in there with a
radio just like the radio in
your car, then you may not be
able to hear the radio,
even though radio waves is a
difficult story because the
shielding that we discussed is
only electrostatic shielding and
radio waves are electromagnetic
radiation which strongly
changing fields.
So it may not be as perfect a
shielding as you may think.
But we all know if someone
breaks off the antenna of your
car which happens in Cambridge
all the time,
you have no reception inside.
Because your car is a Faraday
cage.
And so what I will do,
I will go into the cage,
I will first show you that when
we charge that cage,
that we bring it up to a few
hundred thousand volts,
I'll just hold some tinsel in
my hand, to convince you that
yes indeed this cage will be
charged by
the VandeGraaff provided there
is contact here.
And we'll see that yes Marcos
give me the full blast,
let's just look at the tinsel,
you see this tinsel clearly
indicates like an electroscope
that I'm being charged now.
So I'll jump off,
if you can discharge.
Then I will go inside.
I will have the tinsel with me.
So I will show you that inside
there when they charge that cage
that the tinsels will not spread
out,
and I will bring with me this
wonderful radio and -- Radio:
Said a woman who opposes
embalming is a suspect in the
murders -- [laughter] I didn't
plan that, believe me.
Radio: [unintelligible] --
self-proclaimed prophet,
Catherine Padilla,
grandmother of ten,
denies the charges and tells a
reporter she's not quote -- I'll
first go in without any charge.
But don't do anything.
Radio: [unintelligible] And
she's one that -- when she calls
her own --
[unintelligible] Nothing.
I'm shielded.
However, there is a problem.
You can still hear me and I'm
wearing a transmitter and the
receiver is somewhere outside
this box.
So why can you still hear me?
That means that the kind of
radio waves that I am
transmitting are very high
frequency, it's not a static
field, so somehow they can get
through.
So the shielding is not perfect
for fast changing electric
fields.
But it's good enough for AM
radios.
So now I'll go in and I'll try
to be brave and he's going to
try to zap me now,
to electrocute me.
But since I've taken eight oh
two, I'm not afraid.
I burned my hand,
that's a different story.
OK.
Marcos.
Do the best you can.
Here are the tinsels.
Run it up a hundred thousand
volts.
Two hundred thousand volts.
I feel as happy like a clam at
high tide inside here.
Nothing is happening.
I'm not worried at all.
If lightning were to strike me
who cares?
I'm in a Faraday cage.
Not going to spoil my weekend.
I can touch the inside.
There's no charge anywhere
here.
My weekend won't be spoiled.
And I hope that the new
assignment is not going to spoil
yours either.
See you next Tuesday.