PROFESSOR: Welcome back.
So in this session, we're going
to look at sinusoidal
inputs for ordinary
differential
equations of order one.
So here in question one, you're
asked to use complex
techniques to solve x dot plus
kx equals cosine of omega t.
Here k and omega
are constants.
This is of ODE of first order.
And the sinusoidal input is
referring to the right-hand
side of the ODE where basically
the we are forcing a
system with a function and
its sinusoidal of angular
frequency omega, which
means basically a
period of 2pi over omega.
So you're asked to use complex
techniques to solve this in
question a.
In question b, we're asked to
use what we had in question a
to solve this modified function,
where again, we have
a sinusoidal input on the
right-hand side with an
additional amplitude F,
which is now constant.
In the third part, we're asked
to use superposition principle
to solve this combined equation,
where now we're
introducing a value for example
for F, which is 3.
And you can see also that the
right-hand side is also a
sinusoidal input, because it's
a linear combination of
sinusoidal functions.
All these equations are linear
with constant coefficients,
and hence superposition
principle would hold.
So why don't you stop the video,
take a few minutes, and
work through the problems.
And we'll be back.
Welcome back.
So what is it that we're
asked to do here?
We're asked to solve this using
a trick that you learned
in class to basically convert
a real valued ODE into a
complex form.
So the first thing to do is to
realize that the cosine of
omega t is simply the real part
of the imaginary complex
exponential i omega t.
So when we realize that, and
we see that the ODE is real
valued linear, we can convert
its real value ODE into this
complex valued ODE.
And we're going to label
this equation star.
From this point, we can go back
to the techniques that we
learned in class, namely the
integrating factor, to realize
that we can rewrite the
right-hand side in this form,
introducing a new function u,
so that we need to seek a
function u that will
then recover this
function, this equation.
And from previous recitations
and problem, we saw that
clearly the u that we would
need to pick is just
exponential of kt.
So now from this, basically
we're back to i omega plus k
the whole thing t on the
right-hand side, and here zu
prime that we just need to
integrate on both sides.
So this is simply kt z on
the left-hand side.
And on the right hand side,
we're integrating--
again, it's still
an exponential,
even though it's complex.
And we need to introduce,
of course, constant of
integration.
So the solution for the equation
star is then, I'm
going to write it up here, that
we keep that for the rest
of the problem, minus t minus
kt when I divide by this.
And here, the minus kt of this
exponential is going to be
canceled out by the integrating
factor.
So we need to keep that here.
So here I gave the general
solution with the solution
that would come from the
homogeneous equation, which
could refer to also as a
transient here, because
basically after a long time, t,
this exponential, if k is
positive, would decay.
And the part of the solution
that comes from the sinusoidal
input, or the forcing, which
would be particular solution.
So to go back to the original
question, we were asked to
solve this real valued
equation.
So from what we noticed above,
we saw that the right-hand
side is just a real part of
the right-hand side of the
complex value equation star.
And similarly then, we can do
the same for the actual
solutions themselves.
x is also just a real value
of this complex number.
So here, for this general
solution, I'm going to just
use c bar for general complex
constant here.
And in this case, we will
take the real value.
So at this point, it doesn't
really matter what t is.
It's just we're going to
keep it as a constant.
And now it's just real valued.
That's for the one part.
And then we need to take the
real part of this expression.
Come back to the line here.
So to take the real part of this
expression, you learned
that basically you just need to
multiply the denominator or
the numerator by the
complex conjugate.
And that will only give us--
So we have k minus i omega over
the squares, and then
again, Euler formula that we saw
in a previous recitation.
So x from this expression
is just a real
part of all of this.
So it's going to be this term.
Let me factorize for a moment
here, and then the result of
multiplying the two complex
parts as well,
either i minus 1.
And so that answers part
a of the problem.
So if we look at part b--
I'm just going to do it here--
part b we're asked to
do to solve a very,
very similar equation.
And I'm just going to leave
the f out for now.
It's basically the same
equation, except that the
input now is a sine instead
of a cosine.
So we can use the same trick as
we used for question a by
realizing that now the sine is
just an imaginary part of the
exponential, the complex
exponential.
So we don't need to
redo all the work.
We only need to, if we were
considering this equation, to
just take the imaginary part of
the solution that we just
found here.
And we can just read off the
solution from this line.
Note that in this expression,
I left out the homogeneous
part, which I should
add here from here.
And this was just
a complex part.
So to come back to what I was
saying, the sine is just the
imaginary part of the
complex exponential.
So we're just going to write
down the solution
by reading off here.
So again, we have the
homogeneous part, which would
be another real valued constant,
and then the real
part of this expression,
1 over k
squared plus omega squared.
And it's imaginary part then
would give us a k sine omega t
and a minus omega cos omega t.
So this would be the solution
for part b,
if we had this equation.
But we actually have an equation
with an additional
amplitude F. And what this
leads to do is just an
additional constant that would
appear then for this solution.
And we could see that if we
rewound the way we solved in
part a, and saw that introducing
constant F to the
equation is equivalent to just
multiplying the full equation
with F. And then in the
integrating factor part, we
would end up with an F in front
of our solution when we
are doing the integration.
And so basically, that amplitude
could be absorbed in
the constant of integration
for the homogeneous part.
And the F just remains in the
particular solution here.
So for the last part of the
problem, we were now asked to
use the superposition principle
to combine solutions
of two previous ODEs that
we could split from this
equation, cosine omega t
plus 3 sine omega t.
So you saw from previous
recitations that superposition
principle applies for
linear equations.
This is clearly a
linear equation.
And here on the right-hand
side, we have
two sinusoidal functions.
Because it's linear we can look
at this by splitting it
into two equations.
And I'm just introducing x1, x2
as notation to distinguish
between the two.
And here we can recognize that
we already did this work that
was in part a, and we already
did this work in part b, where
F now has a value of 3.
And so what this is telling
us, because it's a linear
equation, we can use
superposition principle, the
solution, if you were to do
the addition of these two
equations, would just be the sum
of the previous solutions
that we found.
So this would be our x3, if I
had labeled this with a 3.
And so basically, the solution
is simply the sum of the two
previous forms. And so we would
end up still with our c
minus kt, which is this
basically the homogeneous part
that we obtained in
the two previous
parts, which is common.
And then we just need to add
each particular solution
introduced in part
a and part b.
So if I have room I will
write it all out.
So we would have k cos omega t
plus omega sine, omega t from
the first part of the cosine.
And then we're introducing a 3k
sine omega t minus 3 omega
cosine omega t.
And that would be then
the solution of the
combined two equations.
And so you don't need to redo
the full work by using the
superposition principle.
So here the key was just to
recognize that the cosines and
the sines are basically real
parts and imaginary parts of
the complex number, of the
exponential of i omega t.
Again, it's just
Euler formula.
And using that as a shortcut to
be able to kill two birds
with one stone and solve the
two equations by using only
one approach, which is just
the integrating factor.
And this ends the session
for today.