JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've learned
about gradients and about
directional derivatives.
So I have a problem here to
test your understanding of
those objects and give you some
practice computing them.
So I have three functions
here.
And for each function,
I've given you
a point and a direction.
So what I'd like you to do is
compute the gradients of the
functions, then evaluate their
gradients at the point given,
and then compute the directional
derivative of the
function at the point in the
direction of the vector given.
So here, for example, in part a,
I've given you the function
f of x, y equal to x squared y
plus xy squared, at the point
x equal minus 1, y equal 2, and
in the direction of the
vector 3, 4.
And then we've got two more
examples here. g of x, y, z is
equal to the square root of x
squared plus y squared plus z
squared, P is the point 2,
6, minus 3, and v is the
direction 1, 1, 1.
And our third example, h is a
function of four variables, w,
x, y, and z.
It's given by wx plus wy plus wz
plus xy plus xz plus yz, at
the point 2, 0, minus 1, minus
1, in the direction 1, minus
1, 1, minus 1.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to work
out these three problems,
come back, and we can
work them out together.
I hope you had some luck working
out these problems.
Let's get started on
the first one.
So on the first one, our
function f of x, y is equal to
x squared y plus xy squared.
So to compute the gradient, I
just have to compute the first
partials of our function,
and then put them
into a single vector.
So that's what the
gradient is.
So we have that the gradient
of f at x, y is
equal to the vector.
And its first component is the
first partial of f with
respect to x, so that's going
to be 2xy plus y squared.
And its second component is the
partial of f with respect
to y, so that's going to
be x squared plus 2xy.
So this is the gradient
of our function f.
Now, the question asked you to
compute this gradient at the
particular point minus 1, 2.
So we have gradient of f at the
point minus 1, 2 is equal
to-- well, we just put in x
equal minus 1, y equal 2 into
this formula.
So at x equal minus 1, y equals
2, this is 2 times
minus 1 times 2 plus
2 squared.
So that's minus 4 plus
4, so that's just 0.
And the second term is minus
1 squared plus 2 times
minus 1 times 2.
So that's 1 plus 4-- nope--
1 plus negative 4, so
that's negative 3.
All right.
So this is the gradient
of our function f.
This is the gradient at
the point minus 1, 2.
Now we are asked for the
directional derivative.
So we were asked for the
directional derivative of f in
a direction.
So we're given, I didn't give
you, I gave you a vector v.
But when we take directional
derivatives, what we want is a
unit vector.
Right?
So the vector v that
I gave you--
was right over here--
it was this vector 3, 4.
And so we need to find the unit
vector u in the direction
of v in order to apply
our usual formula.
So u is just v divided by the
length of v. So in this case,
the vector 3, 4, by the
Pythagorean theorem,
it has length 5.
So this is equal to the
vector 3/5 comma 4/5.
And so our directional
derivative in the
direction of v--
which is this vector u--
it's just equal to the gradient
at that point dotted
with the direction vector.
So this is equal to gradient
of f at that point dot u.
Which in our case
is equal to--
well, since we're interested
at the point P--
it's equal to 0, minus
3, dot our vector u,
which is 3/5, 4/5.
And that dot product
is negative 12/5.
So in this direction, the
function is decreasing at
about this rate at
the given point.
All right.
That's part a.
Let's go on to part b.
So, you know, you've probably
noticed that these questions
are all fairly similar.
The only real complication is
that I've been increasing the
number of variables.
But of course, you know how to
take a gradient for a function
of three variables as well.
So in this case, our function
g of x, y, z is given by the
square root of x squared plus
y squared plus z squared.
So, if you like, this is the
function that measures the
distance of a point
from the origin.
And so we're asked first
for the gradient, so
the gradient of g.
What do I do?
Well, again, I just take these
partial derivatives.
This is going to be a tiny
bit messy, I'm afraid.
Because I take a partial
derivative of this expression
with respect to x, I've got to
apply the chain rule, right?
Because this is a composition
of functions here.
So OK.
So, what do I get?
I get the derivative of
the inside times the
derivative of the out.
So the outside function
is a square root, so
that's to the 1/2 power.
So I get 1/2 times the thing
inside to the minus 1/2 power.
So it's over 2, times the square
root of x squared plus
y squared plus z squared.
And then I need to multiply by
the derivative of the inside,
which is times 2x.
OK.
So, and then the 2's cancel, and
that's x over square root
of x squared plus y squared
plus z squared.
And similarly, this is a nice
symmetric function, and, you
know, if I changed x and
y, it's the same.
So the other partial derivatives
look very similar.
So they're going to be y over
the square root of x squared
plus y squared plus z squared.
And z over the square root
of x squared plus y
squared plus z squared.
Sorry.
That's a little bit of
a long formula there.
But there we have it.
That's the derivative-- or,
sorry, not the derivative.
That's the gradient.
The vector of partial
derivatives.
So now you were asked also to
compute this gradient at a
particular point.
So the point in question--
I have to look back over here.
And the point in question was
this point 2, 6, minus 3.
So at the point 2, 6,
minus 3, we want
to compute the gradient.
So we just take these numbers
back over to our formula over
there, and we're going
to put them in.
So we take the gradient
of g at 2, 6, minus 3.
Well, OK, so this square root
of x squared plus y squared
plus z squared appears in all
terms. So let's compute that
first.
So x squared is 4, y squared
is 36, and z squared is 9.
So I add those numbers
together, I get 49.
And then I take a square root
of that and I get 7.
So these denominators are all
going to be 7, and then up top
I just have x, y, and z.
So this is going to be 2 over
7 comma 6 over 7 comma
minus 3 over 7.
All right.
So just what I get by plugging
the values at our point into
this formula.
So this is the gradient
at that point.
And now once again, I want
to compute a particular
directional derivative
of this function.
So in order to do that, I just
need the right unit factor,
and I need to dot it.
So the direction that I asked
you was the direction v with
coordinates 1, 1, 1.
So of course again, this
isn't a unit vector.
So we need to divide it by its
length to find the unit vector
that we're going to use.
So the length of this vector
is the square root of 1
squared plus 1 squared plus
1 squared, so that's the
square root of 3.
So u is equal to--
well, I'm just going
to write it as--
1 over the square root of 3
times the vector 1, 1, 1.
And so the directional
derivative dg ds in the
direction u hat is-- again,
it's what I get, I dot the
gradient with this u--
it's gradient dot u.
Which in our case, so that one
over the square root of 3
lives out front.
And now I dot 2/7, 6/7, minus
3/7 with 1, 1, 1.
And that's just going to give
me 2/7 plus 6/7 minus 3/7.
And OK, so we can finish off
the arithmetic there, and I
think that's 5, over 7
square root of 3 if I
didn't make any mistake.
Now, the last one, very,
very similar.
Now we have a function
of four variables.
There's really nothing
new there at all.
So let me rewrite,
so for part c.
We have h of w, x, y, z is equal
to wx plus wy plus wz
plus xy plus xz plus yz.
So, for the gradient of h, I
just take the four partial
derivatives.
Now here, w is first. So I take
the partial derivative
with respect to w as the
first coordinate.
So that's going to be
x plus y plus z.
And then I take the partial
derivative with respect to x
as the second coordinate.
So that's going to be
w plus y plus z.
And similarly, the last two
are w plus x plus z, and w
plus-- that's a plus--
x plus y.
Whew.
OK.
So that's my gradient.
Those are my partial
derivatives.
Now, I asked you again
for the gradient at
a particular point.
So that's grad h at the point
2, 0, minus 1, minus 1.
So we can just plug that in.
Here, it's 0 plus minus 1
plus minus 1 is minus 2.
Here it's 2 plus minus 1
plus minus 1, that's 0.
Here, it's 2 plus 0 plus
minus 1 so that's 1.
And lastly, it's 2 plus
0 plus minus 1 is 1.
So that's the gradient of this
function h at this point P.
And now I gave you again, I gave
you a vector v. So this
was the vector 1, minus
1, 1, minus 1.
And I asked you to find the
directional derivative at this
point in that direction.
Again, we need a unit vector.
This isn't a unit vector.
So u is equal to v over the
length of v. Well, what is the
length of v in this case?
It's over the square root of--
well, we square the coordinates
and add them.
So that's 1 plus 1
plus 1 plus 1.
So that's 4: square
rooted is 2.
So that's v over 2.
And finally, I get that the
directional derivative dh ds
in this direction u, is what I
get when I dot this gradient
together with the direction
in which I'm heading.
So this is minus 2, 0, 1, 1.
The gradient dotted with the
unit vector of the direction.
Which we just computed.
And so finally, you could expand
this out yourself.
I won't right down the final
answer, but it's just a dot
product, right?
All right.
So hopefully this has gotten you
totally comfortable with
computing gradients and with
computing directional
derivatives from gradients.
So I'll end there.