PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
Today in this video, what I'd
like us to do is work on some
solid of revolution problems.
Well, one solid
of revolution problem.
So what I want us to do in this
one is, find the volume
of the solid generated by
rotating the region bounded by
these three curves, x equals 0,
y equals 5, and y equals x
squared plus 1, about
the y-axis.
And I'm forcing you--
or I'm requesting--
that you use the disk method.
So I want us to work on the
disk method in this case.
So why don't you take a
crack at the problem?
And then I'll be back.
OK, welcome back.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to work on finding
the volume of a solid generated
by rotating this
region that's bounded by the
three curves mentioned about
the y-axis.
And as I said before, we're
going to use the disk method.
So when you're solving these
problems, the first thing you
want to do is give yourself at
least a rough sketch of what
this region looks like, of with
the region bounded by
these three curves actually
looks like.
So the first thing I'm going
to do before I do anything
else, is at least get a rough
sketch of what that region
looks like.
And I'll do that over
here on the right.
So, let's see.
We know we've got the region--
let me actually even use some
different colored chalk.
We'll say the x equals 0
is actually the y-axis.
That's x equals 0.
And then y equals 5--
actually we'll put that in last.
But y equals x squared
plus 1 is the parabola
y equals x squared
shifted up by 1.
So if this is y equals 1,
then it's just roughly
something like this.
That might not look like
the best parabola
I've ever seen, but.
Well, something roughly
like that.
Maybe, as I said,
rough sketch.
Maybe more like that.
And then, we want to also put in
the y equals 5, which I'll
say is roughly about here.
So I could--
notice I've got these
three curves.
This curve, this curve,
this curve.
So I'm interested in this
region right here.
Right?
Notice that if I also include
this region, when I rotated
that around, I'd actually get
the same solid, whether I
included this region or not.
But in terms of doing the
integration, I want to make
sure I don't count
anything doubly.
So I'm just looking at what
happens when I take this piece
and I rotate it around
the y-axis.
So what do we want to do?
We said we want to use
the disk method.
Which means ultimately, I'm
looking for finding out what
the radius is.
Right?
I'm doing pi r squared
when I integrate.
So I'm interested in finding
this length--
that's going to be
our radius--
and then we rotate--
you probably can't see that;
so let me just say that's
going to represent our radius.
And then when we rotate
that around the
y-axis we get our disk.
Right?
We've seen some pictures
of this before.
So I'm interested in
this length here.
And because I want to use the
disk method, I'm forcing us to
figure out what is this
value in terms of y?
So we know we have, well we know
that y equals x squared
plus 1 there.
So in terms of y, this is y
minus 1 equals x squared.
So the square root of y
minus 1 is equal to x.
So this is the expression I'm
interested in as our radius,
as my radius.
Right?
And now, what I need to do is
figure out, I know if this is
the radius I need to figure out,
since I'm doing this in
terms of y, what this lower
bound is for y and what the
upper bound is for y.
And then I'm going to be
integrating pi times the
radius squared over y, over
the changes in y.
Now let's see.
This one's easy. y
equals 5 up here.
And what is this value here?
Well, the function that I
had here was y equals x
squared plus 1.
So when x is 0, y is 1.
So this is the value
where y equals 1.
So I know what I'm interested
in doing.
Again, let me write it down.
Is I'm integrating from 1
to 5 of pi r squared dy.
And now, I need to write
r as a function of y.
So r is square root
of y minus 1.
When I square that, I
just get y minus 1.
So what I'm really interested
in integrating is, the
integral from 1 to 5 of--
let me put the pi outside,
because who cares--
pi times that integral,
y minus 1 dy.
And if I actually evaluate
this, figure out, if I
actually take the integral, use
my rules for polynomials,
I can get a numerical value.
I'm going to stop evaluating
here, because from here on I
know you guys can do it.
But, the point of this problem,
what I want to
mention, the point of this
problem is the main thing we
had to do is figure out what is
the radius in terms of y.
That was the main thing we had
to figure out in order to do
this problem.
I said you had to use disks.
So we had to figure out what the
radius was in terms of y.
And then we had to figure
out what the bounds
were in terms of y.
And once we do that, it's a
simple matter of evaluating
this integral, or finding the
actual value for what this
integral is.
So I think that is
where I'll stop.