PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video we're going
to do another solid
of revolution problem.
So what I'd like to do in this
problem is to find the volume
of the solid generated by
rotating the region bounded by
the following curves: y equals
0, x equal 4, and y equals
square root of x, around
the line x equals 6.
And you can choose your favorite
method to do this.
What I would like first, when
you're doing this kind of
problem, is get a rough
sketch of the region.
So you have some picture
of what's
actually going to happen.
You don't necessarily need a
three-dimensional picture.
But at least have the
two-dimensional region and
understand the where the
rotation line is, with respect
to that region.
So I will give you a little
bit of time to
work on that problem.
And when I come back I'll
show you how I do it.
OK, welcome back.
So again, what we're doing in
this video is we're going to
be looking, finding the volume
of a solid of revolution.
And as I mentioned, the first
thing you want to do is get a
rough picture of what the
region looks like
that's being rotated.
So I'm going to draw a
rough sketch of that.
Right here.
So my axes, here's my x-axis
and my y-axis, and I will
draw, first the curve
y equals 0.
That's y equals 0.
And I'm next going to draw the
curve y equals square root of
x to make this a little easier
for myself to do that one
first. So y equals square root
of x looks something like
this, roughly.
And then, x equal 4, because
it's a very rough sketch, I
can just draw this line right
here and say that
line's x equal 4.
And I want the region bounded
by those three curves.
So, this region right here.
And my rotating line, in this
case, is x equals 6.
So to give myself some
perspective, I remember this
is x equals 4, here's
x equals 0.
So x equals 6, which may be
right about here, I'll draw a
dotted line.
And I'm going to draw a little
arrow around there so I know
that's the line I'm
rotating about.
Now we notice there's a little
bit of a gap here.
But you can actually work on
this problem quite simply.
If we use the shell method, we
won't have to worry about the
gap at all.
We will have to be careful in
how we determine our radius.
That's actually where
you'll see this sort
of gap coming up.
So when I rotate this around,
I'm going to get some object
that's going to have
a nice curve here.
And there's going to be a little
cut-out, a cylinder
missing in the middle
when I rotate it.
So I'm going to use
the shell method.
I like the shell method
for this problem.
You could use the Washer method
for this problem, but I
like the shells and that's
what I'm going to use.
So to do the shell method,
remember we are going to be
interested in 2 pi rh.
That's really what we need.
And now what we want to figure
out is, do I want to do this
in terms of x or in terms of y?
All right?
When I talk about these shells
is it better to think about
them as functions of x or y?
And it will, you'll see we sort
of have to think about
them in a certain way.
So if I draw, let's think about
if I draw a straight
line down and I rotate it around
the line x equals 6,
which I should have labeled
here, then I get my shell.
So I need these lines
to go from 0 to 4.
I need to have those lines
go from 0 to 4.
And so I see that it's the
x value I'm varying over.
So I know this is all going to
be an integral in terms of x.
So let's keep that in mind.
So r, I should write as a
function of x and h I should
write as a function of x.
So if I examined this segment
again here, the height is
fairly simple.
Because what is this curve?
This is the curve y equals
square root of x.
So the height is just,
So h is equal to square
root of x.
And so now I just need
r in terms of x.
Well let's look at this
segment again.
It's just a generic position.
How would I find that radius?
What is the radius?
Well I'm going to draw
the three-dimensional
picture over here.
That that's this curve, this
segment, rotated about the
line x equals 6.
Right?
And the radius is not x.
It's the distance from x
equals 6 to my segment.
That's an important distinction
we should
understand.
If we come back and look
at this picture,
this is not the radius.
Right?
The radius is the distance
from this value to
this value in x.
And how do I measure that?
Well that's fairly
straightforward.
That's the difference in x
values between these two.
The x value here is 6.
And the x value here,
this is a generic x.
So the difference, the distance,
is just 6 minus x.
Right?
This is just a simple case
of the distance formula.
Because I'm not interested in
the changes in y, at all.
I'm just interested
in the difference
between these two x values.
So it's simply 6 minus x.
That's our radius.
So now I have the radius
in terms of x.
And I have the height
So I can completely set
up my integral.
So let me come a little
bit further over
and set up the integral.
So I know I'm integrating--
we even said what we were
integrating from and to already.
I'm starting x at 0.
And I'm stopping it
at x equal 4.
And then I want to integrate
2 pi rh.
So I'll put the 2
pi out in front.
The radius is 6 minus x.
And the height is square
root of x.
And then I'm integrating
it all in dx.
And at this point, solving
the problem is fairly
straightforward.
I can write square root of x as
x to the 1/2 to make myself
feel a little better about it.
I can then distribute.
And then I just use the power
rule to do the integration and
evaluate to get an actual
number, to get that volume.
So I'm going to go back and
just make sure we remember
what all the pieces are and that
we feel comfortable with
doing this type of problem.
And I'll let you finish and
evaluate that if you would
like to know an actual number.
So let's come back over.
We were finding the volume
of a solid a generated by
rotating a certain region around
the line x equals 6.
The way this might be different
from some of the
problems you've seen before, is
it's not the x or y axis.
And the region has a gap.
The region is not connected
to the line of rotation.
So if we come to see
our picture, we
can see that clearly.
The rotating region is
the blue region.
The line of rotation
is the dotted line.
So there's a little bit
of a gap there.
I let you pick your
favorite method.
I chose shells, because I didn't
have to worry about
subtracting off pieces, this
little piece here.
It was inherent in the radius,
the way I determined the
radius and the x values
that I chose.
So I used shell method.
And so how did I, I had to
figure out a couple things.
I had to figure out first, what
variable I was doing this
in, x or y.
And then I had to figure out the
radius and height in terms
of that variable.
You figure out what variable you
need by saying, OK if I'm
doing shells, I'm looking at
these kinds of segments.
And I'm varying the x values,
then, as I move and look at
those different segments.
So I know that this is
a dx type of problem.
I know I'm integrating
something in x.
So then I have to find radius
and height in terms of x.
The height's the freebie.
It's just from 0 up
to the function.
The radius is maybe
a little harder.
But that's still just the
distance between the line of
rotation and the point
where you are.
And so that's 6 minus x.
And then I just set up the
integral from there.
So that's really what the idea
is in doing these types of
problems. And because we get to
pick our simplest way, for
me it was shells.
Maybe you picked Washer's.
But for me, this problem, the
simplest way is shells.
So I guess that's
where I'll stop.