DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
In this question, we're going
to be considering a contour
plot, which is given
to us as followed.
The values are not indicated.
So the first thing that
we want to do
is we want to identify--
on this contour plot, there is
a unique saddle point, and we
want to label that as point A,
and there are two points which
are either a maximum
or a minimum.
We can't actually tell because
the labels aren't on this
contour plot, but we want to
go ahead and label those
anyways: B and C. So they're
either maximum or minimum, but
we can still find them and we
can still identify them.
So that's the first part
of the problem.
The second part is since this
doesn't have the values
entered onto the graph, we want
to consider what possible
configurations could we have?
So the second question is: can
B and C both be maximal?
And can we have B maximal
but C minimal?
OK.
And then in each of these
two cases, we want to
sketch the 3D graph.
So why don't you take some
time to work this out.
Pause the video, and we'll check
back, and I'll show you
how I solve this.
Hello, and welcome back.
So to get started, why don't we
answer the first question
by writing the points right
on our original graph.
So I'll just come over here.
Now, when we're looking for a
minimum or a maximum on a
contour plot, you know, the
thing that we should keep in
mind is that a minimal or a
maximal always is going to be
contained in concentric contours
that are either
approaching the minimum
from below or--
excuse me-- approaching the
maximum from below or the
minimum from above.
And so if we look here, we see
that these rings start to
become concentric, and somewhere
in here, there's got
to be either a maximum
or a minimum.
Because, you know, inside this
little region here, the
function doesn't pass through
another contour plot, so we
have to find either a maximum
or a minimum inside the
innermost ring.
And similarly, we have to
find either a minimum
or a maximum here.
So let's just call this one
B and this one C. OK.
Now, we also have a saddle point
A in this problem, and
it's a little bit hard to
see in the contour plot.
I think it'll be a little even
clearer when we draw a 3D
graph, but basically what's
happening is the fact that you
have these contours--
so this contour is, after all,
the same as that contour.
So the value of the function
here and here are the same,
and yet, if we look at this
point and this point, the
values, they'll either
go up or down.
We don't know.
Let's assume that they go up.
So here, in this direction, the
values are going up, and
in this direction, the values
are determined by this contour
curve, and so somewhere in
this middle region here,
there's got to be
a saddle point.
I think this'll be even clearer
when we draw our graph.
So we have a saddle point
A in the middle there.
And, in fact, this is really,
this is the general picture of
what a saddle point is
going to look like.
It's going to be when you have
two either maxima or minima
rising out, and you have a
contour which is containing
the point in the middle.
So those are our points A, B and
C that we're going to be
interested in.
So now, the second question that
we have to consider is
can B and C both be maximal?
And the third question is can
B be maximal and C minimal?
And actually, we'll answer both
of these questions by
just sketching an example,
so that's how will we'll
understand this.
So why don't we see if we can
sketch an example where B and
C are both maximal.
So here's the start of my graph
in three dimensions, and
if we want B and C to both be
maximal, then let me go ahead
and draw the contour lines
that we have. So we have,
first of all, we had this one,
and then we had another one,
and then we had a peak, and
then we had a peak.
So if we want to draw this in
three dimensions, then what we
just need to do is we just need
to follow these contour
plots up out of the plane
and into space.
So this goes up, and then
there's a maximum, and then it
comes back down along the
contour lines, and then it
goes back up, and then
it goes back down.
So that's just one of the curves
that lies on the graph
of the function, but then we
need to flush out the contour
lines, which they look like
these sort of rings here.
OK?
And so, indeed, we do see that
it's possible for both B and C
to be a maximal.
Here's an example
of such a thing.
And so here's our point B,
here's our point C, and as
promised, I think it's much
clearer now how A becomes a
saddle point.
Because you have these two
mountains rising up, and the
valley in between them
is necessarily a
little saddle here.
It increases in this
direction and it
decreases in this direction.
Now, for the second one, we're
asked can B be maximal and yet
C be minimal?
And the answer is still yes.
And a nice way to think about
this problem, to think about
the graph that I'm going to
draw, is imagine that we start
over here and we dig a hole, and
as we're digging, we throw
the dirt over behind us.
So we're going to have a hole,
a dip here, and then we're
going to pile that hole
up over here.
And so then--now, notice that
both of these that I've drawn,
if we don't label the contour
lines, these have the same
contour plot, because the
concentric rings on C, which
are telling us that the function
in increasing,
they're the same below, because
this is essentially
the same thing.
The concentric rings that on
this curve, on this surface,
were telling us that B was a
maximal point, now the same
rings are telling us that
B is a minimal point.
So this illustrates that a
contour plot is really--
doesn't tell you everything
about the graph unless you
actually label the values
of the contours.
So here we see two examples
where the sort of global
behavior of B and C are very
different even though they
have the same contour plot.
Now notice, in both cases,
A is a saddle point.
It's increasing in
one direction and
decreasing in the other.
And I think I'll leave
it at that.