DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
Today what we want to work on
is drawing level curves.
This is for all the artists
out there in the audience.
We have three functions here: z
is 2x plus y, z is x squared
plus y squared, and z is x
squared minus y squared, and
we want to get some practice
drawing their level curves.
Now, just to remind you, the
level curves are not drawn in
three dimensions.
They're drawn in the xy-plane
and they're constructed by
setting z to be a constant and
then graphing the curve that
we get, so we can think about a
relief map that we might use
if we were hiking.
So why don't you get
started on that.
Pause the video, and we'll check
back, and I'll show you
how I solve this.
Welcome back.
So over here, we've got
the equation for part
a already set up.
So z is 2x plus y.
So now, what we need to
do to get started is
just draw the xy-axis.
And, you know, there's really
not a precise science for
drawing these level
curves out.
We just need to choose some
values of z that we feel are
representative and then
just draw them in.
So one thing we notice about
this is that if we choose z to
be a constant, then the
equations that we're going to
get is 2x plus y equals
some constant, right?
So, you know, these are just
going to be lines.
The level curves in this case
are just going to be lines.
So, for instance, if we take the
level curve at z equals 0,
then we have just the equation
2x plus y equals 0.
And so that has intercept--
so we're looking at--
so 0 equals 2x plus y, so that's
just y equals minus 2x.
So that's this level curve.
That's the level curve
at z equals 0.
Now, if you think about it, all
the other level curves,
we're just going to be varying
the constant here, and so
we're just going to be
shifting this line.
So all of our level curves
in this case are
just straight lines.
So let's see if we can make
some sense out of that by
thinking about the
graph in three
dimensions of this function.
So over here, I'm
going to draw.
So this function z equals 2x
plus y, if we draw its graph,
it's just a plane, right?
So it's just a plane, which
I'll just kind of draw in
cartoon form, something
like that.
And now when we do level curves,
what we're doing is
we're slicing this plane with
another plane, which is the
horizontal values where
z is a constant.
And so, for instance, if we
take the level curve here,
then we're just intersecting
these two planes, and their
intersection is just a line, and
that's exactly the lines
that we're drawing here.
So it's not surprising that
we were graphing a linear
function and that our contour
lines, our level curves, were
just straight lines.
So let's go on to a slightly
more interesting example,
which is part b, which I
have written up here.
So this is the function
z equals x
squared plus y squared.
Actually, this is even easier
to get started drawing the
level curves for.
Well, if you think about it, if
I fix the value of z, then
this is exactly the equation
for the circle with radius
square root of z.
So level curves, level curves
for the function z equals x
squared plus y squared,
these are just
circles in the xy-plane.
And if we're being careful and
if we take the convention that
our level curves are evenly
spaced in the z-plane, then
these are going to get closer
and closer together, and we'll
see in a minute where
that's coming from.
So let's draw what's going
on in three dimensions.
So if we graph z equals x
squared plus y squared in
three dimensions, this is just
a paraboloid opening up.
And now what you can see is that
if we slice this through
the constant, through z equals
constant planes, then we're
just getting these circles, and
those are precisely the
circles that we're drawing
on the level curve.
And because the parabola gets
steeper and steeper, that's
telling us that these circles,
if we keep incrementing z in a
constant way, that's telling us
that the circles, which are
the shadows below here, are
going to get closer and closer
and closer.
This reflects the fact
that this is
getting steeper and steeper.
In fact, this is
generally true.
If you're looking at a contour
plot where the intervals
between level curves are at
regular distances, then very
close contour lines means
that the function
is very steep there.
So that's something
to keep in mind.
Let's look at one
more example.
This is z equals x squared
minus y squared.
So to get started with this,
well, again, if we start
choosing constant values of
z, this is just giving us
hyperbola, hyperbolas
of two sheets.
So, for instance, if we take--
so let's see what happens
if we take z equals 0.
So if we take z equals
0, then something a
little special happens.
This becomes x plus y times
x minus y equals 0.
We can factorize x squared minus
y squared as x plus y
times x minus y, and if this is
0, then that means either
plus y is 0 or x minus y is 0.
So that tells is that the zero
level curves for this graph
are the lines y equals minus
x and the lines y equals x.
OK.
And now, if we move z away from
that, then what we're
getting are hyperbolas, and
these hyperbolas will approach
this asymptotic line y equals
minus x or this line--
sorry, this line y equals
x or this line equals y
equals minus x.
They'll approach this as they
go down, but they'll never
quite reach it.
So the level curves here
are just hyperbolas.
So now let's see, what is this
telling us about the
three-dimensional graph
of this function?
OK, so, first of all, we have
these level curves when y
equals x and when y equals minus
x, and so those level
curves we can kind of draw.
OK, so I want you to think that
that sits in the xy-plane.
It's kind of hard to draw
in three dimensions.
And so this is where our
function is going to be zero.
Now, if we take x
to be positive--
sorry.
If we take x to be greater than
y and both positive, then
this is a positive number and
this is a positive number.
So if we look in the region
where x and y are both
positive, that's in here, and
where x is greater than y,
then our function comes up.
So it looks like this, and then
it dips down and goes
down, comes back up,
and goes back down.
And now at the middle here, it
has to dip down to zero, so we
have something like this.
So what we end up getting in the
end, this is a saddle, so
it's a bit hard to draw.
It's a bit hard to see on this
so let me draw a sketch of it
off of the axes for you.
So we have a rise, and then a
drop, and then a rise in the
back, and then a drop, and then
down the middle it dips
down in this direction and it
rises up in this direction, so
it's a saddle like you
could put this on a
horse and ride it.
And so we can see that the
three-dimensional contours of
the saddle when we look at their
projection down onto the
contour plot become
these hyperbolas.
So a saddle is sort of like a
hyperbola stretched out into
three dimensions.
And I think I'll leave
it at that.