PROFESSOR: So today we're
going to take a look at
sinusoidal functions.
And specifically, we're going to
use complex numbers to get
a handle on sinusoidal
functions.
The reason is complex numbers
provide a robust way of
analyzing sinusoidal
functions.
So specifically, we're
interested in this function, e
to the i omega t divided
by 2 plus 3i.
And we're asked to write the
real part of this function
using polar form and then
rectangular form.
And then secondly, we're asked
several properties of this
function, the real part
of this function.
What's the circular frequency?
What's the amplitude?
And what's the phase lag?
And then lastly, we're asked
to sketch the real part of
this function versus time.
So I'll let you take a look at
this and try it for yourself.
And I'll come back
in a moment.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
OK.
So let's take a look
at this problem.
So we're asked to write e to i
omega t divided by 2 plus 3i.
We're asked to write the real
part of this function, using
polar form and then also
rectangular form.
So I'll first start off
with polar form.
And if we take a look at this
function, we see that the
numerator is already written
in polar form.
So just recall that polar
form is of the form
r e to the i theta.
Meanwhile, the denominator is
written in Cartesian form, or
rectangular form.
So we need to convert this
into polar form.
So what we can do is we
can write 2 plus 3i.
We can combine these
two into a modulus.
And the modulus is going to be
the square root of 2 squared
plus 3 squared.
So this is the modulus of
the complex number.
And then we have
e to the i phi.
And the angle phi we can deduce
by writing a triangle,
which is over to the right
by two units, and
then it's up two units.
And this is the angle phi.
So we see from the triangle
that the tangent of phi is
equal to 3/2.
OK.
So putting the pieces together,
we have e to the i
omega t divided by root
13 e to i phi.
And the beautiful thing about
polar form is that when we
divide and multiply these
complex exponentials, it just
turns into a simple addition or
subtraction of the phases.
So we have 1 over root 13, e
to the i omega t minus phi.
So we've successfully combined
all the terms
into one polar term.
And then now we're asked to
compute the real part.
And here we use Euler's
formula.
So just to recall Euler's
formula, we
have e to the i theta.
Then this is equal to cosine
theta plus i sine theta.
OK?
So at the end of the day, we're
interested in the real
part-- and I'm going to use this
notation Re with a curly
bracket to denote
the real part--
of 1 over root 13.
And I'll use Euler's formula
on e to the i
omega t minus phi.
So we have cosine omega t
minus phi plus i sine
omega t minus phi.
Sorry.
1 over root 13 is multiplying
both the sign and the cosine.
And we see that the second
term is purely imaginary.
So when we take the real part
of a real number plus an
imaginary number, we just are
left with the real number at
the end of the day.
So the answer we're looking for
is 1 over root 13 cosine
omega t minus phi, where
from before phi is the
arctangent of 3/2.
And phi can also be thought of
the angle being between zero
and pi over 2.
OK.
So this concludes the polar
form computation.
Secondly, we also have to
compute this using a
rectangular form calculation.
So let's do the calculation
in rectangular form.
And for this, I'm going to use
Euler's formula to expand out
the numerator.
So first, we want to take the
real part of the numerator is
cosine omega t plus
i sine omega t.
The denominator was 2 plus 3i.
And typically what we want to
do is we want to turn the
denominator into an entirely
real number.
So what we do is we multiply
the top and bottom by the
complex conjugate of
the denominator.
So for example, I
have 2 plus 3i.
So I'm going to multiply the top
and bottom by 2 minus 3i.
OK.
And when I do this, you'll note
that when we multiply out
two plus 3i and 2 minus 3i we
have a difference of squares.
So we're left with
2 times 2 is 4.
The cross terms cancel.
And then we have 3i
times negative 3i.
That's going to give us
negative 9i squared,
which is plus 9.
So the denominator is going
to be 4 plus 9.
And then the numerator--
I'll write out all the terms
just for completeness--
it'll be 2 times cosine omega
t plus 3 sine omega t.
And then now we have some
imaginary terms, which are
negative 3 cosine omega t
and plus 2 sine omega t.
OK?
But now we're going to
take the real part of
this complex function.
And if we take a look
at it, this first
term is entirely real.
This second term is entirely
complex because we're
multiplying by an i.
So when we take the real part,
at the end of the day, the
second term is going
to drop out.
So when the dust settles, we
have 1/13 2 times cosine omega
t plus 3 sine omega t.
OK?
So this concludes Part A.
For Part B, we're asked several
questions about this
sinusoidal function when written
in its real form,
specifically, what's the
circular frequency.
And the circular frequency is
just the frequency that this
function oscillates at.
And we can get this from looking
at the rectangular
form or the polar form.
And it's simply just
going to be omega.
So note how this function
oscillates
with frequency omega.
Secondly, we're asked
about the amplitude.
And if we take a look at it,
the amplitude is a little
tricky to get from the
rectangular form, but it's
completely apparent from
the polar form.
So if we take a look at the
polar form, we have 1 over
root 13 cosine omega
t minus phi.
And cosine oscillates between
plus 1 and minus 1.
So this function takes on a
maximum value of plus 1 over
root 13 and a maximum
negative value of
negative 1 over root 13.
So the amplitude of this
function is just going to be 1
over root 13.
And then lastly,
the phase lag.
This is the angle that the
cosine is picked up and
shifted over.
So again, we can get this
directly from the polar form.
Meanwhile, it's a little less
obvious what this angle is
when we take a look at
the rectangular form.
So in our case, the phase lag is
just going to be phi, which
is 10 inverse 3/2.
OK?
So this concludes Part B.
And then lastly, for Part C
we're just asked to sketch
this diagram.
And again, the most direct way
at sketching this function is
through the polar form.
So I'll write time
on this axis.
And if we just recall that
a cosine might look
something like this.
So this is a cosine function.
And in our case, we're looking
at plotting 1 over root 13
cosine omega t minus phi.
So we're interested in a cosine
which has an amplitude
of 1 over root 13 and a maximum
negative value of
minus 1 over root 13 whose
frequency is omega.
So there's a quick way
on finding zeros.
So if the zero of a regular
cosine is at pi over 2, then
if we have an angular frequency
of omega, the zero
here is going to be
pi over 2 omega.
And this zero is going to
be at 3 pi over 2 omega.
And lastly, this is not
necessarily the
cosine of our function.
Our function is this cosine.
However it must be picked
up and shifted over by
some phase lag phi.
So in our case, the function
we're actually looking for is
some shifted cosine, which
looks like this.
And this distance here
is phi over omega.
OK?
So this just gives us a quick
sketch of this function.
And again, we note that we were
able to plot this using
the polar form very quickly.
And the reason is because the
polar form gives us the
amplitude, the circular
frequency, and the phase lag.
Whereas if we were to take
a look at the equivalent
rectangular form, it's a
little less obvious.
The rectangular form is
actually the sum of
a sine and a cosine.
And unless you can just add
sines and cosines in your head
very quickly, it's a little less
obvious on how to come up
with this picture.
OK.
So just to summarize, we've
used complex functions to
analyze sinusoidal functions.
And we've used polar form and
rectangular form to get a
handle on the complex
functions.
And specifically, complex
functions are a very good way
to represent sinusoidal
functions.
And just to reiterate, the
reason is that they contain a
lot of information that we can
graphically handle and turn
into a sketch.
So I'll just conclude there,
and I'll see you next time.