PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In last lecture we talked about
finding the derivatives
of trigonometric functions.
In particular, the
sine function
and the cosine function.
So today let's do an example of
putting that into practice.
So here's a function h of x
equal to sine of x plus square
root of 3 times cosine of x.
And I'm asking you to find which
values of x have the
property that the derivative
of h of x is equal to 0.
So why don't you take a minute
to think about that, work it
out on your own, pause the
video, and we'll come back and
we'll work it out together.
All right.
So you've hopefully had a
chance to look over this
problem, try it out
for yourself.
Now let's see how
to go about it.
So we have the function
h of x--
it's equal to sine x plus square
root of 3 cosine x--
and we want to know when its
derivative is equal to 0.
So in order to answer that
question we should figure out
what its derivative actually
is and try and write down a
formula for its derivative.
So in this case that's
not that bad.
If we take a derivative of
h, well h is a sum of two
functions--
sine x and square root
of 3 cosine x.
And we know that the derivative
of a sum is just
the sum of the derivatives.
So we have the h prime of x is
equal to d over dx of sine x
plus d over dx of square root
of 3 times cosine x.
Now we learned last time in
lecture that the derivative of
sine x is cosine of x, and we
learned the derivative of
cosine of x is minus sine x.
So here we have a constant
multiple, but by the constant
multiple rule that just
gets pulled out.
So this is equal to cosine
x minus square root of
3 times sine x.
So this is h prime of x and
now we want to solve the
equation h prime
of x equals 0.
So we want to find those values
of x such that cosine x
minus square root of 3
sine x is equal to 0.
Now there are a couple
different
ways to go about this.
I think my preferred way is I
would add the square root of 3
sine x to one side, and then I
want to get my x's together,
so I would divide by cosine x.
So that gives me, so on the left
side I'll be left with
cosine x divided by cosine
x, so that's just 1.
And on the right side I'll have
square root of 3 times
sine x over cosine x.
So that's just square
root of 3 times 10x.
Or, and I can rewrite this as 10
of x is equal to 1 divided
by square root of 3.
Now to find x here, either you
can remember your special trig
angles and know which values
of x make this work.
Or you could apply the arc
tangent function here.
So in either case, the simplest
solution here is x
equals pi over 6.
So if you like, you can draw
a little right triangle.
You know, if this is x, if tan
x is 1 over square root of 3,
we should have this side being
1 and this side being
square root of 3.
And in OK, in that case, then
this right triangle the
hypotenuse would be 2.
And so then you, you know, would
recognize this is a 30
degree angle, or pi over
6 radian angle.
But one thing to remember is
that tangent of x is a
periodic function with period
pi, so not only is pi over 6 a
solution, but pi over 6
plus pi is a solution.
So that's 7 pi over 6, or pi
over 6 plus 2 pi, which is 13
pi over 6, or pi over 6 minus
pi, which is minus 5 pi over
6, et cetera.
So there are actually infinitely
many solutions.
They're given by pi
over 6 plus an
arbitrary multiple of pi.
So then we're done.
So I do want to mention, though,
that there's another
approach to this question,
which is, we can start by
multiplying this expression
for h of x.
So if you look at h of x--
that's sine of x plus square
root of 3 times cosine x--
it resembles closely one of your
trigonometric identities
that you know about.
So in particular, to make it
resemble it even more I can
multiply and divide by 2.
So I can rewrite h of x equals 2
times 1/2 sine x plus square
root of 3 over 2
times cosine x.
And now 1/2 is equal to
cosine of pi over 3.
And square root of 3 over 2 is
equal to sine of pi over 3.
So I can rewrite this
as 2 times--
what did I say--
I said cosine pi over 3 sine x
plus sine pi over 3 cosine x.
And this is exactly what you
get when you do the angle
addition formula for sine.
This is the expanded out form,
and so we can apply it in
reverse and get that this is
equal to 2 times sine of x
plus pi over 3.
So, so far we haven't
done any calculus.
We've just done--
so in this solution, our first
solution we did some calculus
first and then some algebra
and trigonometry.
So, so far we've just done some
algebra and trigonometry.
Now the points where h prime
of x is equal to 0 are the
points where the graph of this
function has a horizontal
tangent line.
So either you can compute its
derivative using your rules or
by the definition.
Or you can just say,
oh, we know what
this graph looks like.
So I've sort of drawn
a schematic up here.
So this is a graph,
this graph is--
OK, so this is the graph,
y equals 2 sine of x
plus pi over 3.
It's what you get if you take
the graph, y equals sine x,
and you shift it left by pi over
3 and you scale it up by
a factor of 2.
So this here is at x equals
minus pi over 3.
This root is x equals
2 pi over 3.
And the points we're interested
in are the points
where there's a horizontal
tangent line, where the
derivative is 0.
And so there's one of these
right at this value,
which is pi over 6.
And then the second one is this,
is that minimum there.
So that happens at x
equals 7 pi over 6.
pi over 6 because for the usual
sine function it happens
at pi over 2, but we shifted
everything left by pi over 3.
And so pi over 2 minus pi
over 3 is pi over 6.
And here for this, for just y
equals sine x, this minimum
would happen at 3 pi over
2, but we've shifted it
left by pi over 3.
And so on. you know, every,
there's another trough over
here, and another peak over
there, and so on.
So that's the second way you
can do this question using
this cute trig identity here.
And that's that.