PROFESSOR: Welcome
to recitation.
Today in this video what we're
going to do is look at how we
can determine the graph of a
derivative of a function from
the graph of the function
itself.
So I've given a function here.
We're calling it just y equals f
of x-- or this is the curve,
y equals f of x.
So we're thinking about
a function f of x.
I'm not giving you the equation
for the function.
I'm just giving you the graph.
And what I'd like you to do,
what I'd like us to do in this
time, is to figure out what the
curve, y equals f prime of
x will look like.
So that's our objective.
So what we'll do first is try
and figure out the things that
we know about f prime of x.
So what I want to remind you is
that when you think about a
function's derivative, remember
its derivative's
output is measuring the
slope of the tangent
line at each point.
So that's what we're interested
in finding, is
understanding the slope of the
tangent line of this curve at
each x value.
So it's always easiest when
you're thinking about a
derivative to find the places
where the slope of the
tangent line is 0.
Because those are the only
places where you can hope to
change the sign on
the derivative.
So what we'd like to do is first
identify, on this curve,
where the tangent line
has slope equal to 0.
And I think there are
two places we can
find it fairly easily.
That would be at whatever
this x value is, that
slope there is 0.
It's going to be a horizontal
tangent line.
And then whatever
this x value is.
The slope there is also 0
horizontal tangent line.
But there's a third place where
the slope of the tangent
line is 0, and that's kind
of hidden right in here.
And actually, I've drawn in--
maybe you think there are a
few more-- but we're going to
assume that this function is
always continuing down
through this region.
So there are three places where
the horizontal, tangent
line is horizontal.
So I can even sort of draw them
lightly through here.
You have three horizontal
tangent lines.
So at those points, we know that
the derivative's value is
equal to 0, the output
is equal to 0.
And now what we can determine
is, between those regions,
where are the values
of the derivative
positive and negative?
So what I'm going to do is below
here, I'm just going to
make a line and we're going to
sort of keep track of what the
signs of the derivative are.
So let me just draw.
This would be sort of
our sign on f prime.
OK.
So that's going to tell
us what our signs are.
So right below, we'll
keep track.
So here, this, I'll just
come straight down.
Here we know the sign of f
prime is equal to 0.OK?
We know it's equal to 0 there.
We know it's also equal to 0
here, and we know it's also
equal to 0 here.
OK?
And now the question is,
what is the sign of f
prime in this region?
So to the left of whatever
that x value is.
What is the sign of f prime in
this region, in this region,
and then to the right?
So there really, we can divide
up the x values as left of
whatever that x value is, in
between these two values, in
between these two values, and to
the right of this x value.
That's really, really what we
need to do to determine what
the signs of f prime are.
So again, what we want to do
to understand f prime is we
look at the slope of the tangent
line of the curve, y
equals f of x.
So let's pick a place in this
region left of where it's 0,
say right here, and let's look
at the tangent line.
The tangent line has
what kind of slope?
Well, it has a positive slope.
And in fact, if you look along
here, you see all of the
slopes are positive.
So f prime is bigger
than 0 here.
And now I'm just going
to record that.
I'm going to keep that
in mind as a plus.
The sign is positive there.
Now, if I look right of where
f prime equals 0, if I look
for x values to the right, I
see that as I move to the
right, the tangent line
is curving down.
So let me do it with
the chalk.
You see the tangent
line looks, has a
slope negative slope.
If I draw one point in, it looks
something like that.
So the slope is negative
there.
So here I can record that.
The sign of f prime is
a minus sign there.
Now, if I look between these two
x values, which I'm saying
here is 0 and here it's 0 for
the x values, and I take a
take a point, we notice the sign
is negative there, also.
So in fact, the sign of f prime
changed at this 0 of f
prime, but it stays the same
around this 0 of f prime.
So it's negative and then it
goes to negative again.
It's a negative, then
0, then negative.
And then if I look to the right
of this x value and I
take a point, I see that
the slope of the
tangent line is positive.
And so the sign there
is positive.
So we have the derivative is
positive, and then 0, and then
negative, and then 0, and
then negative, and
then 0, and then positive.
So there's a lot going on.
But I, if I want to plot, now,
y equals f prime of x, I have
some sort of launching point
by which to do that.
So what I can do is, I know
that the derivative 0--
I'm going to draw the derivative
in blue, here-- the
derivative is 0, its output
is 0 at these places.
So I'm going to put
those points on.
And then if I were just trying
to get a rough idea of what
happens, the derivative is
positive left of this x value.
So it's certainly coming down.
It's coming down.
Oops, let me make these
a little darker.
It's coming down because
it's positive.
It's coming down to 0-- it has
to stay above the x-axis, but
it has to head towards 0.
Right?
What does that actually
correspond to?
Well, look at what the
slopes are doing.
The slopes of these tangent
lines, as I move in the x
direction, the slope--
let me just keep my hand, watch
what my hand is doing--
the slope is always positive,
but it's becoming less and
less vertical, right?
It's headed towards
horizontal.
So the slope that was
steeper over here is
becoming less steep.
The steepness is really the
magnitude of the derivative.
That's really measuring
how far it is, the
output is from 0.
So as the derivative becomes
less steep, the derivative's
values have to be headed
closer to 0.
Now, what happens when the
derivative is equal to 0 here?
Well, all of a sudden the slopes
are becoming negative.
So the outputs of the derivative
are negative.
It's going down.
But then once it hits here,
again, notice what happens.
The derivative is 0 again, and
notice how I get there.
The derivative's negative, and
then it starts to, the slopes
of these tangent lines start
to get shallower.
Right?
They were steep and then
somewhere they
start to get shallower.
So there's someplace sort of in
the x values between here
and here where the derivative is
as steep as it gets in this
region, and then gets
less steep.
The steepest point is that
point where you have the
biggest magnitude in that
region for f prime.
So that's where it's going
to be furthest from 0.
So if I'm guessing, it looks
like right around here the
tangent line is as steep as it
ever gets in that region,
between these two 0s, and
then it gets less steep.
So I'd say, right around there
we should say, OK, that's as
low as it goes and now it's
going to come back up.
OK?
So hopefully that makes sense.
We'll get to see
it again, here.
Between these two 0s the same
kind of thing happens.
But notice--
this is, we have
to be careful--
we shouldn't go through 0 here
because the derivative's
output, the sign is negative.
Right?
Notice, so the tangent line,
it was negative, negative,
negative, 0, oh, it's
still negative.
So the outputs are still
negative, and they're going to
be negative all the
way to this 0.
And what we need to see again
is the same kind of thing
happenes as happened
in this region will
happen in this region.
The point being that,
again, we're 0 here.
We're 0 here.
So somewhere in the middle, we
start at 0, the tangent lines
start to get steeper, then at
some point they stop getting
steeper, they start
getting shallower.
That place looks maybe
right around here.
That's the sort of steepest
tangent line, then it gets
less steep.
So that's the place where the
derivative's magnitude is
going to be the biggest
in this region.
And actually, I've sort of
drawn it, they look like
they're about the same steepness
at those two places,
so I should probably put
the outputs about
the same down here.
Their magnitudes are
about the same.
So this has to bounce
off, come up here.
I made that a little sharper
than I meant to.
OK?
So that's the place.
That's the output here--
or the tangent line, sorry.
The tangent line at this x value
is the steepest that we
get in this region, so the
output at that x value is the
lowest we get.
And then, when we're to the
right of this 0 for the
derivative, we start seeing the
tangent lines positive--
we pointed that out already--
and it gets more positive.
So it starts at 0, it starts to
get positive, and then it
gets more positive.
It's going to do something
like that, roughly.
So let me fill in the
dotted lines so
we can see it clearly.
Well, this is not exact, but
this is a fairly good drawing,
I think we can say,
of f prime of x.
y equals f prime of x.
And now I'm going to
ask you a question.
I'm going to write it on the
board, and then I'm going to
give you a moment to
think about it.
So let me write the question.
It's, find a function y equals--
or sorry-- find a
function g of x so that y equals
g prime of x looks like
y equals f prime of x.
OK, let me be clear about that,
and then I'll give you a
moment to think about it.
So I want you to find a function
g of x so that its
derivative's graph, y equals g
prime of x, looks exactly like
the graph we've drawn in blue
here, y equals f prime of x.
Now, I don't want you to find
something in terms of x
squared's and x cubes.
I don't want you to find an
actual g of x equals something
in terms of x.
I want you to just try and find
a relationship that it
must have with f.
So I'm going to give me a moment
to think about it and
work out your answer, and I'll
be back to tell you.
OK.
Welcome back.
So what we're looking for is a
function g of x so that its
derivative, when I graph it, y
equals g prime of x, I get
exactly the same curve
as the blue one.
The blue one.
And the point is that if you
thought about it for a little
bit, what you really need is a
function that looks exactly
like this function, y equals f
of x, at all the x values in
terms of its slopes, but those
slopes can happen shifted up
or down anywhere.
So the point is that if I take
the function y equals f of x
and I add a constant to it,
which shifts the whole graph
up or down, the tangent lines
are unaffected by that shift.
And so I get exactly the same
picture when I take the
derivative of that graph.
When I look at that
the tangent line
slopes of that graph.
So you could draw another
picture and check it for
yourself if you didn't feel
convinced, shift this, shift
this curve up, and then look at
what the tangent lines do
on that curve.
But then you'll see its
derivative's outputs are
exactly the same.
So we'll stop there.