PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to Recitation.
In lecture you've been computing
derivatives of
functions from the limit
definition of derivative.
So today we're going to do
another example of that and do
some graphing, as well.
So I've got a problem written
here on the board.
So we're defining a function f
of x to be 1 over the quantity
1 plus x squared.
So what I'd like you to do is
graph the function of the
curve y equals f of x and to
compute the derivative f prime
of x from the definition.
So why don't you take a couple
of minutes to do that
yourself, then come back, and
we'll work it out together.
All right.
Welcome back.
So to start off, let's try
graphing this function f of x.
So one thing you can always do
when you start out graphing a
function, is to just
plot a few points.
And that'll give you a very
rough sense of where the
function is, at least
around those points.
So, for example, when x is
equal to 0 we have f
of 0 is 1 over 1.
So that's just 1.
So we've got this point
here, 0, 1.
And when x is equal to 1, well,
x squared is 1, so the
denominator is 2, so the
function value is 1/2.
So, all right I'm not going
to draw this to scale.
I'm going to put x
equals 1 here.
And the function value is 1/2,
so this is the point 1, 1/2.
And, OK.
We could do one more.
When x is equal to 2,
this function--
2 squared is 4, so that's
5-- so it's 1/5.
So I don't know.
1/5 is smaller than
1/2, right?
So that's maybe--
down here--
so this is something like
the point 2, 1/5.
All right.
But this is a very rough idea
we're getting, so we can use
some more sophisticated analysis
to get a better idea
of what this graph is
going to look like.
So the first thing we could
notice, for example, is that
this is an even function.
Right?
If I change the sign of x, if I
replace x by minus x, well,
x squared and minus x squared
are both equal to x squared.
So if you replace x by
minus x, the function
value doesn't change.
So this is an even function
that has symmetry
across the axis here.
So, you know, for example,
I could just
mirror image these points.
So these points also have to
be on the graph, the points
minus 1, 1/2 and minus 2, 1/5.
And any other part of the curve
that I draw will be
perfectly mirror imaged.
Another thing to observe is
that x squared is always
greater than or equal to 0.
So 1 plus x squared is
always positive.
So 1 over 1 plus x squared
is also always positive.
Also, 1 plus x squared, it
reaches its minimum when x is
equal to 0 and then as x gets
large, either in the positive
direction or in the negative
direction, this gets larger
and larger.
this, just the 1 plus
x squared part.
So the denominator is getting
larger and larger, while the
numerator stays constant.
The whole fraction gets
smaller and smaller.
So as x gets bigger, either
bigger positive or bigger
negative, the function value
will diminish off to 0, and it
has its maximum value
here at 0.
Because that's when 1 plus x
squared has its minimum.
So the function sort of has
its maximum here at 0, and
then it flattens out.
And as x gets larger and larger
and larger, this goes
to infinity, so the whole
fraction goes down to 0.
But it never reaches
it, right?
Because we said it's
always positive.
And similarly, on
the other side.
OK.
So that's the graph of
the curve y equals 1
over 1 plus x squared.
Roughly speaking.
OK.
So now let's talk about
computing the derivative.
So right now, to compute a
derivative, all you have is
the limit definition
of the derivative.
So when I ask you to compute the
derivative what you've got
to do is write down what
that definition says.
That's the limit of a
difference quotient.
So we have, by definition, that
f prime of x is equal
to-- well, it's the limit--
is delta x goes to 0 of some
difference quotient.
So on the bottom of the
difference quotient we just
have delta x, and on the top
we have f of x plus delta x
minus f of x.
In our case, we have a nice
formula for f of x.
So this is equal to the limit as
delta x goes to 0 of 1 over
the quantity 1 plus x plus delta
x quantity squared--
oh, I guess I didn't need
that parenthesis there--
minus 1 over 1 plus x squared,
and the whole thing
is over delta x.
So, what would be really nice,
of course, is if this were a
limit where we could just plug
in the value delta x equals 0
and evaluate it.
But the way the definition of a
derivative works, that never
works, right?
You're always left with
the numerator.
As delta x goes to 0, that top
is always going to be f of x
minus f of x and it's
going to be 0.
And the bottom is always going
to be delta x going to 0,
which is 0.
So you always, when you have a
differentiable function, you
always have a derivative that's
going to be a limit of
a 0 over 0 form.
So you need to do some sort of
manipulation in order to, in
order to get into a form
you can evaluate it.
What we'd really like is to
manipulate this numerator
somehow and pull out, say,
a factor of delta x.
And then that could cancel with
the delta x we have in
the denominator.
Something, some trick
like that.
Some algebraic or other
manipulation to make this into
a form where we can plug
in and evaluate.
So alrright, so right here
there's sort of only one
manipulation that's natural to
do, which is we can add these
two fractions together.
So let's do that, and we
can rewrite this limit.
The limit is delta
x goes to 0.
All right, I'm going to pull
this 1 over delta x out front
just to make everything look
a little bit nicer.
It's 1 over delta x times--
OK.
i want to, you know, subtract
these two fractions.
I want to put them over a common
denominator, so the
denominator is just going
to be the product of the
denominator.
So that's 1 plus x plus delta
x quantity squared times 1
plus x squared.
OK.
And so this fraction is 1
plus x squared over that
denominator.
And the second one is 1 plus x
plus delta x quantity squared
over that common denominator.
OK.
So we still haven't got where
we want to be yet because we
still have this 1 over
delta x hanging out.
So OK, so we have to, you
know, keep going.
And so here, I guess there's a,
this is sort of a problem
that forces us a little
bit in one direction.
You, know, there's not much we
can do with the denominator,
but here in the numerator we can
expand this out and start
combining stuff.
So let's do that.
So this is equal to--
all right, well, the
limit hangs out--
the limit is delta x goes to
0 of 1 over delta x times--
OK, so 1 plus x squared
minus--
all right, so if you
expand out x plus
delta x quantity squared--
using your favorite, either foil
or the binomial theorem
or just whatever you like,
however you like to multiply
two binomials--
so we get a minus 1 minus x
squared minus 2x times delta x
minus delta x squared.
That's the top.
Ok, and we haven't changed
the bottom.
It's still 1 plus x plus
delta x squared
times 1 plus x squared.
OK.
Well, so what?
OK, so now some nice stuff is
starting to happen, which is
this 1 and this minus 1 are
going to cancel, and this x
squared and this minus x squared
are going to cancel.
And then after we cancel those
terms we see that in the
numerator here, everything is
going to have a factor of
dealt x, right?
These four are going to cancel,
and we'll just be left
with these two terms,
both of which are
divisible by delta x.
So that's where this
cancellation we've been
looking for is going
to come from.
So let's keep going.
So we cancel those, they
subtract, give us 0.
This limit is equal to the
limit delta x goes to 0.
OK.
And then we can divide this
delta x from the denominator
in, and what we're left with
upstairs is minus 2x minus
delta x, the whole thing over
the same denominator, still.
1 plus x plus delta x squared
times 1 plus x squared.
All right.
Great.
So we've done this
manipulation.
We finally found a delta x that
we could cancel with that
delta x we started with
in the denominator.
And now this limit is
no longer this 0
over 0 form, right?
When delta x goes to 0, the
top goes to minus 2x.
And the bottom--
well let's see, this delta x
just goes to 0-- so it's 1
plus x squared times
1 plus x squared.
So that's not 0 over 0.
We can just plug
in to evaluate.
So this is, just works out
to a minus 2x over--
OK, 1 plus x squared times 1
plus x squared is 1 plus x
squared, quantity squared.
And so this is the derivative
that we were looking for.
This is, just to remind you what
that was, that's d over
dx of 1 over the quantity
1 plus x squared.
Now, if you wanted, you could
check this a little bit by
looking at the graph and looking
at this function and
just making sure that
it makes sense.
So for example, this function,
this derivative has the
property that it's
0 when x is 0.
And that's the only
time it's 0.
And if we go back and look at
the graph that we drew over
here, we see that's also
a property that
this graph has, right?
It has this horizontal tangent
line there, and then it
diminishes off to the right and
it, on the left side it
increases, then it has that
horizontal tangent line, and
then it decreases.
And so if we go back to this
function we see, yes indeed,
when x is negative, this whole
thing is positive.
And then at 0 it's 0, and then
it's negative thereafter.
And similarly, you could note
that this function here is an
odd function.
If you change the sign of x,
that changes the sign of this
whole expression, and so OK,
and so that makes perfect
sense back here.
The symmetry of this curve is
such that, you know, if we
look at a tangent line to the
left of 0 and the symmetric
tangent line to the right of
0, they're mirror images of
each other.
So their slopes or exactly
negatives of each other.
So that's a nice way you can
sort of put the two different
pieces of this problem together
in order to double
check your work.
So that's that.