We're doing well-- we are half
a minute ahead of time, so we
can relax a little.
We now come to another
classic problem--
6, which is 24-81.
We have two metal spheres, one
which has the radius R1 --
it's going to be charged, and
the other one is not charged,
and is very far away.
We're going to connect this
charged one with this one.
Now, you're going to see
three concepts--
three birds with one stone.
The first thing that is
important that you recognize
that since all this is metal and
all of this is a conductor
that as soon as they are
connected, the potential of
the two spheres is the same.
There's no potential
difference--
that's number one.
The second thing that you will
find out is that the charge on
the largest sphere will be
larger than the charge on the
smallest sphere--
maybe that comes natural.
What is not so natural, perhaps,
is the electric field
at the surface of the smallest
sphere will be larger than the
electric field at the surface
of the largest sphere.
All of these three
concepts come
together in this one problem.
We first put on here
the charge Q1 ,
and that is not connected.
The electric field
at the surface--
if you're interested, then--
would be Q1 , divided by 4 pi
epsilon zero times R1 squared.
The potential at the surface--
or not even at the surface--
if this is a solid sphere,
then the potential is the same
everywhere throughout this
sphere and would Q1 divided
by 4 pi epsilon 0 R1 .
That's something that should now
be quite obvious after we
have done this assignment.
Now we connect, and charge is
going to divide: we're going
to have here Q1 prime,
and we're going to
have here Q2 prime.
I now make use of the fact that
the potential of this one
must be the same as the
potential as that one, and
therefore, Q1 prime divided by
4 pi epsilon 0 R1 must be the
same as Q2 prime divided
by 4 pi epsilon 0 R2 .
Since you also know that Q1
prime plus Q2 prime equals Q1
, you have two equations with
two unknowns, because you know
the radii: you can solve for
Q1 prime, and you can solve
for Q2 prime.
What you also see is that this
ratio is the same as this
ratio, and so it tells you
immediately that the charge on
this one is larger than the
charge on this one--
notice this ratio is the
same as this ratio.
I want you to do the electric
vectors right here at the
surface, and right here
at the surface.
You will then see that the
electric factors right at the
surface are going to be
proportional to 1 over R.
Since R1 smaller than R2 , you
will find that the electric
field here is stronger than
the electric field there.
They are equipotentials
potentials because they are
connected, but I leave
you with that far.