The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or to view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses visit
MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
Professor: I am Haynes Miller,
I am substituting for
David Jerison today.
So you have a substitute
teacher today.
So I haven't been here in this
class with you so I'm not
completely sure where you are.
I think just been talking about
differentiation and you've
got some examples of
differentiation like these
basic examples: the derivative
of x^n is nx^(x-1).
But I think maybe you've spent
some time computing the
derivative of the sine
function as well, recently.
And I think you have some
rules for extending these
calculations as well.
For instance, I think you know
that if you differentiate a
constant times a function,
what do you get?
Student: [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: The constant
comes outside like this.
Or I could write (cu)' = cu'.
That's this rule, multiplying
by a constant, and I
think you also know about
differentiating a sum.
Or I could write this as (u
v)' = u' + v'.
So I'm going to be using those
but today I'll talk about a
collection of other rules about
how to deal with a product of
functions, a quotient of
functions, and, best of all,
composition of functions.
And then at the end, I'll
have something to say
about higher derivatives.
So that's the story for today.
That's the program.
So let's begin by talking
about the product rule.
So the product rule tells you
how to differentiate a product
of functions, and I'll just
give you the rule,
first of all.
The rule is it's u'v + uv'.
It's a little bit funny.
Differentiating a product
gives you a sum.
But let's see how that works
out in a particular example.
For example, suppose that
I wanted to differentiate
the product.
Well, the product of these
two basic examples that
we just talked about.
I'm going to use the same
variable in both cases
instead of different
ones like I did here.
So the derivative
of (x^n)sin x.
So this is a new thing.
We couldn't do this without
using the product rule.
So the first function is x^n
and the second one is sin x.
And we're going to
apply this rule.
So u is x^n. u' is, according
to the rule, nx^(n - 1).
And then I take v and write it
down the way it is, sine of x.
And then I do it the other way.
I take u the way it is, that's
x^n, and multiply it by
the derivative of v, v'.
We just saw v' is cosine of x.
So that's it.
Obviously, you can
differentiate longer products,
products of more things by
doing it one at a time.
Let's see why this is true.
I want to try to show you
why the product rule holds.
So you have a standard way of
trying to understand this, and
it involves looking at the
change in the function that
you're interested in
differentiating.
So I should look at how much
the product uv changes when
x changes a little bit.
Well, so how do
compute the change?
Well, I write down the value
of the function at some
new value of x, (x
delta x).
Well, I better write down
the whole new value
of the function, and
the function is uv.
So the whole new value
looks like this.
It's u (x
delta x)v(x + delta x).
That's the new value.
But what's the change
in the product?
Well, I better subtract off
what the old value was,
which is u(x) v(x).
Okay, according to the rule
we're trying to prove, I
have to get u' involved.
So I want to involve the
change in u alone, by itself.
Let's just try that.
I see part of the formula for
the change in u right there.
Let's see if we can get
the rest of it in place.
So the change in x = ((u(x)
+ delta x) - u(x)).
That's the change in
x [Correction:___c
hange___in___u].
This part of it occurs up
here, multiplied by v (x
delta x), so let's
put that in too.
Now this equality sign
isn't very good right now.
I've got this product here
so far, but I've introduced
something I don't like.
I've introduced u (v ( x
delta x)), right?
Minus that.
So the next thing I'm gonna
do is correct that little
defect by adding in
u(x) (v (x + delta x)).
Okay, now I cancelled off what
was wrong with this line.
But I'm still not quite
there, because I haven't
put this in yet.
So I better subtract off
uv, and then I'll be home.
But I'm going to do that in a
clever way, because I noticed
that I already have a u here.
So I'm gonna take this
factor of u and make it
the same as this factor.
So I get u(x) times this,
minus u(x) times that.
That's the same thing as
u times the difference.
So that was a little bit
strange, but when you stand
back and look at it, you can
see multiplied out, the
middle terms cancel.
And you get the right answer.
Well I like that because
it's involved the change
in u and the change in v.
So this is equal to
(delta u) v (x
delta x) - u(x) times
the change in v.
Well, I'm almost there.
The next step in computing the
derivative is take difference
quotient, divide
this by delta x.
So, (delta (uv)) / (delta x)
is well, I'll say (delta
u / delta x) v ( x
delta x).
Have I made a mistake here?
This plus magically became a
minus on the way down here,
so I better fix that.
Plus u(delta v / (delta x).
This u is this u over here.
So I've just divided this
formula by delta x, and now I
can take the limit as goes
to 0, so this is as
delta x goes to 0.
This becomes the definition of
the derivative, and on this
side, I get du/dx times... now
what happens to this quantity
when delta x goes to 0?
So this quantity is getting
closer and closer to x.
So what happens to
the value of v?
It becomes equal to x(v).
That uses continuity of v.
So, v (x
delta x) goes to
v(x) by continuity.
So this gives me times v, and
then I have u(n delta v/ v
delta x) gives me dv/dx.
And that's the formula.
That's the formula as I
wrote it down at the
beginning over here.
The derivative of a product
is given by this sum.
Yeah?
Student: How did you get from
the first line to the second
of the long equation?
Professor: From here to here?
Student: Yes.
Professor: So maybe it's
easiest to work backwards and
verify that what I wrote
down is correct here.
So, if you look
there's a u(v (x
delta x)) there.
And there's also one here.
And they occur with
opposite signs.
So they cancel.
What's left is u ( x
delta x) v (x
delta x) - (uv).
And that's just what
I started with.
Student: They cancel right?
Professor: I cancelled out
this term and this term, and
what's left is the ends.
Any other questions?
Student: [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: Well, I just
calculated what delta uv is,
and now I'm gonna divide that
by delta x on my way to
computing the derivative.
And so I copied down the right
hand side and divided delta x.
I just decided to divide
the delta u by delta x
and delta v by delta x.
Good.
Anything else?
So we have the
product rule here.
The rule for differentiating
a product of two functions.
This is making us stronger.
There are many more
functions you can find
derivatives of now.
How about quotients?
Let's find out how to
differentiate a quotient
of two functions.
Well again, I'll write down
what the answer is and then
we'll try to verify it.
So there's a quotient.
Let me write this down.
There's a quotient
of two functions.
And here's the rule for it.
I always have to think about
this and hope that I get
it right. u'v - uv' / v^2.
This may be the craziest
rule you'll see in this
course, but there it is.
And I'll try to show you why
that's true and see an example.
Yeah there was a hand?
Student: [INAUDIBLE]
Professor: What letters
look the same? u and
v look the same?
I'll try to make them
look more different.
The v's have points on the
bottom. u's have little
round things on the bottom.
What's the new value of u?
The value of u at (x
delta x) is (u
delta u), right?
That's what delta u is.
It's the change in u when
x gets replaced by (x
delta x).
And the change in v, the
new value v, is (v
delta v).
So this is the new value of u
divided by the new value of v.
That's the beginning.
And then I subtract off the
old values, which are - u/v.
This'll be easier to work out
when I write it out this way.
So now, we'll cross
multiply, as I said.
So I get (uv
(delta u)v) minus, now I
cross multiply this way,
you get (uv - u(delta v)).
And I divide all this by (v
delta v)u [Correction:___(
v___+___delta___v)v].
Okay, now the reason I like to
do it this way is that you see
the cancellation happening
here. uv and uv occur twice
and so I can cancel them.
And I will, and I'll answer
these questions in a minute.
Audience: [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: Ooo, that's a v.
All right.
Good, anything else?
That's what all hands were.
Good.
All right, so I cancel these
and what I'm left with then
is (delta u)v - u(delta v)
and all this is over (v
delta v)v.
Ok, there's the difference.
There's the change
in the quotient.
The change in this function
is given by this formula.
And now to compute the
derivative, I want to divide by
delta x, and take the limit.
So let's write that down,
delta(u/v)/delta x
is this formula here
divided by delta x.
And again, I'm going to put
the delta x under these
delta u and delta v.
Okay?
I'm gonna put delta x in the
denominator, but I can think
of that as dividing into
this factor and this factor.
So this is ((delta u/ delta
x)v) - u(delta v/delta x)).
And all that is divided by
the same denominator, (v
delta v)v.
Right?
Put the delta x up in
the numerator there.
Next up, take the limit
as delta x goes to 0.
I get, by definition, the
derivative of (u/v).
And on the right hand side,
well, this is the derivative
u(du/ dx) right?
Times v.
See and then u times, and here
it's the derivative (dv/ dx).
Now what about the denominator?
So when delta x goes to
0, v stays the same,
v stays the same.
What happens to this delta v?
It goes to 0, again,
because v is continuous.
So again, delta v goes to 0
with delta x because they're
continuous and you
just get (v*v).
I think that's the formula
I wrote down over there.
(du/dx)v - u(dv/dx).
And all divided by the square
of the old denominator.
Well, that's it.
That's the quotient rule.
Weird formula.
Let's see an application.
Let's see an example.
So the example I'm going
to give is pretty simple.
I'm going to take the
numerator to be just 1.
So I'm gonna take u = 1.
So now I'm differentiating 1
/ v, the reciprocal of a
function; 1 over a function.
Here's a copy of my rule.
What's du/ dx in that case?
u is a constant, so that
term is 0 in this rule.
I don't have to
worry about this.
I get a minus.
And then u = 1, and dv/ dx.
Well, v is whatever v is.
I'll write dv/dx as v'.
And then I get a v^2
in the denominator.
So that's the rule.
I could write it as (v^-2)v'.
(-v'/v^2).
That's the derivative of 1 / v.
How about sub-example of that?
I'm going to take the special
case where u = 1 again.
And v = x^n.
And I'm gonna use the rule that
we developed earlier about
the derivative of x^n.
So what do I get here? d / dx
(1/x^n) is, I'm plugging into
this formula here with v = x^n.
So I get minus, uh, v^-2.
If v = x^n, v^-2 is, by the
rule of exponents, x^-2n.
And then v' is the derivative
of x^n, which is (nx)^(n-1).
Ok, so let's put
these together.
There's several
powers of x here.
I can put them together.
I get -nx ^ ((- 2n)
(n - 1)).
One of these n's cancels.
And what I'm left
with is ((-n) - 1).
So we've computed the
derivative of 1 / x^n,
which I could also
write as x^-n, right?
So I've computed the derivative
of negative powers of x.
And this is the
formula that I get.
If you think of this - n as a
unit, as a thing to itself, it
occurs here in the exponent.
It occurs here, and
it occurs here.
So how does that compare
with the formula
that we had up here?
The derivative of a power of
x is that power times x to
one less than that power.
That's exactly the same as the
rule that I wrote down here.
But the power here happens to
be a negative number, and the
same negative number shows
up as a coefficient and
there in the exponent.
Yeah?
Student: [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: How did I do this?
Professor: Where did
that x^-2n come from?
So I'm applying this rule.
So the denominator in the
quotient rule is v^2.
And v was x^n, so the
denominator is x^2n.
And I decided to
write it as x^-2n.
So the green comments there...
What they say is that I
can enlarge this rule.
This exact same rule is true
for negative values of n, as
well as positive values of n.
So there's something new in
your list of rules that you
can apply, of values
of the derivative.
That standard rule is true
for negative as well
as positive exponents.
And that comes out
of a quotient rule.
Okay, so we've done two rules.
I've talked about the product
rule and the quotient rule.
What's next?
Let's see the chain rule.
So this is a composition rule.
So the kind of thing that I
have in mind, composition of
functions is about
substitution.
So the kind of function that
I have in mind is, for
instance, y = (sin t)^10.
That's a new one.
We haven't seen how to
differentiate that
before, I think.
This kind of power of a trig
function happens very often.
You've seen them happen, as
well, I'm sure, already.
And there's a little notational
switch that people use.
They'll write sin^10(t).
But remember that when you
write sin^10(t), what you mean
is take the sine of t, and then
take the tenth power of that.
It's the meaning of sin^10(t).
So the method of dealing with
this kind of composition of
functions is to use
new variable names.
What I mean is, I can
think of this (sin t)^10.
I can think of it it as
a two step process.
First of all, I compute
the sine of t.
And let's call the result x.
There's the new variable name.
And then, I express
y in terms of x.
So y says take this and raise
it to the tenth power.
In other words, y = x^10.
And then you plug x = sine of
t into that, and you get the
formula for what y
is in terms of t.
So it's good practice to
introduce new letters when
they're convenient, and
this is one place where
it's very convenient.
So let's find a rule for
differentiating a composition,
a function that can be
expressed by doing one function
and then applying
another function.
And here's the rule.
Well, maybe I'll actually
derive this rule first, and
then you'll see what it is.
In fact, the rule is
very simple to derive.
So this is a proof first, and
then we'll write down the rule.
I'm interested in delta y /
delta t. y is a function of
x. x is a function of t.
And I'm interested in how
y changes with respect to
t, with respect to the
original variable t.
Well, because of that
intermediate variable, I can
write this as ((delta y /
delta x) (delta x/ delta t)).
It cancels, right?
The delta x cancels.
The change in that immediate
variable cancels out.
This is just basic algebra.
But what happens when I
let delta t get small?
Well this give me dy /dt.
On the right hand side,
I get (dy/dx) (dx/dt).
So students will often
remember this rule.
This is the rule, by saying
that you can cancel
out for the dx's.
And that's not so
far from the truth.
That's a good way
to think of it.
In other words, this is
the so-called chain rule.
And it says that
differentiation of a
composition is a product.
It's just the product of
the two derivatives.
So that's how you differentiate
a composite of two functions.
And let's just do an example.
Let's do this example.
Let's see how that comes out.
So let's differentiate,
what did I say?
(sin t)^10.
Okay, there's an inside
function and an
outside function.
The inside function is
x as a function of t.
This is the inside
function, and this is
the outside function.
So the rule says, first of
all let's differentiate
the outside function.
Take dy/ dx.
Differentiate it with
respect to that variable x.
The outside function
is the 10th power.
What's it's derivative?
So I get 10x^9.
In this account, I'm using
this newly introduced
variable named x.
So the derivative of the
outside function is 10x^9.
And then here's the inside
function, and the next thing I
want to do is differentiate it.
So what's dx /dt, d/dt (sine
t), the derivative of sine t?
All right, that's cosine t.
That's what the
chain gives you.
This is correct, but since we
were the ones to introduce
this notation x here, that
wasn't given to us in the
original problem here.
The last step in this process
should be to put back, to
substitute back in what
x is in terms of t.
So x = sin t.
So that tells me that I
get 10(sin(t))^9, that's
x^9, times the cos(t).
Or the same thing
is sin^9(t)cos(t).
So there's an application
of the chain rule.
You know, people often
wonder where the name
chain rule comes from.
I was just wondering
about that myself.
So is it because it
chains you down?
Is it like a chain fence?
I decided what it is.
It's because by using it, you
burst the chains of
differentiation, and you can
differentiate many more
functions using it.
So when you want to think of
the chain rule, just think
of that chain there.
It lets you burst free.
Let me give you another
application of the chain rule.
Ready for this one?
So I'd like to differentiate
the sin(10t).
Again, this is the composite
of two functions.
What's the inside function?
Okay, so I think I'll introduce
this new notation. x = 10t, and
the outside function
is the sine.
So y = sin x.
So now the chain rule
says dy/ dt is...
Okay, let's see.
I take the derivative of
the outside function,
and what's that?
Sine' and we can substitute
because we know what sine' is.
So I get cosine of whatever,
x, and then times what?
Now I differentiate the inside
function, which is just 10.
So I could write this
as 10cos of what?
10t, x = 10t.
Now, once you get used to this,
this middle variable, you don't
have to give a name for it.
You can just to think about it
in your mind without actually
writing it down,
d/dt (sin(10t)).
I'll just do it again without
introducing this middle
variable explicitly.
Think about it.
I first of all differentiate
the outside function,
and I get cosine.
But I don't change the thing
that I'm plugging into it.
It's still x that I'm
plugging into it. x is 10t.
So let's just write 10t and
not worry about the name
of that extra variable.
If it confuses you,
introduce the new variable.
And do it carefully
and slowly like this.
But, quite quickly, I think
you'll get to be able to keep
that step in your mind.
I'm not quite done yet.
I haven't differentiated
the inside function, the
derivative of 10t = 10.
So you get, again,
the same result.
A little short cut that
you'll get used to.
Really and truly, once you have
the chain rule, the world
is yours to conquer.
It puts you in a very,
very powerful position.
Okay, well let's see.
What have I covered today?
I've talked about product rule,
quotient rule, composition.
I should tell you
something about higher
derivatives, as well.
So let's do that.
This is a simple story.
Higher is kind of
a strange word.
It just means differentiate
over and over again.
All right, so let's see.
If we have a function u or
u(x), please allow me to just
write it as briefly as u.
Well, this is a sort
of notational thing.
I can differentiate
it and get u'.
That's a new function.
Like if you started
with the sine, that's
gonna be the cosine.
A new function, so I can
differentiate it again.
And the notation for
the differentiating
of it again, is u''.
So u'' is just u'
differentiated again.
For example, if u = sin
x, so u' = cos(x).
Has Professor Gerison
talked about what the
derivative of cosine is?
What is it?
Ha, ok so u'' = - sin x.
Let me go on.
What do you suppose u''' means?
I guess it's the
derivative of u''.
It's called the
third derivative.
And u'' is called the
second derivative.
And it's (u')'
differentiated again.
So to compute u''' in this
example, what do I do?
I differentiate that again.
There's a constant term,
- 1, constant factor.
That comes out.
The derivative of sine is what?
Okay, so u''' = - cos x.
Let's do it again.
Now after a while, you get
tired of writing these things.
And so maybe I'll use
the notation u^(4).
That's the fourth derivative.
That's u''''.
Or it's (u''')' the
fourth derivative.
And what is that
in this example?
Okay, the cosine has derivative
-sin , like you told me.
And that -sin cancels with that
sine, and all together, I get
sin x.
That's pretty bizarre.
When I differentiate the
function sine of x four
times, I get back to
the sine of x again.
That's the way it is.
Now this notation, prime
prime prime prime,
and things like that.
There are different
variants of that notation.
For example, that's
another notation.
Well, you've used the notation
du/ dx before. u' could
also be denoted du/ dx.
I think we've already here,
today, used this way
of rewriting du/ dx.
I think when I was talking
about d/dt(uv) and so on, I
pulled that d / dt outside
and put whatever function
you're differentiating
over to the right.
So that's just a
notational switch.
It looks good.
It looks like good
algebra doesn't it?
But what it's doing is
regarding this notation
as an operator.
It's something you apply to a
function to get a new function.
I apply it to the sine
function, and I get
the cosine function.
I apply it to x^2,
and I get 2x.
This thing here, that symbol,
represents an operator, which
you apply to a function.
And the operator says, take the
function and differentiate it.
So further notation that people
often use, is they give a
different name to
that operator.
And they'll write
capital D for it.
So this is just using capital
D for the symbol d/dx.
So in terms of that
notation, let's see.
Let's write down what higher
derivatives look like.
So let's see.
That's what u' is.
How about u''?
Let's write that in terms
of the d/dx notation.
Well I'm supposed to
differentiate u' right?
So that's d/dx applied
to the function du/ dx.
Differentiate the derivative.
That's what I've done.
Or I could write that as d/dx
applied to d/dx applied to u.
Just pulling that u outside.
So I'm doing d/dx twice.
I'm doing that operator twice.
I could write that as
(d/dx)^2 applied to u.
Differentiate twice, and
do it to the function u.
Or, I can write it as, now
this is a strange one.
I could also write
as like that.
It's getting stranger
and stranger, isn't it?
This is definitely just a
kind of abuse of notation.
But people will go even further
and write (d^2)u/dx^2.
So this is the strangest one.
This identity quality is the
strangest one, because you
may think that you're taking
d of the quantity x^2.
But that's not what's intended.
This is not d(x^2).
What's intended is
the quantity dx^2.
In this notation, which is very
common, what's intended by the
denominator is the
quantity dx^2.
It's part of this second
differentiation operator.
So I've written a bunch of
equalities down here, and the
only content to them is that
these are all different
notations for the same thing.
You'll see this notation
very commonly.
So for instance the
third derivative is
(d^3)u/dx^3, and so on.
Sorry?
Student: [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: Yes, absolutely.
Or an equally good notation is
to write the operator (D^3)u.
Absolutely.
So I guess I should also write
over here when I was talking
about d^2, the second
derivative, another notation
is do the operator
capital D twice.
Let's see an example of
how this can be applied.
I'll answer this question.
Student: [INAUDIBLE].
Professor: Yeah, so the
question is whether the fourth
derivative always gives you the
original function back,
like what happened here.
No.
That's very, very special
to sines and cosines.
All right?
And, in fact, let's see
an example of that.
I'll do a calculation.
Let's calculate the nth
derivative of x^n.
Okay, n is a number,
like 1, 2, 3, 4.
Here we go.
Let's do this.
So, let's do this bit by bit.
What's the first
derivative of x^n?
So everybody knows this.
I'm just using a new notation,
this capital D notation.
So it's n x ^ (n -1).
Now you know know, by the way,
n could be a negative number
for that, but for now, for this
application, I wanna take n to
be 1, 2, 3, and so on;
one of those numbers.
Ok, we did one derivative.
Let's compute the second
derivative of x ^ n.
Well there's this n constant
that comes out, and then the
exponent comes down, and
it gets reduced by 1.
All right?
Should I do one more?
D^3 (x^n) = n(n-1).
That's the constant from here.
Times that exponent, (n -
2), times 1 less, (n -
3) is the new exponent.
Well, I keep on going until
I come to a new blackboard.
Now, I think I'm going to stop
when I get to the n minus first
derivative, so we can see
what's likely to happen.
So when I took the third
derivative, I had the n
minus third power of x.
And when I took the second
derivative, I had the
second power of x.
So, I think what'll happen when
I have the n minus first
derivative is I'll have the
first power of x left over.
The powers of x
keep coming down.
And what I've done it n - 1
times, I get the first power.
And then I get a big constant
out in front here times more
and more and more of these
smaller and smaller
integers that come down.
What's the last integer
that came down before
I got x^1 here?
Well, let's see.
It's just 2, because this
x^1 occurred as the
derivative of x^2.
And the coefficient in
front of that is 2.
So that's what you get.
The numbers n( n - 1)...2)x^1.
And now we can differentiate
one more time and calculate
what (D^n)(x^n) is.
So I get the same
number, n(n-1)...
and so on and so on, times 2.
And then I guess
I'll say times 1.
Times, what's the
derivative of x ^ 1?
1, so times 1.
Time 1, times 1.
Where this one means the
constant function 1.
Does anyone know what
this number is called?
That has a name.
It's called n factorial.
And it's written n!
And we just used an example
of mathematical induction.
So the end result is
(D^n) (x^n) = n!
constant.
Okay that's a neat fact.
Final question for the
lecture is what's D^n
1 applied to x ^ n?
Ha.
Excellent.
It's the derivative
of a constant.
So it's 0.
Okay.
Thank you.