The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
Some content in this audio is
not covered under a Creative
Commons license.
For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT
OpenCourseWare website.
PROFESSOR: Grabbing a bunch of
index cards and scribbling
things down.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR: Pretty much
how I get by.
Another group?
AUDIENCE: So our group
is [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], and Jason.
We don't have a rep
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[LAUGHTER]
We're doing like a real
time, supernatural
horror/cooperative game.
PROFESSOR: OK.
Oh, like real time
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] theme?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: I'm excited.
I'm excited.
PROFESSOR: One, two,
three, four.
All right, who else?
AUDIENCE: it's me, it's
Tanya, Patrick, and
Justin who are here.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
OK.
You guys have kind of
a [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: And how do you
describe this game?
AUDIENCE: It's building
a family tree game.
AUDIENCE: Geneology
path building.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
It's a path building game
involving family members.
AUDIENCE: Consider it geneology
path building.
AUDIENCE: It's kind of like
a Family Feud game.
Except, it's a little
bit stranger.
PROFESSOR: So I think
Jay and Mia.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: And Calvin and
Jason, you've been
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] in that.
AUDIENCE: Oh.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and things.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So right now we
have a-- we don't have a
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
The idea we have is pretty much
you want to get a certain
sets of cards.
And we get sets by drawing cards
or trading with other
people or--
but it's also you can take cards
if you want, but if you
get caught, then it's up to the
other players whether you
get punished or not.
PROFESSOR: OK, if you
get caught then--
OK.
So [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
That sounds good.
So it sounds like we
have four teams.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
So today I'm planning on, for
the most part, just going
through the lecture stuff that
I had planned for today and
for last Wednesday.
And if there's any time left,
we could finish up with
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And that's what I'd
like to do.
But if there's only like an hour
left, then I think I'd
probably rather you play
one more game.
As this is a useful exercise,
but playing these games are
just as useful and frankly
a better design.
All right.
Let's see.
So I think I'll start with
Wednesday's stuff first, which
is the last [COLERA]
reading for the entire
semester.
I did, in fact, actually look
a little bit into the weird
eskimo stuff from Monday, and
one thing, I don't actually
think he was speaking
figuratively.
I think he was actually
describing something that he
had done some anthropoligical
research on-- this is a ritual
that a very, very
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], just a fine
group of eskimos do.
It reminds me a lot of the sort
of recitations that you
get that sometimes has
a morbid quality,
sometimes they don't.
But this reminds you of either
historical events, or
important things to do.
Like the easiest one that
I keep in my brain is
righty-tighty, lefty-loosey.
That teaches you something
of how screws work.
But then they're a little bit
like ring around the rosy,
with a pocket full
of poseys, ashes,
ashes, we all fall down.
But it's actually a
commemorative little poem
about the black death.
That's what that
song is about.
So you have these
little things.
That particular example that
he was describing was more
about this recitation that you
sort of remember the procedure
in which things are supposed
to be done.
But they're [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
they're sort of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
reenactment about what you
do in order to I guess
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
or something like that
to basically perform
taxodermy on an animal.
One of those ways where a
playful experience was pretty
much it's been used as
a learning tool.
And that kind of gets back to
something I was mentioning
much earlier in this course.
In many ways, learning
how to play a game is
literally very exotic.
You can't figure out how to play
the game unless you have
figured out all the rules.
And if the rules happen to have
some sort of correlation
to something real world, you
might end up learning
something about that
real world.
Whether you transfer to back
to actually something real
world is kind of actually the
topic of what Wednesday's
reading about.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
talks about mimicry and things
being kind of taken over by
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Now he uses these grand,
sweeping statements which I
think sound a lot more modest
when they're in the original
language, and what to translate
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
sound like you're saying, and
this huge wave of competitive
games took over witch doctors.
But I think what he's referring
to, and if we notice
the readings for that chapter
three and chapter eight.
So there's a whole bunch of
stuff that's missing, and we
kind of wanted to spare you
from the bad translation.
But the idea is that there is a
lot of stuff that basically
mimicry, the old process of
putting on masks, putting on
costumes, and being someone else
has great societal power.
This had great societal power.
And this is more of an
anthropological thing.
But the idea being you have
these people-- who are
effectively leaders
of groups--
shamans, witch doctors, fortune
tellers, maybe just elders.
And they would have costumes,
they'd have masks that not
only gave them station, what
when I wear this robe I am now
in charge of this tribe,
but also turned them
into somebody else.
Now, if you look at ancient
accounts of the Egyptian
pharoahs, for instance, in
order to actually give up
their own name and then they
take on a new name.
And a lot of them actually just
become Pharaoh in the
same way that a lot of Roman
emperors just become Caesar.
You can think of Caesear
as just being king.
So it becomes a title, but
you also become a person.
A lot of the--
I'm trying to remember--
Persian, I think, emperors
become Darius or Cyrus.
Kind of just one word.
This is one name that was
given to the king.
That's who you become.
And that kind of combined with
aesthetic solemn rituals.
A lot of these are not what
you would recognize
as games right now.
But in many ways they sort of
tap into the same sort of
pleasures of sort of critical
and losing control.
Once in a while, you don't
have to be sort of all
inhibited and obeying laws.
You can just cut loose.
And in superstitious tribes,
superstitition will be the excuse.
But you don't actually
necessarily need that reason.
And I think one thing that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
sort of describes in chapter
eight is how--
we kind of get that today too.
He was describing stuff like
identification, for instance,
when somebody who could be
you wins something for no
particular good reason, against
incredible odds.
And is there some sort of
mechanism for you to feel I am
now happy partly for this
person's success, therefore,
I'm a winner.
Then you get to have that
experience of ecstasy.
You get to that news.
A couple of videos.
Some of them it's tongue and
cheek, but hopefully that
you-- it will kind of illustrate
my point as well.
So was anyone here in
Boston in 2004?
You were in Boston in 2004?
What happened in
Boston in 2004?
AUDIENCE: With the Red Sox?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
The Red Sox won after, what, 86
years of coming real close
and never actually winning
a World Series.
And I'm going to--
This is a neat little
video that I have.
I just kind of then just use
this as a back drop.
I think this is right
around Fenwick Hall.
I'm not so sure it's
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Sorry, the wireless in this
particular corner of the
office can be bad.
This is-- actually let
me skip a little bit.
So for those of you who don't
know the story, actually how
many of you don't know what
happened in 2004 around here?
AUDIENCE: Well I don't
know exactly what
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: So basically what
happened around here was the
Red Sox were down 3, 0
against the Yankees.
And managed to come
back from them.
And then they beat the Cardinals
and they won the
World Series.
Now, this is, of course,
after 86 years, again.
I mentioned really people
just not winning at all.
But coming really close.
Each time they get really,
really close and then they'd
magnificently flub it.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So this earlier video here is
what Boston looked like when
it was down 3, 0.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
The funniest thing that every
time the Red Sox actually won
it was like an awakening.
So they weren't at Fenway.
When all of these celebrations
that-- can you see once the
buffering stops.
All the celebration that's going
on is occurring miles
and miles, probably 100 miles
away from where the game's
actually happening with
the Cardinals.
And of course, everyone was
watching it on TV, everyone's
identifying with the Red Sox.
And right now you are sort of
seeing like, as far as I can
tell probably the Northeastern
students
who were around Fenway.
But in here, the vehicles
driving by and
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Everybody was listening on the
radio, you can see the cars
driving by.
Everybody knows immediately.
Everyone in Boston immediately
knew it
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
If they weren't watching
the game, they would
have heard it anyway.
Because they have no
affirmative claims.
The only way that you would
cheer the Red Sox is to say
Mackie sucked, which is
kind of sad actually.
For those of you who weren't
around, it was a really,
really awesome night.
There was, of course, a little
bit of violence.
Things got a little bit
out-- a bunch of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
But it wasn't like a huge
riot or anything.
For the most part it was
pretty much this.
A lot of people with a lot
of the hands in the air.
No cars being turned over
or anything like that.
But it was being--
But these are the kind of
aesthetic movements that
[? Colera ?]
talks about in his write-up.
Yup?
AUDIENCE: I have a video on my
phone in Barcelona right after
they won the semi-finals
over the summer.
And I had a video of the
streets at 11 PM.
I could show you
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I have a video of the
streets at 12:30,
so half past midnight.
And it's the exact same scene.
And the exact same people are
still in the street with their
shirts off, still twirling
their shirts around.
PROFESSOR: It was probably more
rowdy I would imagine.
AUDIENCE: Oh, it was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] rowdy
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
This is America, they don't
know how to be rowdy in
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: I think for every
three people there was a cop.
You don't see that
in the video.
But there were a lot of cops out
there that night just to
make sure that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
But I think Barcelona also
would have been partying.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: So the idea--
of course, the idea of a sports
team is something which
you identify with because
associated with the city that
you live in.
They win.
I didn't do anything, but
because I because I'm a
supporter of sports
team, I get to
identify myself with them.
And [? Colera ?]
makes the assertion that this
is important because if you
look at the forces of human
chance, of there, which I
think gives the various athletes
the opportunities, as
well as the physical ability,
to actually perform well.
The likelihood of any of the
people actually celebrating,
actually being able to perform
that same feat
is extremely low.
In fact, the likelihood of
even someone who has the
ability and the opportunities of
actually winning is pretty
much random and the odds
are against you.
But because you identify so
strongly with a group of
people who can win, you are
allowed to sort of enjoy that
victory, even though you weren't
the one who actually
got that victory.
And it gets stronger actually
for some games--
well for some kind of games
where you actually did have
something to do with
the victory, for
instance, talent shows.
Especially the modern
talent shows.
Maybe you've already
seen this.
[BEGIN VIDEO PLAYBACK]
PROFESSOR: So [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the Outward Bound are on about
next week's show.
They're going to--
remember that when you look at
things like Britain's Got
Talent, like American Idol,
all of these things are
popularity contests.
You have judges, but the
judges don't actually
determine very much who's
actually going to win.
The only people who actually
determine who's going to win
are popular vote.
And that vote is happening
through short messages
basically, which people
are being charged for.
The basic idea is that because
you might have had voted for
someone, you now identify with
that person who might win.
Whether that person wins or not
is effectively random for
other purposes.
Now sure, that some of them have
talent, but later on--
but when you look at who
actually tends to progress in
these competitions, I think
some of the results are
really, really random.
Like you have some people who
move onto the next stage
because they are just strange.
And you just want to see them
next week because they may be
entertaining, not necessarily
because they're talented.
So this is [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
example.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
[WATCHING VIDEO]
AUDIENCE: Yes, but their
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Dancing.
AUDIENCE: That's
an obvious one.
Singing for everyone.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Getting married.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Cypress.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, what
do they do?
PROFESSOR: I should have
looked up what their
particular is, but they can
all do different things.
So the first one is short
message vote in.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: Slick-backed hair.
PROFESSOR: I notice the camera
moves at this point.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: They just like
the looks of their
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: They're obviously
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It looked like
a dance thing.
And if you look at the other
celebration's like the Susan
Boyle video, where I think
it got pretty viral.
So I'm assuming a lot
of you have seen it.
It's one of those things where
even if you don't necessarily
that you're rooting
for a person.
It's so easy for you to be
convinced that you're actually
rooting for this person as soon
as you have a reason to.
So--
AUDIENCE: It's like oh wow,
that guy is from Texas.
PROFESSOR: Hey,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It's good for you.
You don't really need that much
of a reason to identify
with somebody.
And that's where you get sort
of still see some of that
power of the vertigo,
basically.
It's not the vertigo of actually
playing the game, the
vertigo of watching a game,
but it's still part of the
entire game experience.
Britain's Got Talent, American
Idol, everything like that
wouldn't have the power if it
didn't have the hundreds and
hundreds of screaming fans
voting in and having their
faces changing on camera,
and applauding and
screaming their heads off.
And of course, that's the
identification part of it.
But even when you're talking
about sort of just basic
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Here's a shrine festival
in Japan.
And basically what they're doing
is just getting started.
Everyone's gotten assembled.
All of the folks here who are
wearing basically the same
colored outfit are basically
from the same town.
Including that logo.
And what you've got is basically
like a little house
for a deity.
They're both carried
on the shoulders.
And those three up there look
really precarious, but I think
they're having a good time.
That's a completely different
talent [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But you know, this is not unlike
what you'd see in a
sporting event.
It's kind of getting
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: Isn't the town versus
town like competition?
PROFESSOR: It's not really
so much a competition.
But I think there's
a certain amount
that you have to represent.
AUDIENCE: That show existed
in France, it's called
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE], and
they literally get towns in
the countryside and have
them compete in various
competitions.
So like each town, for example,
designates the
strongest person to have
an arm wrestling match.
PROFESSOR: Sort of
like champions.
You send your champions.
AUDIENCE: You send
your champions.
Then you have like a
horseback thing.
And I think like other
weird events.
And it's pretty popular.
1,000 people/person
town versus
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: I think you get that
in the Scottish Highland
games as well.
Basically it's sending people
to throw giant pieces of
lumber as far as they can.
But [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
competition.
This is not [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
This is a lot closer
to kind of the
earlier kind of situation.
Because they're not vying
to win anything.
They are really just trying to
all get into it together.
So if you think of it as
what kind of thing.
The aim of the game is
don't drop the damn--
[LAUGHTER]
It's quite simple.
Get thrown--
in fact, it's actually a fair
amount of effort because I
think they walk a
couple of miles.
I'm not quite sure what the
traditions are on where it
starts and where it ends.
But it's like a huge
street parade.
And the whole idea is let's
get everybody involved.
The people are packed really
close with each other, so it's
not like you can actually move
one foot without colliding
into somebody else unless you're
all moving in unison.
And can you keep in sync.
And all the shouting, all the
whistles, and all the chance
actually just helped that entire
process move along.
It continues today, not just
in sports, not just in
televised shows, but
in street fairs and
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
that's great.
And those folks really look
like they're having fun.
So that's kind of what we were
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
And the version of this, the
version of what [? Colera ?]
describes as since your ability
to succeed is so
random, especially if you think
of it outside of the
game context, but more
in the silo context--
your ability to be a great
athlete, your ability to be a
great politician, your ability
to make a lot of money, just
to succeed in life
is so random.
But people kind of don't
necessarily want to
acknowledge that it's random
because you have rules,
because you have sort of rules
set in to promote merit to
sort of equalize systems.
Is this the equilaterian
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], which I
think actually he meant.
I think the original word
was egalitarian.
While there are a lot of
processes trying to stabilize,
in the end you can't
really ignore the
forces of one's birth.
At least that's the
way he sees it.
When you get competitions that
are effectively just
completely random, which means
anybody can win, people really
do understand and sort of
ascribe to that kind of power.
They accept.
The likelihood of me winning the
lottery is about as good
as the likelihood that I'm
going to succeed in life.
A lot of it is based on who was
I born to, and which year,
and which region
are we born in?
What's happening in the world as
I-- at least that's the way
of how he puts it.
So he has a really hilarious
video, by the way,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
This is an ad.
Let me get--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: I guess so.
Sorry about the--
It looks damn pretty.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
[BEGIN VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-Mos of us when we buy a lottery
scratch-off ticket,
we're thinking this
is my day, right?
OK, if that's the case, then
a 19-year-old Mills college
student is super
lucky tonight.
-Louis Jay became an instant
millionaire with the scratch
of a ticket, and he told Rob
Robert all about it today.
-It was on his birthday when
Towson University student,
Louis Jay, decided to buy a
scratch-off lottery ticket.
-I actually won $20 on the
scratch-off the prior week.
-Louis Jay went to this
giant [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Mills and used the $20 he won
on a scratch-off ticket and
bought another one.
As he began scratching off the
numbers, Louis couldn't
believe his eyes.
-I'm at the second to the
last line and it's
not going too well.
And I was starting to see six.
I was like oh, it matched up.
All right, I won $30 or
something, why not.
I saw a million.
I started double-checking,
triple-checking everything.
Make sure all the numbers
matches and everything.
I was like oh, my God.
-And when it came time to
scratch off the last number,
his mother told him--
-He was scratching
on every one.
And when it was the next to
the last one I said, don't
scratch it from right to left,
do it from left to right.
[LAUGHTER]
-And there it was.
Louis had won himself
one million dollars.
-This little dollar sign bag
right here that I won on, I'm
actually got number six for my
lucky number right here.
And down here it matches the
six with the prize for a
million dollars.
-He's a hardworking young man,
and he has fun and he likes
the lottery.
He buys a ticket on his 19th
birthday, and lo and behold,
he wins a million dollars.
I don't know if he told you the
other part of the story.
He bought a ticket on his 18th
birthday, his first one, and
he won $100.
So I don't know what's going
on his 20th birthday.
Everyone in the family about
Louis's good fortune.
-I'm happy for him.
AUDIENCE: Isn't it a story that
they're trying to tell
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
-And yes, he does have
plans for the money.
-I'm putting some money away for
my brother and sister to
finish schooling.
They go to [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
school.
I'm going to put some money
away for myself, help my
parents pay off some bills
so we could all--
We always said what we'd do if
we won the lottery, we'd go to
England, visit my father's
relatives and stuff.
We're going to go there
next summer hopefully.
Just going to do a lot of things
we always said what if
we won the lottery,
and now we did.
-Rob Robert, Linda.
BBAL TV, 11 News.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
PROFESSOR: So this is
just a story that
they're trying to tell.
It's like this is hard--
he's a hard-working young man,
as if that had anything to do
with his [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: He deserved it.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
[LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: Behind that is that
well, and and if you're a
hard-working person as well,
and if you bought a lottery
ticket, you could win.
That's the story that they're
trying to tell.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
is like perfect time
for opportunity.
Like with the lotto idea,
what if a really, really
unlikeable, despicable character
wins the lottery,
what's the news reports
going to be like?
She never worked a
day in her life.
PROFESSOR: But I think you can
still turn that in the way of
this is not a person
whose odds in life
were already in favor.
And everyone can sort of
identify with that.
It's like yeah, things aren't
quite working my way, but you
could be a lottery
winner tomorrow.
That's the story that
they are telling.
And of course, the idea being
what the lottery director was
saying, yeah, remember, he
didn't just buy one ticket.
He bought one ticket
the year before, he
might buy another ticket.
They're trying to encourage
you to buy more tickets.
That's the story.
The story is buy more tickets,
which oddly enough is actually
the only way to increase
your chances
of winning the lottery.
Buy more tickets.
Pity that doesn't work for like
past deals and things.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: And reapply for more
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] classes
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
But the basic idea that they're
trying to because the
forces of life are so random,
these kinds of like totally
random, high stakes games
have incredible power.
And not just because of the
possibility of winning.
But because it resonates very,
very strongly with the idea
that you could win.
And if you identify with
somebody else, even better
because then you don't
even have to win.
That person could win.
And in fact, increases the range
of different winners
that you can identify with.
Help people sort of get that
thrill of winning without
necessarily even having
competed.
So that's kind of the power
that we have in chance.
I haven't actually talked
about, well so how do we
actually use chance in games
yet, which is what
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
But I think in their book,
they describe--
the reason why I like challenges
for you to design
is that they're very concrete
about well if you're stuck and
you don't know what to do with
a game, have you considered
bam, bam, bam, bam, bam, bam.
They're very, very systematic
about that.
You know, have you considered
doing options?
Have you thought--
That's not chance.
That's the second chapter.
The first chapter was have you
considered using dice, using
cards, using spinners.
I don't remember what other
randomizing systems they had.
Computer or random number
generated [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Are you using it to equalize
different skill levels, or are
you just trying to make it
so that there's sometimes
predictability, that sometimes
solveability in the system.
There are all these different
ways that you can use
randomness.
But don't forget how powerful
randomness is.
It's one of those things where
you normally assume that you
don't actually [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
in the game.
And you don't want him
to [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
First of all, as the designer,
randomness makes it hard for
you to predict what's going to
happen, and as a result, it
becomes difficult to design.
But the power of the this I
could be a winner for reasons
that are entirely out of my
control is actually more
powerful than a lot of folks
what will naturally assume
right off the bat.
So I'm not going to go too much
into the various options
that Brenda and Ian described as
a challenge because you can
look those up.
But do look those up, especially
if I'm having
difficulty in your game.
If you're having difficulty,
oh this game is too
predictable, and you
can see that there
is the optimal strategy.
Well then you can think about
maybe writing those might be a
good [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Or maybe I want to be able to
play this with people who have
never played this game before I
had met them, and still have
a fighting chance.
That's another good
opportunity to win
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But know what problem you're
trying to solve before you're
throwing something away.
Because sometimes you can have
a lot of fun with games that
are effectively just
like fun butteries.
You know, oh, I draw a card.
Munchkin is kind of like
this actually.
You draw a card.
Oh, look at, funny.
And you read the text.
That was silly.
And now they've added a Twitter
version of Munchkin
where every hour you introduce
a new rule.
And it's like the player whose
name starts with the letter M
gets double the hit point
for something.
But totally random.
And that can be kind
of fun, but that's
really short-lived fun.
That's one of the things where
once you look through all of
the cards-- the game's pretty
much done for you.
Even if you haven't even
finished playing the game, the
game might end for yourself.
So try not to go down
that track.
There was a group last year that
did a game where pretty
much you just drew silly things
to do out of a hat.
And, yeah, it was fun until
everyone got through the hat,
and then once everyone knew
pretty much the range of the
little silly things, that's
it, game was over.
There was no replay.
So [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
"The [? Side Note ?]
About Replayability," that's
actually a really excellent
essay on I think gamasutra about
how replayability isn't
actually a well-defined word.
Nobody really knows what
that word means, but
everyone uses it.
So if you're interested,
check it out.
I haven't actually had a
chance to form a real
opinion on it yet.
So by the way, a lot of the
roots of the kinds of
randomness things that we use,
like dice and cards, have some
sort of root in fortune telling,
which connects it
back to kind of the ritualistic
aspects of games again.
The idea of you can tell whether
you're going to be a
success in life by your
success in this game.
And the game might be draw
a card from this deck
and hope it's good.
Which parallels what a lot
of people think like it.
If I roll the dice, and if
I'm lucky, things are
going to work out.
But there's a couple of
interesting things about how
strategy and skills start
to work with things of
randomness.
For instance, there is one
argument that [? Colera ?]
makes that the reason why you
get things like chance and
skill games taking over
mimicry and vertigo
experiences is because we
started developing systems of
enumeration.
Started being able to count, we
started being able to rank
things to tell whether something
was actually better
than other, and some sort of
empirical numerical way.
So if you think about it from
that sense, then actually when
you look at skill and when you
look at chance, they're
actually kind of on both
on the same side.
They're sort of dealing
with number
systems one way or another.
If you had a system that has
a lot of chance, any number
could come up.
Any card could come up.
Any dice roll having some
set of probability.
What skill is dealing with what
could happen, having a
plan, having a strategy.
Maybe that element of chance
isn't a random die roll.
Maybe a person that you've never
met before that you're
playing against, and you don't
know how good they are, they
don't know what the strategies
are, they don't
know how they play.
They're effectively a die roll,
and your skill is kind
of or the element of skill in
the game are all about how do
you deal with all the
probabilities that have happened.
So one of the things that
[? Colera ?] talked about is a
lot of the competitive games
kind things actually come up
from tests-- tests of physical
skill, tests of mental skill.
Tests the ability to be able
to take an administrative
position and in society.
That sort of thing.
But your ability to actually
do well on those tests also
kind of depends on your luck of
having the ability in the
first place.
It's like did you get the
right of education?
Did you study the
right questions?
Do you happen to have really
good genes so that you can
jump really high?
That sort of thing.
So the idea of whether it is
actually just luck, if you
would talk about a modern game,
you can talk about skill
of someone being able
to play chess.
Or you can talk about the luck
of somebody having had the
chance to play chess many,
many, many times before
they're playing this one
particular game.
Because not everybody in the
world has that option.
And that's kind of the case
that [? Colera ?]
is trying to make.
When you're bringing a new
person to a game, they haven't
had the luck of playing
your particular game.
I'm going to say the good
fortune of playing your
particular game, whereas
you have had that.
So if you wanted to think of
it as that, as well they're
bad luck, now how do we use
rules, either rules of chance
or rules of skill to be able
to give them a fighting
chance, a fighting edge.
Probably more rules of chance.
So a there's a couple
of different things.
One thing that I do want
to bring up is you
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
information
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Sorry.
I could probably just draw it.
But I just want to make
sure I get it right.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: Can we also
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] shift it over
to the big screen?
PROFESSOR: It's really very
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So it's incredibly blurry--
OK, all right.
So this is the basic idea.
Claude Shannon, back in
the '60s, I believe--
I think [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE],
basically came up with a model
of how communication works.
How information gets from
a sender to a receiver.
How does this have anything
to do with games?
I will get to that quickly.
But let me just talk
about models first.
So the sender had some sort
of like message, right?
And they're going to
send it end of this
conversation I believe--
yeah.
This is transmission.
I'm going to shorten it
and say X-mission.
So a sender has a message.
They want to set up--
they want to translate it, and
then it needs to be received
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
by the receiver.
In between the two, there
is some sort of channel.
So if you think of this as I got
a computer and my message
is an email.
I'm going to transmit it
through the internet.
And then it's going to be
received by some sort of other
mail server and then it's
going to the other.
This is the important part of
this model is that this is
where noise gets
in the channel.
The reason why this model is
useful for thinking about
games is you can actually
think of the
sender as the game.
This this game space.
And the message could be
something, it could be
valuable information about the
current state of the game in
order for you to make
a good decision.
In poker, it will be, well
everybody's hands.
That's the message.
That's valuable information.
If you knew what everybody had
in your hand, and if you knew
everything in the deck in the
order in which the deck is
shuffled, you will be able to
make a great decision about
whether to raise your
bid on the floor.
And so you have rules that
sort of encode what that
message is going to be, and
you have rules that--
you have strategies to help you
figure out what to do with
that, with the receiver kind of
becomes and you think of it
as [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
as a player's position,
actually.
Or the player's strategy if you
would think about it over
a long-term strategy.
The trick is noise.
And noise is actually something
that you get to
control [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
What is hidden?
What is obfiscated?
What can be deliberately
introduced to confuse you
about what the game
state actually is?
Noise can be random, or noise
can be just plain old you
don't know.
Just deleting information out
of the [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So for instance, you guys know
the rules of Texas Bulldog?
There is a set of cards in the
middle called the river.
I could be wrong, so if you
really know the rules
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And these cards are dealt pretty
early in the game.
They're not dealt right at
the beginning, but the--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
at the beginning?
AUDIENCE: Not all at once
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: The first three.
AUDIENCE: The flop, yeah.
And then [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Oh, the flop
and the river, right.
Which is the one
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: The flop is data?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Everyone gets dealt
the two cards, and then you
turn the flop over, which
[INTERPOSING VOICES].
And then the river is the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: The river's
the big one.
AUDIENCE: And betting
zero, yeah.
AUDIENCE: Well no, technically
when you deal you put one card
face down then you put the
flop [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: That part doesn't
have anything to do
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but I
don't know what--
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
But the cards would
get dealt out.
It's pretty much an unknown.
It is random.
But on and above this, if you
just put five cards in
whatever side and then
just dealt them out.
It's a fixed quantity.
But you still don't know
what the heck it is.
Someone else could have picked
those cards and still don't
know what it is.
So they're effectively
a random thing.
They're noise.
They're a bit of information
we don't know.
And in Texas Hold'em, a bit of
information that everybody
does know, so that's great.
The information is kind of
equally shared among everybody
except for the one card.
They'd be fine.
So--
--when you think about how you
can even things out for the
players, or how you can make
the challenge a little bit
higher for decent players, you
can think about, well how much
information am I currently
giving them about what
a game state is?
And maybe I can, I'll just
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] them.
Not necessarily lie,
just hide.
Just deny them information
that is necessarily
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It's also a good way to sort
of think of well maybe if
you're a little bit behind and
you need a little help, then
what are you going to do
to give them a fighting
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] channel.
Let them have the next card
that's coming up.
Because we're talking about
card games here.
Let them re-roll the
next die roll.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
This model, about like
thinking what sort of
information are you giving your
player can also sort of
be useful in thinking whether
they're giving too much
information strictly from a
decision-making point of view.
It's like I'm throwing all this
game state information,
but really, all the player needs
to know is half of that
in order to make a
good decision.
You might actually
want to consider
reducing that somehow.
Let me think of an example.
I think Settlers of Catan that
should be a pretty good
example of that.
You can see the entire board.
Everyone can see the entire
board at any given time.
And everyone's got cards
in their hands.
You don't know what other people
have in their cards.
But for the most part, when
you're trying to make a
decision about what to do with
your cards, you're really just
concerned about your cards.
As time goes on, you pretty much
know what other people
have in their hand if you've
been paying attention, because
people are picking up resources
fairly openly.
But you don't really care.
And that's one nice thing about
Settlers is that they're
hiding this information from
you, even though it is
information that need
to be hidden.
Because in order to make a good
decision in that game,
you do not need to know
that information.
So they're introducting noise,
they're deliberately hiding
information from you so that you
can just focus on the two
or three decisions that
are actually worth
making on your turn.
And that's one reason why
Settlers games actually go
pretty fast because people
aren't paralyzed by too much
information.
If your game's getting
too long.
The game's supposed to be a half
an hour and it's taking
an hour long, think about the
information that you're giving
your player.
All of it might be relevant to
the game state, but not all of
it might be relevant to what the
players need to know right
now in order to make
their next move.
And if you find a way to control
that, sometimes just a
clever color coding.
Making your card in such a way
that it's really, really
obvious that there's a certain
part of the card that you need
to look at at certain times,
and you kind of ignore it
outside on a [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
call other times, and that
might help.
But often what I find is
in a lot of games like
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] card games,
for instance, board games,
they would use a lot of icons to
describe what the value of
something is, or what kind
of effect it has.
And the reason why they use
icons instead of using words
is because you don't have
translate icons.
And they want their games to
sell in Germany, in Spain, in
England, and US, and Greece, and
Italy, and so if you made
cards, you couldn't use those
same cards in every one of of
those countries, so
you use icons.
The only problem is that now you
have to learn what every
one of those icons mean.
If it's just a stack of coins,
oh 5 coins means 5?
OK, all right, I can probably
figure that out.
That's fine.
But this is a picture of a
hammer, what does a hammer do?
I'll have to check in the
reference manual, which
happens to be in six different
languages.
And that's one of the barriers
that a lot of folks have to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
in card games and board games.
It's not necessarily that
the games are all that
complicated.
It's just that you have to
actually have translation that
has to be done because
they're not really
built for one language.
So I probably have more to say
about information, but I'm
going to save it till
next class.
Any questions so far?
Everything that I'm sort of
directing at you right now are
pretty much just different
ways to look at the game
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It's a card game, but try to
see it from different ways.
Not just how do I get this one
game mechanic to work.
But what are people going to be
getting out of this game.
When they're going to be drawing
this big card, how are
they going to be feeling?
Are they going to be
getting excited?
Apprehensive?
Are they going to be counting
on the next card to win them
the game, or is this just
going to be giving them
options, and do they know
what options they have?
So I'm just going
to do a complete
transition at this point.
So new topic.
One thing I want to talk about,
which is not actually
covered in any of the
readings is the body
motion think plate.
I think it's probably
used as, sort of--
Jason and I use this
story quite a bit.
We haven't really designed
it all that well.
But if you think of the
definition of what a good game
could be, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
offers, a good game is a series
of interesting choices.
Our answer is all interesting
decisions.
So what's an interesting
decision?
One argument is that an
interesting decision is one
where you're using mechanics
to affect the game state.
And you're going to get some
information, you're going to
use that mechanic and effect
the game state.
The game state, the game's going
to respond in some way.
And how that decision you make
corresponds to the result that
you get back from the game state
as could be interesting.
If there's no correspondence
at all, if it's completely
random or, even worse,
completely predictable, than
these are not interesting
options that you've got.
And [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
huh.
That result logically made
sense, but I didn't expect
that it was going to do
it, or that turned out
better than I expected.
Now it becomes really
interesting.
And if it's just a--
it could be anything.
It could be awesome.
I could win this game
with this next--
oh, look I won.
That's not interesting either.
So if that's an interesting
decision, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
calls it a meaningful decision,
then the converse
will be a meaningless
decision.
So like a game like what
I just described.
A decision where making a choice
doesn't actually affect
your outcome.
Because [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
makes card flip, or you had to
do the card flip anyway.
You can't choose.
Then that's not a meaningful
decision.
Or you make a decision and have
no change in the game
state at all.
That's not interesting either.
So what you want in your game is
something where you've got
a system that's nonlinear,
that's one that's still
deterministic.
All of your rules will result
in some sort of outcome.
But nonlinear enough that
you can't really sort of
anticipate the entire
possibility space when you're
making that decision.
If you're thinking of games,
that's a huge possibility
space, then you, as the
designer, your job is to try
to make them most frazzled areas
of possibility space
interesting and fun.
So actually do folks know the
phrase possibility space.
Yeah, and if you think of a game
as just a series of terms
or series of decisions.
Then possibility space is
basically every single result
that would come out from
every single legal
decision in your game.
Some of them are going
to make sense.
Like--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: In process, which
now I'm getting back to the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Someone's got zero and zero,
and it's my turn.
Putting in actually
what makes sense.
Putting it anywhere else
doesn't make any sense.
So I would argue that putting
an X anywhere really isn't--
well it is part of the
possibility space, because I
could put it here, here,
here, here or here.
You as a game designer, your job
is to make sure that the
things that people won't
naturally do are interesting.
You do not have necessarily
any responsibility for
somebody who's just trying to
play your game in a way that's
entirely not what you planned.
Say somebody plays one of these
card games and says,
well I'm just going to play
all my card face up.
Those specific rules that says
that I have to bite my hand,
but [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
You don't really need
to keep it for that.
Nice to have a rule that
explains, OK, this is what you
should hide your cards is
crucial to your game.
But for the most part, when
somebody plays your game in a
way that doesn't logically make
sense, you're not really
obliged to make sure
that they have fun.
On the other hand when people
are making rational, if you
are making rational
decisions--
somebody puts an x here, and
then the next move goes on and
you design your game, then it's
your job to make sure
that OK, within the realm of
the things that are legally
good, and strategically make
sense, we're going to try to
make that game as interesting
as possible.
That's your job.
So in order to sort of like help
you figure out how to get
that, the reading from
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] today,
introduce a few terms, if you've
already taken game
theory and economic class or
a math course, you probably
already know these in far more
detail than you necessarily
need it for the [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
is useful.
But utility it's a very
useful concept.
It's difficult to quantify
sometimes, but you're talking
about just like regular game
design as opposed to the pure
mathematic thought experiment.
But a basic idea is if utility
is like how winning a move is.
Is the likelihood that something
is going to actually
call you a winner.
And in some ways, it's a measure
of the games that
you're [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
example has this like ridiculous
game where you
guess whether somebody
has heads or tails.
And the person's like literally
just choosing
whether it's going to be
a heads or a tails,
and you just guess.
The idea being if
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So this is the guesser,
this is the flipper.
So if the guesser guesses
right, the
guesser gets a point.
And that's a choice of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
If the flipper chooses tails,
the guesser chooses tails, the
guesser will get one.
And if not, then it reverses.
So the flipper again gets
the penny if the
guesser gets it wrong.
So you can sort of tell that,
just by looking at this, this
is a ridiculous game.
It's like at best, your average
over multiple games is
just going to be zero.
On average it's just going to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
And you use this as example to
describe how we can come up
with a strategy where you're not
basically doing the same
thing all the time.
In this particular case, he's
advocating that the best way
to win this game is pretty much
to break even in this
game, and that's to just
play it randomly.
Every single time just really
caught up in it.
As soon as you get consistence,
and either you'll
get this for your flips,
then you are now
in a different package.
But what you're trying
to do in--
but in this particular case, the
likelihood of whether it
is a heads or a tail, and
you're actually doing it
randomly, but if you throw a
kink and say, well if it most
comes up heads, instead of
winning one penny, you win one
million dollars or something.
There's certainly the
probability that the flipper
is going to choose heads,
drops it, drops
like rubber, right?
Not a wise strategy.
If a flipper chooses heads 50%
of the time, then the guesser
is going to be winning several
million dollars pretty soon.
They'll be losing a couple of
pennies once in a while, sure.
fine, I'll lose a couple of
pennies, I'll just guess heads
all the time.
And if I know that they are
flipping heads 50% of the
time, I'm going to be getting
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So in this particular case,
the way how the flipper
balances it out is basically
to flip tails about one
million to one.
I think it's more accurately
it's like one million to two.
So it's like for every one
million tail flips, I'm just
going to throw in a head flip
every once in a while just
don't force the guesser to
occasionally guess heads.
Because if the guesser knows the
flipper will be crazy to
guess heads all the time, and
does tails all the time, then
the guesser just guesses tails
all the time, and after 50
games the guesser is ahead.
So the idea is every once in a
while you throw in a head.
And it's roughly the opposite
probability of the ability.
Approximately.
The numbers don't quite
work out that easy.
But it's I guess in the scale
that I'm using right now, one
million to one.
And when you're talking about
balancing a game, if you can't
actually break down a decision
in your game, say a particular
decision that a player has got
to fake given a certain hand
or having a certain card.
And now they can make one or
two or three decisions.
And knowing the card
distribution well enough
saying well, 30% of the
time decision A
is going to be good.
20% of the times decision
B is going to be good.
And the other 50%, it's going
to be decision C.
Then a balanced game, at least
one definition of it, is that
the utility of all those
decisions, the benefit that
you're going to get out
of that maybe is
raw, winning points.
Victory points that you need to
be able to get in the game.
Maybe some sort of cash.
The benefit of actually making
that decision should probably
be in reverse proportion
of those numbers.
So the thing that you will pick
50% of the time, that you
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So say you've got decision
A, B, C. And--
actually, I'm not sure if I need
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
I'm actually really
bad at this.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
C is 50% of the time
C is good.
30% of the time A is good.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
If anyone knows how to do
this better than me,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: What are
you trying to do?
PROFESSOR: So the idea is
that A should give you
disproportion will be
higher than it is.
Not disproportionally,
but should give you
proportionately higher than it
did in decision C. So if C
gives you--
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: Say what?
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: I'm just picking pure
probability right now.
Assuming that you're just
playing a game with this.
They're not playing
as we presume
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So say doing decision C
gives you five points.
AUDIENCE: You should do it with
30 the numbers would work
out better.
PROFESSOR: Say what?
AUDIENCE: If you use 30 the
numbers will work out better.
PROFESSOR: OK.
30 coins for 50?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So if you choose B,
then what sort of benefit
should you be getting?
About 13?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: 20.
AUDIENCE: 20.
PROFESSOR: But B only works
less of the time.
This is [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: Oh, great.
AUDIENCE: Oh.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It would
be 48, right?
AUDIENCE: Yup.
AUDIENCE: I would say 50?
AUDIENCE: I'm going with 50.
You want the multiplication
in the probability
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So when you multiply them
AUDIENCE: And what would A do?
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: And this makes it a
situation where choosing A, B
or C becomes fairly even.
You could choose A, and you
could get and 20% of the time
you've got a pretty
good payout.
I'm really terrible at
math, so I'm going to
see if this is right.
But this makes it so that you
don't have an immediate
dominant strategy just like
looking at your cards.
It's like well, obviously,
I'm just going to do
this all the time.
This is very, very,
very basic.
And I crap at doing
this other thing.
But once in a while, it's a
good idea to actually just
write out the numbers.
OK, I know that my opponent is
always going to have five
cards in hand.
And out of the five cards
they're going to have some
combination of cards that's
going to be result in the
probability of A, B, C affects
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
So I have part A, I have part B,
I have part C. I could play
any one of those, and making
that decision, you want to
give them rewards that are in
inverse proportion to this.
That's one way that you
can balance a game.
It is very much a first stab.
This is how you mathematically
take that first stab, and then
you actually need to test
it out, out of that.
You can't actually just
assumed that that's
going to work out.
But it can get you pretty close,
which is kind of nice.
If you're getting a situation
where OK, they'll still seeing
a dominant strategy, but it's
only a small number
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE],
then you don't
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Actually those can sometimes be
the hardest kinds of games
of balance because you keep
making really, really small
changes, and you know
when you get them.
But still,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
That's really the only contact
that I found utility to be a
useful part of this
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
It's an interesting concept
to be able to talk about
strategies, we talk about
decisions making.
When it actually comes to now
I'm going to sit down and
design a game, this is the only
time when I'm actually
using [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
If you found better uses for
utility, please by all means
share it because I have
not found any.
That's pretty much all.
Any questions?
AUDIENCE: The utility.
When we played the x game--
PROFESSOR: Which one?
AUDIENCE: The game where you can
either click on tokens or
roll the dice.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: The one that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Oh, yes, yes,
yes, yes, yes, yes.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
if you viewed the kind of
strategy developed and the
game we built based on different
dice and things,
that was kind of the
utility model.
That we're trying to maximize
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And if you win you expect
your utility
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
And then like you can do a bunch
of path [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
to maximize these things
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], which is--
I don't know.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
I mean the thing about it
though, of course, if the
method you do basically says
well the way to maximize our
expected value is just to do the
same thing all the time,
and then that particular game,
that's a very standard
strategy that tends to work.
Then you've got a game that's
not interesting.
Then you've got a game where
those decisions that you're
asking someone to make don't
actually matter because
there's [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So yeah, that game is a fine
example of a game that you
could use for work.
I'm not going to say the broken
game because that was
specifically designed for
the [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
that class act.
Here's this game, now I'm
going [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But yeah, that's a good game
where the utility's pretty
obvious, right?
How far are we going to get?
Well I could pick this token or
I could roll the die, wait
a minute, on average you all
come out to be about the same.
So it doesn't matter anymore.
Why this decision is no
longer interesting.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
because the whole point was that
you, the meaningful weave
is that you're pulling at the
variance table, right?
Your expected values
are the same.
Both of the cases when you're
doing just a kind of
computation, right?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Now I can
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Sometimes it's incredibly
painful to not get the reward.
Sometimes you just
want consistency.
So imagine in Settlers of Catan
where you can go for a
strategy where you have a
diverse set of numbers that
you can possibly rob.
And before you can just get up
and [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Usually it's better to go for
consistency, because you'll
get robbed.
AUDIENCE: You can use a large
range of numbers.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
The chances you'll get a huge
payoff off turn, and then a
seven will be rolled
before you get
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
They would have been better
off generating
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Even if the expectation you
generate [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: But in the back of
your head you always know that
you could go to the
big payoff round.
And usually in a game--
AUDIENCE: What I'm saying
is there's a meaningful
difference between
these things.
Even if your expected
value/computation shows you
that there
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
strategies [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
the variance
can really be different.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: The decisions
are very different.
If you're playing a three player
version of Settlers you
want to be equally
very diverse.
Whereas you imagine if there
were a version of Settlers
where there were 10 players, you
would want to like cluster
all around a couple
different numbers.
Because then it's unlikely that
if everyone's diverse,
everyone's not equal.
So you'd rather have a little
bit of a [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
you'd be like way ahead
of everybody.
Than having just the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: Well basically,
again,
counting on the huge payout.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
But that comes out
to like variance.
And where the expected value of
the resources you get, this
is the same as the expected
value of like winning the game
where you're really
trying to maximize
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: There was a really,
really, really funny video
that I didn't show you guys
about how to win at a lottery.
And they actually did trot out
various facts, basically
saying that oh, some percent
of the time two numbers--
this is one of those lotteries
where you pick six numbers,
and the number of numbers that
correspond will get you a
certain payout.
And it's like some percentage
of the time you will get two
numbers adjacent to each other,
like 39 and 40 or
something like that. and there's
like that's all, you
should pick two numbers.
That makes no sense at all.
Because [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
In that particular case,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
I think it was a good point to
say, that you get to choose
how much variance
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
How much risk are you willing
Because in a game like Settlers,
the nice thing about
it is if they're going for the
big payout is it increases the
risk and increases the payout
[UNINTELLIGIBLE],
or potential payout.
So that's what's
nice about it.
That's a nice balancing act.
AUDIENCE: I don't know if
anyone's played-- it's not
really a game, it's more
of a math problem.
PROFESSOR: I haven't
played that one.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: It's pretty cool.
Can you put that up on
the board maybe?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
I can tell you right now.
It's first cube has three
5s, the three 2s.
PROFESSOR: Oh,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Three 5s and three 3s?
AUDIENCE: Three 2s.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
One of them is 5, 4 and a 1.
PROFESSOR: 5, 4--
AUDIENCE: They all have expected
value of 3 and 1/2.
same as the regular value.
Last one is one 6 and five 3s.
PROFESSOR: One 6 and five 3s.
AUDIENCE: They all have the
expected value of 3 and 1/2.
Now, the game is first player
chooses a die, and the second
player chooses a die.
And then
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: Just
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: And then do you
re-roll with the game dice?
AUDIENCE: No.
The first player chooses the
die, and the second player
sees what the first person
chose and then the second
player chooses a die.
So truthfully, the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] take it
reverse, and the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] second, even
though they
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: I see.
AUDIENCE: If you're first, you
want to [UNINTELLIGIBLE] the
board, is that right?
But five 2s beats the 4s, but
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: They can probably
just use the 4s for
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: It's the first player
tries [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I don't know exactly,
but I'm pretty sure
if you're first,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
It's three 6s so dominated
by the 4s, but it's like
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
The second always wins.
AUDIENCE: They can
probabilistically win.
PROFESSOR: So what you're
describing is a strategy for
the second player.
Basically, if the first player
can [UNINTELLIGIBLE], you pick
something, and on average
you will win
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: It would be more
interesting if you did it in
two rounds
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
everyone takes a die
sequentially.
And then they roll to
see who goes first.
Because then you're aiming to
try to like hit the middle.
PROFESSOR: Will you do
that one more time?
AUDIENCE: So you randomly
decide who goes first.
So the first person chooses a
die, and then the next person
chooses a die, then next
person chooses die.
And they roll to determine the
order of the actual game.
So what you're trying to roll
for is to get in second place
rather than first because
the optimal strategy
is the second choice.
AUDIENCE: Oh that's bizzare.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but the problem
is if you take 6 and
3, you also have a pretty
high chance of
getting the last one.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: Well yeah,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Evolution is
something which happens
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] is well.
OK, you show that it's clearly
a dominant strategy, but how
you get to deciding what
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] strategy to
use gave meaningful information
because
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: That's possible
as well.
PROFESSOR: Once it gets to that
point, then you want to
think about well maybe there's
something you can do to your
original game to make it easier
for people to get to
that second level of the game.
And you don't necessarily always
have to, because there
are going to be people who are
just going to have fun at this
point, to sort of like playing
this game as opposed to
figuring out who goes first.
But it'll be interesting if in
the process of designing this
game, you've got rules to
actually let people decide who
goes first.
And the people who haven't
figured out the dominant
strategy, this is where
the game is at.
Just like the first player has
an equal [UNINTELLIGIBLE] as
the second player.
And then later on when people
start to realize that there is
actually a strategy, they got
playing the other game of who
goes first.
But if you design your game
right, then you can make it
all the same game.
It's just which set of rules
that they're most concerned
about and you could
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It would be nice if your
games could do that.
Let's see how [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
they get.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE] move
away from game period
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
Are you even going to mention
Prisoner's Dillema because I
think that's a great tool to
try to look at dramatic
tension and interesting
discussions for players.
AUDIENCE: That does happen
often in strategy games.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
Well--
AUDIENCE: Not in a game where
you're [INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: There are two
arguments about that one.
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
I guess we actually have
human beings playing.
PROFESSOR: So the Prisoner's
Dillema as
covered in the reading.
I don't know the
exact numbers.
But basically you've
got two people--
AUDIENCE: Well they didn't
say exact numbers
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: I think
we have a chart.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
punishment [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: In fact, I may be
thinking of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: The one that
I know is that--
let's see, I know defect
is one of the cases.
Anybody remember what the term
we use for cooperating?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
So if both people cooperate,
they get something like what,
five years in prison?
So it's like the town.
OK, we get two people who
are involved in the same
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and they both get caught but
then there's not enough
evidence to throw both of them
away for a real long time.
So the basic idea is each of
them is separated, and then
you give us information
on the other guy.
Then we will reduce your
sentence, and that other guy
is going to get hammered with a
sentence but we'll give you
a get out of jail free card.
But if you don't tell us
anything, if you cooperate
with your partner, and don't
give us the evidence that we
need, we still have enough
evidence to put you away for
five years.
So that's [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Both of you will go away
for five years.
Now, if you do decide to give
us the information, then you
really get away with just
one year in prison.
But the the guy you
just ratted on
goes away for 30 years.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
And of course, if both of you
decide to rat on each other,
oh now we've got
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] charges.
That's awesome.
Both of you go away for
a very long time.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: You need to make
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] defecting
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
a person cooperating and
another defecting.
PROFESSOR: Oh, right.
Right.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: I seen versions
where it's not equal.
But yeah, it's--
AUDIENCE: Separate game.
PROFESSOR: RXY72?
AUDIENCE: No.
Defect should be 66.
Defect should be--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] were you
cooperating, but better than
getting out.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
Yeah.
You're right.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
So this [UNINTELLIGIBLE] is
probably too high too, too.
But--
AUDIENCE: I mean it
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
AUDIENCE: All that matters is
that it doesn't matter what
your opponent does that he
will [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Although--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
looking at.
PROFESSOR: --they told me that,
which is true for a
single instance of this game.
The thing that gets really
complex is what happens is you
had to play this multiple times
because you're multiple,
repeat offender bank robber who
gets caught all the time.
AUDIENCE: Just give up.
PROFESSOR: And that's where
you get into various
strategies.
The strategy in that particular
dilemma is you
should always betray your
partner because on average,
you're going to come
out ahead.
Is that right?
AUDIENCE: The strategy is you do
whatever the partner did to
you last time.
PROFESSOR: No.
That's a single game
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Oh yeah,
single game.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: You always send out
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: So let me see, if you
defect, then what happens
is that you could get away
with one or six years.
Six, you don't know what your
opponent is going to do.
That's something like
three months time.
If you cooperate then
it's going to be
between three and seven.
So that's more like expected
value of five.
AUDIENCE: You're not trying to
win this game, you're trying
to [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
is actually right.
Say your opponent couldn't
cooperate.
Then what if you didn't
cooperate?
If you were to cooperate
you get three years.
If you defect you
get one year.
So you should defect.
What if they were to defect?
Well if you were to cooperate,
then you'd get one year.
And if you would cooperate
then you'd seven years.
But if you were to defect,
you'd only get six years.
So you defect then too.
So you should just go
ahead with that.
PROFESSOR: That's--
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
PROFESSOR: That's basically
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
what's the minimum--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
higher numbers to represent that
thing happening to you.
But the whole principle of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
we are trying to maximize your
minimum benefits, and the
minimum benefit in
this particular
case, happens in defect.
Because the most you can
possibly get is six years if
you defect.
If you ever cooperate, there's
a chance that you're going to
get to the years.
So [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
The only problem is, again,
once you get into this
repeated over many, many
times, then you're in a
situation where if you build
up a reputation, that all
you're going to do is defect,
then you can almost assume
that your--
you can pretty much assume that
whoever you're playing
against is also going
to defect.
At which point you will always
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
You will never be able
to get here.
There is a concept that helps
deal with situations like this
that actually make cooperation,
again, a viable strategy.
I'm hoping I'm getting
this right.
Well [UNINTELLIGIBLE] in the
reading suggested there are
saddle points.
There are saddle points that
basically mean this is where
all the strategies pretty much
end up because of the
reasoning that we just
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
You are maximizing the
minimum chaos.
The minimum benefit
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
And they all
If everyone did the
same analysis,
they all end up here.
But John Nash comes along and
he suggests that there are
other kinds of saddle points
that could be found.
And these are points where,
assuming that everybody sticks
with whatever strategies that
they've got, if I were to
change my strategy I will end
up in a horrid situation.
So--
AUDIENCE:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: Defective for that.
Defective
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
remains one of the saddle points
Nash [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But the other thing about it is
that what actually becomes
an unstable equilibrium.
It's one of those things,
especially in a multiple game,
is like if you're going to
assume and you're going to be
playing this game over and over
and over and over again,
switching out of coop has a
long-term detrimental effect.
Because especially-- if you know
that other people have a
strategy of basically
I'm going to do
what you did to me.
It's called tit for tat.
If you actually stick with coop,
and if everybody else is
using the same reasoning as
you are, which is another
interesting bit of a wrinkle
that Nash throws in.
Whatever analysis you are
capable of solving, everybody
else because everybody's
a natural player.
Therefore, what actually
becomes a unstable, but
possible because
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] points.
Because switching out actually
leads to the net loss for
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
And that was kind of the little
thing that he threw in
that kind of made his name and
then [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
But the basic idea is what is
useful from a one table like
this becomes really, really
interesting when you think
about what you're going to
do in the long-term.
I believe there's a couple of
other strategies that involve
things like instead of just
doing what I did to you last,
just sort of like well if you
defect and I were to defect
the next time, which I think
that's a pretty good
perspective.
But they didn't cooperate
and I wouldn't
cooperate next time.
There's also strategies like
well as soon as you defect,
I'm going to nothing
but defect.
And that actually was an
interesting group, because
that I think changes the utility
numbers in a way where
a single defection has a huge
negative [UNINTELLIGIBLE] in a
way that you might want
to [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But for the most part, I think
tit for tat turned out to be
the best strategy over
the long term.
Depending on hos the numbers
are weighted, tit for tat
basically says whatever
you do, I'm going
to do to you next.
And that actually turns out
pretty good because that
actually is not [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
coop actually
works [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
Yeah.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: This also only works
if there's an unknown number
of future games.
Because if you know you're
going to play any finite
number of times--
PROFESSOR: True.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
There is basically it's
just like induction.
It goes on forever.
But you're going to hope that
your game's going to get
played infinite number
of times.
We are planning for it.
Not an infinite number
of turns.
AUDIENCE: The winner can
only resolve after
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
PROFESSOR: First one who gives
up [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I really need to
get some water.
AUDIENCE: Game break.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
I'm going to give
a quick break.
But does everyone have your
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
sheets?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: OK.
I will lecture and pick up on
that in about 10 minutes.