PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this video what I'd
like us to do is
practice Taylor series.
So I want us to write the
Taylor series for the
following function, f of x
equals 3x cubed plus 4x
squared minus 2x plus 1.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to work
on that, and then I'll come back
and show you what I get.
All right, welcome back.
Well we want to find the
Taylor series for this
polynomial f of x equals 3x
cubed plus 4x squared
minus 2x plus 1.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
just going to write down
Taylor's, or the expression we
have for the sum for the
Taylor series in general and
then I'm going to start
computing what I need and I'm
going to see what I get.
So what do I need to remember?
Well let's remind ourselves
what the formula is.
We should get f of x is equal to
the sum from n equals 0 to
infinity of the nth derivative
of f at 0 over n factorial
times x to the n.
So that's what we want.
So what I obviously need to
start doing is figuring out
derivatives of f at 0.
And so what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to make myself
a little table.
So let's see, we're going to say
f0 at 0, f1 at 0, f2 at 0,
f3 at 0, f4 at 0.
And I'm getting tired
of writing, so I'm
going to stop there.
OK, so let's take the function,
the 0's derivative
of f is just the function
itself, so
let's come back here.
What is the function if
I evaluate it at x
equals 0, 0, 0, 1.
I get 1.
All right.
What is the first derivative?
So I'm going to write out the
first derivative and then I'm
going to say I'm evaluating
it at x equals 0.
So the first derivative looks
like it's 9x squared
plus 8x minus 2.
So I'm gonna write this down.
9x squared plus 8x minus 2.
Evaluate it at x
equals 0, 0, 0.
I get negative 2.
All right, well, let me take
the second derivative.
OK let's see what I get here.
I get 18x plus 8.
And I'm going to evaluate
that at x equals 0.
This is just a way to write, I'm
going to evaluate what's
here at x equal this
number, so if you
haven't seen that before.
So I get 8.
OK and then the third derivative
is 18, oh just 18.
Evaluate it at x equals 0.
I get 18.
And then the fourth
derivative.
What's the derivative of
a constant function?
It's 0.
What do you think the fifth
derivative is evaluated at 0?
Looks like it'll be 0.
You take the sixth derivative.
Looks like everything bigger
than 3, so the nth derivative
at 0 is equal to 0 for
n bigger than 3.
So it looks like we should only
have 4 terms in this.
So that maybe seems a little
weird, but let's keep going
and see what happens.
Let's start plugging
things in.
So again let's remember
the formula.
I'm going to walk over here to
the right and I'm going to
start using that formula and
using these numbers that I
have and writing it out.
So the first term is going to be
the function evaluated at 0
divided by 0 factorial
times 1.
0 factorial is 1, so it's just
going to be the function
evaluated at 0 times 1.
The function evaluated at 0, we
said was 1, so that's the
first term in the
Taylor series.
OK what's the next term?
The next term remember is the
first derivative evaluated at
0 divided by 1 factorial, which
is still 1, times x.
So the first derivative, if I
come back over here, evaluated
at 0, I get negative 2.
So I'm going to get minus 2x.
The next term, so I had zeroth
derivative, first derivative,
now I'm at the second
derivative.
Now it's getting confusing.
I'm going to start writing
the things above.
The second derivative evaluated
at 0 divided by 2
factorial times x squared.
That's what I should
have here.
Let's come over here.
Second derivative evaluated
at 0 was 8.
So it's going to be
8 over 2, 'cause 2
factorial is 2x squared.
So it's going to be
plus 4x squared.
And then I have to have the
third derivative evaluated at
0 divided by 3 factorial
times x cubed.
What's 3 factorial?
3 factorial is 6.
What was the third derivative
evaluated at 0?
It was 18.
18 divided by 6 is 3.
So I get plus 3x cubed.
And all the other terms
were 0, so I'll just
stop writing them.
OK now if you watched the video
all the way through
here, at some point maybe you
said "Christine this is
madness." Well why
is it madness?
Because what is this?
Well this is the function
again, right?
It's exactly what
we started with.
The order is opposite of what
it was before 'cause now the
powers go up instead of down,
but it's the same polynomial.
OK we talked about this briefly
I think when we were
doing some quadratic
approximations.
And I mentioned way back that
quadratic approximations of
polynomials at x equals 0 are
just the polynomials again.
This is the exact same kind
of thing happening.
Because what is the
Taylor series?
It's just better and better
approximations as n gets
larger and larger.
So if I wanted to have a fourth
order approximation of
this function f of x at x equals
0, I would get the same
function back.
That's really the idea of
what's happening here.
So maybe you saw the sort of
trick in this question, and
when you saw this problem you
laughed at me and you said,
"Well I'm just going to write
down the function again and
I'll be done." Maybe you didn't
see that right away,
and if you didn't see that
right away that's OK.
I bet you're in good company.
And it's totally fine because
now you've seen this.
You've seen how it works out.
And you know, hey, now any time
I see a polynomial and I
want to do the Taylor series
for this polynomial, I just
have to write down the
polynomial again.
So that was the main
goal of this video.
It took us a long time to get
there, but I think we got it.
So the answer to the ultimate
answer to the question of
write the Taylor series of this
function, it's just this
function again.
All right, that's
where I'll stop.