Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In class, Professor Jerison
and Professor Miller have
taught you a little bit about
Taylor series and some of the
manipulations you can do with
them, and have computed a
bunch of examples for you.
So I have three more examples.
Here of functions whose Taylor
series are nice to compute.
So the first one is cosh x.
That's the hyperbolic cosine.
So just to remind you, this can
be written in terms of the
exponential function as e
to the x plus e to the
minus x over 2.
The second one is the function 2
times sine of x times cosine
of x, just your regular
sine and cosine here.
And the third one is x times the
logarithm of the quantity
1 minus x cubed.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to work
out the Taylor series for these
three functions, come
back, and we can work
them out together.
So here we have three functions
whose Taylor series
we're trying to compute.
Let's start with the first
one and go from there.
So this first one is the
hyperbolic cosine that's given
by the formula e to the x plus
e to the minus x over 2.
So there are a couple different
ways you could go
about this one.
This is actually, the hyperbolic
cosine is very
susceptible to the method of
just using the formula that
you have. So if you remember,
the derivative of the
hyperbolic cosine is the
hyperbolic sine.
The derivative of the hyperbolic
sine is the
hyperbolic cosine again.
So this function has very
easy-to-understand
derivatives, which you can see,
you know, just by looking
at its formula.
It's easy to understand,
because the exponential
function has very simple
derivatives, and e to the the
minus x also has very
simple derivatives.
So you could do it like that.
The other thing you could do,
is that you already know the
Taylor series for e to the x.
And I believe you've also seen
the Taylor series for e to the
minus x, and even if you
haven't, you can figure it out
just by substitution.
So if you remember, so e to the
x is given by the sum from
n equals 0 to infinity of x
to the n over n factorial.
I'm going to pull the
1/2 out in front.
And e to the minus x is given by
the same thing, if you put
in minus x for x.
So it's n equals 0 to infinity,
so that works out to
minus 1 to the n x to the
n or n factorial.
Now, when you add these two
series together, what you see
is that when n is even, over
here, you have x to the n over
n factorial, and over
here, you have x to
the n over n factorial.
So what you get is, well, you
get 2 x to the n over n
factorial, and then you multiply
by a half, so you
just get x to the n
over n factorial.
When n is odd, here you have x
to the n over n factorial, and
here you have minus 1 x to
the n over n factorial.
So you add them and you get 0.
So what happens is that this
series looks just like the
series for e to the x, except
the odd terms have died off.
So we're left with just 1 plus
x squared over 2 factorial
plus x to the fourth over 4
factorial plus x to the sixth
over 6 factorial, and so on.
And if you wanted to write this
in summation notation,
you could write it as the sum
from n equals 0 to infinity of
x to the 2n over 2n factorial.
So this is the Taylor
series for the
hyperbolic cosine function.
Also, if you wanted, say, the
hyperbolic sine function, you
could do something very similar,
or you could remember
that the hyperbolic sine is
the derivative of the
hyperbolic cosine, and just take
a derivative right from
this expression.
One other thing that you should
notice is that this
looks very similar to the
expression of the Taylor
series for cosine of x.
So more of our sort of funny
coincidences between regular
trig functions and hyperbolic
trig functions.
All right.
That's the first one.
How about the second one?
So here we have just some
regular trig functions.
We have 2 sine x cosine x.
Let me see where I've
got some space.
I can do it right here.
Let me box off a little
space for myself.
So 2 sine x cosine x-- there
are a couple different ways
you could proceed with
this function.
So one is, you know the Taylor
series for sine x
and cosine x already.
So if all you wanted was a few
terms of this Taylor series,
one natural thing to do would be
to take the series for sine
x, take the series for cosine x,
multiply them together like
you would multiply polynomials,
and what you
would get is the Taylor
series for this
expression, for this function.
That's one way to proceed.
That works perfectly well.
Another thing you could do,
is you could try taking
derivatives.
You could have a situation where
every time you take a
derivative, you apply
product rule.
It's going to get more
and more complicated.
It still works.
It's a little complicated to do
it that way, if you wanted
more than just a few terms.
The other thing you could do,
is you could remember your
trig identities.
So if you look at this
expression, this should be
familiar to you, because
it's just sine of 2x.
So once you realize that this is
sine of 2x, there's a much,
much shorter path available to
you, which is that you already
know the Taylor series for sine
of x, so what you can do,
is you can just plug in 2x
into that Taylor series.
So sine of x is, well so OK,
x, so in this case, that's
going to be 2x, then minus, so
in sine of x, we have x cubed
over 3 factorial.
So here we're going to have 2x
cubed over 3 factorial plus--
OK.
So then, you know, and so on.
So here we'll have 2x to the
fifth over 5 factorial minus--
so on.
If you wanted to write this in
summation notation, you could
write it as the sum from
n equals 0 to infinity.
Well, the denominator has got
to be 2n plus 1 factorial,
because we want it to
go through the odds.
And then we've got minus 1 to
the n times 2 to the 2n plus 1
times x to the 2n plus 1.
So this is 2x.
What we've got here, if you
didn't have the 2's there,
that would just be the series
for the regular sine.
OK.
So this is the series for this
function, 2 sine x cosine x.
And I'll go over here
to do the third one.
So what is the third one?
It's x ln 1 minus x cubed.
Well, what can we do
with this series?
The x out front is
just multiplying
this logarithm part.
That's something we can
save until the end.
If we can figure out what the
Taylor series for the ln of 1
minus x cubed part is, then we
just multiply x into it, and
that'll give us the Taylor
series for this whole thing.
So the x out front
is pretty simple.
So now what about this ln of
1 minus x cubed stuff?
Well, a thing to remember is,
does it remind you of anything
we've done before?
Well, we have a Taylor
series for a
logarithm function, right?
We've already seen in lecture,
I believe, we've seen that ln
of 1 plus x is equal to x minus
x squared over 2 plus x
cubed over 3, minus x to the
fourth over four, and so on,
alternating signs.
Notice that the denominators,
when you have a logarithm,
these are not factorials.
These are just the integer 2,
the integer 3, the integer 4,
unlike for exponentials
and trig functions.
So this what log of 1 plus x,
this is the Taylor series for
log of 1 plus x.
Well, how does that help us?
Well, log of 1 minus x cubed we
can get from log of 1 plus
x, with the appropriate
substitution.
So in particular, we just
have to put minus x
cubed in for x here.
So what does that give us?
It gives us the ln of 1 minus
x cubed is equal to-- well,
minus x cubed minus, so we put
minus x cubed in here, we
square it, and we just
get x to the sixth.
x to the sixth over 2.
Then, all right.
So minus x cubed quantity cubed
is minus x to the ninth.
So minus x to the ninth over 3,
minus x to the twelfth over
4, and so on.
And so finally, x ln of 1 minus
x cubed, we just get by
multiplying this whole
expression through by x.
So this is equal to minus x to
the fourth minus x to the
seventh over 2 minus x-- whoops,
not ten,-- minus x to
the tenth over 3, minus x to
the 13 over 4, and so on.
And I'll leave it as an exercise
for you to figure
out, how to write this
in summation
notation, if you wanted.
So just quickly to summarize,
we had these three power
series, these three functions
that we started out with, and
we used a bunch of different
techniques that we've learned
in order to compute their
power series.
So over here, we took the
function that we'd seen, and
we knew a formula for it in
terms of other functions that
we already knew, and so we
plugged in those power series,
and used our addition rule
for power series.
We could have also done this
one directly from the
definition, if we
had wanted to.
For the second one, for the 2
sine x cosine x, we recognized
that as something that is
susceptible to a substitution,
although also, with a little
more, work, we could have done
it by a couple of different
methods.
For example, by multiplying
two power series together.
And finally, for this third one,
for the x ln of 1 minus x
cubed, we first saw the
substitution here that we
could make, and then we just
did a multiplication by a
polynomial, which is a
relatively easy thing to do
for power series.
So that's what we did in
this recitation, and
I'll leave it at that.