PROFESSOR: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, I'd like to tackle
a problem in undetermined
coefficients, specifically find
a particular solution to
each of the following equations
using undetermined
coefficients.
So for part A, we have x
dot plus 3x equals t
squared plus t.
And for B, we have x
dot, dot plus x dot
equals t to the four.
So I'll let you work
this problem.
And I'll come back
in a minute.
Hi Everyone.
Welcome back.
So we're asked to solve this
problem using the method of
undetermined coefficients.
And specifically, the
observation is if we have a
differential equation with
constant coefficients, and we
have a forcing on the right-hand
side which is a
polynomial, then there's
always going to be a
particular solution, which is
a polynomial, that has the
form of some constant times
t to the power of r plus
constant tr minus 1 plus a
constant C or minus 2tr minus
2 plus dot, dot, dot plus C1t
and then possibly plus C0.
And typically, the problem is to
find out what's the highest
order polynomial that
we should guess.
These constant C's, they're
referred to as the
undetermined coefficients.
And these are the constants
that we seek to solve.
So for our first differential
equation, we have x dot plus
3x equals t squared plus t.
And the power that we should
guess for a solution are, it's
always going to be at least as
high as the highest power on
the right-hand side.
So the right-hand side tells us
at least the largest that
we should at least start
our guess at.
And then, sometimes, we have
to knock it up a few orders
depending on what the lowest
order derivative on the
left-hand side is.
So in this case, the term on the
left-hand side, there's no
derivative term.
And so what we can do for this
case is we can just take r is
equal to 2, the power
of the polynomial on
the right-hand side.
So we're going to seek a guess
or an ansatz, which is some
constant A times t squared
plus B times t plus some
constant C. And again, I've
taken the highest polynomial
that we should guess to be 2,
because the right-hand side is
2 in this case.
So now what we do is we just
substitute this in into the
differential equation.
And we choose our
A, B, and C to
construct this as a solution.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So taking its derivative, we
have 2At plus B. And then, we
have 3 times At squared plus Bt
plus C. And we want this to
be equal to t squared plus t.
And now, the only way that the
left-hand side is going to
equal the right-hand side is if
the coefficients in front
of each polynomial
are the same.
So in the left-hand side, we
only have one term that has a
t squared in it.
And that must, therefore, equal
the t squared term on
the right-hand side.
So these two terms have to
be equal to each other.
So we end up getting that
3A has to be equal 1.
And so A is equal
to one third.
And now what we do is
we collect terms
with a power of t.
This gives us 3B plus 2A on the
left-hand side, so that's
this term and this term.
And we want that t equal t on
the right-hand side or just 1.
Now, we already know that
A is equal to one third.
So we end up getting that 3B is
equal to 1 minus 2/3, which
is equal to one third.
Put 3B as one third, which
means that B is
equal to one ninth.
And now lastly, to determine
C, we see that B
plus 3C must be 0.
So B plus 3C is 0, or C is
equal to negative 1/27.
So notice how we always start
with the highest power.
In this case, A is
the coefficient
in front of t squared.
That lets us solve for A.
And then the rest of the
undetermined coefficients, we
can solve for, almost like a
giant zipper.
So the particular solution that
we just constructed, when
the dust settles is one third
t squared plus one ninth t
minus 1/27.
So this concludes part A.
For part b, we have the
differential equation, x dot
dot plus x dot equals
t to the four.
And in this case, we know
that the right-hand side
is a power of four.
So we should guess at least
a fourth order polynomial.
However, we see that there's
no constant multiple of x.
In fact, the lowest order
derivative is 1.
So what this means is we should
actually knock the
solution that we guess up
one order polynomial.
So we should try and guess x
is equal to At to the fifth
plus B t to the four plus Ct
cubed plus Dt squared plus Et.
And we can leave
out an F term.
We can leave out a constant.
Because if we just substitute
that in the left-hand side, we
see that the x dot, dot is going
to vanish, and x dot is
going to vanish.
So we can omit any
constant term.
So let's seek this ansatz,
and plug it into the
differential equation.
And if we do that, we
get 20At cubed.
And this is plugging into
the x dot dot term.
This term is going to give us 12
Bt squared plus 6Ct plus D.
And then the x dot term is going
to give us 5At to the
four plus 4 Bt cubed plus 3Ct
squared plus 2Dt plus E.
And we want the sum of
these two terms to
equal t to the four.
So again, what we do is we start
with the highest power.
We see that on the left-hand
side, we have 5A must be
equated with just 1.
So we have 5A is equal to 1,
or A is equal to one fifth.
Secondly, we're going to have
20A plus 4B equals the 0
polynomial, or the 0 which is
the coefficient of t cubed.
And this gives us B is equal
to negative 5A, which is
negative 1.
And now for the quadratic
terms, we have
12B plus 3C is 0.
So C is going to equal negative
4B, which is negative
4 times negative 1, which
just gives us 4.
The linear term is going to give
us 6C plus 2D equals 0,
which gives us D is equal to
negative 3C, which gives us
negative 12.
And then the last term is D plus
E is 0, which gives us E
is equal to 12.
So at the end of the day, we
end up with a particular
solution, which is a polynomial
of one fifth t to
the five minus 2 to the four
plus C, which is 4t cubed plus
D, which is negative
12t squared plus E,
which is 12 times t.
And by construction, this
polynomial solves the
differential equation with a
forcing of t to the four on
the right-hand side.
So just to recap, when we're
faced with an undetermined
coefficient problem, what we
have to do is we just guess a
solution, which is
a polynomial.
And the main difficulty is
just guessing the highest
power of the polynomial.
And that's always going to
be at least as big as the
polynomial on the
right-hand side.
But as we saw in part B, we
sometimes have to knock it up
a few orders depending on what
the differential equation
actually is.
So I'd like to conclude here.
And I'll see you next time.