A x equal lambda x.
x is the eigenvector and
lambda's the eigenvalue.
Now to use that.
And the, the good way to,
after we've found -- so,
so job one is to find the
eigenvalues and find the
eigenvectors.
Now after we've found them,
what do we do with them?
Well, the good way to see that
is diagonalize the matrix.
So the matrix is A.
And I want to show -- first of
all, this is like
the basic fact.
This, this formula.
That's, that's the key to
today's lecture.
This matrix A,
I put its eigenvectors in the
columns of a matrix S.
So S will be the eigenvector
matrix.
And I want to look at this
magic combination S inverse A S.
So can I show you how that --
what happens there?
And notice, there's an S
inverse.
We have to be able to invert
this eigenvector matrix S.
So for that,
we need n independent
eigenvectors.
So that's the,
that's the case.
OK.
So suppose we have n linearly
independent eigenvectors
of A.
Put them in the columns of this
matrix S.
So I'm naturally going to call
that the eigenvector matrix,
because it's got the
eigenvectors in its columns.
And all I want to do is show
you what happens when you
multiply A times S.
So A times S.
So this is A times the matrix
with
the first eigenvector in its
first column,
the second eigenvector in its
second column,
the n-th eigenvector in its
n-th column.
And how I going to do this
matrix multiplication?
Well, certainly I'll do it a
column at a time.
And what do I get.
A times the first column gives
me the first column of the
answer, but what is it?
That's an eigenvector.
A times x1 is equal to the
lambda times the x1.
And that lambda's we're --
we'll call lambda one,
of course.
So that's the first column.
Ax1 is the same as lambda one
x1.
A x2 is lambda two x2.
So on, along to in the n-th
column we now how lambda n xn.
Looking good,
but the next step is even
better.
So for the next step,
I want to separate out those
eigenvalues, those,
those multiplying numbers,
from the x-s.
So then I'll have just what I
want.
OK.
So how, how I going to separate
out?
So that, that number lambda one
is multiplying the first column.
So if I want to factor it out
of the first column,
I better put -- here is going
to be x1, and that's going to
multiply this
matrix lambda one in the first
entry and all zeros.
Do you see that that,
that's going to come out right
for the first column?
Because w- we remember how --
how we're going back to that
original punchline.
That if I want a number to
multiply x1 then I can do it by
putting x1 in that
column, in the first column,
and putting that number there.
Th- u- what I going to have
here?
I'm going to have lambda -- I'm
going to have x1,
x2, ...
,xn.
These are going to be my
columns again.
I'm getting S back again.
But now what's it multiplied
by,
on the right it's multiplied
by?
If I want lambda n xn in the
last column, how do I do it?
Well, the last column here will
be -- I'll take the last column,
use these coefficients,
put the lambda n down there,
and it will multiply that n-th
column and give me lambda n xn.
There, there you see matrix
multiplication just working for
us.
So I started with A S.
I wrote down what it meant,
A times each eigenvector.
That gave me lambda time the
eigenvector.
And then when I peeled off the
lambdas, they were on the
right-hand side,
so I've got S,
my matrix, back again.
And this matrix,
this diagonal matrix,
the eigenvalue matrix,
and I call it capital lambda.
Using capital letters for
matrices and lambda to prompt me
that it's, that it's eigenvalues
that are in there.
So you see that the eigenvalues
are just sitting down that
diagonal?
If I had a column x2 here,
I
would want the lambda two in
the two two position,
in the diagonal position,
to multiply that x2 and give me
the lambda two x2.
That's my formula.
A S is S lambda.
OK.
That's the -- you see,
it's just a calculation.
Now -- I mentioned,
and I
have to mention again,
this business about n
independent eigenvectors.
As it stands,
this is all fine,
whether -- I mean,
I could be repeating the same
eigenvector, but -- I'm not
interested in that.
I want to be able to invert S,
and that's where this comes in.
This n independent eigenvectors
business comes in to tell me
that that matrix is invertible.
So let me, on the next board,
write down what I've got.
A S equals S lambda.
And now I'm,
I can multiply on the left by S
inverse.
So this is really --
I can do that,
provided S is invertible.
Provided my assumption of n
independent eigenvectors is
satisfied.
And I mentioned at the end of
last time, and I'll say again,
that there's a small number of
matrices for -- that don't have
n independent
eigenvectors.
So I've got to discuss that,
that technical point.
But the great -- the most
matrices that we see have n di-
n independent eigenvectors,
and we can diagonalize.
This is diagonalization.
I could also write it,
and I often will,
the other way round.
If I multiply on the right by S
inverse, if I took this equation
at the top and multiplied on the
right by S inverse,
I could -- I would have A left
here.
Now S inverse is coming from
the right.
So can you keep those two
straight?
A multiplies its eigenvectors,
that's how I keep them
straight.
So A multiplies S.
A multiplies S.
And then this S inverse makes
the whole thing diagonal.
And this is another way of
saying the same thing,
putting the Ss on the other
side of the equation.
A is S lambda S inverse.
So that's the,
that's the new
factorization.
That's the replacement for L U
from elimination or Q R for --
from Gram-Schmidt.
And notice that the matrix --
so it's, it's a matrix times a
diagonal matrix times the
inverse of the first one.
It's, that's the combination
that we'll see throughout this
chapter.
This combination with an S and
an S inverse.
OK.
Can I just begin to use that?
For example,
what about A squared?
What are the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors of A squared?
That's a straightforward
question with a,
with an absolutely clean
answer.
So let me,
let me consider A squared.
So I start with A x equal
lambda x.
And I'm headed for A squared.
So let me multiply both sides
by A.
That's one way to get A squared
on the left.
So -- I should write these if-s
in here.
If A x equals lambda x,
then I multiply by A,
so I get A
squared x equals -- well,
I'm multiplying by A,
so that's lambda A x.
That lambda was a number,
so I just put it on the left.
And what do I -- tell me how to
make that look better.
What have I got here for if,
if A has the eigenvalue lambda
and eigenvector x,
what's
up with A squared?
A squared x,
I just multiplied by A,
but now for Ax I'm going to
substitute lambda x.
So I've got lambda squared x.
So from that simple
calculation, I -- my conclusion
is that the eigenvalues of A
squared are lambda squared.
And the eigenvectors -- I
always think about both of
those.
What can I say about the
eigenvalues?
They're squared.
What can I say about the
eigenvectors?
They're the same.
The same x as in -- as for A.
Now let me see that also
from this formula.
How can I see what A squared is
looking like from this formula?
So let me -- that was one way
to do it.
Let me do it by just taking A
squared from that.
A squared is S lambda S inverse
-- that's A -- times S lambda S
inverse -- that's A,
which is?
This is the beauty of
eigenvalues, eigenvectors.
Having that S inverse and S is
the identity,
so I've got S lambda squared S
inverse.
Do you see what that's telling
me?
It's, it's telling me the same
thing that I just learned here,
but in the -- in a matrix form.
It's telling me that the S is
the same, the eigenvectors are
the same, but the eigenvalues
are squared.
Because this is -- what's
lambda squared?
That's still diagonal.
It's got little lambda one
squared, lambda two squared,
down to lambda n squared o- on
that diagonal.
Those are the eigenvalues,
as we just learned,
of A
squared.
OK.
So -- somehow those eigenvalues
and eigenvectors are really
giving you a way to -- see
what's going on inside a matrix.
Of course I can continue that
for -- to the K-th power,
A to the K-th power.
If I multiply,
if I have K of these together,
do you see how S inverse S will
keep canceling in the,
in the inside?
I'll have the S outside at the
far left, and lambda will be in
there K times,
and S inverse.
So what's that telling me?
That's telling me that the
eigenvalues of A,
of A to the K-th power are the
K-th powers.
The eigenvalues of A cubed are
the cubes of the eigenvalues of
A.
And the eigenvectors are the
same, the same.
OK.
In other words,
eigenvalues and eigenvectors
give a great way to understand
the powers of a matrix.
If I take the square of a
matrix,
or the hundredth power of a
matrix, the pivots are all over
the place.
L U, if I multiply L U times L
U times L U times L U a hundred
times, I've got a hundred L Us.
I can't do anything with them.
But when I multiply S lambda S
inverse by itself,
when I look at the eigenvector
picture a hundred times,
I get a hundred or ninety-nine
of these guys canceling out
inside, and I get A to the
hundredth is S lambda to the
hundredth S inverse.
I mean, eigenvalues tell you
about powers of a matrix in a
way that we had no way to
approach previously.
For example,
when does -- when do the powers
of a matrix go to zero?
I would call that matrix
stable, maybe.
So I could write down a
theorem.
I'll write it as a theorem just
to use that word to emphasize
that here I'm
getting this great fact from
this eigenvalue picture.
OK.
A to the K approaches zero as K
goes, as K gets bigger if what?
What's the w- how can I tell,
for a matrix A,
if its powers go to zero?
What's -- somewhere inside that
matrix is that information.
That information is not present
in
the pivots.
It's present in the
eigenvalues.
What do I need for the -- to
know that if I take higher and
higher powers of A,
that this matrix gets smaller
and smaller?
Well, S and S inverse are not
moving.
So it's this guy that has to
get small.
And that's easy to --
to understand.
The requirement is all
eigenvalues -- so what is the
requirement?
The eigenvalues have to be less
than one.
Now I have to wrote that
absolute value,
because those eigenvalues could
be negative, they could be
complex numbers.
So I'm taking the absolute
value.
If all
of those are below one.
That's, in fact,
we practically see why.
And let me just say that I'm
operating on one assumption
here, and I got to keep
remembering that that assumption
is still present.
That assumption was that I had
a
full set of,
of n independent eigenvectors.
If I don't have that,
then this approach is not
working.
So again, a pure eigenvalue
approach, eigenvector approach,
needs n independent
eigenvectors.
If we don't have n independent
eigenvectors,
we can't diagonalize the
matrix.
We can't get to a diagonal
This diagonalization is only
possible if S inverse makes
sense.
OK.
Can I, can I follow up on that
point now?
So you see why -- what we get
and, and why we want it,
because we get information
about the
powers of a matrix just
immediately from the
eigenvalues.
OK.
Now let me follow up on this,
business of which matrices are
diagonalizable.
Sorry about that long word.
So a matrix is,
is sure -- so here's,
here's the main point.
A is sure to be -- to have N
independent eigenvectors
and, and be -- now here comes
that word -- diagonalizable if,
if -- so we might as well get
the nice case out in the open.
The nice case is when -- if all
the lambdas are different.
That means, that means no
repeated eigenvalues.
OK.
That's the nice case.
If my matrix,
and most -- if I do a random
matrix in Matlab and compute its
eigenvalues -- so if I computed
if I took eig of rand of ten
ten, gave, gave that Matlab
command, the -- we'd get a
random ten by ten matrix,
we would get a list of its ten
eigenvalues, and they would be
different.
They would be distinct is the
best word.
I would have -- a random matrix
will have ten distinct -- a ten
by ten matrix will have ten
distinct eigenvalues.
And if it does,
the eigenvectors
are automatically independent.
So that's a nice fact.
I'll refer you to the text for
the proof.
That, that A is sure to have n
independent eigenvectors if the
eigenvalues are different,
if.
If all the, if all eigenvalues
are different.
It's just if some lambdas are
repeated, then I have to look
more
closely.
If an eigenvalue is repeated,
I have to look,
I have to count,
I have to check.
Has it got -- say it's repeated
three times.
So what's a possibility for the
-- so here is the,
here is the repeated
possibility.
And, and let me emphasize the
conclusion.
That if I have repeated
eigenvalues, I may or may not,
I may or may not have,
have n independent
eigenvectors.
I might.
I, I, you know,
this isn't a completely
negative case.
The identity matrix -- suppose
I take the ten by ten identity
matrix.
What are the eigenvalues of
that
matrix?
So just, just take the easiest
matrix, the identity.
If I look for its eigenvalues,
they're all ones.
So that eigenvalue one is
repeated ten times.
But there's no shortage of
eigenvectors for the identity
matrix.
In fact, every vector is an
eigenvector.
So I can take ten independent
vectors.
Oh, well, what happens to
everything -- if A is the
identity matrix,
let's just think that one
through in our head.
If A is the identity matrix,
then it's got plenty of
eigenvectors.
I choose ten independent
vectors.
They're the columns of S.
And, and what do I get from S
inverse A S?
I get I again,
right?
If A is the identity -- and of
course that's the correct
lambda.
The matrix was already
diagonal.
So if the matrix is already
diagonal, then the,
the lambda is the same as the
matrix.
A diagonal matrix has got its
eigenvalues sitting right there
in front of you.
Now if it's triangular,
the eigenvalues are still
sitting there,
but so let's take a case where
it's triangular.
Suppose A is like,
two one two zero.
So there's a case that's going
to be trouble.
There's a case that's going to
be trouble.
First of all,
what are the -- I mean,
we just -- if we start with a
matrix, the first thing we do,
practically without thinking is
compute the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors.
OK.
So what are the eigenvalues?
You can tell me right away what
they are.
They're two and two,
right.
It's a triangular matrix,
so when I do this determinant,
shall I do this determinant of
A minus lambda I?
I'll get this two minus lambda
one zero two minus lambda,
right?
I take that determinant,
so I make those into vertical
bars to mean determinant.
And what's the determinant?
It's two minus lambda squared.
What are the roots?
Lambda equal two twice.
So the eigenvalues are lambda
equals two and two.
OK, fine.
Now the next step,
find the eigenvectors.
So I look for eigenvectors,
and what do I find for this
guy?
Eigenvectors for this guy,
when I subtract two minus the
identity, so A minus two I has
zeros here.
And I'm looking for the null
space.
What's, what are the
eigenvectors?
They're the --
the null space of A minus
lambda I.
The null space is only one
dimensional.
This is a case where I don't
have enough eigenvectors.
My algebraic multiplicity is
two.
I would say,
when I see, when I count how
often the eigenvalue is
repeated, that's
the algebraic multiplicity.
That's the multiplicity,
how many times is it the root
of the polynomial?
My polynomial is two minus
lambda squared.
It's a double root.
So my algebraic multiplicity is
two.
But the geometric multiplicity,
which looks for vectors,
looks for eigenvectors,
and -- which means the null
space of this thing,
and the only eigenvector is one
zero.
That's in the null space.
Zero one is not in the null
space.
The null space is only one
dimensional.
So there's a matrix,
my -- this A or the original A,
that are not diagonalizable.
I can't find two independent
eigenvectors.
There's only one.
OK.
So that's the case that I'm --
that's a case that I'm not
really handling.
For example,
when I wrote down up here that
the powers went to zero if the
eigenvalues were below one,
I didn't really handle that
case of repeated eigenvalues,
because my reasoning was based
on this formula.
And this formula is based on n
independent eigenvectors.
OK.
Just to say then,
there are some matrices that
we're, that, that we don't cover
through diagonalization,
but the great majority we do.
OK.
And we, we're always OK if we
have different distinct
eigenvalues.
OK, that's the,
like, the typical case.
Because for each eigenvalue
there's at least one
eigenvector.
The algebraic multiplicity here
is one for every eigenvalue and
the geometric multiplicity is
one.
There's one eigenvector.
And they are independent.
OK.
Now let me come back to the
important case,
when, when we're OK.
The important case,
when we are diagonalizable.
Let me, look at -- so -- let me
solve
this equation.
The equation will be each -- I
start with some -- start with a
given vector u0.
And then my equation is at
every step, I multiply what I
have by A.
That, that equation ought to be
simple to handle.
And I'd like to be able to
solve it.
How would I find -- if I start
with a vector u0 and I multiply
by A a hundred times,
what have I got?
Well, I could certainly write
down a formula for the answer,
so what, what -- so u1 is A u0.
And u2 is -- what's u2 then?
u2, I multiply -- u2 I get
from u1 by another multiplying
by A, so I've got A twice.
And my formula is uk,
after k steps,
I've multiplied by A k times
the original u0.
You see what I'm doing?
The next section is going to
solve systems of differential
equations.
I'm going to have derivatives.
This section is the nice one.
It solves difference equations.
I would call that a difference
equation.
It's -- at first order,
I would call that a first-order
system, because it connects only
-- it only goes up one level.
And I -- it's a system because
these are vectors and that's a
matrix.
And the solution is just
that.
OK.
But, that's a nice formula.
That's the, like,
the most compact formula I
could ever get.
u100 would be A to the one
hundred u0.
But how would I actually find
u100?
How would I find -- how would I
discover what u100 is?
Let me,
let me show you how.
Here's the idea.
If -- so to solve,
to really solve -- shall I say,
to really solve -- to really
solve it, I would take this
initial vector u0 and I would
write it as a combination of
eigenvectors.
To really solve,
write u
nought as a combination,
say certain amount of the first
eigenvector plus a certain
amount of the second eigenvector
plus a certain amount of the
last eigenvector.
Now multiply by A.
You want to -- you got to see
the magic of eigenvectors
working here.
Multiply by A.
So Au0 is
what?
So A times that.
A times -- so what's A -- I can
separate it out into n separate
pieces, and that's the whole
point.
That each of those pieces is
going in its own merry way.
Each of those pieces is an
eigenvector, and when I multiply
by A,
what does this piece become?
So that's some amount of the
first -- let's suppose the
eigenvectors are normalized to
be unit vectors.
So that says what the
eigenvector is.
It's a -- And I need some
multiple of it to produce u0.
OK.
Now when I multiply by A,
what do I get?
I get c1, which is just a
factor, times Ax1,
but Ax1 is lambda one x1.
When I multiply this by A,
I get c2 lambda two x2.
And here I get cn lambda n xn.
And suppose I multiply by A to
the hundredth power now.
Can we, having done it,
multiplied by A,
let's multiply by A to the
hundredth.
What happens to this first term
when I multiply by A to the one
hundredth?
It's got that factor lambda to
the hundredth.
That's the key.
That -- that's what I mean by
going its own merry way.
It, it is pure eigenvector.
It's exactly in a direction
where multiplication by A just
brings in a scalar factor,
lambda one.
So a hundred times brings in
this a hundred times.
Hundred times lambda two,
hundred times lambda n.
Actually, we're -- what are we
seeing here?
We're seeing,
this same, lambda capital
lambda to the hundredth as in
the, as in the diagonalization.
And we're seeing the S matrix,
the, the matrix S of
eigenvectors.
That's what this has got to --
this has got to amount to.
A lambda to the hundredth
power times an S times this
vector c that's telling us how
much of each one is in the
original thing.
So if, if I had to really find
the hundredth power,
I would take u0,
I would expand it as a
combination of eigenvectors --
this is really S,
the eigenvector matrix,
times c, the,
the coefficient vector.
And then I would immediately
then, by inserting these
hundredth powers of eigenvalues,
I'd have the answer.
So -- huh, there must be -- oh,
let's see, OK.
It's -- so, yeah.
So if u100 is A to the
hundredth times u0,
and u0 is S c -- then you see
this formula is just this
formula, which is the way I
would actually get hold of this,
of this u100,
which is -- let me put it here.
u100.
The way
I would actually get hold of
that, see what,
what the solution is after a
hundred steps,
would be -- expand the initial
vector into eigenvectors and let
each eigenvector go its own way,
multiplying by a hundred at --
by lambda at every step,
and therefore by lambda to the
hundredth
power after a hundred steps.
Can I do an example?
So that's the formulas.
Now let me take an example.
I'll use the Fibonacci sequence
as an example.
So, so Fibonacci example.
You remember the Fibonacci
numbers?
If we start with one and one as
F0 -- oh, I think I start with
zero, maybe.
Let zero and one be the first
ones.
So there's F0 and F1,
the first two Fibonacci
numbers.
Then what's the rule for
Fibonacci numbers?
Ah, they're the sum.
The next one is the sum of
those,
so it's one.
The next one is the sum of
those, so it's two.
those, so it's three.
Well, it looks like one two
three four five,
but somehow it's not going to
do that way.
The next one is five,
right.
Two and three makes five.
The next one is eight.
The next one is thirteen.
And the one hundredth Fibonacci
number is what?
That's my question.
How could I get a formula for
the hundredth number?
And, for example,
how could I answer the
question, how fast are they
growing?
How fast are those Fibonacci
numbers
growing?
They're certainly growing.
It's not a stable case.
Whatever the eigenvalues of
whatever matrix it is,
they're not smaller than one.
These numbers are growing.
But how fast are they growing?
The answer lies in the
eigenvalue.
So I've got to find the matrix,
so let me write down the
Fibonacci rule.
F(k+2) = F(k+1)+F k,
right?
Now that's not in my -- I want
to write that as uk plus one and
Auk.
But right now what I've got is
a single equation,
not a system,
and it's second-order.
It's like having a second-order
differential equation with
second derivatives.
I want to get first
derivatives.
Here I want to get first
differences.
So the way, the way to do it is
to introduce uk will be a vector
-- see, a small trick.
Let uk be a vector,
F(k+1)
and Fk.
So I'm going to get a two by
two system, first order,
instead of a one -- instead of
a scalar system,
second order,
by a simple trick.
I'm just going to add in an
equation F(k+1) equals F(k+1).
That will be my second
equation.
Then this is my system,
this is my unknown,
and what's my one step
equation?
So, so now u(k+1),
that's -- so u(k+1) is the left
side, and what have I got here
on the right side?
I've got some matrix
multiplying uk.
Can you, do -- can you see that
all right?
if you can see it,
then you can tell me what the
matrix is.
Do you see that I'm taking my
system here.
I artificially made it into a
system.
I artificially made the unknown
into a vector.
And now I'm ready to look at
and see what the matrix
is.
So do you see the left side,
u(k+1) is F(k+2) F(k+1),
that's just what I want.
On the right side,
this remember,
this uk here -- let me for the
moment put it as F(k+1) Fk.
So what's the matrix?
Well, that has a one and a one,
and that has a one and a zero.
There's the matrix.
Do you see that that gives me
the right-hand side?
So there's the matrix A.
And this is our friend uk.
So we've got -- so that simple
trick -- changed the
second-order scalar problem to a
first-order system.
Two b- u- with two unknowns.
With
a matrix.
And now what do I do?
Well, before I even think,
I find its eigenvalues and
eigenvectors.
So what are the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors of that matrix?
Let's see.
I always -- first let me just,
like, think for a minute.
It's two by two,
so this shouldn't be impossible
to do.
Let's do it.
OK.
So my matrix,
again, is one one one zero.
It's symmetric,
by the way.
So what I will eventually know
about symmetric matrices is that
the eigenvalues will come out
real.
I won't get any complex numbers
here.
And the eigenvectors,
once I get those,
actually will be orthogonal.
But two by two,
I'm more interested in what the
actual numbers are.
What do I know about the two
numbers?
Well, should do you want me to
find this determinant of A minus
lambda I?
Sure.
So it's the determinant of one
minus lambda one one zero,
right?
Minus lambda,
yes.
God.
OK.
There'll be two eigenvalues.
What will -- tell me again what
I know about the two eigenvalues
before I go any further.
Tell me something about these
two eigenvalues.
What do they add up to?
Lambda one plus lambda two is?
Is the same as the trace down
the diagonal of the matrix.
One and zero is one.
So lambda one plus lambda two
should come out to be one.
And lambda one times lambda one
times lambda two should come out
to be the determinant,
which is minus one.
So I'm
expecting the eigenvalues to
add to one and to multiply to
minus one.
But let's just see it happen
here.
If I multiply this out,
I get -- that times that'll be
a lambda squared minus lambda
minus one.
Good.
Lambda squared minus lambda
minus one.
Actually, I -- you see
the b- compare that with the
original equation that I started
with.
F(k+2) - F(k+1)-Fk is zero.
The recursion that -- that the
Fibonacci numbers satisfy is
somehow showing up directly here
for the eigenvalues when we set
that to zero.
WK.
Let's solve.
Well, I would like to be able
to factor that,
that quadratic,
but I'm better off to use the
quadratic formula.
Lambda is -- let's see.
Minus b is one plus or minus
the square root of b squared,
which is one,
minus four times that times
that, which is
plus four, over two.
So that's the square root of
five.
So the eigenvalues are lambda
one is one half of one plus
square root of five,
and lambda two is one half of
one minus square root of five.
And sure enough,
they -- those add up to one and
they multiply to give minus one.
OK.
Those are the two eigenvalues.
How -- what are those numbers
approximately?
Square root of five,
well, it's more than two but
less than three.
Hmm.
It'd be nice to know these
numbers.
I think, I think that -- so
that number comes out bigger
than
one, right?
That's right.
This number comes out bigger
than one.
It's about one point six one
eight or something.
Not exactly,
but.
And suppose it's one point six.
Just, like, I think so.
Then what's lambda two?
Is, is lambda two positive or
negative?
Negative, right,
because I'm -- it's,
obviously negative,
and I knew that the -- so it's
minus -- and they add up to one,
so minus point six one eight,
I guess.
OK.
A- and some more.
Those are the two eigenvalues.
One eigenvalue bigger than one,
one eigenvalue smaller than
one.
Actually, that's a great
situation to be in.
Of course, the eigenvalues are
different, so there's no doubt
whatever -- is this matrix
diagonalizable?
Is this matrix diagonalizable,
that original matrix A?
Sure.
We've got two distinct
eigenvalues and we can find the
eigenvectors in
a moment.
But they'll be independent,
we'll be diagonalizable.
And now, you,
you can already answer my very
first question.
How fast are those Fibonacci
numbers increasing?
How -- those -- they're
increasing,
right?
They're not doubling at every
step.
Let me -- let's look again at
these numbers.
Five, eight,
thirteen, it's not obvious.
The next one would be
twenty-one, thirty-four.
So to get some idea of what F
one hundred is,
can you give me any -- I mean
the crucial number -- so it --
these -- it's approximately --
what's controlling the growth of
these Fibonacci numbers?
It's the eigenvalues.
And which eigenvalue is
controlling that growth?
The big one.
So F100 will be approximately
some constant,
c1 I guess, times this lambda
one, this one plus square root
of five over two,
to the hundredth power.
And the two hundredth F -- in
other words, the eigenvalue --
the Fibonacci numbers are
growing by about that factor.
Do you see that we,
we've got precise information
about the, about the Fibonacci
numbers out of the eigenvalues?
OK.
And again, why is that true?
Let me go over to this board
and s- show what I'm doing here.
The --
the original initial value is
some combination of
eigenvectors.
And then when we start -- when
we start going out the theories
of Fibonacci numbers,
when we start multiplying by A
a hundred times,
it's this lambda one to the
hundredth.
This term is,
is the one that's taking over.
It's -- I mean,
that's big, like one point six
to the hundredth power.
The second term is practically
nothing, right?
The point six,
or minus point six,
to the hundredth power is an
extremely small,
extremely small number.
So this is -- there're only two
terms, because we're two by two.
This number is -- this piece of
it is there, but it's,
it's disappearing,
where this piece is there and
it's growing and controlling
everything.
So, so really the -- we're
doing, like, problems that are
evolving.
We're doing dynamic u- instead
of Ax=b, that's a static
problem.
We're now we're doing dynamics.
A, A squared,
A cubed, things are evolving in
time.
And the eigenvalues are the
crucial, numbers.
OK.
I guess to complete this,
I better write down the
eigenvectors.
So we should complete the,
the whole process by finding
the eigenvectors.
OK, well, I have to -- up in
the corner, then,
I have to look at A minus
lambda I.
So A minus lambda I is this one
minus lambda one one and minus
lambda.
And now can we spot an
eigenvector out of that?
That's, that's,
for these two lambdas,
this matrix is singular.
I guess the eigenvector -- two
by two ought to be,
I mean, easy.
So if I know that this matrix
is singular, then u- seems to me
the eigenvector has to be
lambda and one,
because that multiplication
will give me the zero.
And this multiplication gives
me -- better give me also zero.
Do you see why it does?
This is the minus lambda
squared plus lambda plus one.
It's the thing that's zero
because these lambdas
are special.
There's the eigenvector.
x1 is lambda one one,
and x2 is lambda two one.
I did that as a little trick
that was available in the two by
two case.
So now I finally have to -- oh,
I have to take the initial u0
now.
So to complete this example
entirely, I have to say,
OK, what was u0?
u0 was F1 F0.
So u0, the starting vector is
F1 F0, and those were one and
zero.
So I have to use that vector.
So I have to look for,
for a multiple of the first
eigenvector and the second to
produce u0, the one zero
vector.
This is what will find c1 and
c2, and then I'm done.
Do you -- so let me instead of,
in the last five seconds,
grinding out a formula,
let me repeat the idea.
Because I'd really -- it's the
idea that's central.
When things are evolving in
time -- let me come back to this
board, because the ideas are
here.
When things are evolving in
time by a first-order system,
starting from an original u0,
the key is find the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors of A.
That will tell -- those
eigenvectors -- the eigenvalues
will already tell you what's
happening.
Is the solution blowing up,
is it going to zero,
what's it doing.
And then to,
to find out exactly a formula,
you have to take your u0 and
write it as a combination of
eigenvectors and then follow
each eigenvector separately.
And that's really what this
formula, the formula for,
-- that's what the formula for
A to the K is doing.
So remember that formula for A
to the K is S lambda to the K S
inverse.
OK.
That's,
that's difference equations.
And you just have to -- so the,
the homework will give some
examples, different from
Fibonacci, to follow through.
And next time will be
differential equations.
Thanks.