PROFESSOR LEWIN: Problem number
four, which is 32-19.
I have an R, I have an L, I
have a C, I have E zero
cosine omega t.
300 Ohms, 0.25 Henry, 8 times 10
to the minus 6 Farads, 120
volts, 400 radians per second.
Forget the transients, we'll
only look at the
steady state solution.
I equals I zero cosine
omega t minus phi.
And the tangent of phi equals
omega L minus 1 over omega C
divided by R. I think it's
the third time that
you see this now.
It's interesting to write down
the reactance of the three
components.
It's 312 Ohms for the capacitor,
it's 100 Ohms for
the self inductance, and it is
300 Ohms for the resistor.
And so since Z equals the square
root of omega L minus
omega C squared, plus R squared,
you can immediately
calculate that this is 367 Ohms.
And since I zero equals
E zero divided by Z,
you'll find that
this is 0.327 Amperes.
And you find that phi
is minus 35 degrees.
So the current is ahead of
the driving voltage.
Because if phi is negative, then
minus phi is positive, so
the current is ahead of
the driving voltage.
That should not surprise you.
Because the capacitor is more
potent than the self inductor.
If the self inductor was more
potent, it would have the
capability of delaying
the current.
But if the capacitor
is in charge, it
puts the current ahead.
And that's exactly what you will
see, the current is ahead
of the driving voltage.
If we now put volt meters over
the R, C, and the L. Then,
you're being told that those
volt meters, V R, as I have
drawn them before, V C and V L,
there's no sense in drawing
them again.
They are volt meters.
That they now only
show amplitudes.
So all phase information is
lost. You don't see them shake
back and forth with
frequency omega.
There is no phase information.
All they will indicate
is the amplitude.
If they could show the
instantaneous values, V at any
moment in time, then you would
see, when V R is a maximum,
and I repeat myself, because
I've said it before, then V L
would be zero, and then
V of C would be zero.
The volt meter over
the capacitor.
And when V R was zero, that
means when I is zero, V L
would read a maximum value, and
so would V C also read a
maximum value.
Even though these two would be
180 degrees out of phase.
All that is lost here.
These volt meter are designed
in such a way that all they
record are amplitudes.
So the amplitude of the volt
meter over the capacitor
equals I zero times the
reactance off the capacitor.
The volt meter over to resistor
would read I zero
times R. And the amplitude of
the volt meter over the self
inductance would read I
zero times omega L.
Again, I repeat myself, at the
risk of boring you, that these
values do not occur
simultaneously.
It is more common when we deal
with alternating currents, to
have volt meters that express
not the amplitude of the
voltage, but the root
mean squared.
Which is simply the amplitude
divided by the
square root of two.
There's nothing very
sacred about that.
So if you wanted, in this
particular problem, to covert
the values to RMS values, all
you would have to do is divide
them by the square
root of two.
And there's nothing more
to it than that.