And so this brings us now
to problem number
six, which is 32-25.
Believe it or not, again, we
have an R, we have an L, we
have a C, and we have an
E0 cosine omega t.
We know E0, we know C, we
know L, and we know R.
And we had told that this
is at resonance.
That means I know immediately
that omega equals omega 0.
At resonance, 1 over omega C
equals omega L. That's when
the current reaches a maximum.
In this case, they're
both 600 ohm.
They better be the same, because
they're 180 degrees
out of phase when you measure
the voltage over the self
inductor and the capacitor.
That's why they cancel.
R equals 400 ohms.
Phi equals 0.
And Z equals R. That's very
characteristic for resonance.
It's almost as if there
were no self
inductance and capacitor.
They completely, at any
moment in time, cancel
each other's effect.
This one would want
the voltage to be
ahead of the current.
This one wants the voltage
to be behind the
current by 90 degrees.
They each are equally strong, so
to speak, and so the whole
thing cancels out.
And that's why you get such
a very simple result.
Now, you're being asked what the
voltmeters over each one
of these would read if you
attach them and if they were
to read only rms values.
That means no phase
information.
All the phase information is
lost. The voltmeter over the
self inductor would read
undoubtedly I0 divided by the
square root of 2-- because
that's the root mean square of
the current--
times omega 0L.
The voltmeter over the
capacitance rms would read I0
divided by the square root of
2 times 1 over omega 0 C.
And since omega 0L and omega 0C
is exactly the same value
because we are at resonance--
omega 0 equals 1 over the
square root of LC--
this voltage is exactly the same
as this voltage, whatever
the answer may be.
They are the same.
But they are 180 degrees out of
phase, and that you will no
longer see when you read
these voltmeters.
Keep that in mind.
The authors are not so stupid.
They want you to think
a little bit harder.
There is here an L and there is
here a C. Circuit goes on.
So here is that VL.
And here is that VC--
voltmeters.
And they also have a voltmeter
here, which they call V4.
It's true that since the phase
information is lost, this
value will read the same
value as that value.
But since they are 180%
degrees out of phase,
V4 will read 0.
Because at any moment in time
the voltages here and here
will exactly cancel
each other.
So that is something that I
want you to keep in mind.