I want to discuss with you an
RLC circuit that is not so
conventional.
It's not a series circuit, but
it's a parallel circuit.
It is trivial, it is very
pedestrian, but I hope you
will learn something
from that.
I have here some driving
[? voltage choice ?]
e0 cosine omega t.
Let there be here a capacitor c,
here a self-inducted l, and
here a resistance r.
Very different from the circuits
that we have seen
before, because they're not in
series, but they are parallel.
I always, when I solve these
problems, take a moment that
this is plus and that this
is minus, and I make the
assumption that there
are no charges
anywhere on the capacitor.
This is always correct, because
my sign convention
comes always out OK.
That means this side of the
capacitor will then be charged
positive, and I get
an e field in the
capacitors in this direction.
The e field in the
[? voltage choice ?]
goes from plus to minus.
So it goes in this direction.
There is no e field here, and
there is an e field in the
resistor, in this direction.
There is a total current going
like this, and the total
current will split into one
current that will go through
the capacitor, one current
that goes through the
self-inductor, and
one current that
goes through the resistor.
So at any moment in time, the
total current at any moment in
time, must be ic plus
il plus ir.
At any moment in time.
So I put a little t here, a
little t here, a little t
here, a little t here.
I assume that no charge can
pile up at any of these
intersections, so therefore the
total current that flows
in here must be the total
current that flows out here
into some of the
three currents.
I will only solve for steady
state solutions, and so I
immediately turned to Faraday's
Law, the closed loop
integral of e dot dl, and I
do that for three loops.
Now follow me closely.
I'm first going to
do it clockwise.
In this loop, I call that
loop number one.
Then I'm going to do it
clockwise in this loop.
I call that number two.
And then I'm going to do it
clockwise in this loop.
I call that number three.
And for number one and
for number three,
Kirchoff's Law holds.
It is a non-conservative e
field, so this equals 0.
But for loop number two,
Kirchoff's Law does not hold.
We have a non-conservative
e field And the answer
is minus l dil dt.
So I can write down now, if I
want to, the differential
equations for these
three loops.
I start here.
I go up against the
electric field.
So I got minus e0
cosine omega t.
This is for loop one.
Then I go across the capacitor,
so I get the charge
on the capacitor divided by c.
That's the integral of
e dot dl to this gap.
And that must be 0.
And I keep in mind that
dqcdt is the current
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] capacitor.
For loop number two, I have
minus e0 cosine omega t.
When I go through here, when I
go through the self-inductor,
there is no electric field, so
that component equals 0.
I close the loop, and Faraday's
Law tells me that
that is l dil dt.
So I can change these minus
signs into plus signs.
And then for loop number three,
I get minus e0 cosine
omega t plus ir times
r equals 0.
That is again, if you want to
call it, Kiechoff's Law.
And the total current at any
moment in time is the sum of
the individual ones.
This is total plus il plus ir.
And that must be i0 cosine
omega t minus
some phase angle phi.
And this holds for any
moment in time.
Namely for this moment
in time.
If you want to, you
can replace all
these things by currents.
In this case, it's easy.
You take the first derivative
of this equation, and so you
find the current through the
capacitor at any moment in
time, which is qdt, which would
become minus c e0 omega
sine omega t.
The current, through its
self-inductor, at any moment
in time, would become e0 divided
by omega times the
sine omega t.
If you execute this integral,
you will immediately see that.
It's true that there could
be some constant here,
integration constant, but that
would be a DC components, and
that would certainly
not be valid here.
Then we have the current through
the resistor at any
moment in time equals e0 cosine
omega t divided by r.
So what do we have here now?
We have a minus sine omega t,
we have a plus sine omega t,
and we have a cosine omega t.
And so that's telling you that
there are phase lags between
these three currents.
If I try to be a little bit
pedestrian, almost high
school-like, but we have time
for that, and I, without
wanting to insult you, I draw
here a cosine term.
So this is the driving voltage,
the cosine term.
And if I draw here
a sine term--
this is a plus sine term.
And the plus sine term holds
for the self- inductor.
So I put a self-inductor
here, which is
my shorthand notation.
And if I put in minus sine omega
t, minus the sine, which
is the one that holds for the
capacitor, then you see
immediately, when you look at
this point and this point,
that the current in the
capacitor is 90 degrees ahead
of the voltage, which
is nothing new.
And you see here that the
voltage driver is 90 degrees
ahead of the current in
the self-inductor.
The current in the self-inductor
is lagging.
We have mentioned that before,
because the self-inductor has
the ability to quiet
down the current.
It doesn't like the current
to come up.
So the current will
be lagging.
And you see that very clearly
in these curves, and you see
that very clearly in the minus
sign omega t, the plus sign
omega t, and the
cosine omega t.
And therefore, this problem
is screaming
for a phasor diagram.
A phasor diagrams will tell
me all the answers.
I have here a vector
at i, 0, 4.
This is the amplitude of the
current, which equals e 0
divided by r.
This one rotates around with
angular velocity omega.
At this moment, it has
a positive value.
When it is here, a quarter of
an oscillation later, the
projection on this axis is 0,
and there's no current going
through a resistor.
When it is here, the current is
going through the resistor,
but in the opposite direction.
When it is here, there is no
current going through the
resistor, and when it is here,
it's going through the
resistor again in the
same direction.
So the current through the
resistor, which is no
surprise, is oscillating back
and forth, and there are
moments that it is 0.
Now I put here in the vector the
current, amplitude current
for the capacitor, which
is e 0 omega c.
You can see that immediately
from my previous text, if I
can find my previous text--
oh, it's somewhere on the floor,
so I can't find it.
But if you go back, you will see
that is the amplitude of
the current when I derived
the current from the
differential equations.
And of course, this one also
goes around with angular
velocity omega.
At this moment in time, the
projection is 0, but when it's
here, it is maximum in one
direction, and when it's here,
it is a maximum in the
other direction.
And i0 going through the
self-inductor equals e0
divided by omega l, which
follows from what I just did
only minutes ago.
And this also goes around with
angular velocity omega.
And this whole system,
these three spikes
together are couples.
They all go around with angular
velocity omega.
So if I add this one to this
one, I get here a vector e0
times omega c minus
1 divided omega l.
And so the net vector, adding
all these three currents
together, and that's
what I have to do.
Because in this case, the
currents through the system is
the sum of these
three currents.
And I add them now, so to speak,
in a vectorial sense,
Then this current, i0, which
is the amplitude, equals e0
times the square root of omega
c1 over omega l squared plus 1
over r squared.
Be careful!
This may look similar to the one
you have seen in a series,
but it is very different.
And the angle of phi, the way
we define that follows
immediately, also from
this phasor diagram.
The tangent of phi equals omega
c minus 1 over omega l
divided by r.
And of course, you can clean
that up a little
bit, if you want to.
And i0 itself, within the
e0 times this monster.
and since e0, per definition,
equals i0 times the cell
impedance, the cells impede
in v equals 1
divided by this monster.
Now comes the question,
when is i0 a maximum?
What I'm trying to drive at is,
either perhaps residences,
like we have in an
RLC circuit.
Well, look at this result.
When is i0 a maximum, it's
immediately clear
when r equals 0.
Because then this term
goes to infinity.
Well, that is immediately
obvious!
We didn't have to do such fancy
differential equations.
If r is 0, you short circuit
this battery.
And if this battery has no
internal resistance, of course
you get an infinite current.
So that's totally trivial.
That's something that you could
have immediately predicted.
So now, let's assume
that r is fixed.
Where, now, is i0 maximum?
Well, now i0 is maximum when
omega c minus 1 over omega l
squared is a maximum.
Because you see here, in the
phasor diagrams, you see here
this term, and you
see this term.
So when this is a maximum, you
expect i0 to be a maximum.
When will that be?
Well, it will be the case
when il equals 0 and
when c equals infinity.
So when l equals 0, i0
becomes infinity.
And when c goes to infinity,
then also i0 goes to infinity.
Is that obvious?
Of course that's obvious!
If I have l0, then this
is just a solid bar.
It has no self-inductance,
it has no resistance.
So I'm short-circuiting
the system.
So I get an infinite current
going if this
[? voltage choice ?]
has no internal resistance.
What happens if c is
infinitely high?
That's also a short circuit.
Because infinitely high c is
like a lake that is so large
in area that when you put water
in it, that it can take
infinite amounts of water, but
the water level doesn't rise.
Or to talk in more electric
terms, the capacitor can take
on any amount of charge, but the
integral e dot dl, across
the gap, and you may want
to call that the voltage
overcapacitor, will
then not change.
So that, effectively, is also
a short circuit here.
It can take an infinite
amount of charge.
And so this current that will
flow through here is then also
infinitive.
So all these wonderful
differential equations leads
us only to totally trivial
answers we could've predicted
without any differential
equations.
But now suppose that r, l, and
c are all three fixed.
And now I want to ask you to
question, is there a value for
omega for which i0
is a maximum?
Because I'm still interested to
see whether somehow there
is a resonance in this system.
Well, that would be the case
when omega c minus omega l
squared is a maximum.
Because again, I go back
to my phasor diagram.
r is a given.
I can't change that.
l and c are givens.
But I can manipulate, I can
massage omega, to see whether
I can make this a maximum.
So some of you may be very
clever, and you may say, aha,
I take the derivative of this,
and I make it equal to 0, and
of course I will find the
maximum value, no doubt.
Well, why don't you do that.
Let's do that together.
We get 2 omega c minus
1 over omega l.
I use the chain rule, then I get
here a c, and then I get
here a plus 1 over l omega
squared, and that must be 0.
I lose the 2, and I
multiply this out.
So I get omega c squared plus c
divided by omega l, minus c
divided by omega l minus 1
divided by l squared omega to
the third, and that is 0.
And these two cancel out,
and what do I find?
I find that omega equals 1 over
the square root of l c,
if you solve this equation.
And I say, aha!
There is a resonance.
But if I say that, I'm wrong.
Because this is not a maximum,
but it is a minimum.
If you take the derivative of
that function as a function of
time, and you make it equal to
0, you have a chance to find a
maximum, and you have a chance
to find a minimum.
And it is immediately obvious
that this is the minimum.
Because look at this equation.
When omega equals the square
root of 1 over lc, this term
has become 0.
Well, that means that this arrow
will always be shorter--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
put it this way.
This arrow, which is the one I
have left if this is 0, is
only shorter than if
this is not 0.
Any value that I have in
this vector that is
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
0 will make the current
larger.
So the current will be a minimum
when this one is 0,
and I only have simply i0
through r is e 0 through r.
So you can look at the phasor
diagram, and convince yourself
that when this is 0,
you actually have
a minimum in current.
There is no resonance.
And if you now were to make a
plot of i0 as a function of
omega, it will be very boring.
When omega goes to 0, the
current goes to infinity.
And the reason why the current
goes to infinity is, when
omega goes to 0, this value
goes to infinity.
So it is the l that
is doing it.
And then it goes through a
minimum, and then again, it
goes to infinity, and that is
the c that is doing it,
because when omega goes to
infinity, this value goes to
infinity, and so the current
goes to infinity.
And then there is here
this minimum.
And this minimum is as
e0 divided by r.
And this minimum is when
omega equals 1 over the
square root of lc.
So you've seen the
whole thing now.
This is a parallel circuit.
Behaves very differently.
But still, it's good to do
this kind of an exercise.
It builds up some confidence
in how you deal with phasor
diagrams, how you deal with
differential equations, and
more important for me, how you
get totally trivial answers
that you could have
predicted anyhow.