PROFESSOR: Now a few more words
about phasor diagrams.
Phasor diagrams can be very
useful, but again, like
always, you have to have
a lot of practice.
And if you don't have the
practice, they may scare you
at first. And they may
even confuse you.
I will do one problem in which
I will use phasor diagrams.
That's my last problem that
I will do-- seven--
because I will leave you
alone with eight.
I don't think eight is
all that difficult.
L, R, C. And we have an
alternating voltage source, E0
cosine omega t, and I think
it's called E of s.
And again, getting boring, I
keep drawing the same circuit,
C, L, R. I'm going to put
a voltmeter over here.
Nothing is new now.
We've seen this now
several times.
I'm going to put a voltmeter,
VL, over here, and I'm going
to put a voltmeter over here.
And now I also am going to put
a voltmeter over here, which
the authors call V out.
Earlier we had 1 over L
and C, you remember?
And we argued that at resonance
it always reads 0.
But now I put 1 over L and R.
Now like in the previous problem
whereby we had V4,
which was over L and C, we now
have to take the phase
difference between this voltage
and this voltage into
account if we evaluate
the V out.
Well, this is now
where a phasor
diagram can be very useful.
We treat the voltages,
in a way, as vectors.
If the current at one particular
moment is I0, which
is the maximum value, then the
amplitude of the voltmeter
over the resistance will be I0
times R. And I put that here
as a vector.
It is true that the maximum
amplitude of the voltmeter
over the self-inductance will
read I0 times omega L, but not
at the same time
that this one.
It is ahead of this one.
And it is true that the
voltmeter over the
capacitance, the amplitude, will
be I0 times 1 over omega
C, but it will not occur
at the same time that
this one does it.
In fact, it will do
with it later.
It is 90 degrees behind this
voltage, and this one is 90
degrees behind that voltage.
I can now make a
factor diagram.
This is a vector.
And this is a vector.
I add, first, these
two vectors up.
That gives me here a vector
omega L minus 1 over omega C.
And now I have here a vector.
And this vector, V, which is now
the total voltage around
the whole circuit, which equals
the square root of
omega L minus omega C squared
plus R squared times I, which
is I times Z. It's I0.
Because I have I0's
everywhere.
And here is that angle phi the
way I have defined it before.
Now, all these four vectors--
this one, this one, this
one, and this one--
rotate around in this direction
with angular
velocity omega.
And the actual value that the
voltmeter will read--
that's the way you should
interpret this phasor diagram--
is the projection of
that vector onto
the horizontal axis.
And so you can see when the
voltmeter of the resistor
reaches the maximum value, this
projection is zero and
this projection is zero.
I've stated that many
times before.
When this reads a maximum value,
this reads zero and
this reads zero.
But now if you have a quarter of
a period later, this vector
will be here, this vector will
be here, and so this vector
will reach, this voltmeter
will reach a maximum.
And this vector will be here
and this voltmeter
will reach a maximum.
And this vector here, if you
want to know what the voltage
of the driver is--
because this is the voltage
of the driver--
well, that's at E0
cosine omega t.
And we call that E of S. When
that goes around, it's the
projection on the horizontal
that at all moments in time
gives you the driving EMF.
And this is not so easy to
digest, but once you get the
hang of it, it's actually
very nice.
Because if now you want to know
what the voltage is of
the voltmeter that is attached
to the self-inductance and the
resistor, all you have to take
into account is the phase
difference between this vector
and that vector.
And so I will make a new
diagram for that.
This is the vector amplitude
Ir times R. And this is the
vector, which is ahead,
amplitude I0 times omega L.
Taking the phase into account,
this will now be what the
voltmeter V out will read--
amplitude.
This is over the R and the L
simultaneously, which is I0
times the square root of omega
L squared plus R squared.
You see that immediately
from this diagram.
And this phase angle is not the
phi that we have defined
before, but you can determine
what it is.
You can take the tangent--
it's omega L divided by R-- if
you were interested in this.
So we're looking at these
voltages now as vectors.
V out zero equals V amplitude R
plus V amplitude over L. And
the phase differences now have
be taken into account.
And so the magnitude of the
output voltage equals I0 times
this square root.
And so if you want to know now
what the ratio is of V out
over Es, well, they have the
I0 in common, so you would
get, then, that you find here
the square root of omega
squared L squared plus R divided
by the square root of
Z. I think you will have
no difficulties
finding this because--
this is Es--
because E0, that's the amplitude
of the driver,
equals I0 divided by Z. That's
the definition of Z. And so
this shouldn't be too hard.
And I think I'll leave
you alone with this.
Because now that you have this,
well, I think you are
very, very well on your way.