Again, an RMC circuit.
I have an L, I have a R, I have
a C, and I have an E0
cosine omega t.
This is 110 ohms and you're
being told that the impedance
is 150 ohms.
Are you're being asked, what
is the mean power that is
delivered to the circuit?
I have to say mean because I
have to average it over one
complete cycle, one period
of oscillations.
Because as you will see, the
power delivered to the
circuits is not constant.
It oscillates.
I think it oscillates with omega
squared, some kind of
sine squared, omega squared, but
you figure that one out.
In any case, the mean value
equals the voltage rms times
the current rms times the cosine
of that angle phi the
way I defined that before.
And I will refer you to equation
32-30 without any
further elaborating
on why this is so.
Now, Vrms is obviously Irms
times Z for the simple reason
that V 0 equals I0 times Z.
That's the way it is defined.
This V0, by the way,
is that E0.
And the tangent of phi, which we
have mentioned many times,
is omega L minus 1 over
omega C divided by R.
So you shouldn't have any
difficulties calculating these
values because you know the
Vrms, that is, the V0 divided
by the square root of 2.
You know V0.
And you know Z. And so you can
clearly calculate Irms, so you
know this one.
So you're almost there
as long as you can
calculate cosine of phi.
How can I convert this
into a cosine?
Well, that's a trick
that I already
learned in high school.
I have here a triangle whereby
this angle equals phi.
And I know that this is omega L
minus 1 over omega C. And I
know that this is R because the
tangent of phi is exactly
what we gave before.
That means this here must be
the square root of omega L
minus omega C squared
plus R squared.
But that is exactly Z.
And so the cosine of phi equals
nothing but R over Z.
Since C was given, and since R
was given, you can find the
cosine of phi, which
I believe is 0.73.
So it's very easy to go
from tangent of phi
to cosine of phi.