Problem number three is 32-58.
It is an R L C circuit.
The L value is 1.0 times 10
to the minus 6 henry.
We don't know C, we don't know
R, but they are in series.
It is an FM radio, and I tune
in on a broadcast--
I do that by varying
the capacitor.
This arrow through C means
that the capacitor can be
varied, and I have broadcast
station number one, which
broadcasts at an angular
frequency of 6.00 times 10 to
the eighth radians per second.
I tune dead onto this one.
There is an annoying nearby
station which radiates at a
frequency almost the same as
this one, but I don't want to
hear this one.
Let's first calculate what the
value for C is-- if I tune
exactly in with my variable
capacitor on this frequency,
then omega 1 must be omega 0,
and omega 0 is 1 over square
root of L C, as we have
seen many times for a
series R L C circuit.
You'll find that C--
I square this--
equals L 1 divided by
L omega 1 squared.
I know what omega 1 is, I know
what L is, and I found--
I could have made a mistake--
2.778 times 10 to the minus
12 [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I know how I should tune C in
order to receive omega 1 at
its resonance frequency.
Now we're also told that the
mean power that's coming from
the second station delivers to
the resistor R, which is
presumably the loudspeaker.
From station number one, that is
one hundredths of the mean
power through a complete cycle
of station number 1.
The question now
is, what is R?
I'll put this here, because
I may need this again.
Let us remind you of what the
maximum current I looks as a
function of omega for a
given R L C circuit.
At the beginning, this is more
or less linear, it flares up,
and we call that resonance,
and then it dies off.
Right here, at the maximum value
for I 0, which is the
resonance frequency, omega 0
equals omega 1, because that's
the way I have tuned
the system.
My second frequency comes in
here, and so you see that the
current is highly reduced--
reduced so to the point that
the power is only one
hundredths that the resistor
receives from
station number 1.
What is mean power in general?
It is the v r m s, coming in
through the antenna, times the
I r m s driven in the circuit,
times the cosine of phi.
This is the general equation
for power delivered to that
resistance r, and you have
seen this before.
The current that is going to
flow into the system equals I
cosine omega t minus phi.
This is something you have seen
before, and it is only to
refresh your memory.
The way that you can best solve
this is in the following
way: let me first calculate
the value for phi.
The value for phi is given as
follows: this is r, this is
omega L minus 1 over omega C.
We got this from phasor
diagrams, and we call
this the impedence--
which is omega L minus
1 over omega C
squared plus r squared.
The tangent of phi equals omega
L minus 1 over omega C
divided by r, and so the cosine
of phi equals R divided
by z, which is this
whole square root.
We have assumed nos--
I will assume--
that the input voltage r
m s from both stations
is exactly the same.
Now, how about the
power ratios?
The power ratio of 1 over 2 mean
values would be I r m s
circuit 1 cosine phi 1 divided
by I r m s circuit 2-- not
circuit 2, station 2--
times cosine phi 2.
Remember, the values for
R L C are values that
are going to be given.
In fact, you have to
calculate R now.
This value now we
want to be 100.
At resonance, cosine phi
1 equals 1, because
phi 1 equals 0--
you can immediately
see that here.
Let's write down
what I r m s--
I don't know what problem
I have with this sheet--
is in general for an
R L C circuit.
It is I 0 divided by the square
root of 2, and that
would be v 0 divided by the
square root of 2 times that
value for C. Let me write that
in-- omega L minus 1 over
omega C squared plus r squared,
and you have seen
this many times before.
If I go to station number 1, I
get that I r m s for station
number one equals simply
v 0 times the square
root of 2 times r.
When this is zero at resonance,
I only have an R
here, and cosine phi equals 1.
If I now go to station
number 2--
I r m s for station number 2
equals v 0, and we've assumed
that the v zeroes are the same,
the square root of 2.
Now, I get the square root,
which is now omega 2 L minus 1
over omega 2 C squared
plus R squared.
I also must multiply by the
cosine of phi, and the cosine
of phi equals R divided by that
same square root, so the
same square root for
occurs twice.
Now my task is to calculate the
ratio: P 1 divided by P 2,
which is 100.
I take the ratios of these two
values, because the v r m s
here is exactly the same
as the v r m s here.
When I take the ratio of the
power, I can delete the v r m
s's, and I can also delete
the square roots of 2.
I get upstairs 1 over R, and
I get downstairs R over the
square root of this, times
the square root of this.
Maybe I'm going a little
bit too far--
I could've left you now solving
this equation, but we
have plenty of time,
so why not?
It is omega 2 L minus omega
2 C squared plus R squared
divided by R squared.
That is now the requirement for
the power ratio to be 100.
C was 2.778 times 10 to the
minus 12 and L was 10 to the
minus 6, so that gives omega 2
L equals 599.0, and it gives
me 1 over omega 2
C equals 601.0.
This here is 2, so 2 squared
is 4, and so I got 4 plus R
squared divided by R squared,
and that equals 100.
When I solve that equation, I
found that R is approximately
0.21 ohms.
With this resistor, you will get
a hundred times less power
from station number 2 than you
get from station number 1, and
you have exactly tuned your
radio or television station,
for that matter, on station
number one.
With television, the frequencies
will be different.