PROFESSOR LEWIN: Let's now turn
to a situation where by
we drive the circuit with
an alternating current.
The emf equals E zero times
cosine omega t.
Now there is an extremely
important difference between
the two cases.
In the first case, the omega,
that means the oscillating
frequency of the current, was
entirely dictated by R, L and
C. It imposed on the circuit
it's will so to speak.
Well, if we give this
alternating current sufficient
amount of time, so that all of
the transient phenomenon have
died out, so that the system
cannot impose, any more it's
own idiosyncrasies, it's own
frequencies onto the system,
ultimately what will prevail,
and what must prevail is the
frequency of the driver.
So the system must, when all
transient phenomenon have died
out, it must start
to oscillate at
the frequency omega.
Suppose I take you by the
shoulders, and I start to
oscillate you at some
moment in time
with a certain frequency.
In the beginning, your system
will respond in a sort of
erratic way, having it's own
sense of the frequency at
which it wants to oscillate.
But that will ultimately die
out, and ultimately you will
have to follow my frequency with
which I am shaking you.
The transience will die out and
my frequency will prevail.
And that's exactly the
same case here.
So the current that will start
to flow equals I zero times
cosine omega t minus phi, we'll
get back to this phi,
and this omega is exactly
the same as this omega.
And it's completely independent
or R, L and C.
I zero, which can be derived, if
you solve the differential
equation, is a little
bit clumsy.
Omega L minus omega C squared
plus R squared.
And we called this also, Z. This
thing is also called Z.
This value of I zero, reaches
a maximum value,
when we have resonance.
Given a value for E zero, if I
change the frequency of the
driving voltage, I get a maximum
when this equals zero.
And that's the case when omega
square equals 1 over omega L
and we call that omega
zero squared.
As I mentioned before,
just a name.
The tangent of phi and phi
indicates to face difference
between the current and
the driving voltage.
When phi equals positive,
because there's a minus sign
here, the current is behind
the driving voltage.
When phi equals negative, the
current is ahead of the
driving voltage.
This equals omega L minus omega
C divided by R. And I
will get back to this.
If I make a plot of I zero as
a function of omega, then
you'll see that it always
speaks at omega
equals omega zero.
So this is now only I zero,
it's the maximum current,
which I plot as a functional
of omega.
And I keep E zero constant.
At the valley of omega, which
is 1 over the square root of
LC, there's no R in here,
I reach a maximum.
And this maximum, as follows
immediately from our solution,
this is zero.
It simply is E zero divided by
R. So this value is E zero
divided by R.
Now since the E zero is a
constant, you see immediately,
that if I make R smaller,
that I get a
peak which goes higher.
So this is my short
hand notation
for saying R is small.
And if you prefer a much larger
value for R, R is large.
Omega zero is independent of
R. But keep in mind, that I
zero maximum, which is this
value here, that is
independent of L and C. That
only depends on R and of
course on the value that we
have chosen for E zero.
If we look at this solution,
we gives names to these
quantities, omega L
1 over omega C. We
call this the reactance.
Omega L is the reactance of
the self inductor, it has
dimensions ohm.
And 1 over omega C is the
reactance of the capacitor,
which also has units
in terms of v.
And we call this entire square
root, we call that Z. And that
is called the impedance.
Just words, but it's useful
to remember them.
When omega goes up, this value
becomes very large.
When omega becomes large,
sorry, this value
becomes very small.
And the capacitor plays
a minor role
and L has a big effect.
Because if omega is large,
omega L is large.
Well immediately obvious,
because if omega is large, dI
dt, the change of current with
time is very fast. Because
that's means a high frequency.
And so L becomes powerful.
If omega is low, then the L
plays a minor role, but then
the C becomes very important.
In your mind, if you make omega
go to zero, that means
that there's almost no
change in the emf
of the driving voltage.
The capacitor simply
blocks the current.
It's like an opening
in the wires.
So it's very low value value
of omega when omega goes to
zero, it's obvious that the
current and goes to zero.
Are you see that because when
omega become zero, this value
goes to infinity.
And indeed you see that the
current goes to zero.
So it does make sense to think a
little bit about the role of
omega, of L, and the role of C
in terms of this amplitude of
the current.