JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about line integrals
of vector fields.
And I have a couple of nice
questions on that subject for
you right here.
So I want F to be the vector
field whose first coordinate
is xy and whose second
coordinate is x
squared plus y squared.
And so what I'd like you do is
compute the line integral of F
around two different curves C.
So both curves start at the
point 1, 1 and they end
at the point 2, 4.
So in part a, the curve is just
the straight line that
connects the point
1, 1 to 2, 4.
And in part b, the curve is
this sort of piecewise.
It's two sides of a
rectangle, right?
It goes straight up until it
gets to the point 1, 4, and
then it goes across
to the point 2, 4.
So it's a piecewise, smooth,
curved path that connects
those two points.
So I'd like you to compute the
integral over each of these
curves of F dot dr. So why don't
you pause the video,
have a go at that,
come back, and we
can work it out together.
So, when you're computing a line
integral over a curve,
really the thing that you want
to do is you want to
parametrize the curve, and then
that gives you stuff that
you can plug in.
You'll have expressions
for x and y in
terms of your parameter.
So you can plug it in and you
just turn this integral right
into a nice single variable
integral, and then you can
compute it.
So that's our basic strategy
for computing integrals of
this form line integrals
of vector fields.
So let's have a go.
Let's start with part a.
So in part a, what we need to
do to apply this method is
that we need to parametrize
the curve in question.
So this is a straight line.
And if you look at it, it's the
line through the points 1,
1 and 2, 4.
So this line has equation
y equals 3x minus 2.
That's our line, and OK.
So we need to choose some
parameter that will give us
this segment of this line.
So a natural thing to
do on this case
is --it's easy enough--
y is already written in terms
of x, so it's natural enough
just to take a parameter
that's equal to x.
So it's up to you whether you
introduce the letter t in
order to do this, or not.
I'm going to do it with the
letter t here in part a, but
you could do this problem
exactly the same way just
using the letter x.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to let x equals t so
that y is equal to 3t minus 2.
OK, so that is the parametric
equation for the entire line,
but we only want the
part between the
points 1, 1 and 2, 4.
So the part between the lines
1, 1 and 2, 4 is the part
where t is between 1 and 2.
Where x is between 1 and 2.
OK.
So this is our parametrization.
So now we need to figure out
what is the field F in this
parametrization, and what is
dr. And then after we have
those, we can just put them into
our integral and compute.
So F. In this parametrization,
well, we take the equation for
F, which is xy comma x squared
plus y squared, and
we just plug in.
So in this case, xy is going to
be 3t minus 2 times t, so
that's 3t squared minus 2t.
And x squared plus y squared,
well that's t squared, plus 3t
minus 2 quantity squared.
So that's what F is.
And also we have that dr--
well, we just take the
differentials of x and y-- so
this is going to be
dt comma 3dt.
Or if you like, 1 comma 3 times
dt if you like to factor
out your dt.
So that's what F and dr is.
So now we need to compute
our integral.
So the integral over C
of F dot dr, well,
you just plug in.
So this is the integral
over C now.
So OK.
So now we need to look
at our bounds.
So the integral over C means
the integral as t varies in
the range that we
need to cover.
That whole curve.
So in this case, we said that
was from t equals 1 to 2.
So it's the integral as t goes
from 1 to 2 of F dot dr.
So in the first coordinates,
let me factor out
the dt at the end.
So that's going to be 3t squared
minus 2t, times 1,
plus --OK well, let's expand
this out now--.
3t minus 2 quantity squared
that's going to give me a 9t
squared minus 12t plus 4
--so this is 9t squared
minus 12t plus 4--
and then we have to add
t squared to it.
So this is plus 10t squared
minus 12t plus 4, times 3, and
then this whole thing is dt.
dt is the whole integrand,
there.
I could even put in another pair
of parentheses just to
emphasize that, perhaps.
OK.
Now this is straightforward.
I mean, it's a little
complicated looking, but it's
just an integral of
a polynomial.
Easy enough to do.
Let's first just combine terms.
OK, so let's look at
the t squareds.
We have a 10t squared times 3.
So 30t squared, and then
another 3 times 1.
So 33t squared minus 2t minus
36t is minus 38t plus 12--
4 times 3--
dt.
OK, and now we integrate.
So this is equal
to 11t cubed--
that's a 3--
minus 19t squared plus 12t as
t varies between 1 and 2.
And all right.
OK, so now we've got to plug
in and evaluate and so on.
So at 2, this is 88 minus
76 plus 24, minus 11
minus 19 plus 12.
So you do some arithmetic
and this is going
to work out to 32.
OK, so there's part a.
It's a nice, simple curve,
so we had a nice, simple
parametrization.
We computed F and dr, then we
dotted them, and integrated.
OK, so now we're going to do the
same exact thing for part
b, but in part b, the curve is
a little more complicated.
Let's come over here where we've
got some empty space.
So in part b, our curve
looks like this.
So it starts at the point 1, 1,
and then it goes up to the
point 1, 4, and then it goes
over to the point 2, 4.
All right?
So it's hard to parametrize in
one fell swoop something that
makes a sharp right
angle like that.
So a natural thing to do is to
split the integral over this
whole curve into the integrals
over the two different pieces.
So let's call this vertical
part C1 and this
horizontal part C2.
And so we know that the integral
over C of F dot dr is
equal to the integral over C1 of
F dot dr plus the integral
over C2 of F dot dr. And so
now, it's easy enough to
parametrize these two separate
curves separately.
C1, for example, is the straight
line segment that
goes from 1, 1 to 1, 4.
So C1.
So that means we have x equal to
1, and 1 less than or equal
to y less than or equal to 4.
So a natural parametrization
here is just the
parametrization that uses
the parameter y.
Right?
So in this one, I'm not going
to bother introducing
a new letter t.
I'm just going to stick
with x and y.
So we have x equals 1, and y is
our parameter and it goes
from 1 to 4.
So now let's look at
what F and dr are.
So in this case,
F is equal to--
its first coordinate is xy,
and x is just 1 here--
so this is y.
And its second coordinate was x
squared plus y squared, and
so that's going to be
1 plus y squared.
And dr--
well, r here is 1 comma y--
so dr is equal to 0 comma dy.
Or 0, 1 times dy, if you wanted
to factor that dy out
to the end.
OK.
Good.
So we're all set to do
that first integral.
So let's do that.
So we have the integral over
C1 of F dot dr is equal to
what we dot these two
things together.
And the first term gives me y
times 0, and that's just 0.
So that's going to die, and
all we're left with is the
second term.
So it's the integral
of 1 plus y squared
dy, but we need bounds.
Right?
OK, so y was going from 1
to 4 in this integral.
So it's the integral from 1 to
4 of 1 plus y squared dy.
OK.
So we can either continue and
evaluate this now, or we could
go and do the second one.
Let's finish evaluating it since
we've already got it
written up here.
So this is equal to y, plus y
cubed over 3, between 1 and 4.
So what is this?
This is 4 plus 64/3,
minus 1 plus 1/3.
So that looks like
it's 24 to me.
OK, so we get 24 for
the first part.
Now, let's do the second part.
So it's C2 here.
I'll draw a little line there
to separate them.
Now on curve C2 --let's go
back and look at it--
OK, so curve C2 is the segment
connecting the points 1, 4 and
the point 2, 4.
OK, so y is always 4 on this
curve, and x goes from 1 to 2.
So 1 is less than or equal to
x less than or equal to 2, y
is equal to 4.
So a natural parametrization
here again, is just to take x
to be our parameter.
And again, I'm not going to
introduce a letter t.
We're just using x
as our parameter.
So in this case, F--
well, it's xy, so x is
just x and y is 4--
so that's 4x comma--
and the second coordinate is x
squared plus y squared-- so
that's x squared plus 16.
And dr is equal to dx comma 0.
OK, so that's F and dr.
So the integral that I want now
is the integral over C2 of
F dot dr. OK, so we just plug
in here what we've got.
So this is equal to
the integral of--
well, the first coordinates
are 4x dx and the second
coordinates just give me
0-- so it's 4x dx.
And again, I need my bounds.
Well, I had-- over here--
I had 1 less than or equal to x
is less than or equal to 2.
So that's the integral
between 1 and 2.
4x--
integrate that-- and I get 2x
squared between 1 and 2, which
is equal to 8 minus 2, or 6.
All right.
So let's see what we've got.
So we had--
back here--
we had our curve C, which
we split into the two
parts, C1 and C2.
And we wanted to know what the
integral over C was, and we've
separately computed the
integral over C1.
And we computed that to be 24.
And we computed the integral
over C2, and that was 6.
So the integral over the whole
curve of F dot dr is equal to
24 plus 6, which is 30.
OK.
So there's your answer
for the second part.
Now one thing I'd like you to
notice is that over this curve
C in part b--
over the whole curve
in part b--
we got that the integral
of this field F was 30.
And now if you remember, right
here, in the first part, in
part a, we computed the integral
over a different
curve that connected the
two same endpoints.
And we found that the integral
came out to 32.
So one thing you should take
away from this is that the
integral over a curve joining
two points can depend on which
curve you choose, right?
So we had two different curves
and we got two different
answers, even though
the two curves
connected the same points.
So that's interesting.
And the other thing to take
away from this is just the
general approach.
Which is that whenever you have
a problem like this, what
you want to do is you want
to take your curve--
so whether it be well, in part
a we had this straight line,
slanted line.
In part b where we had this
nice piecewise linear with
these vertical and horizontal
parts--
you want to break it into nice
pieces and parametrize them.
You know, sometimes you only
need one piece when it's an
easy-to-parametrize
curve like that.
Sometimes, if it has corners
or so on, you
might want more pieces.
Break it into pieces, choose a
nice parametrization, and that
reduces your problem just to
computing integrals, just like
we've done in Calculus
I-- in 18.01--
and then you just integrate.
All right.
I'll end there.