JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about line integrals
of vector fields.
And I have one problem here that
requires you to do two
line integrals of vector
fields on that subject.
So OK.
So in both problems, F is going
to be the vector field
of whose coordinates are xy and
x squared plus y squared.
And C is going to be the arc
of the parabola y equals x
squared that starts at the point
1, 1 and ends at the
point 2, 4.
All right?
So what I'd like you to do is
to compute the integral over
this curve C of F.dr in
two different ways.
So the first time, I'd like
you to use the natural
parametrization x equals
t, y equals t squared.
For me, at least, that's the
first parametrization that I
think of when I think
about this curve.
But I'd also like you to do
it again using a different
parametrization, using the
parametrization x equals e to
the t, y equals e to the 2t.
So this still parametrizes the
curve y equals x squared,
since e to the t squared
equals e to the 2t.
So why don't you pause the
video, have a go at computing
this integral using these two
different parametrizations,
come back, and we can work
it out together.
So let's get started.
We want to compute a line
integral of a vector field F.
So we know that the integral
over our curve C of F.dr--
well, usually we write--
F equals M, N. The two
components are M and N. So in
this case, this is going to be
equal to the integral over C
of M dx plus N dy.
Now, in our case, we
know what F is.
We know that F is the
vector field xy, x
squared plus y squared.
So this is equal to the integral
over C of xy dx, plus
x squared plus y squared dy.
And now we just need to plug
in for our two different
cases, into our
parametrizations, and this
will turn into an integral
that we can evaluate.
So let's have a look-see.
So in our first parametrization
over here, we
have x equals t and y
equals t squared.
And we want this parametrization
to go from the
points 1, 1 to the point 2, 4.
So that means that t--
x--
t is going from 1 to 2.
OK.
So I'm going to just write
equals, and continue on.
So in this first part, t is our
parameter, and it's going
from 1 to 2.
So xy is going to be t times
t squared, and dx is dt.
And then plus--
so x squared plus
y squared is--
t squared plus t
to the fourth.
And dy is times 2t dt,
since y is t squared.
All right.
So this is our integral.
And now it's straightforward
to compute.
This is single variable integral
of a polynomial, so
we might have some fraction
arithmetic in our future, but
nothing horrible.
So let's collect our dt's.
So this is the integral
from 1 to 2.
So here I've got 2t cubed
plus 2t to the fifth.
And here I have t cubed.
So that's 3t cubed plus
2t to the fifth dt.
OK, and so now we have
to evaluate.
So this is equal to-- let
me just continue it.
So 3t cubed becomes 3t
to the fourth over 4.
Plus 2t to the fifth becomes--
well, t to the sixth over 6--
2t to the sixth over 6, so
that's-- plus t to the sixth
over 3, between t
equals 1 and 2.
And let me just bring that
computation up here.
So that's equal to 3 times 16
over 4, plus 64 over 3, minus
3/4 plus 1/3.
OK, and now we gotta
work this out.
So this is maybe 12, and the
thirds give me 21, so that's
33 minus 3/4.
So that's 32 and 1/4, or 129
over 4, if you prefer.
OK, so that's going to
be our answer there.
So now let's go back and do it
again using this alternate
parametrization.
So in this alternate
parametrization, we had x
equal e to the t, and
y equal e to the 2t.
So in that case, that means that
dx --also x is e to the t
y equals 2t-- so our integral
that we want,
let me rewrite it.
Well, actually, let
me not rewrite it.
Let me just go back here
and take a look at it.
So we want the integral of F.dr,
and we know that that's
equal to the integral over C of
xy dx plus x squared plus y
squared dy.
So x is e to the t, y is e to
the 2t, so that means dx is
going to be e to the t dt
and dy is going to be
2e to the 2t dt.
So OK.
So we'll just have to plug
these things in.
So our integral--
maybe I'll give it a
name: What We Want.
WWW.
What We Want is equal to the
integral of, well we start
plugging in.
So xy dx is e to the t times e
to the 2t times, we said dx is
e to the t dt.
Plus, now x squared
plus y squared, so
that's e to the 2t--
that's x squared, plus
e to the 4t--
that's y squared--
times 2e to the 2t dt.
That's dy.
Whew.
OK.
But this integral is missing
something, right?
Because it needs to be
a definite integral.
Right now, I've written down
an indefinite integral.
So that's a problem.
So we need to think, what are
the bounds on this curve?
What are we integrating
from and to?
So let's go all the way
back and look at the
problem over here.
So this is the parametrization
of the curve, and we need it
to connect the points
1, 1 and 2, 4.
So we need to know which value
of t puts this parametrization
at the point 1, 1, and which
value of t puts it at the
point 2, 4.
Well, I think the easiest way
to do that is to solve this,
and we have t equals
natural log of x.
So natural log of 1 is 0,
and natural log of 2 is
natural log of 2.
So OK.
So we want t to go from
0 to natural log of 2.
To go from this point
to that one.
OK, so 0 to natural log of 2.
Let's remember that, and
come back over here
and put that in.
So we want this integral that
we're trying to compute using
this alternate parametrization--
we've already written down
what the integrand is--
but it's going to be the
integral, we just said, from 0
to the natural log of 2.
OK.
Great.
So now let's take this integral
and let's start
simplifying it.
So let's see.
This is an e to the t times e to
the 2t times e to the t, so
that's e to the 4t dt.
And here we have--
that looks like-- a 2e to the
4t plus 2e to the 6t dt.
So if we combine like terms, we
get the integral from 0 to
natural log of 2.
So we had an e to the 4t and a
2e to the 4t, so that's 3e to
the 4t plus 2e to the 6t dt.
OK, 3e to the 4t plus
2e to the 6t.
OK.
And this is also a
different-looking integral
than the one we had before, but
it's not a difficult one
to evaluate, because it's just
e to a constant times t dt.
Pretty straightforward
stuff, I think.
So what does it actually
give us?
Let me come up here and
write it up here.
So this is equal to--
all right, integrate
e to the 4t--
and you get e to the 4t over 4,
so this is 3/4 e to the 4t,
plus 2/6, so that's plus 1/3
e to the 6t, and we're
evaluating that between
0 and ln 2.
And I will leave it to you to
confirm that what you get when
you do this is you get exactly
129 over 4 when you plug in
these values and take
the difference.
So one thing to notice here is
that doing it with the second
parametrization, we
got 129 over 4.
Now, if you look back just right
here, you see that when
we did it with the first
parametrization, we also got
129 over 4.
Now this is a general
phenomenon, right?
The parametrization
doesn't change the
value of the line integral.
So when you have a line integral
of a vector field,
you can parametrize the curve
that you're integrating over
in a bunch of different ways.
I mean, in fact, infinitely
many different ways.
There are all sorts of different
choices, and they
all give the same answer.
They have to.
So no matter what
parametrization you choose,
you get the same number out for
the line integral over the
same curve of the same
vector field.
All right.
So what that means for you is
that when you're given just a
curve and a vector field and
you get to choose your
parametrization, you should
always just choose whatever
the nicest one is.
Because it doesn't matter which
one you choose, and
there's no reason
ever to choose
anything harder than necessary.
All right.
So now, I want to quickly
recap what we did.
So we had a curve and a vector
field F, and we were asked to
compute the line integral of
F.dr, and we did it two
different ways.
So in both cases, we used
the fact that F.dr
is M dx plus N dy.
We wrote that out using the
known values of M and N, and
using the known components of F.
And then we plugged in for
both cases.
In this case, we used that
first parametrization.
And then over to my left,
we used this second
parametrization that
I gave you.
And in both cases, that reduced
it to an integral in
terms of a single variable t
that was the parameter that we
could compute.
And the answer came out the same
both times, as it had to.
So one thing you can notice is
if you compare this with the
preceding lecture video, you'll
see that this curve and
vector field, they connect the
same points and it's the same
vector field, and these answers
both differ from both
of the answers in the preceding
recitation video.
So this is further illustration
that different
curves can give you different
values, but if you take the
same curve, different
parametrizations always have
to give you same values for that
line integral of the same
vector field.
I'll end there.