CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video I'd like us to
work on the following problem.
We're going to let capital D
denote the portion of the
solid sphere of radius 1 that's
centered at 0, 0, 1,
which also lies about
the plane z equal 1.
And then I'd like us to first
supply the limits for D in
spherical coordinates.
In other words, I want you to
determine the values for rho,
theta, and phi that will give us
all of D. And then, I would
like us to just set up the
integral for the average
distance of a point in
D from the origin.
So there are two parts
to this problem.
The first is to determine what
values of rho, theta, and phi
describe this solid region D.
And then second is just set up
the integral for the average
distance of a point in that
region from the origin.
So why don't you pause the
video, work on those, and then
when you're ready to see my
solutions, you can bring the
video back up.
OK, welcome back.
Well, I would say from looking
at this problem, actually part
a is potentially a little bit
more hazardous for some of us
then part b.
Once we know the bounds that
describe D, it's not too hard
to set up this integral.
So the hard part of this problem
is understanding how
to write this solid region D
in spherical coordinates.
But it's actually really not
that hard either, so I'm going
to try and take us through
it in a reasonable way.
So the first thing: I'm going
to draw a very rough picture
of the region so we understand
what it looks like.
So in order to do part a.
And if you did not do this, I
would highly recommend that
next time you encounter such a
problem, you begin by drawing
yourself a picture.
Even if it's not a great
picture, it will give you some
intuition about what's
happening.
So let me first draw the axes.
And ultimately what I have--
say here, is the point
(0, 0, 1)--
I have a sphere that's looking
in the z-y plane.
It looks something like this.
And so it has this depth here.
And that's the solid sphere
I want to be considering.
And then I'm going to be
removing the bottom half.
I'm only going to be looking at
the part that is above the
z equals 1 plane.
So actually it's going to be
all of the circular slices
that are in the top
half in the upper
hemisphere of this sphere.
And so it's this solid
region there.
That's D.
And what I want to do
is to determine rho
and theta and phi.
Actually, the theta is
the easy one, right?
Because theta at each value
here, I go all the way around
in the theta direction.
At any given height or radius,
I want to go all the way
around in the theta direction
from 0 to 2 pi.
So my theta bounds are
the easy ones.
I'm covering 0 to
2 pi in theta.
Because if I cut off the back
half of the sphere, I want to
only have a restricted
value of theta.
But because I'm covering all
the way around and my
restriction is only in the
bottom half, my theta values
haven't changed.
So theta is easy: 0 and 2 pi.
Now the harder ones are going
to be rho and phi.
But in fact, actually, phi
is not that hard either.
I notice phi is the angle that
I make from the z-axis to any
given point.
So I notice that I certainly am
including the point where
phi is 0, and then I'm going
all the way down to a point
out here, which is a 45 degree
angle with the z-axis.
So phi is also easy.
It's actually just between
0 and pi over 4.
And the rho will be the
slightly harder part.
So that's really the only really
tricky part in this
problem is determining
the rho value.
Now, the rho value, to get the
outer boundary, we'll look at
that part first.
Well, the boundary of this
sphere here has a certain
equation in x, y, and z
that we know, right?
It's x squared plus y squared
plus the quantity z minus 1
squared equals 1.
I mean, that's just the equation
for a sphere of
radius 1 centered
at (0, 0, 1).
So I'm going to write that here,
and we're going to show
how we can manipulate that.
Right?
x squared plus y squared
is r squared.
r squared is rho squared
sine squared phi.
So I can replace this by rho
squared sine squared phi.
If you didn't know that
immediately, you could make
the substitution for x and y in
spherical coordinates, and
it simplifies to this.
So either way, if you didn't
know r squared was this, you
can get it from just doing
the substitution.
And then z is going to
be rho cosine phi.
So here, I'm going to have
a rho cosine phi minus 1
quantity squared equals 1.
This in the spherical
coordinates is describing the
boundary of this entire
sphere, right?
And so I can actually
simplify this.
It's not too hard.
If I square this, I get
a little cancellation.
And then because I want
my rho to be--
I'm assuming in this region,
rho is greater than 0--
I can do a little
simplification.
I come up with the fact that rho
is equal to 2 cosine phi.
And let's describe exactly
where that is.
That's the entire boundary
of this entire sphere is
described by rho is equal
to 2 cosine phi.
And so I want to think about
what my bounds are for rho.
Actually, I'm going to grab
a piece of colored chalk.
If I start at the origin, I
think about what is rho?
So say this is a point on the
boundary of the sphere.
I am going to start my rho
value-- whatever it is when it
hits the plane z equals 1--
and I'm going to stop
it when it hits the
boundary of this sphere.
So my outer boundary for rho
is going to be this value.
It's going to be determined
by phi, right?
And now I have to determine
my inner boundary, right?
And my inner boundary is
actually quite simple.
It's a very simple
geometric thing.
And so my inner boundary deals
with the fact that if this is
my plane z equals 1, and I look
at this triangle I make
right here.
This angle down here, the bottom
angle is phi, and this
is a right angle, and the rho
value I'm interested in is
this hypotenuse, right?
I need to figure out what the
length of this is right here.
And you can see it right away
from just the fact that phi is
this angle here, you get
rho is secant phi.
So the bottom boundary comes
from just simple geometry.
You get this length is 1 here.
So you get rho is equal
to secant phi, right?
This length here is 1, this is
the rho I'm interested in--
the blue part here-- and so rho
is equal to secant phi is
the lower bound.
And it's equal to 2 cosine phi
at the upper bound, OK?
And the thing I want to be
careful of is I'm not supposed
to include--
it won't matter for
the integral--
but I'm not supposed to
include the plane.
Let me write this,
and make sure.
Rho is going to be greater than
secant phi and it's going
to be less than or equal
to 2 cosine phi, right?
Right?
So let me double-check and
make sure I didn't make a
geometry mistake here,
just to be sure.
This picture tells me
that cosine phi is
equal to 1 over rho.
That's good.
So rho is equal to 1
over cosine phi.
So I get secant phi there.
So my rho values start at the
secant phi length and they go
to the 2 cosine phi length.
I know maybe I'm beating a dead
horse here, but I want to
make sure we understand
where the rho
values are coming from.
So actually, I have all
the bounds I need now.
I have the theta bounds, and I
have the phi bounds, and the
rho bounds.
Now you notice that theta and
phi don't depend on the other
variables, but rho
depends on phi.
So we're going to have to
integrate that first. So now
we can deal with part b.
Part b-- let's come back
over and remind
ourselves what it said--
said set up the integral for
the average distance of a
point in D from the origin.
So I'm taking the average
value of a function.
What is that function
I'm averaging?
How do I find the distance
from the origin?
Well, the distance from the
origin is a great function to
have in spherical coordinates,
because it's just rho.
So the function I'm supposed
to average over is the
function rho.
In spherical coordinates,
that's the function.
So let me write down what we're
going to have here.
So in part b, the average
distance is going to equal 1
divided by the volume of D times
the triple integral over
D of the function rho dV, OK?
So now I have to write dV in the
spherical coordinates, and
I have to write D in the
spherical coordinates bounds.
And then I know I have to figure
out the volume of D. So
we're going to figure out each
of these things, and then
we'll be done.
All right.
So first, what is
the volume of D?
Well, the volume of D, let's
think about what it is.
It's a sphere of radius 1.
And so the volume of a sphere of
radius 1 is 4/3 pi r cubed.
And I want half of that.
So I want 2/3.
Since my radius is 1, I just
have to do 2/3 pi.
So the first part is 1
divided by 2/3 pi.
That's the volume of a
half-sphere of radius 1.
And now let's integrate.
I'll leave a little space
to write my bounds.
I'm going to write the bounds
last, after I have everything
in order over here. dV is
rho squared sine phi d
rho d theta d phi.
So I'm going to end up with a
rho cubed sine phi d rho d
theta d phi, right?
The dV gave me an extra rho
squared and a sine phi.
That whole part is dV. And then
I keep one rho from the
fact that the distance
function is rho.
And so I get a rho
cubed there.
So hopefully that makes sense.
Now for d rho, I know the bounds
are secant phi to 2
cosine phi.
For d theta, my bounds
are 0 to 2 pi.
And for d phi, my bounds
were 0 to pi over 4.
I didn't make you evaluate it,
I'm just making you set it up.
That actually is the solution
we wanted for part b.
I wanted to average the distance
from any point in D
to the origin.
So I just took the average value
of the function rho over
that region D. And so that's
how you finish that up.
And so in this problem,
basically we want you to get
really familiar with how to do
some things in these spherical
coordinates, which are sometimes
a little hard to do.
But if you noticed, what we were
doing in trying to figure
out the bounds-- in
particular, trying
to figure out rho--
we took what we knew in the x-,
y-, z-coordinates about
certain relationships, and then
we replaced the x-, y-,
z-values by the values in terms
of rho and theta and
phi, and you can simplify to
figure out the relationships
you have between rho and
theta and phi for
the boundary value.
So that was one of
the techniques
we were using there.
And hopefully, the geometric
understanding of why these
angles go from 0 to 2 pi and
0 to pi over 4 is clear.
And actually, the fact that this
is rho equals 2 cosine
phi should remind you of the
two-dimensional case where you
had some problem like r
equals 2 cosine theta.
And that drew a circle
off-center from the origin.
It's the analogous thing
happening here.
Maybe I should stop there before
I say too many things.
But again, the object of this
was just to get really
comfortable with spherical
coordinates, and I hope it's
helped you.
I'll stop there.