DAVID SHIROKOFF: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, I'd like to tackle a
problem on direction fields.
So given a differential
equation, y prime equals
negative y divided by x squared
plus y squared, we're
asked to first sketch
the direction field.
And then secondly, given the
curve that goes through y 0
equal to 1, we're asked several
questions about it.
Why is y of x greater than
0 for x greater than 0?
And then, why is y of
x decreasing for x
greater than 0?
So I'll let you think about
this for a moment
and I'll get back.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
OK, so to start off this
problem, we're asked to sketch
the direction field.
Now when asked to sketch a
direction field, the first
thing to do is to look at
a couple isoclines.
So what is an isocline?
Well, it's a curve where the
derivative y prime is equal to
m, which is some constant.
So what are the isoclines for
this differential equation?
Well, it would be minus y
divided by x squared plus y
squared equals m.
Now, of particular interest,
there's a very specialize
isocline, which is usually
the easiest to plot.
And that's a nullcline.
And this is just a special case
where m is equal to 0.
So what's the nullcline
for this ODE?
Well, when m is equal to 0, the
only way that y prime can
be 0 is when y is 0.
So the nullcline for this
ODE is y equals 0.
Now, for more general isoclines,
we're left with
this relation between x and y.
And we can massage this
expression to see exactly what
the isoclines are.
So specifically, I'm going to
multiply through by x squared
plus y squared, and I'm
going to divide by m.
And we see that we have a
quadratic in x and y.
And we have one linear term.
So whenever we have a relation
like this and we want to
understand what it looks like,
typically the approach is just
to complete the square.
So I'm going to bring the 1 over
m y to the other side of
the equation.
And I'm going to combine
it with y squared to
complete the square.
And when we do this, we obtain
the following equation.
And we recognize this equation
as the equation for a circle.
Specifically, it's a circle
that's centered at x is equal
to 0 and y is equal to
negative 1 over 2m.
And in addition, the circle
has a radius r squared is
equal to 1 over 4m squared,
which means its radius is 1
over 2 times the absolute
value of m.
OK, so why don't we
take a look and
plot a couple isoclines?
So as I mentioned before,
typically the first isocline
that we should plot is the
nullcline, which is
m is equal to 0.
And we know that this
is y is equal to 0.
So all along the line y is equal
to 0, I'm just going to
dry dashes that correspond to
a slope of y is equal to 0.
From the other isoclines, we
just have to pick some values
of m and start plotting.
So I'll take the value m
is equal to negative 1.
And when m is equal to negative
1, we have a circle
which is centered at 0 and
1/2 with radius 1/2.
So here's 1/2.
Here's 1.
And at every point along the
circle, we just draw a little
slope of negative 1.
So at every point along this
curve, the solution has slope
negative 1.
Now, in addition, we can also
get another circle, which is
centered at negative 1/2.
And this corresponds to
the isocline of m is
equal to plus 1.
And every point on this circle
has slope plus 1.
Those should all be the same.
And now we can pick some
other values of m.
So for example, m
is equal to 2.
If m is equal to 2, then we
have a circle which is
centered at negative
1/4 and radius 1/4.
So it might look something
like this.
And m is equal to negative
2 might look
something like this.
So this is m is equal
to negative 2.
This is m is equal to 2.
And the slope on this curve
is going to be steeper.
It's going to be negative 2.
And the same goes
for this circle.
And then lastly, I can draw a
sketch of m is equal to 3/4,
which would go up something
like this.
Sorry, m is equal
to negative 3/4.
And that would have a slightly
weaker slope like this.
So notice how the collection of
isoclines are a family of
circles that all are tangent
to the origin.
And in fact, if we think about
it, the nullcline, the m equal
0 line, is actually, in some
sense, a limit circle where we
take the radius in the center
going to infinity.
So as the circles become larger
and larger, they tend
to approach this line
y equals 0.
So this concludes part one.
So for part two, we're now asked
several questions about
the curve which goes through
y of 0 is equal to 1.
So I'll just sketch
what this solution
curve might look like.
And it's going to start off
at a slope of negative 1.
And then it's going to hit these
circles, which have a
steeper slope.
And then eventually it's going
to go through the circles with
a steeper slope and come back
to the circle that has slope
negative 1.
And eventually, decay
outwards.
So this is what the solution
curve might look like.
I'm just sketching this to set
up parts 2a and 2b here.
OK, so why is y of x always
bigger than 0 for x
greater than 0?
Well, we see that this solution
curve stays in the
upper half plane.
And we note that y is equal to
0, which is the nullcline, is
actually a very special curve.
Not only is it the nullcline,
but it's actually a solution
to the differential equation.
So if we look back at the
differential equation, we see
that y is equal to 0
has 0 derivative.
And the right-hand side
of the differential
equation is also 0.
So this is not only a nullcline,
but it's a solution
to the differential equation.
Note that this is extremely
special.
In no way does every nullcline
have to be a solution to a
differential equation.
But in this case,
we get lucky.
Now we know from the theory of
ODEs that solution curves
can't cross.
So a solution curve that starts
in the upper half plane
can't cross another solution,
which in this case is the y
equals 0 curve.
Hence, it must be bounded in the
upper half plane for all x
bigger than 0.
The second part, why is y
of x decreasing for x
greater than 0?
Well, what we have to look at--
so I'll just write in
here part 2.
We have to look at the
sign of y prime.
Now y prime is equal to negative
y divided by x
squared plus y squared.
So as I've just argued, a
solution that starts in the
upper half plane and goes
through the point y of 0 is
equal to 1, stays in the upper
half plane for all
x bigger than 0.
What this means is that the
solution curve has y bigger
than 0 for all x
bigger than 0.
So that means the numerator
is always positive.
The denominator is also
always positive.
So we have negative a positive
number divided
by a positive number.
And so this quantity is always
going to be less than 0.
So for x bigger than 0, y prime
is always going to be
less than 0.
Hence, the solution that starts
at y of 0 is equal to 1
is going to monotonically decay
to y is equal to 0.
OK?
So this concludes the problem.
Now just to recap, we
were given an ODE.
The standard approach when
sketching direction fields is
to pick a few nullclines.
Or to pick a few isoclines.
And specifically pick
the nullcline.
Sketch the isoclines.
And then, if you're asked to
plot any integral curves or
solutions to the differential
equation, you just simply
connect the dots.
OK, so I'd like to conclude
here, and I'll
see you next time.