PROFESSOR: The isoclines
applet.
Let's explore graphs of
solutions of differential
equations using direction
fields and isoclines.
The first thing to do is to
choose an equation from the
pull down menu here.
And for this demonstration, I
will choose the differential
equation y prime equals
y squared minus x.
In the window at left, you can
see the direction or slope
field drawn.
This is a representation of
the differential equation.
When I move the cursor over this
window, a readout of the
x- and y-coordinates shows
up on the right
hand side of the screen.
This is very useful in
making measurements.
If I click on the graphing
window, the solution through
the point that I've clicked
on is drawn.
This is an interesting function,
probably one you've
never seen before.
Certainly, it's not an
elementary function.
Clicking some more points makes
more solutions appear.
In fact, every point on this
plane has exactly one solution
through it.
This is the meaning of the
existence and uniqueness
theorem for differential
equations.
Now, let's clear the solutions
using this button down here,
Clear Solutions button.
You see a blank screen again.
You can control how the slope
field looks by using this
Slope Field toggle here.
You can make them blank,
or bright for a
display, for example.
Or the way it was originally.
And I think I'm going to turn
it off altogether, so now
we're faced with
a blank screen.
Now, how would you go about
drawing some solutions to this
differential equation by hand
just knowing the differential
equation and this
blank screen?
Well, isoclines give you a good
way of doing this, and
they reveal things about the
qualitative behavior of the
differential equation as well.
An isocline is the subset of
the plane where the slope
field takes on a given value.
I can choose that value, m,
using this slider here.
And when I click here and move
this, the isocline with the
given value of m is drawn
in yellow on the screen.
And you can see the value of the
slope field drawn as well.
So here is the value is 1, and
the slope field is given by
little intervals of value
1 of slope 1.
I can choose that value using
the slider marked m.
If I click on the handle and
drag it, you see the isocline
for the corresponding value
of m drawn on the screen.
And on the isocline is also
drawn the direction fields.
So when m is 2, the direction
field has slope 2.
And when I drag the slider back
down to 0, the isocline
value 0 has a horizontal
direction field
marked along it.
Each one of these is a curve
where y squared minus x equals
m, or x equals y squared
minus m.
This is a parabola lying on its
side with the vertex at x
equals negative m.
Let's draw out to the isocline
for value 1, for example.
I've now released the
mouse key, and the
isocline is left behind.
And I can easily draw in some
other isoclines as well by
clicking on different
values of m and
releasing the mouse key.
So once you've drawn several
of these isoclines on the
plane, it's pretty easy to
envision what the solutions
will look like to this curve.
You just have to thread your
way along the part of the
direction field that
you've drawn.
I can check that by clicking
on the screen and drawing a
solution in.
This is quite easy
to do by hand.
It's easy to draw the isoclines
and then sketch a
solution accordingly.
But you can see other things
as well from isoclines.
I'm going to clear all of these
and redraw the m equals
0 isocline on the screen.
And I think I'm going
to redraw the
slope field as well.
Now, critical points of a
function occur where the
derivative is equal to 0.
And the derivative is exactly
what we know about the
solution to a differential
equation.
So the critical points, the
minima or maxima of solutions
to this differential equation,
occur when the solution
crosses the m equals
0 isocline, also
known as the nullcline.
All maxima and minima of
solutions to this differential
equation occur along this
particular yellow parabola.
I can check that by drawing in
some solutions, and you can
see that these functions have
maxima which occur just along
that parabola.
If the solutions miss the
parabola, they don't have any
critical points.
Another thing you can see from
this picture is that
apparently many of the solutions
to this differential
equation cluster near to this
branch of the nullcline.
And maybe we can see why this is
using the isocline picture.
I'm going to clear the solutions
now to make the
picture clearer and draw in one
more isocline, namely the
m equals minus 1 isocline.
Now, suppose that a solution
finds itself below the m
equals minus 1 isocline.
So it's in here somewhere.
Can it ever across the m equals
minus 1 isocline?
Once it's below it, can
it ever cross it?
Well, it's below it.
So if it crosses the m equals
minus 1 isocline, it must
cross it with a slope which is
bigger than the slope of that
yellow curve.
But when it crosses it, it
also has to cross it with
slope minus 1, because this is
the m equals minus 1 isocline.
But the slope of this yellow
parabola is bigger than minus
1 along here, and so
the solution curve
can never cross it.
Similarly, suppose that you have
a solution which is above
the nullcline.
Can it ever cross
the nullcline?
Well, if it crosses the
nullcline, it must cross it
from above, so when it crosses
it, its slope must be less
than the slope of the nullcline,
which is negative
as you can see.
But when the solution crosses
the nullcline, it must cross
it with slope 0.
And so, that can't happen.
And so you see, if a solution
is between those two
isoclines, then it stays between
them forever more.
It's trapped between them.
This is called a funnel.
It's trapped between these two
things, and gets closer and
closer because these two
isoclines become asymptotic as
x gets large.
These are called
fences as well.
Once a solution is in here, it
can't cross either of these
two fences.
This let's us estimate
the value of
solutions for large x.
These solutions, anyway,
for large x.
For example, if x is equal to
100, the solution has to be
bigger than the value of this
parabola, which is minus 10,
and less than the value along
this parabola, which is minus
the square root of 99.
So you get a very good estimate
for the value of
solutions for large x from these
kinds of considerations.
One more thing you can see
from this applet is this.
If a solution is well above the
nullcline, cline, it gets
caught in this powerful updraft
and goes off to infinity.
In fact, all these solutions
become tangent to
the vertical lines.
They don't continue
for all large x.
They blow up in finite time.
On the other hand, if you're
just a little bit smaller than
these solutions, then you get
solutions which cross the
nullcline, get trapped into this
parabolic region and fall
down in between our funnel,
down here, and so become
asymptotic to minus the square
root of x when x gets large.
There's just one solution which
doesn't do either of
these very different behaviors,
and it's right
along here.
It becomes asymptotic to the
positive branch of the
parabola, and every solution
above it blows up in finite
time, and every solution below
it falls down and becomes
asymptotic to minus the
square root of x.
This special solution--
which doesn't do either of
those two behaviors, but
continues to exist for all
positive values of x and
become asymptotic to the
square root of x--
this is called the separatrix.
It separates solutions showing
two very different types of
behavior, the ones that
fall down and the
ones that blow up.
Well, these are just a few of
the things you can understand
using this applet.
Play with different
menu items.
Open a copy of this applet
in your browser window.
Play with some other
menu items.
Maybe the default item at
the bottom of this pull
down menu down here.
Are there funnels?
Are there separatrices?
What happens to solutions as x
goes to minus infinity rather
than x equals plus infinity?
Where are the critical points of
solutions of this equation?