JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about critical points
of functions, how to find them
using the first derivatives
and how to classify them using
the second derivative test. So
I have a question here
for you about that.
So we have a function w.
It's a function of two variables
x and y, and it's
given by this polynomial
function of them.
So w equals x cubed minus
3xy plus y cubed.
So what I'd like you to do is
to first find the critical
values of this function and
then classify them.
Are they minima or maxima or
saddle points using the second
derivative test?
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time
to work that out.
Come back and we can work
it out together.
Hopefully, you had some luck
working out the solution to
this question.
Let's have a go at it.
So in order to find the critical
points, we need to
look at the first derivative.
So the critical points are the
points where both partial
derivatives or all partial
derivatives, if we had a
function of more variables,
are equal to zero.
So we need to look at
the first partials.
So the first partials here,
w sub x, the partial with
respect to x, well, it's just
a polynomial so it's easy to
compute those partial
derivatives.
It's going to be 3x squared
minus 3y, and then the last
term gets killed because we
treat y as a constant, and so
we want that to be
equal to zero.
And similarly, we want the first
partial with respect to
y, w sub y, to be
equal to zero.
And so that's minus 3x plus
3y squared equals 0.
Now, luckily, these are fairly
simple equations, so to solve
them, we could, for example,
take the first equation and we
could solve the first equation
for y in terms of x.
So that'll give us y
equals x squared.
And now if we plug y equals
x squared into this second
equation, well, we get minus
3x plus 3x squared squared.
So that's x to the fourth is
equal 0, and we can divide out
by that 3, so that means
minus x plus x to the
fourth equals 0.
Well, OK, so we could have x
equal to 0, or you can divide,
and then you get x cubed
equals 1, and that has
solution x equals 1.
So x equals 0 or 1.
Those are the only solutions
to this equation.
And then the corresponding
y-values, well, we know y is
equal to x squared, so this
gives us critical points when
x is 0, y is 0 and when
x is 1, y is 1.
So this function has
two critical
points: 0, 0 and 1, 1.
Now we need to figure out
whether those critical points
are minima, maxima,
saddle points, sum
of several of those.
So in order to do that, we're
going to use this nice tool
that we have: the second
derivative test. So in order
to apply the second derivative
test, the first thing I need
is the second derivatives.
So let's compute them.
So the second--
let's do the xx first. So we
take our first partial, 3x
squared minus 3y, and we take
another partial of it with
respect to x.
So that's, in this case, that's
just going to be 6x.
And then we've got the other
pure second partial yy, so we
go back over here, and we look
at what our first partial wy
was, and then we take another
partial of this with respect
to y, so that's just
going to be 6y.
And then we have the mixed
partials wxy and wyx, which,
of course, are equal to each
other whenever our function is
nicely behaved like
a polynomial.
So wxy, we just take the two
mixed partials and--
OK, so we take the partial of
wx with respect to y, for
example, and that gives
us minus 3.
So these are our three partials,
and then often, we,
you know, call this one A and
this one C and this one B. I
guess I kind of mixed up the
order a little bit there.
So we look at these three
expressions, and now we want
to look at what sometimes people
call the discriminant,
although I don't know
if Professor
Auroux used that term.
So we want to study what the
expression AC minus B squared
is, so we want to know is this
positive, is this negative at
the critical points.
So at the critical
points, right?
This is important.
At the critical points.
So let's do the point 1, 1
first. So at 1, 1, we have A
is equal to what we put in--
x is 1, y is 1 into the
expression for A here--
and that just gives a 6.
We put x 1, y 1 into the
expression for C, and that
also gives a 6, we put x 1, y
1 into the expression for B,
and that gives us minus 3.
So A is 6, B is minus 3, C is
6, so AC minus B squared is
equal to, well its equal to
36 minus 9, so that's 27.
And, in particular,
it's positive.
So when this is positive, that
means we either have a maximum
or a minimum.
So in order to figure out
whether we have a maximum or a
minimum, we check the sign of
A. So in this case, the sign
of A is positive.
A is a positive number.
So when you have that AC minus B
squared is positive and A is
positive, that means
you have a minimum.
So the critical point
1, 1 is a local
minimum for this function.
All right.
Now we can do the same thing for
the critical point 0, 0.
So recall A was 6x, so at 0,
0, A is equal to 0, B was
equal to negative 3 everywhere,
and C was equal to
6y, so at 0, 0, that's 6 times
0 so that's also 0.
So then our quantity that we
want to look at, AC minus B
squared, well, that's 0 times 0
minus 9, so that's equal to
negative 9.
And negative 9 is less than 0,
so when AC minus B squared is
less than 0, that means we
have a saddle point.
So in this case, the second
derivative test was able
successfully to distinguish what
kinds of critical points
we had, and it found that the
first critical point 1, 1 was
a minimum and that the second
critical point 0, 0 was a
saddle point.
So just to quickly rehash what
we did, we had a function.
Back over here, we started
with this function w.
We had a nice formula for it.
We computed its first
derivatives.
We set them both equal
to zero and we solved
that system of equations.
So we found two solutions to
that system of equations, and
those two solutions are the
critical points, the points
where both partial derivatives
are equal to zero.
So when you have the two
critical points, then you want
to apply the second derivative
test to figure out for each
critical point whether it's
a saddle point, a
minimum or a maximum.
So we took our two critical
points 1, 1 and 0, 0, and at
those points, we evaluated
the second derivative.
So A is the xx second
derivative.
B is the mixed partial wxy,
and C is the yy second
derivative.
So we evaluate those expressions
at the points in
question, and then we look
at AC minus B squared.
And then the sign of AC minus
B squared, if it's negative,
that gives us a saddle point.
If it's positive, that gives
us either a maximum or a
minimum, and we check which one
by looking at the sign of
A. So here A was positive, so
we got a minimum at 1, 1.
So I'll stop there.