CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, we want to work
on using the change of
variables technique.
In particular, we're going to
look at the following problem.
It says, using the change of
variables, u is equal to x
squared minus y squared, and v
is equal to y divided by x.
Supply the limits and integrand
for the following
integral, which is the double
integral over region R of 1
over x squared, dxdy.
And R is the infinite region in
the first quadrant that is
both under the curve y equals 1
over x, and to the right of
the curve x squared minus
y squared equals 1.
So this is a challenging
problem.
Again, I want to point out we
just want to find the limits
and the integrand.
You don't actually have to
compute the integral.
But it is going to be tough,
but stick with it.
Pause the video, give it your
best shot-- hopefully you find
the appropriate limits
and integrand--
and then when you feel
comfortable, bring the video
back up, and I'll show
you how I do it.
OK.
Welcome back.
So once again, what we want to
do is this change of variables
problem where we've defined
u to be x squared minus y
squared, v to be y divided by
x, and we have this region
that is in the first quadrant
and it's under the curve y
equals 1 divided by x and it's
to the right of the curve x
squared minus y squared
equals 1.
And we want to compute the
limits and integrand for that
particular integral.
So what I'm going to do to try
and make this as organized as
possible is I'm going to try,
first to graph the region R--
to figure out what the region
R is in the xy plane.
Then I'm going to try and figure
out what the region R
is mapped to in the uv plane.
So what it looks like
in the uv plane.
That will give me my limits.
And then I'm going to try and
determine the Jacobian.
And then I will determine from
that and the fact that I
started with 1 divided by x
squared as my function I was
integrating, I will put
those two together to
figure out the integrand.
So there are a bunch of steps
to these problems. But the
first one, again is I'm going
to graph the region R.
So I'm going to give you a very
rough sketch over here of
the region R. And I know it's
in the first quadrant and I
know it's infinite.
I was already told that.
OK.
So in the xy plane, the region
R is below the curve y
equals 1 over x.
So let me draw that curve.
Again, this is very rough.
This is a rough sketch.
I'm putting up no scale
on purpose.
I'll put in one value, maybe,
in this whole thing.
OK?
And so this is the curve
y equals one over x.
And then I need the curve which
is part of the hyperbola
that is x squared minus
y squared equals 1.
So I'll draw in the part
we need, which looks
roughly like this.
Something like that.
Again, this is not meant to be
an exact graph, but to give
you an idea of what the
region looks like.
And the only thing I'm going to
mention is that this point
we know is x equals
1 and y equals 0.
So the region we're interested
in that is both to the right
of x squared minus y squared
equals 1 and below y equals 1
over x and in the first quadrant
is exactly this
region I'm shading here.
So we want to understand what
the values of u and v are
along these bounds.
We need to understand where this
region maps to when I do
the change of variables in order
to understand what the
limits are.
So let me put the graph of this
region in the uv plane so
that we can really understand
what our bounds are.
And I know already
where it's going.
So I'm going to just make the
first quadrant, because I know
this is going into the
first quadrant.
So it doesn't always work that
something in the first
quadrant maps into the first
quadrant, but in this case, I
already did the work,
so I know it does.
So let me point out a few
things about where
this region R maps.
The first thing I want to point
out is that we actually
know that this curve under
the change of variables
maps to u equals 1.
Because if you remember,
u is equal to x
squared minus y squared.
So this whole curve is going
to map to u equals 1.
Now, I don't want the whole
curve for my region.
I only want this little
piece of it.
So I'm going to have--
in my uv plane--
I'm going to have some
segment at 1.
And actually, I'll just know
that it's some part of the
line u equals 1 is going
to show up in there.
But if you notice, I know where
it starts right away.
Because at x equal 1, y equals
zero, if I look at what v is--
if we come back here and
remember what v is-- at x
equal 1, y equals 0-- v is 0.
And so my starting point on this
segment --if we come back
here-- my starting point
on this segment is
actually also at 1, 0.
OK?
So I know there's some point
right here that maps down to
here where the segment
will stop.
I'll find that point later,
algebraically.
Right?
And then now we need to figure
out where these two curves go.
And then we can get a picture,
and then we'll figure out what
that point is, and we'll
understand all the limits.
So the first thing I want to
point out is along this curve,
we have y equals 0 and
x is non-zero.
And just to help ourselves, I'm
going to rewrite what the
change of variables is here,
so I don't have to keep
walking over to the
other side.
Our change of variables was u is
equal to x squared minus y
squared, and v was equal
to y divided by x.
So this whole curve
has y equals 0.
So what happens to u and what
happens to v along that curve?
Well, u is going to be
x squared, and v is
going to equal 0.
And so the point of this,
really, is-- that even though
in u, this curve maybe is
mapping at a different speed
in some form to this
curve here--
it still it's just taking that
segment goes, or that
infinitely long ray goes to an
infinitely long ray here along
the u axis.
And again, that's because along
this ray, y equals 0.
And so v is equal to 0
everywhere on that ray and u
is positive-- it's equal
to x squared.
OK?
So I'm going to move the u out
of the way, because we're
going to say this is part of
the region, or that's one
bound of the region.
And now I have to figure out
where this curve goes.
This curve is slightly more
complicated, but I can still
figure it out.
So I'm going to show you how I
do that sort of algebraically.
That curve-- if you notice, if
you remember-- is y equals 1
divided by x.
So that means that
on that curve--
let me even write it down-- on
y equals 1 divided by x, v is
equal to 1 divided by
x divided by x.
So v is equal to 1 divided
by x squared, right?
And then what does that
mean about u?
u, then, is equal to--
well, x squared is 1 divided
by v, and then y squared,
because y squared on that curve
is just 1 divided by x
squared, is v. So let me just
make sure we all followed that
one more time.
We're looking at where the curve
y equals 1 over x goes
in the change of variables,
right?
So that's the top
curve up here.
y equals 1 over x is the top
curve of our region R. So we
want to know where that goes.
Well, on y equals 1 over x, v
is exactly equal to 1 over x
squared, because v-- we
know-- is y over x.
So if I just substitute in for
y, I get 1 over x squared.
Now, if I look at this
relationship, this means x
squared is equal to 1 over v.
So in terms of u, x squared
becomes 1 over v. And
then y squared--
which is 1 over x squared--
become v. So that curve is u
equals 1 over v minus v.
Now that curve, roughly,
is going to look
something like this.
And it might seem strange.
The thing is, I'm graphing this
in the uv plane, and I'm
writing what looks like u as a
function of v, and so it's
sort of turned around from
how you usually see
these things written.
But this is the equation that
describes this curve.
And that is sufficient to
understand, because when we
use, determine our bounds, we
can determine our bounds from
u equals 0 now, to u equals 1
over v minus v. So we now have
the bounds in u.
We're actually doing
quite well.
So we have this region.
We now have the bounds
completely in u.
u is going from u equals 0 to u
equals 1 over v minus v. But
the problem is now we don't know
the bounds in v. We don't
know what the bounds are in v,
and so we have to be a little
bit careful.
So actually, no.
I think I was wrong.
It's not 0, is it?
I said that twice now, and
that was incorrect.
u is going from 1, to 1 over
v minus v. So I apologize.
Because the slices of u are
going from whatever the
u-value starts-- which is
at the value 1-- and
it's coming this way.
So I apologize.
I was moving my arm like I was
doing the v-values, but I
actually wanted to
do the u-values.
So I want to go from
where u starts--
which is at u equals 1--
to where u stops-- which is when
it hits the curve 1 over
v minus v equals u.
So hopefully I didn't confuse
anyone by that.
I'm glad I caught it, then.
OK, so now we understand
the bounds in u.
And then to understand the
bounds in v, all we need to
understand is what is the
v-value at this point.
So once I know the v-value at
this point, then I'm done with
the bounds.
So let's see if we
can find that.
Well, the v-value at that point
is going to be at the
point where these two
curves intersect.
So let's see if we can do a
little algebra to understand
what that will look like.
So let me point out that where
those curves intersect, I have
the equation x squared minus 1
over x squared is equal to 1.
And if I want to find x-values
that satisfy this, I'm also
looking for x-values that
satisfy x to the fourth minus
1 is equal to x squared, which
I can rewrite as x to the
fourth minus x squared minus
1 is equal to 0.
So I can actually use the
quadratic formula on this in
terms of x squared.
So what I get is I get x
squared is equal to 1--
I get plus or minus root 5--
over 2.
And if you look at it, the one
you're actually interested
in-- you can figure this out
pretty quickly-- is the one
that is plus.
OK?
I want the one that is
plus root 5 over 2.
So then that means x is the
square root of this quantity
at that point, right?
Or I could actually think
about it this way.
Let me point out this. v is
equal to 1 over x squared at
that point, because it's on
that curve where we were
talking about y equals
1 over x.
So v is 1 over x squared.
So 1 over x squared is just
1 over this quantity.
So it's the reciprocal
of this.
It's also negative 1 plus
root 5, over 2.
You can check that
if you need to.
But I will write it down this
way as the following: this is
the point 1 comma a.
And if I come over here, I
will denote a will equal
negative 1 plus root
5, over 2.
And that's really just 1
divided by x squared.
So let me point that out again,
that a is equal to 1
divided by x squared at the
point of intersection.
So hopefully you can
see all that.
So that tells us our
bounds completely.
We still have some work to do.
So I'm going to put in the
bounds and I'm going to leave
an empty space.
Actually, no.
I won't do that, because
this can get a
little messy and confusing.
So I'm just going to do the
Jacobian, and then we'll
figure it all out and write the
answer right at the end,
so there's no confusion.
But hopefully you see at this
point that we have the bounds.
We know that u goes from 1, to
1 over v minus v. And v goes
from 0 up to a, where a is the
value I've written here.
So we know the bounds.
So now we have to figure
out the integrand.
So let's first compute
the Jacobian, OK?
So now we're looking at del u,
v, del x, y using the notation
we've seen in class.
And so del uv, del xy is going
to be the determinant of the
following matrix:
2x, negative 2y.
And then the derivative respect
to v of x is negative
y over x squared.
And the derivative of v with
respect to y is just 1 over x.
So if I take the determinant of
that, I get 2, minus 2, y
squared over x squared.
Which if you notice, in terms of
our change of variables, is
exactly equal to 2
minus 2v squared,
because v is y over x.
And so I can rewrite
this as 2 times the
quantity 1 minus v squared.
OK?
So, so far so good, hopefully.
Now let's figure out how
to do the final step.
So the final step--
I'm going to come back over and
just remind us what the
integrand was, OK?
If we come over here, we're
reminded that we were
integrating over the region R
of 1 over x squared, dxdy.
Right?
That's what we were interested
in initially.
So now, if we come back, I'm
going to write that down just
to have it as a reference.
OK, that's what we
had initially.
Let me make sure.
Yes, that's what we
had initially.
And so now we know dxdy is equal
to dudv over 2 times 1
minus v squared.
So that is going to
replace the dxdy.
And now we have to figure
out what to do with
the 1 over x squared.
But, what do we have here?
Now I have to remind myself.
I can't remember all
the steps anymore.
We have u is equal to x squared
minus y squared.
Let me come back.
Now I've forgotten
what I was doing.
Ah, yes.
Now I remember, sorry.
OK.
So the point I should have
remembered that I forgot, is
that 1 minus v squared
is equal to u
divided by x squared.
That's what I had figured out
earlier that I just forgot
when I was staring
at the board.
And to notice that, what
do we have to remember?
u is x squared minus y squared,
so if I divide
everything by x squared, the
first term is 1 and the second
term is v squared.
So, whew, that's good.
So I was a little nervous there
for second, but I did in
fact do this earlier.
And I'd forgotten what I did.
So now, the 1 minus v squared
is actually the same as u
divided by x squared.
And notice what that does
to this term here.
That tells us that dxdy over x
squared is actually equal to
dudv over--
instead of the 1 minus v
squared, I put u over x
squared and I get--
notice, I get-- an x
squared times 2, u
divided by x squared.
Right?
I just replace the 1 minus v
squared with what I know it
is, the x squareds divide out,
and so I get dudv over 2u.
So now the good news is I have
all the pieces, because I'm
about to run out
of board space.
So I have all the pieces, so
I'm just going to put them
together, and then we're done.
So let me come here in the final
spot, and say this is
our final answer.
Our final answer is that we're
integrating u from 1, to 1
over v minus v. And then we're
integrating v from 0 to a--
where a is the value I
determined earlier--
of 1 over 2u, dudv. So this is
the final, final answer.
This was a long one.
And I'm sorry I had a little
brain freeze in the middle.
I couldn't remember how I'd
fixed that problem.
So what I did at that point--
I just want to point out-- that
when I was working on
this problem, and I had a 1
minus v squared, I knew
somehow I had to figure out how
to relate that and the x
squared in terms of u and v.
And so I actually saw
this expression.
I could have written it better,
maybe, as x squared
times this equals u.
OK.
And maybe that would have
been more obvious,
if that's the case.
But that was really the step
that allowed me to replace all
of this by things in terms of u
and v. Which I know I should
have been able to do,
it's just a matter
of figuring it out.
So let me just go back to the
beginning and remind you of
each of the steps very
briefly, and
then we'll be done.
So we come back over
to the beginning.
We were starting with change of
variables supplied for us.
We already had an integral in
terms of x and y, and we had
an infinite region.
And what we were asked
to do is find the
limits and the integrand.
So the first step for me is I
always find it very helpful to
draw the region in the xy plane,
and then draw the new
region in the uv plane.
Neither one of them has to be
perfect, but the understanding
of the values of the curves in
terms of equations of u and v
are very important, to
understand that.
That gives you the bounds,
the limits.
And then, so we did
all this work.
We found the limits.
There was a little algebra
in the middle.
We found the limits.
And then we found the Jacobian,
which was going to
tell us how the variables
were changing.
We found it in terms
of x and y.
We rewrote it in terms
of u and v.
And so when we came back and we
compared what our integrand
was initially, we could compare
dxdy to dudv. But then
we also had to figure
out how to replace
the 1 over x squared.
So once we did all that, we had
everything in terms of u
and v, and then we finally
had what the integrand
was going to be.
So there were a lot of steps,
but this was ultimately what
the problem was.
And again, I'll just point
out, this is the final
solution right here.
We integrated from 1, to 1
over v minus v, for u.
And we integrated from 0 to a in
v, the function 1 over 2u.
OK.
That is where I will stop.