PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
In this problem, I'd like to
take a look at convolution and
Green's formula.
Specifically, for part one,
we're just asked to compute
the convolution of
t with itself, t.
In the second part, we're
asked to compute the
convolution of e to the
minus kt with another
exponential, e to the at.
And then in part B, we're to use
the result from part A as
well as Green's formula
to solve x dot plus kx
equals e to the at.
And specifically, we're
interested in the rest initial
condition solution
to this formula.
OK.
So I'll let you think about this
problem, and I'll be back
in a minute.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
OK, so for part one, we're
asked to compute the
convolution of two functions,
t with itself--
and I'll just quickly write
down the formula for
convolution.
So if I have two functions, f
and g, then the convolution is
defined as, in this case, the
integral from zero to t of f,
so the function f evaluated at,
we're going to use tau as
the integration variable,
multiply by g, t
minus tau, d tau.
So notice how the variable
t appears in two
places in this formula.
It appears in one place in the
argument of g, and it appears
in the bound of integration.
Meanwhile, tau is the variable
we're integrating over, and
tau appears in two places as
well, one in f and one in g.
So if we're interested in t
convolved with t, we have the
integral from zero to t of
tau times t minus tau.
So notice how f is just t and g
is t, so when we insert tau
and t minus tau into the
function, we end up just
getting tau times t
minus tau, d tau.
And just expanding this out, we
have t times tau minus tau
squared, d tau.
So in the integral, the variable
t always appears just
as a constant.
So in this case, we have t,
tau integrated becomes t
squared over 2.
When I integrate from zero to
t, tau squared integrates to
1/3 t cubed, and zero
drops out from the
other end of the integral.
So we end up with t cubed, 1/2
minus 1/3, which is equal to
1/6 t cubed.
So there's the answer
we're looking for.
For part B, or for question
two, again we have another
computation to do.
So we have more integrals
to work out.
And in this case, it's
two exponentials.
So we have zero to t.
The first one is going
to be e to the k tau.
And the second one is e to
the at minus tau, d tau.
So we can just expand things
out, and I get e to the at
times e to the minus a plus
k tau d tau, zero to t.
And again, because t is just
a dummy variable in this
integral, we're not integrating
over t, I can just
think of e to the at
as a constant.
So I'm really just integrating
the function e to the minus a
plus k tau.
And when I integrate this
function, I get 1 over minus a
plus k, e to the minus a plus
k, tau evaluated at the
bounds, zero and t.
So the negative sign here
just flips the bounds.
So we have a plus k.
Substituting in zero just
gives us 1, and then
substituting in t gives us
e to the minus a plus kt.
And I can expand out, multiply
out, e to the at.
And when the dust settles, we
have e to the at minus e to
the minus kt.
So this is just the computation
of the convolution
e to the minus kt and e to at.
So note now if, for example, k
were to equal negative a, we
would have zero in
the denominator
and zero on the numerator.
So one way to compute the
special k case when k is equal
to negative a is to use
L'Hopital's Rule and
differentiate the top
and the bottom.
For example, with
respect to k.
Another alternative way of
computing the special case
when a is equal to negative k is
just to plug in e to the k,
and then just work out this
integral, and you'll obtain a
different answer.
And now lastly, for part B,
we're interested in the
differential equation x dot plus
kx equals e to the at.
And we're interested in
finding the particular
solution that has rest
initial conditions.
So for example, x of zero
is equal to zero.
And we want to use
Green's formula.
So just recall that there's the
impulse response formula
for the weight function w,
which solves the same
differential equation, but with
the delta function on the
right hand side.
And w, in this case, as we've
seen in lecture, is actually e
to the negative kt when t is
bigger than zero, and at zero
when t is less than zero.
So notice how e to the minus
kt is exactly the function
that we convolved in part A.
Specifically, we convolved it
with e to the at.
So for example, Green's
formula says that the
particular solution that has
rest initial conditions is
going to be the wave function
convolved with the right hand
side of the differential
equation, e to at.
In this case, on the domain
of integration for the
convolution, w is just
e to the minus kt.
So we have e to the minus kt
convolved with e to the at.
So Green's formula gives
us the solution to this
differential equation, which has
rest initial conditions.
And specifically--
we've already worked this out
from part A, so I can just
write down what the answer is.
It's 1 over a plus k, e to the
at, minus e to the minus kt.
And just as a quick check to
make sure that we've done
everything correctly, we can
plug in t equals zero.
And when t equals zero,
we have 1 minus 1,
which gives us zero.
So indeed, this x is the
solution to this differential
equation, which has rest
initial conditions.
I'd just like to conclude
this problem.
Quick recap.
We worked out several
convolutions, and specifically
we were able to use Green's
formula in addition to the
convolution that we worked out
to compute the solution with
rest initial conditions
to an ODE.
Moreover, Green's function is
very useful because notice how
we could have computed the
convolution for any right hand
side function here.
So in some sense, we're able
to generalize and find
solutions to differential
equations which have arbitrary
right hand side forcings, not
just sines and cosines,
periodic functions, or other
simple functions which we've
been looking at in the past.
So I'd like to conclude here,
and I'll see you next time.