PROFESSOR: Convolution is a
tricky concept and hard to
understand.
But it gives so much insight
that it's worthwhile coming to
grips with it.
The convolution accumulation
mathlet provides one
perspective on the convolution
integral.
I'll explain the applet
using a story.
There's a lake in Iowa with a
stream running into it and a
stream running out of it.
Farm runoff puts phosphate
into the lake.
The rate of deposition
of the phosphate
varies over the year.
Most in the summer, none
in the dead of winter.
Suppose the farm is new and that
t equals 0, there is no
phosphate in the lake.
This is called rest initial
conditions.
The question is, how much
phosphate is there in the lake
at some later time, say t.
This will be an accumulation of
contributions from earlier
times, but the earlier
contributions will have
decayed somewhat by time t.
We can visualize this process
using the convolution
accumulation mathlet.
I'll set it up to model
what we're looking at.
The signal f of t is the
rate of input of
phosphate into the lake.
And I will model it by the
menu item f of t is
1 plus cosine bt.
You can see it drawn in the
lower graphing window here.
A certain proportion of the
phosphate in the lake leaves
it during each unit of time.
This results in an exponential
decay of each contribution.
This decay profile is called the
weight function, denoted
here by g of t.
And I will select the weight
function, giving exponential
decay e to the minus at.
Now let's see what happens
if I let a small
amount of time elapse.
How small?
Well I can select that by
picking the step size.
And I will select a step
size of one eighth.
So now let's let a little
bit of time elapse.
Say, amount of time
of one eighth.
If I click on the time
slider at one
eighth, I get this picture.
T equals 0 happens to occur at
mid-summer, so that the signal
has a value of 2 in kilograms
per unit time.
This phosphate decays away as
water comes into the lake and
carries it off according
to the weight function.
And this is indicated by the
exponential decay function
here in the bottom window.
The weight function is a rate.
It needs to get multiplied by
the step size before it gives
an actual amount of phosphate
in the lake.
The step size is one eighth, and
the product is the signal,
the value of the signal at t
equals 0, that's 2, times the
weight function, that's the
exponential decay, times the
step size, which
is one eighth.
So that gives all together
one quarter times
that exponential decay.
And you see that drawn in the
top graphing window here, the
value near t equals 0 is a
quarter and it decays away
exponentially.
Now let's move on to the
next time interval.
I'll click here, and you
see what happens.
The signal is now a little
bit less and the time is
a little bit later.
So the weight function is scaled
and shifted a little
bit differently in this bottom
graphing window.
It gets multiplied by the step
size one eighth again, and
laid down on top of the graph of
the phosphate arising from
the first time interval.
So the sum of those two is a
record of the phosphate in the
lake arising from these first
two time intervals as it
decays away in later time.
This process continues.
You can see the next few steps
by clicking them up.
Here's the effect of the third
time interval as it decays
away, but laid down on top of
the preceding contributions to
the lake, and so on.
Or I animate the entire process
and watch the thing
evolve as time increases.
So you can see, the effect is
a steady state is reached
after a while, you get a
sinusoidal total amount of
phosphate in the lake.
It's delayed a little
bit from the peak.
The maximum amount of phosphate
in the lake occurs a
little after mid-summer.
Now imagine shrinking
the step size.
In the limit, as the step size
goes to 0, this process is
described by the convolution
integral.
At time t, all the contributions
from time 0 to
time t are present.
And so we're going to take
an integral from u equals
0 to u equals t.
The contribution from time u
decays by the factor of g of t
minus u by time t.
So the contribution from between
time u and time u plus
tu is given by the product f
of u, the signal of time u,
times g of t minus u, the weight
function evaluated at t
minus u, times du.
And the integral of this
differential, from u equals 0
to u equals t, is the amount
of phosphate in the
lake at time t.
And it's given by the
convolution integral.
This system is modeled by a
differential equation, namely
dx dt plus ax equals f of t.
The weight function of the
operator dx dt plus ax is e to
the minus at.
And the solution to the
differential equation with
rest initial conditions is
given by the convolution
integral of the input signal
with the weight function.
This statement is a general fact
for LTI operators, not
just first order operators.