JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've learned a
little bit about the dot
product, and how the dot product
can be used to compute
angles between vectors, or the
relationship between the dot
product of vectors and the
angle between them.
So, here I have two questions,
two related questions for you.
So the first one, you've
got two vectors.
i hat plus j hat plus 2k hat.
And a second vector, 2i hat
minus j hat plus k hat.
I'm probably going to stop
saying the hats in a minute,
just warning you.
So you've got these two
different vectors, and what
I'd like to know is what the
angle between them is.
And the second one is that
we have three points.
So the P has coordinates
a, 1, and minus 1.
Q has coordinates 0, 1, and 1.
And R has coordinates
a, minus 1, and 3.
So when you've given
three points,
that define some angles.
So what I'd like to know is for
which values of a is the
angle PQR a right angle?
So why don't you take some time,
work out these problems,
come back, and we can work
them out together.
Hopefully you had some
luck on these
problems. Let's get started.
Let's start with
the first one.
So we have these two vectors,
i plus j plus 2k, and 2i
minus j plus k.
And we want to know what the
measure of the angle
between them is.
So the thing that we have to use
here, is that for vectors
v and w, we know that v dot w
can be written in terms of the
angle between them.
So in particular, we know that
for vectors v and w, if the
angle between them is equal to
theta, then cosine of theta is
equal to v dot w, but I have to
divide by the length of v
and the length of w.
So I have this simple formula
for cosine of theta in terms
of v and w.
And so then if we want,
we can find theta by
taking an arc cosine.
So let's apply this formula
in the case of problem a.
So we could say that v is equal
to i plus j plus 2k, and
w is equal to 2i
minus j plus k.
And so what that means is that
in our case, v dot w-- well,
we just take, you know, the
products of the coordinates
and add them up.
So in that case, this is 1 times
2 plus 1 times minus 1
plus 2 times 1.
So this is 1 times 2 plus 1
times minus 1 plus 2 times 1.
So that's 2 minus 1 plus 2,
so that's equal to 3.
And so then we also need to know
what the length of v and
w are in order to apply
this formula.
So the length of v is equal to,
well it's the square root
of the sum of the squares
of the coordinates--
or the square root of v dot v.
So in this case, that's the
square root of 1 squared plus
1 squared plus 2 squared.
So that's the square
root of 6.
And the length of w is equal to
it's the square root of 2
squared plus minus 1 squared
plus 1 squared, which is also
equal to the square root of 6.
So if you put these three things
together, we have that
cosine of theta is equal--
so I'm going to write it right
up here next to this general
formula just to save a
little bit of space--
so in our case, this is equal
to 3 divided by the square
root of 6 times the
square root of 6.
So that's 3 divided by 6,
which is equal to 1/2.
So if cosine of theta is equal
to 1/2, well we know that that
means that theta is equal
to pi over 3.
OK?
So the angle between these
two vectors is pi over 3.
OK, great.
That's part a.
Now let's talk about part b.
So we have these three points
and we want to know for what
values is the angle that they
define a right angle.
For what values of
this parameter.
Right?
Our points depend on
this parameter, a.
So in order to do that,
we have these
three points in space.
Let me draw a picture up here.
So we have point P somewhere
and point Q somewhere and
point R somewhere, and they
define this angle, and we want
to know when this angle
is a right angle.
Well, we don't have any vectors
yet, but it's easy to
get some vectors involved
in this problem.
We can look at the vectors
QP and QR.
So those two vectors are the two
sides of this angle that
we're interested in.
And it's easy when you're given
coordinates for points
to find the vector
between them.
So you just subtract, right?
So QP.
In order to get from our point
Q over here-- in order to get
from 0, 1, 1 to a, 1, minus 1--
well, you have to increase
the first coordinate by a, the
second coordinate has to stay
the same, and the third
coordinate has
to decrease by 2.
So this vector QP is equal
to a, 0, minus 2.
So now I'm using
angle brackets,
because this is a vector.
SPEAKER 1: Positive
2 or negative 2?
JOEL LEWIS: Negative 2.
Yes.
Right.
Negative 2, yeah?
Because we're going
from 1 to minus 1.
OK, good.
And similarly QR.
So to get from Q to R--
I have to go back and look at
the coordinates over here-- so
I increase the first coordinate
by a, decrease the
second coordinate by 2, increase
the third coordinate
by 2, to get from Q to R. So the
vector QR is equal to a--
what did I say--
minus 2, 2.
So these are the vectors QP and
QR, and we want to know
when the angle between these two
things is a right angle.
We want to know when these
vectors are perpendicular.
OK?
So the two vectors are
perpendicular exactly when
their dot product is 0.
Right?
When the angle is 90 degrees.
Cosine of 90 degrees.
Cosine of pi over 2 radians is
equal to 0, so those two
things are the same.
The dot product equals 0 and
the angle is 90 degrees.
So OK.
So in our case, we just have
to look then at QP dot QR.
So that's equal to-- well, we
just take this dot product
here-- so it's equal
to a squared plus--
0 times minus 2 is 0--
minus--
2 times 2, so plus minus 2 times
2-- so that's minus 4.
So that's a squared minus 4.
And so this dot product is
equal to 0 exactly when a
squared minus 4 is equal to 0.
So a squared minus 4 is equal
to 0 when a is equal to 2 or
when a is equal to minus 2.
So there are two values of a for
which those three points
form a right angle at Q.
So just to quickly summarize,
we used this general formula
here for the cosine of an angle
in terms of the two
vectors that are the
sides of the angle.
And with that formula, we can
compute the measure of angles
between two vectors as here--
or, as in the first
part, in part a.
Or in a special case when we're
looking for a 90 degree
angle, we can use the simplified
form when we just
need to figure out when the
dot product is equal to 0.
OK.
So I'll end there.