Let's now turn to problem number
three, which is 22-36.
We have a y, and we
have a x-axis.
This is x and this is y.
There is a charge q1 at these
locations in x and y.
Here is q1 and there is here a
charge q2, and q1 is positive
and is 4 times 10 to
the - 9 coulomb.
Also, q2 equals - 6 times
10 to the - 9 coulomb.
You're being asked: What
is the electric
field at the original?
How is an electric
field defined?
If I have a point A here, I have
a point B here, and there
is a charge plus q here at point
B, then the electric
field is defined radially
outwards from B pointing in
the direction of A, because
this is a positive charge.
If this were a negative charge,
it would be reversed,
and it would be pointing to in
the direction of B, so I
called it E of A. If the
separation between them is R,
then E of A, if I take the
magnitude of it now, is the
charge at location
q divided by four
pi epsilon 0 r squared.
I have already indicated
the direction.
The use of electric field,
which, by the way, has as a
unit newtons per coulomb, is the
following: If you were to
place at location A the charge
capital Q, then the force that
this capital Q would experience
would be simply the
electric fields at A times
capital Q. That's the reason
why electric fields
is introduced.
Let us now be specific here,
and first calculate the
electric field due
to this point q1.
Here is that electric field E1,
and I will decompose it
into the x- and into
the y-direction.
Here is E1 in the y-direction,
and here we have E1 in the
x-direction.
The separation from O to q1 is
one meter, and the angle here
I will call theta, so this
is also theta, and
this is also theta.
What is the magnitude of E1?
Let's do that first. The
magnitude of E1--
I put a bar here, so
it is magnitude--
is simply this charge here, 4
times 10 to the - 9 times 9
times 10 the plus 9, because
that's the 1 over 4 pi epsilon
0 divided by the distance
squared, which is one squared.
This is 36 newtons
per coulomb.
What, now, are the
x-components?
I now have to multiply by the
cosine of theta, so E1 in the
x-direction, then multiplying
by the cosine of this angle
theta would be - 28.8
newtons per coulomb.
Why minus?
Because it's pointing in
the minus x-direction.
What is E1y?
Now I have to multiply by the
sine of theta, and so I get -
21.6 newtons per coulomb.
Why minus?
Because clearly you can
see it's pointing
in the minus direction.
I have to also calculate the
electric field due to q2.
q2 is negative, so it
is pointing in the
direction of q2.
I call this E2.
It turns out it has only a
component in the x-direction,
so E2 you should be able to
find now quite easily.
It is already in the
x-direction, so I can already
put an x here that if you put
in the numbers, it will turn
out to be 84.44 newtons
per coulomb.
You know have to calculate then
net electric fields, so
you have to take E1 and E2,
E net, vectorially.
It equals E1 plus E2, and I'm
sure you can do that.
It's a parallelogram, so this is
the net electric field, and
you should have no problems
calculating both the magnitude
as well as this angle alpha.
I will leave you with that.
That should not pose
any more problems.