review, and then on Wednesday
I'll do all I can in reviewing
the whole course.
So my topic today is --
actually, this is a lecture I
have never given before in this
way, and it will -- well,
four subspaces,
that's certainly fundamental,
and you know that,
so I want to speak about
left-inverses and right-inverses
and then something called
pseudo-inverses.
And pseudo-inverses,
let me say right away,
that comes in near the end of
chapter seven,
and that would not be expected
on the final.
But you'll see that what I'm
talking about is really the
basic stuff that,
for an m-by-n matrix of rank r,
we're going back to the most
fundamental picture in linear
algebra.
Nobody could forget that
picture, right?
When you're my age,
even, you'll remember the row
space, and the null space.
Orthogonal complements over
there, the column space and the
null space of A transpose
column, orthogonal complements
over here.
And I want to speak about
inverses.
OK.
And I want to identify the
different possibilities.
So first of all,
when does a matrix have a just
a perfect inverse,
two-sided, you know,
so the two-sided inverse is
what we just call inverse,
right?
And, so that means that there's
a matrix that produces the
identity, whether we write it on
the left or on the right.
And just tell me,
how are the numbers r,
the rank, n the number of
columns, m the number of rows,
how are those numbers related
when we have an invertible
matrix?
So this is the matrix which was
-- chapter two was all about
matrices like this,
the beginning of the course,
what was the relation of th- of
r, m, and n, for the nice case?
They're all the same,
all equal.
So this is the case when r=m=n.
Square matrix,
full rank, period,
just -- so I'll use the words
full rank.
OK, good.
Everybody knows that.
OK.
Then chapter three.
We began to deal with matrices
that were not of full rank,
and they could have any rank,
and we learned what the rank
was.
And then we focused,
if you remember on some cases
like full column rank.
Now, can you remember what was
the deal with full column rank?
So, now, I think this is the
case in which we have a
left-inverse,
and I'll try to find it.
So we have a -- what was the
situation there?
It's the case of full column
rank, and that means -- what
does that mean about r?
It equals, what's the deal with
r, now, if we have full column
rank, I mean the columns are
independent, but maybe not the
rows.
So what is r equal to in this
case?
n.
Thanks.
r=n.
The n columns are independent,
but probably,
we have more rows.
What's the picture,
and then what's the null space
for this?
So the n columns are
independent, what's the null
space in this case?
So of course,
you know what I'm asking.
You're saying,
why is this guy asking
something, I know that-- I think
about it in my sleep,
right?
So the null space of this
matrix if the rank is n,
the null space is what vectors
are in the null space?
Just the zero vector.
Right?
The columns are independent.
Independent columns.
No combination of the columns
gives zero except that one.
And what's my picture over,
-- let me redraw my picture --
the row space is everything.
No.
Is that right?
Let's see, I often get these
turned around,
right?
So what's the deal?
The columns are independent,
right?
So the rank should be the full
number of columns,
so what does that tell us?
There's no null space,
right.
OK.
The row space is the whole
thing.
Yes, I won't even draw the
picture.
And what was the deal with --
and these were very important in
least squares problems because
-- So, what more is true here?
If we have full column rank,
the null space is zero,
we have independent columns,
the unique -- so we have zero
or one solutions to Ax=b.
There may not be any solutions,
but if there's a solution,
there's only one solution
because other solutions are
found by adding on stuff from
the null space,
and there's nobody there to add
on.
So the particular solution is
the solution,
if there is a particular
solution.
But of course,
the rows might not be - are
probably not independent
-- and therefore,
so right-hand sides won't end
up with a zero equal zero after
elimination, so sometimes we may
have no solution,
or one solution.
OK.
And what I want to say is that
for this matrix A -- oh,
yes, tell me something about A
transpose A in this case.
So this whole part of the
board, now, is devoted to this
case.
What's the deal with A
transpose A?
I've emphasized over and over
how important that combination
is, for a rectangular matrix,
A transpose A is the good thing
to look at, and if the rank is
n, if the null space has only
zero in it, then the same is
true of A transpose A.
That's the beautiful fact,
that if the rank of A is n,
well, we know this will be an n
by n symmetric matrix,
and it will be full rank.
So this is invertible.
This matrix is invertible.
That matrix is invertible.
And now I want to show you that
A itself has a one-sided
inverse.
Here it is.
The inverse of that,
which exists,
times A transpose,
there is a one-sided -- shall I
call it A inverse?
-- left of the matrix A.
Why do I say that?
Because if I multiply this guy
by A, what do I get?
What does that multiplication
give?
Of course, you know it
instantly, because I just put
the parentheses there,
I have A transpose A inverse
times A transpose A so,
of course, it's the identity.
So it's a left inverse.
And this was the totally
crucial case for least squares,
because you remember that least
squares, the central equation of
least squares had this matrix,
A transpose A,
as its coefficient matrix.
And in the case of full column
rank, that matrix is invertible,
and we're go.
So that's the case where there
is a left-inverse.
So A does whatever it does,
we can find a matrix that
brings it back to the identity.
Now, is it true that,
in the other order -- so A
inverse left times A is the
identity.
Right?
This matrix is m by n.
This matrix is n by m.
The identity matrix is n by n.
All good.
All good if you're n.
But if you try to put that
matrix on the other side,
it would fail.
If the full column rank -- if
this is smaller than m,
the case where they're equals
is the beautiful case,
but that's all set.
Now, we're looking at the case
where the columns are
independent but the rows are
not.
So this is invertible,
but what matrix is not
invertible?
A A transpose is bad for this
case.
A transpose A is good.
So we can multiply on the left,
everything good,
we get the left inverse.
But it would not be a two-sided
inverse.
A rectangular matrix can't have
a two-sided inverse,
because there's got to be some
null space, right?
If I have a matrix that's
rectangular, then either that
matrix or its transpose has some
null space, because if n and m
are different,
then there's going to be some
free variables around,
and we'll have some null space
in that direction.
OK, tell me the corresponding
picture for the opposite case.
So now I'm going to ask you
about right-inverses.
A right-inverse.
And you can fill this all out,
this is going to be the case of
full row rank.
And then r is equal to m,
now, the m rows are
independent, but the columns are
not.
So what's the deal on that?
Well, just exactly the flip of
this one.
The null space of A transpose
contains only zero,
because there are no
combinations of the rows that
give the zero row.
We have independent rows.
And in a minute,
I'll give an example of all
these.
So, how many solutions to Ax=b
in this case?
The rows are independent.
So we can always solve Ax=b.
Whenever elimination never
produces a zero row,
so we never get into that zero
equal one problem,
so Ax=b always has a solution,
but too many.
So there will be some null
space, the null space of A --
what will be the dimension of
A's null space?
How many free variables have we
got?
How many special solutions in
that null space have we got?
So how many free variables in
this setup?
We've got n columns,
so n variables,
and this tells us how many are
pivot variables,
that tells us how many pivots
there are, so there are n-m free
variables.
So there are infinitely many
solutions to Ax=b.
We have n-m free variables in
this case.
OK.
Now I wanted to ask about this
idea of a right-inverse.
OK.
So I'm going to have a matrix
A, my matrix A,
and now there's going to be
some inverse on the right that
will give the identity matrix.
So it will be A times A inverse
on the right,
will be I.
And can you tell me what,
just by comparing with what we
had up there,
what will be the right-inverse,
we even have a formula for it.
There will be other --
actually, there are other
left-inverses,
that's our favorite.
There will be other
right-inverses,
but tell me our favorite here,
what's the nice right-inverse?
The nice right-inverse will be,
well, there we had A transpose
A was good, now it will be A A
transpose that's good.
The good matrix,
the good right -- the thing we
can invert is A A transpose,
so now if I just do it that
way, there sits the
right-inverse.
You see how completely parallel
it is to the one above?
Right.
So that's the right-inverse.
So that's the case when there
is -- In terms of this picture,
tell me what the null spaces
are like so far for these three
cases.
What about case one,
where we had a two-sided
inverse, full rank,
everything great.
The null spaces were,
like, gone, right?
The null spaces were just the
zero vectors.
Then I took case two,
this null space was gone.
Case three, this null space was
gone, and then case four is,
like, the most general case
when this picture is all there
-- when all the null spaces --
this has dimension r,
of course, this has dimension
n-r, this has dimension r,
this has dimension m-r,
and the final case will be when
r is smaller than m and n.
But can I just,
before I leave here look a
little more at this one?
At this case of full column
rank?
So A inverse on the left,
it has this left-inverse to
give the identity.
I said if we multiply it in the
other order, we wouldn't get the
identity.
But then I just realized that I
should ask you,
what do we get?
So if I put them in the other
order -- if I continue this down
below, but I write A times A
inverse left -- so there's A
times the left-inverse,
but it's not on the left any
more.
So it's not going to come out
perfectly.
But everybody in this room
ought to recognize that matrix,
right?
Let's see, is that the guy we
know?
Am I OK, here?
What is that matrix?
P.
Thanks.
That matrix -- it's a
projection.
It's the projection onto the
column space.
It's trying to be the identity
matrix, right?
A projection matrix tries to be
the identity matrix,
but you've given it,
an impossible job.
So it's the identity matrix
where it can be,
and elsewhere,
it's the zero matrix.
So this is P,
right.
A projection onto the column
space.
OK.
And if I asked you this one,
and put these in the opposite
order -- so this came from up
here.
And similarly,
if I try to put the right
inverse on the left -- so that,
like, came from above.
This, coming from this side,
what happens if I try to put
the right inverse on the left?
Then I would have A transpose
A, A transpose inverse A,
if this matrix is now on the
left, what do you figure that
matrix is?
It's going to be a projection,
too, right?
It looks very much like this
guy, except the only difference
is, A and A transpose have been
reversed.
So this is a projection,
this is another projection,
onto the row space.
Again, it's trying to be the
identity, but there's only so
much the matrix can do.
And this is the projection onto
the column space.
So let me now go back to the
main picture and tell you about
the general case,
the pseudo-inverse.
These are cases we know.
So this was important review.
You've got to know the business
about these ranks,
and the free variables --
really, this is linear algebra
coming together.
And, you know,
one nice thing about teaching
18.06,
It's not trivial.
But it's -- I don't know,
somehow, it's nice when it
comes out right.
I mean -- well,
I shouldn't say anything bad
about calculus,
but I will.
I mean, like,
you know, you have formulas for
surface area,
and other awful things and,
you know, they do their best in
calculus, but it's not elegant.
And, linear algebra just is --
well, you know,
linear algebra is about the
nice part of calculus,
where everything's,
like, flat, and,
the formulas come out right.
And you can go into high
dimensions where,
in calculus,
you're trying to visualize
these things,
well, two or three dimensions
is kind of the limit.
But here, we don't -- you know,
I've stopped doing two-by-twos,
I'm just talking about the
general case.
OK, now I really will speak
about the general case here.
What could be the inverse --
what's a kind of reasonable
inverse for a matrix for the
completely general matrix where
there's a rank r,
but it's smaller than n,
so there's some null space
left, and it's smaller than m,
so a transpose has some null
space, and it's those null
spaces that are screwing up
inverses, right?
Because if a matrix takes a
vector to zero,
well, there's no way an inverse
can, like, bring it back to
life.
My topic is now the
pseudo-inverse,
and let's just by a picture,
see what's the best inverse we
could have?
So, here's a vector x in the
row space.
I multiply by A.
Now, the one thing everybody
knows is you take a vector,
you multiply by A,
and you get an output,
and where is that output?
Where is Ax?
Always in the column space,
right?
Ax is a combination of the
columns.
So Ax is somewhere here.
So I could take all the vectors
in the row space.
I could multiply them all by A.
I would get a bunch of vectors
in the column space and what I
think is, I'd get all the
vectors in the column space just
right.
I think that this connection
between an x in the row space
and an Ax in the column space,
this is one-to-one.
We got a chance,
because they have the same
dimension.
That's an r-dimensional space,
and that's an r-dimensional
space.
And somehow,
the matrix A -- it's got these
null spaces hanging around,
where it's knocking vectors to
zero.
And then it's got all the
vectors in between,
which is almost all vectors.
Almost all vectors have a row
space component and a null space
component.
And it's killing the null space
But if I look at the vectors
that are in the row space,
with no null space component,
just in the row space,
then they all go into the
column space,
so if I put another vector,
let's say, y,
in the row space,
I positive that wherever Ay is,
it won't hit Ax.
Do you see what I'm saying?
Let's see why.
All right.
So here's what I said.
If x and y are in the row
space, then A x is not the same
as A y.
They're both in the column
space, of course,
but they're different.
That would be a perfect
question on a final exam,
because that's what I'm
teaching you in that material of
chapter three and chapter four,
especially chapter three.
If x and y are in the row
space, then Ax is different from
Ay.
So what this means -- and we'll
see why -- is that,
in words, from the row space to
the column space,
A is perfect,
it's an invertible matrix.
If we, like,
limited it to those spaces.
And then, its inverse will be
what I'll call the
pseudo-inverse.
So that's that the
pseudo-inverse is.
It's the inverse -- so A goes
this way, from x to y -- sorry,
x to A x, from y to A y,
that's A, going that way.
Then in the other direction,
anything in the column space
comes from somebody in the row
space, and the reverse there is
what I'll call the
pseudo-inverse,
and the accepted notation is A
plus.
So y will be A plus x.
I'm sorry.
No, y will be A plus times
whatever it started with,
A y.
Do you see my picture there?
Same, of course,
for x and A x.
This way, A does it,
the other way is the
pseudo-inverse,
and the pseudo-inverse just
kills this stuff,
and the matrix just kills this
stuff.
So everything that's really
serious here is going on in the
row space and the column space,
and now, tell me
-- this is the fundamental
fact, that between those two
r-dimensional spaces,
our matrix is perfect.
Why?
Suppose they weren't.
Why do I get into trouble?
Suppose -- so,
proof.
I haven't written down proof
very much, but I'm going to use
that word once.
Suppose they were the same.
Suppose these are supposed to
be two different vectors.
Maybe I'd better make the
statement correctly.
If x and y are different
vectors in the row space --
maybe I'll better put if x is
different from y,
both in the row space -- so I'm
starting with two different
vectors in the row space,
I'm multiplying by A -- so
these guys are in the column
space, everybody knows that,
and the point is,
they're different over there.
So, suppose they weren't.
Suppose A x=A y.
Suppose, well,
that's the same as saying
A(x-y) is zero.
So what?
So, what do I know now about
(x-y), what do I know about this
vector?
Well, I can see right away,
what space is it in?
It's sitting in the null space,
right?
So it's in the null space.
But what else do I know about
it?
Here it was x in the row space,
y in the row space,
what about x-y?
It's also in the row space,
right?
Heck, that thing is a vector
space, and if the vector space
is anything at all,
if x is in the row space,
and y is in the row space,
then the difference is also,
so it's also in the row space.
So what?
Now I've got a vector x-y
that's in the null space,
and that's also in the row
space, so what vector is it?
It's the zero vector.
So I would conclude from that
that x-y had to be the zero
vector, x-y, so,
in other words,
if I start from two different
vectors, I get two different
vectors.
If these vectors are the same,
then those vectors had to be
the same.
That's like the algebra proof,
which we understand completely
because we really understand
these subspaces of what I said
in words, that a matrix A is
really a nice,
invertible mapping from row
space to columns pace.
If the null spaces keep out of
the way, then we have an
inverse.
And that inverse is called the
pseudo inverse,
and it's a very,
very, useful in application.
Statisticians discovered,
oh boy, this is the thing that
we needed all our lives,
and here it finally showed up,
the pseudo-inverse is the right
thing.
Why do statisticians need it?
And because statisticians are
like least-squares-happy.
I mean they're always doing
least squares.
And so this is their central
linear regression.
Statisticians who may watch
this on video,
please forgive that description
of your interests.
One of your interests is linear
regression and this problem.
But this problem is only OK
provided we have full column
rank.
And statisticians have to worry
all the time about,
oh, God, maybe we just repeated
an experiment.
You know, you're taking all
these measurements,
maybe you just repeat them a
few times.
You know, maybe they're not
independent.
Well, in that case,
that A transpose A matrix that
they depend on becomes singular.
So then that's when they needed
the pseudo-inverse,
it just arrived at the right
moment, and it's the right
quantity.
OK.
So now that you know what the
pseudo-inverse should do,
let me see what it is.
Can we find it?
So this is my -- to complete
the lecture is -- how do I find
this pseudo-inverse A plus?
OK.
Well, here's one way.
Everything I do today is to try
to review stuff.
One way would be to start from
the SVD.
The Singular Value
Decomposition.
And you remember that that
factored A into an orthogonal
matrix times this diagonal
matrix times this orthogonal
matrix.
But what did that diagonal guy
look like?
This diagonal guy,
sigma, has some non-zeroes,
and you remember,
they came from A transpose A,
and A A transpose,
these are the good guys,
and then some more zeroes,
and all zeroes there,
and all zeroes there.
So you can guess what the
pseudo-inverse is,
I just invert stuff that's nice
to invert -- well,
what's the pseudo-inverse of
this?
That's what the problem comes
down to.
What's the pseudo-inverse of
this beautiful diagonal matrix?
But it's got a null space,
right?
What's the rank of this matrix?
What's the rank of this
diagonal matrix?
r, of course.
It's got r non-zeroes,
and then it's otherwise,
zip.
So it's got n columns,
it's got m rows,
and it's got rank r.
It's the best example,
the simplest example we could
ever have of our general setup.
OK?
So what's the pseudo-inverse?
What's the matrix -- so I'll
erase our columns,
because right below it,
I want to write the
pseudo-inverse.
OK, you can make a pretty darn
good guess.
If it was a proper diagonal
matrix, invertible,
if there weren't any zeroes
down here, if it was sigma one
to sigma n, then everybody knows
what the inverse would be,
the inverse would be one over
sigma one, down to one over s-
but of course,
I'll have to stop at sigma r.
And, it will be the rest,
zeroes again,
of course.
And now this one was m by n,
and this one is meant to have a
slightly different,
you know, transpose shape,
n by m.
They both have that rank r.
My idea is that the
pseudo-inverse is the best -- is
the closest I can come to an
inverse.
So what is sigma times its
pseudo-inverse?
Can you multiply sigma by its
Multiply that by that?
What matrix do you get?
They're diagonal.
Rectangular,
of course.
But of course,
we're going to get ones,
R ones, and all the rest,
zeroes.
And the shape of that,
this whole matrix will be m by
m.
And suppose I did it in the
other order.
Suppose I did sigma plus sigma.
Why don't I do it right
underneath?
in the opposite order?
See, this matrix hasn't got a
left-inverse,
it hasn't got a right-inverse,
but every matrix has got a
pseudo-inverse.
If I do it in the order sigma
plus sigma, what do I get?
Square matrix,
this is m by n,
this is m by m,
my result is going to m by m --
is going to be n by n,
and what is it?
Those are diagonal matrices,
it's going to be ones,
and then zeroes.
It's not the same as that,
it's a different size -- it's a
projection.
One is a projection matrix onto
the column space,
and this one is the projection
matrix onto the row space.
That's the best that
pseudo-inverse can do.
So what the pseudo-inverse does
is, if you multiply on the left,
you don't get the identity,
if you multiply on the right,
what you get is the projection.
It brings you into the two good
spaces, the row space and column
space.
And it just wipes out the null
So that's what the
pseudo-inverse of this diagonal
one is, and then the
pseudo-inverse of A itself --
this is perfectly invertible.
What's the inverse of V
transpose?
Just another tiny bit of
review.
That's an orthogonal matrix,
and its inverse is V,
good.
This guy has got all the
trouble in it,
all the null space is
responsible for,
so it doesn't have a true
inverse, it has a
pseudo-inverse,
and then the inverse of U is U
transpose, thanks.
Or, of course,
I could write U inverse.
So, that's the question of,
how do you find the
pseudo-inverse
-- so what statisticians do
when they're in this -- so this
is like the case of where least
squares breaks down because the
rank is -- you don't have full
rank, and the beauty of the
singular value decomposition is,
it puts all the problems into
this diagonal matrix where it's
clear what to do.
It's the best inverse you could
think of is clear.
You see there could be other --
I mean, we could put some stuff
down here, it would multiply
these zeroes.
It wouldn't have any effect,
but then the good
pseudo-inverse is the one with
no extra stuff,
it's sort of,
like, as small as possible.
It has to have those to produce
the ones.
If it had other stuff,
it would just be a larger
matrix, so this pseudo-inverse
is kind of the minimal matrix
that gives the best result.
Sigma sigma plus being r ones.
SK.
so I guess I'm hoping --
pseudo-inverse,
again, let me repeat what I
said at the very beginning.
This pseudo-inverse,
which appears at the end,
which is in section seven point
four, and probably I did more
with it here than I did in the
book.
The word pseudo-inverse will
not appear on an exam in this
course, but I think if you see
this all will appear,
because this is all what the
course was about,
chapters one,
two, three, four -- but if you
see all that,
then you probably see,
well, OK, the general case had
both null spaces around,
and this is the natural thing
to do.
Yes.
So, this is one way to find the
pseudo-inverse.
The point of a pseudo-inverse,
of computing a pseudo-inverse
is to get some factors where you
can find the pseudo-inverse
quickly.
And this is,
like, the champion,
because this is where we can
invert those,
and those two,
easily, just by transposing,
and we know what to do with a
diagonal.
OK, that's as much review,
maybe --
let's have a five-minute
holiday in 18.06 and,
I'll see you Wednesday,
then, for the rest of this
course.
Thanks.