DAVID SHIROKOFF: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So today I'd like to tackle a
problem on pseudoinverses.
So given a matrix A, which
is not square, so
it's just 1 and 2.
First, what is its
pseudoinverse?
So A plus I'm using to denote
the pseudoinverse.
Then secondly, compute A
plus A and A A plus.
And then thirdly, if x is in the
null space of A, what is A
plus A acting on x?
And lastly, if x is in the
column space of A transpose,
what is A plus Ax?
So I'll let you think about this
problem for a bit, and
I'll be back in a second.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
OK, so let's take a look
at this problem.
Now first off, what is
a pseudoinverse?
Well we define the pseudoinverse
using the SVD.
So in actuality, this
is nothing new.
Now, we note that because A
is not square, the regular
inverse of A doesn't necessarily
exist. However, we
do know that the SVD exists
for every matrix A whether
it's square or not.
So how do we compute the
SVD of a matrix?
Well let's just recall that the
SVD of a matrix has the
form of u sigma V transpose
where u and V
are orthogonal matrices.
And sigma is a matrix with
positive values along the
diagonal or 0s along
the diagonal.
And let's just take a look at
the dimensions of these
matrices for a second.
So we know that A is
a 1 by 2 matrix.
And the way to figure out what
the dimensions of these
matrices are I usually always
start with the center matrix,
sigma, and sigma is always
going to have the same
dimensions as A, so it's going
to be a 1 by 2 matrix.
u and V are always
square matrices.
So to make this multiplication
work out, we need V to have 2,
and because it's square
it has to be 2 by 2.
And likewise, u has
to be 1 by 1.
So we now have the dimensions
of u sigma and V. And note,
because u is a 1 by 1 matrix,
the only orthogonal 1 by 1
matrix is just 1.
So u we already know is just
going to be the matrix, the
identity matrix, which
is a 1 by 1 matrix.
OK, now how do we compute
V and sigma?
Well we can take A transpose
and A, and if we do that we
end up getting the
matrix V sigma
transpose sigma, V transpose.
And this matrix is going to be
a square matrix where the
diagonal elements are squares
of the singular values.
So computing V and the values
along sigma, just boil down to
diagonalizing A transpose A.
So what is A transpose A?
Well in our case is 1 2 times 1
2, which gives us 1 2, 2 4.
And note that the second row
is just a constant multiple
times the first row.
Now what this means is we
have a zero eigenvalue.
So we already know that lambda
1 is going to be 0.
So one of the eigenvalues
of this matrix is 0.
And of course, when we square
root it, this is going to give
us a singular value sigma,
which is also 0.
And this is generally a case
when we have a sigma which is
not square.
We typically always have
0 singular values.
Now to compute the second
eigenvalue, well we already
know how to compute the
eigenvalues of a matrix, so
I'm just going to tell
you what it is.
The second one is lambda is 5.
And if we just take a quick look
what the corresponding
eigenvector is going to be to
lambda is 5, it's going to
satisfy this equation.
So we can take the eigenvector
u to be 1 and 2.
However, remember that when we
compute the eigenvector for
this orthogonal matrix
V, they always have
to have a unit length.
And this vector right now
doesn't have a unit length.
We have to divide by the length
of this vector, which
in our case is 1 over root 5.
And if I go back to the lambda
equals 0 case, we also have
another eigenvector, which
I'll just state.
You can actually compute it
quite quickly just by noting
that it has to be orthogonal to
this eigenvector, 2 and 1.
So what this means is A has a
singular value decomposition,
which looks like 1, so this is
u, times sigma, which is going
to be root 5 0.
Remember that the first sigma is
actually the square root of
the eigenvalue.
Times a matrix which looks like,
now we have to order the
eigenvalues up in the
correct order.
Because 5 appears in the first
column, we have to take this
vector to be in the first
column as well.
So this is 1 over root 5, this
is 2 over root 5, negative 2
over root 5, and
1 over root 5.
And now this is V, but the
singular value decomposition
is defined by V transpose.
So this gives us a
representation for A. And now
once we have the SVD of A, how
do we actually compute A plus,
or the pseudoinverse of A?
Well just note if A was
invertible, then the inverse
of A in terms of the SVD would
be V transpose times the
inverse of sigma.
Sorry, this is not V transpose,
this is just V. So
it'd be V sigma inverse
u transpose.
And when A is invertible,
sigma inverse exists.
So in our case, sigma inverse
doesn't necessarily exist
because sigma, note this is
sigma, sigma is root 5 and 0.
So we have to construct a
pseudoinverse for sigma.
So the way that we do that is
we take 1 over each singular
value, and we take the
transpose of sigma.
So when A is not invertible,
we can still construct a
pseudoinverse by taking V sigma
and approximation for
sigma inverse, which in our case
is going to be 1 over the
singular value and 0.
So note where sigma is
invertible, we take the
inverse, and then we fill
in 0s in the other
areas, times u transpose.
And we can work this out.
We get 1 over root 5, 1 minus
2, 2 1, 1 over root 5, 0.
And if I multiply things
out, I get 1/5, 1 2.
So this is an approximation for
A inverse, which is the
pseudoinverse.
So this finishes up part one.
And I'll started on part
two in a second.
So now that we've just computed
the pseudoinverse of
A. We're going to investigate
some properties of the
pseudoinverse.
So for part two we need to
compute A times A plus and A
plus times A. So we can just
go ahead and do this.
So A A plus you can
do fairly quickly.
1/5, 1 2.
And when we multiply it
out we get 1 plus 4
divided by 5 is 1.
So we just get the one by one
matrix, which is 1, the
identity matrix.
And secondly, if we take A plus
times A we're going to
get 1/5, 1 2 times 1 2.
And we can just fill
in this matrix.
This is 1/5, 1 2, 2 1.
And this concludes part two.
So now let's take a look at what
happens when a vector x
is in the null space of A, and
then secondly, what happens
when x is in the column
space of A transpose.
So for part three, let's assume
x is in the null space
of A. Well what's the
null space of A?
We can quickly check that the
null space of A is a constant
times any vector minus 2 1.
So that's the null space.
So if x is, for example, i.e.
if we take x is equal to minus
2 1, and we were to, say,
multiply it by A plus
A, acting on x we
see that we get 0.
And this isn't very surprising
because, well if x is in the
null space of A, we know
that A acting on x
is going to be 0.
So that no matter what matrix A
plus is, when we multiply by
0, we'll always end up with 0.
And then lastly, let's
take a look at the
column space of A transpose.
Well A transpose is 1 2, so it's
any constant times the
vector 1 2.
And specifically, if we were to
take, say, x is equal to 1
2, we can work at A plus A
acting on the vector 1 2.
So we have 1/5, 1 2, 2 1.
So recall this is A plus A. And
if we multiply it on the
vector 1 2, we get 1 plus 4 is
5 divided by 5, so we get 1.
2 plus 2 is 4--
sorry, I copied the
matrix down.
So it's 2 plus 8, which is
10 divided by 5 is 2.
And we see that at the end
we recover the vector x.
So in general, if we take A plus
A acting on x, where x is
in the column space of A
transpose, we always recover x
at the end of the day.
So intuitively, what does
this matrix A plus A do?
Well if x is in the null space
of A, it just kills it.
We just get 0.
If x is not in the null space of
A, then we just get x back.
So it's essentially the identity
matrix acting on x
whenever x is in the column
space of A transpose.
Now specifically, if A is
invertible, then A doesn't
have a null space.
So what that means is when
A is invertible, A plus A
recovers the identity because
when we multiply it on any
vector, we get that
vector back.
So I'd like to conclude here,
and I'll see you next time.