The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
Some content in this audio is
not covered under a Creative
Commons license.
For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT
OpenCourseWare website.
PROFESSOR: OK, so today, we have
a guest lecturer, Clara.
Some of you have probably
already taken her class.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
My current victims.
PROFESSOR: And past victims.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: We'll probably
need to do
something about the lights.
[INAUDIBLE].
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
I'm still operating on
Tylenol and caffeine.
So today we're going to talk
about stories in games.
And Clara teaches not just the
Intro to Video Game Studies
class, but also the Writing
for Video Games
class in the spring.
I wanted her to come in and
bring her expertise because
she's [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
probably a
lot more than I have.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Hello, perfect.
[INAUDIBLE].
So yeah, Philip asked me to
come here and talk about
stories in games, and as far
as I remember, he said you
guys had to read two
articles for today.
Chapter four in [INAUDIBLE]
and Soren Johnson's Theme
is Not Meaning.
Didn't I [INAUDIBLE], too?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
And he's late, OK.
PROFESSOR: Shh!
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: [LAUGHS]
Anyway, so preparing
this has been kind
of interesting because--
I thought about this quite a bit
because there's this focus
in my research studying how
games and stories can be
brought together.
What does it mean to have
a story in a game?
Where do we put the story?
But the interesting challenge
was thinking, well, the guys
are working mostly on
non-visual games.
And what do stories have to do
with non-fictional games.
So here what I'm going to need
is your input, because you
guys have been playing all these
board games, card games,
and I want a bit of your input
of what you think.
How you think these concepts
apply to non-digital games,
because the part of digital
games I can do pretty
confidently.
But I don't know as much about
board games or card games.
So I need your expertise.
This is why you guys are here.
So the first thing that I wanted
to ask you about is
that we have two different
meetings, and one is sort of
about fiction and the other
is sort of about theme.
But what is the fiction
of a game?
I turn it to you.
AUDIENCE: The fiction of a game
is, well, whatever you
want it to be.
It could be the characters
in a digital game.
It could be a real environment,
but you just have
fictional characters.
It could be an environment
that may not exist.
It's pretty much up to the
designer to figure out what
they want to--
like with [INAUDIBLE] be in the
game that are real, or if
they want it to be fiction.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Well,
there's something there, but
it might be a bit more
intuitive than that.
I think that you're on
the right track, yes.
AUDIENCE: I'd say it's the
setting or the universe in
which the user perceives the
events of the game to take
place in, or the one that the
designer intends the user to
see the game take place in.
AUDIENCE: OK, so
you can mention
environment as the big--
what was the word you used--
the universe, the setting,
something like that.
Back there.
AUDIENCE: Oh yeah, I was going
to say that the word that is
used over and over is world.
It's just a world,
pretty much.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: And
that's the keyword.
When [UNINTELLIGIBLE] is talking
about fiction, he's
really talking all throughout
about fictional worlds.
In a way, designing games and
designing video games
specifically, is always thinking
about what is the
world of this game.
And at times there might be
games that don't have worlds.
You can make Tetris.
You could make--
There's very few video
games without worlds.
But there are some.
Tetris--
AUDIENCE: Peggle.
So does Peggle.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Peggle?
Well, Peggle has characters,
you know.
You were talking about this.
Characters are already
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] in fiction.
AUDIENCE: You said it has
nothing to do with unicorns.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes.
Who wants to say something?
We have two hands here.
AUDIENCE: I'm stealing it.
OK, in print or with board
games, I think of fiction much
more as the specific explicit
things they give you, like the
pictures, the rules, and all of
that stuff versus what it
feels like you're doing.
So if they don't specifically
tell you you're in blah place,
then that's not part
of the fiction.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
OK, yeah.
So you put your finger on it,
but when we're talking about
non-digital games, there are
some non-digital games where
thinking about worlds
is a bit shaky.
Do you want to say something?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, just going to
add that in an environment,
you have a set of things
you can do.
So you're basically
given rules.
Like in a board game, you could
be given a character
that has to jump for
some reason.
The board game could
say that they could
jump some insane distance.
Well, in real life, they
can't do that.
That's just part
of the fiction.
So it's whatever laws apply
within that world, as well.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: This is
a very interesting point
because when you were
talking about--
what's that word
that he uses--
incongruous worlds?
Incoherent, incoherent.
He talks about incoherent
worlds, and it's like, well,
incoherent according to what?
It's obviously not the rules
that are also creating part of
the fiction.
The rules are also creating what
are the laws of gravity
in a specific world that we are
playing in, for example.
So when we're talking about
fiction, we're mainly talking
about fictional world.
Now, how does that
relate to theme?
And you were already kind
of hinting at that.
That in fiction and board games,
it's kind of like,
well, it almost can
be about anything.
But what is the theme of a g--
when you-- if you remember
Soren Johnson's discussion--
what does he refer
to as a theme?
He is not an academic, so he
has a more wobbly, loose
definition.
What is the theme of a game?
AUDIENCE: The theme of the game
is what the designer says
to the player, this is what
the game is about.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
But when--
Soren Johnson is saying
theme is not meaning.
So he's making a point that
theme might not be what the
game is about.
Right?
AUDIENCE: This is what the
game designer tells you.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah.
The example that he gives is
Ticket to Ride, right?
And Ticket to Ride is not
about riding trains.
It's about--
it's about--
well, the description is
about going from one
end to another, right?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
And travelling across--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Is building--
AUDIENCE: It's about travelling
across the United States.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: But is it
really travelling, or is it
building the--
AUDIENCE: It's not even
a story about--
the story's about travelling.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah, the
story's about travelling,
that's the theme.
But what you actually do is--
AUDIENCE: The official story
is that I think it's some
number of years after the events
that were Around the
World in Eighty Days, and to
commemorate that, the original
people who were involved in
that race decided they're
going to race across
America in trains.
And that is the theme of the
game, according to--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
that's the theme of the game.
AUDIENCE: Well, that sort of
what drives to the point of
what Sorenson's talking about,
that when theme and meaning
are incongruous--
as they are in Ticket to Ride to
an extreme extent-- it can
actually turn people off from
the game sometimes.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Well, and it's not
that it's a bad game--
AUDIENCE: Or Halo Wars.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Well,
not necessarily.
AUDIENCE: The thing about Halo
Wars was that it sounded like
you bought it thinking it was
going to be an action game,
then got disappointed
and were like, blah!
AUDIENCE: In the case with
Ticket to Ride, it is pretty
much just what they were
saying there, right?
That the theme seems to just
be whoever it is that wrote
the instruction booklet say that
you're doing, which may
not necessarily have anything
to do with the actual
mechanics of the game.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
I have the game.
I didn't know if you guys
have played it.
I made you want to play it.
[INAUDIBLE]
As of right now,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
is a game called Too Many Cooks,
and it seems to be
about cooking.
Yeah, you have ingredients,
and you're
making a soup of sorts.
But really what you're doing
is resource management and
exchanging.
Just imagine being a cook and
having to, like, well, I have
to wait until I get the right
ingredient or maybe exchange
it for another.
That's not how you
cook really.
So there's always the clash of
how the fiction of the game
relates to the rules.
And the interesting distinction
between fiction
and theme is that theme seems
to be like a layer, seems to
be like a decoration.
At times, it can be
part of the title.
It can be how the tokens
look like, or what
the board looks like.
That is setting up the
fiction of the game.
Not the fiction, the theme.
But it doesn't really have
a fictional world.
When when you're playing Ticket
to Ride or when you're
playing Settlers, you
have a feeling
like you're in a world.
AUDIENCE: At least, more
so than Ticket to Ride.
So, I will argue that maybe the
world that you feel is not
that they're telling you
that you're in, right?
One of the problems of Ticket
to Ride is that you never
really feel these characters
exist.
But the world of the United
States is very, very present.
Like the positioning of the
cities, the fact that these
cities exist and can be
connected by land is very--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: You guys
have read the levels of
abstraction?
Talked about levels of
abstraction here at all?
PROFESSOR: Not in great
detail, but--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: OK, it's
the idea that it's a world,
but the way that it works is so
abstracted that it doesn't
really-- you're not in
a world anymore.
It's just these little
bits and pieces.
OK, we have fiction and
we have theme, but
we also have stories.
And what do stories have
to do with this?
How do we have the story
in non-digital games?
What principle--
a story--
I'm going to find it for
you to save time.
A story is a series of connected
events that involve
characters.
So those characters perform
actions, or there are
happenings, things that happen
to them, and those actions
happen in time and in a
specific setting, in a
specific place.
And in the case of games, they
also involve objects.
That's like my telegraphic
version of what a story is.
So what we do in games, in
games we have changes of
state, right?
Every step of a non-digital
game, particularly.
We can think about non-digital
games as changes of state, and
having a change of state can
constitute an event.
So that is one way.
So how do we generate rules that
generate changes of state
that can be thought of as
an event in the story?
But I want to know a bit more.
Of the games that you've
played so far, how can
non-digital games--
and maybe you've played more
board than card games than
anything, but--
how can we have a story?
How can we have those
events happen?
AUDIENCE: So one game that I've
played that has a really
nice story to it is Battlestar
Galactica.
In a way, that places--
it works off of what the
player already knows.
So it sort of assumes that the
player has a knowledge of the
Battlestar Galactica world,
and so it keeps
referring to that.
Whenever you play a card that
has special abilities,
[INAUDIBLE], so it relies
on previous knowledge.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: That's
a very good point.
The point of--
in digital games and non-digital
games, but is also
in digital games--
a lot of storytelling in games
happens in the player's head.
Is it evoking [INAUDIBLE]
, is tapping on the player's
knowledge.
Is not, as we've got to say,
is not so much about
storytelling, but like,
OK, what do you know?
We are making the player
fill in the gaps.
So that designing a game that
involves storytelling is
usually giving cues to the
player to create the story, if
that makes sense.
Patrick?
AUDIENCE: I was going to say
that a lot of board and card
games, a lot of the fiction just
comes from the metaphors
of the mechanics.
So, for example, in Settlers,
when you want to build a road,
if you strip away all the
fiction, it's just I have
these cards, I put them down,
I can put this piece here.
But adding the fiction to it,
you say now, I'm not just
putting cards down, I'm using
the resources to build a road.
And so that metaphorical
action is another
event in the story.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Well, it
becomes a meaningful action.
That's another--
I'm sure that you guys have
been talking about that.
What is a meaningful action?
And at times, meaningful action
is it constitutes a
story event.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: I think the whole
point of Munchkin and and
Shiggy and those games are
to construct stories.
When we played it, there was a
moment when someon trashed
someone else's shrooms, and then
the other person played a
Go Dumpster Diving card to go
pick up the shrooms and a bong
from the dumpster.
And this whole sequence of
events, the [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
text on the cards, what they
were, and the actions you were
taking, and you string them all
together, I did this, and
this happened, and this happened
with this object, and
you've got a perfect story,
because you know you're
playing the geek, and that--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Well, there's that.
But the other thing that is good
about Munchkin is that
reading the cards is fun.
There are bits of the story
you'll get in Munchkin that
are like, [INAUDIBLE].
That is kind of like
engaging already.
Oh, and you wanted
to say something?
AUDIENCE: I was just going to
say that there are some games
which are entirely about
telling stories.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Thank you.
AUDIENCE: Role-playing games are
the number one, and then
another example is something
like Once Upon a Time, which I
think is [INAUDIBLE].
And then they have, also,
The Adventures of Baron
Munchausen, if you've
ever seen--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes.
Oh, I should bring it, yes.
I have it in my office.
Thought that's kind of
difficult to set
up in half an hour.
But yes.
AUDIENCE: And actually, a friend
of mine invented a game
which is vaguely based on
The Adventures of Baron
Munchausen, where each person
is telling a story and they
have cards in front of them
which needs to be flipped over
by incorporating the elements
of the story into
their hand of cards--
Anyway, don't worry about it.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you're going a
bit faster, but that's fine
because yeah, there are games
that are about storytelling,
communal storytelling,
and role-playing
games are about that.
And again, as game designers,
what we are given when we have
the rule book from D&D
is a fictional
world that has rules.
But then we have, as a designer,
as a DM, we are
coming up with what
is the situation?
What is the world?
What is the the specific
challenges that we're
situating in this world?
How are we going to do that?
But it's about communal
storytelling.
As we're going to see in a
minute, there are also games
that are about coming
up with stories.
We're being thrown in
a similar way--
well, in Munchkin, you're
kind of constructing the
story as you go.
But in the games that we're
going to play today, or some
of you are, like Gloom or Once
Upon a Time, the game is being
able to produce a narrative.
Being able to make sense given
the specific cues.
You've had your hand up?
AUDIENCE: I was going to do the
opposite extreme of a game
with a very basic story, and you
kind of make a story up as
you go along, but it's not
really that crazy.
This card game, Falling, where
pretty much the pretense is
you are [UNINTELLIGIBLE], and
you're falling to your demise.
And so while you guys are
falling, you guys decide we'll
make a contest of who hits
the ground last.
And so it's a real-time game,
and you're dealt cards in
order, and it keeps
going until you
reach the ground card.
And so you can attack
other people.
OK, this is going to
happen to you and
different effects happen.
And so when you're actually
playing it, it's kind of like
the intensity when
you're falling.
Like, oh, I'm going to die, I
have to do this fast because,
before you know it, the ground
is already at you.
AUDIENCE: It's interesting
because it creates a longer
event of something that's
supposed is
supposed to be, pop!
Gone.
Scratch, right?
But it's kind of zooming in on
how long that would feel if
you were actually falling,
making a mini-story of that.
It's interesting because I don't
know how strongly-- this
is one of the questions we'll be
talking about in stories in
games is what kind of an
event constitutes an
event in the story?
Is opening a door an
Well, in some games, it can be
because it might give you
access to new areas, there might
be someone showing up
that changes things.
But in other cases, like
Monopoly, going around and
getting the--
how many, $100?--
$200, is that an event?
AUDIENCE: Maybe it's not.
It doesn't seem like a story
event because it's such a
mundane thing that happens all
the time, although clearly, it
has [INAUDIBLE].
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah, it
does have an effect, but as a
storytelling art, is kind
of questionable.
The other thing I wanted to ask
you, seeing as you guys
have been playing particular
board games, there are board
games that have similar
mechanics.
So, I played Race to the Galaxy,
which I really like.
And I've been told that
[? Potomac Coast ?]
is very similar, yes?
So does changing the theme--
those two games have
different themes--
but does changing the theme
affect the rules in any ways?
For those of you who might
have played both?
AUDIENCE: Not really.
Not for--
San Juan, I think is closer.
San Juan is with the cards.
But it doesn't really change
the game, because the
mechanics are almost
identical.
It's just covered in a different
shell, or whatever
it is, whatever the mechanic
they're trying to mimic.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So it's
like maybe you don't like
colonial or whatever--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, if you
don't like the--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: The
science fiction part--
AUDIENCE: The science fiction
theme, you could go for this
more Earth town building
theme.
But if you don't like playing
the game itself, switching to
the other game is probably
not going
to be all that different.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes, yeah,
which I think is kind of
interesting, and it's like,
so [INAUDIBLE].
Yes?
AUDIENCE: The interesting thing
is that in neither of
those cases, unlike, say,
Ticket to Ride, do these
things feel like they're
tacked onto the theme?
And in each case, the actual
mechanics of the card
faithfully represent what
they're supposed to be in the
game fiction, right?
So I feel that the fact that
the themes are essentially
interchangeable, or that the
same mechanics underlie both
games, despite the fact that
they have different themes,
doesn't necessarily mean
that there's something
wrong with the theme.
It's just that--
AUDIENCE: But the meaning
is similar--
AUDIENCE: It's just that the
mechanics are flexible, or
something like that.
AUDIENCE: But what I mean, the
meaning of what you actually
do in the games is similar.
Resource management, planning
ahead, knowing when you can
deploy a certain--
they are about the same
thing, even if they
have different settings.
So that's probably
the connection.
It's not about oh, if you like
science fiction games, you can
play the Battlestar Galactica
game, Race to the Galaxy,
whereas I'm guessing that for
most people, it's, well, if I
like Puerto Rico, or I'm
thinking of San Juan, sorry,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] wrong place.
AUDIENCE: Their themes
are close enough.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
But you would play
something that is similar.
Does that make sense?
AUDIENCE: If the meaning of both
games is really empire
building in some sense, right?
In San Juan, it's got historic
themes, and Race to the Galaxy
it's futuristic.
But they're both empire
building.
The theme is very well defined
in both of these games.
That will make sense because
both themes are about empire
building, only one's in the
future and one's in the past.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
OK, so we have--
this has taken a bit of the
time, but these are the
foundations of the concepts that
I wanted to get across
today and discuss today.
When we talk about video games,
there's an extra layer,
which is video games that are
story driven versus just games
with a story.
An example I have here.
So this is Soul Calibur 2,
as far as I remember--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
Soul Calibur II--
[INAUDIBLE]
I think so.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
I don't know.
[INAUDIBLE]
Soul Calibur hoping that it was
familiar to [INAUDIBLE]
designing.
Anyway, so in Soul Calibur,
what's the game about?
AUDIENCE: Fighting.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: It's about
fighting hand-to-hand.
AUDIENCE: It has some
weird story.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: And it
does have a weird story that's
like, well, does anybody
know the story?
I know that there's something,
and there's some reason why
Sandra or Sophitia--
Sophitia, right?
I don't know.
I think her sister is Sandra.
AUDIENCE: They're related
somehow, they're mother and
daughter or brothers or
sisters or something.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Oh, OK.
Maybe that's what she's
asking for.
I didn't know.
I still like these games.
But do I know their stories?
No.
But does it?
Eh, not really.
Enough of these.
For some people, I'm sure that
they do care about the stories
of these, or the stories of
the characters in Street
Fighter, for example.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Well I was going to
say for games like this, I
actually kind of like the
story because it adds--
the game is not the story.
There are two separate
entities.
But one kind of adds
to the other.
Like Diablo, for example.
There's lots of people that have
played Diablo II without
really caring about
the actual story--
AUDIENCE: Those cinematics were
so cool back in the day.
AUDIENCE: But even though you
can pretty much separate the
story from Diablo II and people
would probably still
play it, the story definitely
adds a layer of, I am attached
to this game.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: But
Diablo, in Diablo, the
difference is that Diablo's
closer to being a
story-driven game.
It's closer to being an
art-boutique game, where the
quests, you have to know who
you're going to talk to, what
are you going to do.
I had a friend, we were working
in this game service,
and we had to test all these
role-playing games.
And one of my coworkers was
like, oh, I have to play--
it was Baldur's Gate II.
One of the cool ones.
And he was like, OK, I have to
test this, and I just have to
see that it works.
And he was not paying attention
to any other text.
He was just doing the
technical testing.
But then he got stuck, and we
were supposed to finish the
games, and he was stuck, and he
was going slower because he
didn't know what to do.
I said, well, if you had read
what you actually had to do.
Well, for him, it was like,
it was just a story!
Well, you're playing an RPG.
You can't leave the story out.
Somebody's telling you that
you have to squash I don't
know how many arts, be happy
to know that you have to
support the arts.
You have to know where to go.
So in story-driven games, what
happens is that the story's
really so tied to the rules and
the goals of the game that
you have, as you advance in
the game, you're also
advancing in the story.
That something that, here, when
you beat up somebody in
Soul Calibur or Street Fighter,
whatever fighting
game you can think of, there
might be a little cut scene
that tells us who they are.
One thing that I like about--
is it Soul Calibur?
Yeah.
There's a bit of taunting,
like, oh, he beat me, or
something like that.
But that is building character a
bit, and that means writing.
But really, it's not really
story-driven.
The fact that we're getting
bits of the story as we
complete challenges, doesn't
mean that if we ignore the
game, we can still
complete the game
without knowing the story.
Does it make sense?
So this is something that video
games are doing that, to
a certain extent, some of the
board games that you might
have been playing
don't quite do.
Does it make sense?
We can still think of-- and
there might be some people who
play these board games still
at the mathematical level
without paying any attention
to what the event that's
representing of.
But that's one potential of
video games, that idea of
having a story-driven game where
you're playing a game,
you are interacting with the
world with a strong--
in the cases of story-driven
games, you also have the
struggle of a fictional world
that you are interacting with,
that you are exploring, that
you're poking around.
So one thing I wanted to make
clear here is that when we
talk about storytelling--
and let's try to use the term.
We're talking about the stories,
but is it really
storytelling?
And the thing is that
technically
games don't tell stories.
Who's telling the story?
Who's the narrator?
There might be games that have
a kind of gimmick of having
the narrator, like Prince of
Persia: Sands of Time.
When you make a mistake, and
he's supposed to be telling
what's happened to him, and he's
like, no, no, no, wait,
when are you guys going
to learn, no,
that's not how it happened.
But really, most games, again
like Baldur's Gate or Diablo,
or more recently like Mass
Effect, who is the
storyteller?
And the thing is that
there are also
different types of stories.
When we are interacting with a
game, what we are doing is
performing, and as we perform,
we are creating a story.
There's a story that has been
maybe prepared for us.
Going back to the Munchkin
thing, in every card, we have
a bit of the story, and we are
kind of putting it together,
laying it out.
So the game designers have
designed each game, each chunk
of the story, what
are the cues that
we're giving the player?
But then there's also what else
this player is bringing
to the game.
As I was saying before, there's
part that is the game
itself telling its story, and
the other is what we are
evoking, what we are having the
player bring to the game.
Is the story happening in
that player's head?
So what I'd like to say is
that it's not really
storytelling, it's about story
building, and as game
designers, we are designing
those little chunks.
We are creating stories that are
meant to be reconstructed,
that are meant to be together.
So the difference between
storytelling and story
building basically, when we
have storytelling, we have
somebody who's narrating, or
maybe there's someone who's
re-enacting what's happened,
so a thing like
theater, for example.
But this continuous, it's
something that just happens
and is not fragmented, which is
what story building means.
We have something that has
not already happened.
It's communicated one way, and
what those events are and what
order they're told, that's
determined by the author.
If we think about stories and
how stories apply to games in
terms of story building,
we're talking
about fragmented stories.
Stories in pieces.
Stories that we have to put
together like a puzzle.
And we're game designers.
We make puzzles.
That's one of the many things
that we can do.
What those fragments are, how
are we giving cues to the
player to put together those
fragments, or to come up with
their own ways of coming
up with the story.
In a way, it's a kind of
collaboration between the
designer and the player, because
we rely on the player
to put this story together, to
come up with their own ways of
filling the gaps, to really
have a proactive role in
figuring out what the story
is, and what the
order of events is.
But there are--
you guys have seen the games of
progression and the games
of emergence?
Yes?
You discussed that?
AUDIENCE: Could you
[INAUDIBLE]
I'm trying to remember
where this--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: It's like
the [INAUDIBLE] in the
first chapter, second chapter?
AUDIENCE: Well it's
a seperate--
I think we had actually looked
at the individual paper.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, we have the
individual, not the book.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Not the chapter?
AUDIENCE: But it's basically
the same thing.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: OK, yeah,
because he talked about
the same thing in a couple
of different places.
So what happens is that at
times, there are games that
have a specific order of events,
and there are some
adventure games, like Syberia
for example, where you have to
go through a very specific
sequence of events, and when
you get to a scene it's like,
you have to do this.
Things like Dragon's Lair,
the laser disc DVD.
When you go to a place and you
have to figure out what is the
action that you have to do, and
if you don't do it, you
die in horrible ways.
So those are games that set
the order of events very
specifically.
But most of the games tend to
have some more flexibility,
and let the players
explore the world.
Things that happen in the world
are generated by how the
player is interacting
with the world.
So in RPGs, for example,
depending on the RPG, there
might be the main quest and
the side quests, and there
might be flexibility in what
order that happens.
Even how a player might solve
a specific quest.
In terms of table top, who here
has been dungeon master?
OK, a bunch of you.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
OK, so we have a
corner of dungeon masters.
So you probably know that when
you design a quest, and then
you set it up, and you have your
players, and then your
players come up with a couple of
different ways of tackling
your quest, whatever they
can come up with.
And you have to improvise
and try to--
you're building the rails
of their living.
It's like they're trying
to anticipate what
they're going to do.
So we're trying to get that into
video games, too, but we
don't have the improvisational
capacity built
into computers yet.
But as you see, it's like the
dungeon masters, as dungeon
masters, we're responding to
the actions of the player.
Does it make sense?
When we're talking about story
building, there are games, as
I was saying, that are about
story building, where the
challenge is constructing a
story, improvising as you go.
You're given chunks, and you
have to be able to be a
storyteller.
But you'll play these later.
We've actually talked
about this before.
So when we're talking about
building the fictional world
of the game--
I'm going to [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
through this a bit fast.
We have until 4:30, right?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: OK.
So there are also very minimal
ways in which we can construct
our fiction, and these are
lessons that I've taken from
digital games.
But if you think about it, many
of these also apply to
non-digital games.
So for example, we have the
title of a game can tell us
something about the fictional
world, right?
What about board games
or card games?
How do the titles build
the fictional world?
AUDIENCE: The board game Mafia
Wars is pretty clear about
what you're doing.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
So that's a way.
It's evoking some things,
like the type or
kind of world on itself.
And also setting
the situation.
So here, Mafia Wars is about
AUDIENCE: Mafia having--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: There's
different factions.
AUDIENCE: Getting in trouble--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
There's going--
yeah.
There's going to be betrayal
probably, shooting down people
in horrible ways.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Any licensed game?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Any licensed game?
Yes.
Thought at times, things like
versions of Monopoly or
Trivial Pursuit where
it's kind of like--
AUDIENCE: Star Wars--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Star
Wars everything.
AUDIENCE: Risk gets
kind of broad.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: And there
are also skimmings of
Risk, right?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, lots.
AUDIENCE: Lord of the Rings.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Lord of
the Rings everything, too.
Kind of like Barbie.
AUDIENCE: I just feel like
there are so many Risks.
AUDIENCE: I know there's
[? God's ?] which takes place
back in like mythological,
[INAUDIBLE]?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
apart from franchises, what
other titles are--
AUDIENCE: The Settlers
of Catan.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Settlers
of Catan, which is evoking--?
AUDIENCE: Settling.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Building cities.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Building, sure.
AUDIENCE: San Juan.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
San Juan's going to--
that's what you told me, too.
AUDIENCE: Chinatown.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Chinatown?
AUDIENCE: It's set
in Chinatown.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
And what do you do?
AUDIENCE: You build businesses
that are stereotypically
associated with being
in Chinatown.
[LAUGHTER]
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So with
one title, it's not only we're
evoking the world, but we
can also evoke rules.
What do you have
to do to here?
So like Mafia Wars,
you kill people.
But then, Settlers of Catan.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: But you
are maybe playing what some of
the rules are, what the game
is about, which is what is
important here.
And again, Soren Johnson calls
attention to the fact that if
you're announcing that your game
is about something in the
description booklet, the people
might not always read,
or at least a part of
people don't read.
You should follow up with that,
because it's helping,
it's giving cues to the player
about how is the story of the
game going to build up.
What is the key?
I like talking about giving
keys to the player a lot
because I come from theater.
It's a very intuitive way
of understanding.
It's not about us selling the
story, it's about helping the
player construct the story.
So I have two examples from
video games I really like
about how to build a fictional
world with a title.
One obvious one in video games
is Space Invaders, right?
Space Invaders means we're
on Earth and--
AUDIENCE: Invaders, aliens.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Invaders
from space, and we'll probably
have a fight.
AUDIENCE: Invading from space.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Another good one,
Zombies Ate My Neighbors.
There's a whole story
right there.
So what's the story
of this game?
AUDIENCE: Zombies ate
the neighbors?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: The
zombies ate the neighbors?
So what do I do in this game?
AUDIENCE: Probably
kill zombies.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So
probably killing zombies.
AUDIENCE: Are zombies
eating my neighbors?
Or the zombies ate my neighbors
and then just left.
AUDIENCE: Maybe the zombies
are your neighbors.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
maybe you have to kill your
neighbors, too, now.
If there's anything left,
because they ate them.
But this is a whole situation.
What do I have to do?
OK, zombies.
Whacking zombies, I'm sure,
or running away from them.
AUDIENCE: The fact that you
have neighbors in the
neighborhood, right?
It's not like a military
zombie shooter.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes,
it's not Resident Evil.
AUDIENCE: They looked
vaguely like '50s.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
I'm not sure about that.
This is like a Genesis game.
AUDIENCE: I just played a
game with an old, like--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yeah, yeah, right.
AUDIENCE: Harkening back to the
zombie movies of the day.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah.
Another great title that I found
not too long ago, Earth
Dies Screaming.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: Wow.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Which is
actually about the '70s--
AUDIENCE: Whoa.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: The title
is from a '70s British
movie that I think has nothing
to do with the game.
This is like Space Invaders
in a way.
You are defending the earth,
it kind of looks like that.
You have your space ship, and
you have invaders, and you
have to destroy it before
it lands on earth.
But again, it's very
evocative.
It's more memorable than Space
Invaders in a way,
because it's got--
there's people attacking
earth, whoever it is.
And this is going
to end badly.
That's another thing, but Space
Invaders and things like
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and all those arcade games that
do have an ending, you
know the ending.
You cannot really save earth.
It's really ominous in a way.
But again, we have a whole.
We have a whole situation
is about--
in the title.
It's also very memorable.
I really like this title.
Another way in which
we can give cues to
players to build worlds--
and I had more of this, but
this applies more to video
games than to board games,
card games, and even
role-playing games, is
character design.
Because when we are making--
and tell me from your
own experience--
but when you're making
non-digital games, and even
when you're preparing your
Dungeons & Dragons campaign,
you don't really come up
with the characters.
The characters is something
that the player brings.
For card games, if you have any
examples that are counter
examples for this, please
let me know.
But character design is not
something that you do so much
in non-digital games.
Do you have any examples
of that?
AUDIENCE: Well, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
can be.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yeah, in a way, yes.
AUDIENCE: I was thinking
[? Acompora ?]
and other games where you have
a character which is assigned
to you and often they
have back story.
In [? Acompora ?] there's
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], Byron, or
what have you.
AUDIENCE: I was going to
say the game where
you're trying to--
Clue, Clue.
Where you choose a character
and they all have their
[INAUDIBLE] and whatnot.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
The things that I--
As a player, are you really
involved with those
characters?
AUDIENCE: I think I can think
of one game which is an
example where you are, and
it's called Android.
This game was released, I think,
two years ago now, and
part of the--
actually, you should
probably play it--
part of the point is that
it was trying to include
developments of--
resolving characters' personal
stories through
mechanics in the game.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Oh, yeah.
AUDIENCE: So you're actually
playing through this choose
your own adventure-ish
type scenario.
And the choices that you make
throughout the game influence
what directions your
character's
personal story arc.
It's a very good game.
But it's interesting, right?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah, what
I'm trying to get at here
is that at times, the
characters are--
and again, evoking actions,
evoking certain emotions, too.
I think that that detachment
with non-digital games--
with role-playing games,
it's different.
But again, when you're building
your own characters
in role-playing, you have an
investment when you're making
it yourself.
I'm talking more of the point
of view of the designer.
Here?
AUDIENCE: So another
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] game again,
Battlestar Galactica.
You are assigned a character,
and if you know Battlestar
Galactica, you're probably
going to go for certain
characters, because like, oh,
that character's hilarious, I
want to be him, or,
I'm going to be
Starbuck, Starbuck's awesome.
And then each player actually
also has certain traits, which
are characteristic of their--
for the player in the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], like
[? tie ?], except he's now
taller, so there's a certain
negative attribute to him if
you're in a certain situation.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: OK.
All right, we have--
near the back.
AUDIENCE: I was going to say
in live-action role-playing
games, like expansion,
Assassin's Guild, and stuff,
the characters are entirely
designed by the game designers.
But you still get the players
who take up this character and
become involved with it, because
all of their actions
are based on what the designer
chose to make that character.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yep, yep,
that's true, that's true.
And one?
AUDIENCE: Two other games.
Cosmic Encounter is where
probably a lot closer to the
thousand island kind of
situation you've got.
You pick a race at the beginning
of the game.
So it's not a single
character.
But that's effectively the same
thing in that, if you
pick something like the Cubans,
you have different
goals, and you have different
powers that you
can use in the game.
Whereas if you play a game like
Illuminati, instead of
playing an individual you're
playing a corporation, or
actually a [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
for society, for the most part,
and your actual game
winning goals are different,
depending on who you pick.
And part of the game is also
figuring out what certain
characters are trying-- how
certain characters are trying
to win the game, because not
everybody has the same game
winning goal.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: OK.
Patrick, last one.
AUDIENCE: In the card game
Saboteur, if your role is the
saboteur, then it is in the
player's best interest to act
in that role.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: To
perform like what?
AUDIENCE: Yes, to be some person
to the other players
without letting them catch on.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Well, awesome.
You see, and this is why, I
think, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I was asking.
Yeah, I think the LARPing one
is the obvious case, yeah.
In video games, what we do,
we can build character in
cinematic ways and cut scenes
and whatever, but really, it's
very difficult to build a
character that is at the same
time you, and not you are the
player and not the player.
And what we can do is give
them cues about the
personality of that character.
And one of the examples I wanted
to give was Sonic,
because Sonic is
not really you.
This is always the--
a bit of this trouble in a lot
of the examples that you were
doing, except for LARPing, where
LARPing is a bit more
involved, is that it's kind
of like you but not you.
Who am I?
I'm the saboteur, because
I'm doing this.
In games, we have Sonic,
for example.
We are Sonic.
What are we?
We are a blue hedgehog.
And what do we do?
AUDIENCE: Collect rings.
AUDIENCE: Run.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So, run
and collect coins, and
liberating cute animals.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yes, that too.
And one of the things, one of
the goals of designing a
character, particularly
in video games, is
making it seem alive.
Making it go beyond the
functional part.
Like, oh, we are the saboteur,
we are whatever character in
Clue, for example.
Having that emotional
involvement, that is something
that we are trying to achieve
in video games.
And Sonic does it in a very
subtle, very cool way.
Does anybody know what
this picture is of?
What he's doing?
AUDIENCE: When you don't do
anything, he starts tapping
his foot and looking at you.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So it's
kind of like, you're not
controlling me.
Come on.
I wanna go.
I really have to go.
I have to run, because
what I do is running.
So, let's go.
AUDIENCE: Mario goes to sleep.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yeah, Mario goes to
sleep, that's right.
AUDIENCE: Starts--
[INAUDIBLE]
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: And do
you remember any of the
Earthworm Jim games?
He does crazy stuff.
He starts--
he flips his head, and he
dresses up, like he is
thinking, why don't I--
Yeah.
Or he gets an afro wig
at some point.
What are you doing?
But it's pulling attention
to, who am I?
When you're not controlling me,
I'm gonna do it myself.
And is the case of Sonic, it's
like, OK, I'm a running guy,
but I need you to
run, so come on.
And it's very subtle, something
that is very
minimal, but is building
character, but is also telling
the player who this
character is.
The last thing-- and this is
something that, again, video
games can do very well-- is
something that role-playing
games can do very well, or
LARPing, but I'm not sure that
card games or board games can
do this, is environmental
storytelling.
It's telling the story in the
space as you go around, as
you're examining the space
and what's going on.
Video games, what they do very
well, is construction of a
virtual world that we can
navigate, that we can explore,
that we can interact with.
And one of--
those of you who've been in my
classes before, you know that
I love the beginning of Bioshock
as an example of
environmental story telling,
because you know what is this
world, what has happened before,
and they don't tell it
with a word.
It's just going to the
space and figuring
out what has happened.
Another example that I really
love is Portal where a lot of
the story is told, or you
figure it out, as
you explore the world.
So what is this in Portal?
So, first of all, what is the
premise of Portal, the story?
AUDIENCE: You're a test subject
testing a new device
at Aperture Labs.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes,
so you're a test subject.
But very soon, you realize
that there's
something kind of wrong.
This voice that keeps talking
to, kind of warps around, and
she goes and comes back.
But there's something broken,
and you just go on because you
don't know what else to do.
But here, what is this?
Once you start realizing, OK,
there's something really
wrong, what is this?
AUDIENCE: This is when you're
trying to escape.
AUDIENCE: The hole
in the wall.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
There's a hole--
AUDIENCE: One of the things is
stuck forward, and you can
sneak under it or something?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah, you
go behind the scenes and
you realize, OK, so there's
something really wrong here, I
kind of guessed it, but here
we have what looks like
somebody's refuge, like where
somebody was hiding, and they
were writing all
these messages.
And, of course, it's very funny,
because the famous "The
cake is a lie," is not something
that everybody has
to go through.
You have to find it.
You have to find
it in the game.
It's part of exploring
the game.
So the reason why I like--
I like Portal for many,
many reasons--
but one is because the
storytelling is very
brilliant--and is not something
that we're told,
this is what happened.
We figure it out. by listening
to the voice, by listening to
GlaDOS, by going behind
the scenes.
We are piecing the
story together.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: If you ever pay
attention to what's written on
the wall in the safe houses in
Left for Dead, there's a lot
of funny stuff, as well.
And I initially hadn't realized
Left for Dead had a
story, really.
And then, when you actually
pause and read what's written
on the walls in the safe houses,
there's almost flame
wars between different people
who run to the same houses and
are writing facts about the
zombie apocalypse, and saying,
oh, that's not true, that town
is completely overrun, no,
you're totally stupid, I was
there last week, and it had
these things going on and
various two bits of trivia and
facts about the world.
And it's very, very clever,
and often quite hilarious.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Because
what environment storytelling
is doing, after all, we're
telling the story of the
fictional world.
That can be part of the goal of
solving games, figuring out
what is the story of the
fictional world?
Yes, Andrew?
AUDIENCE: Was there a conscious
decision to use
environmental storytelling as
opposed to story building?
Well, you mentioned the
difference between
storytelling and story building
earlier, and you
mentioned that that was
environmental story telling as
opposed to story building.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
and probably is
really story building.
So the thing is that
environmental storytelling is
what people call it.
I'm using a phrase.
But yeah, this is a type
of story building.
We're building a
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], build it for
the player.
But yeah, this is
story building.
PROFESSOR: More precisely,
you will see talks on
environmental storytelling when
you go to a conference.
But what they're really talking
about, so you know, is
just that [INAUDIBLE] involved
in research.
AUDIENCE: So maybe the closest
to this kind of thing is in
flavor text in CCG's and
other such stuff.
So if you think, for instance,
of Magic the Gathering, then
there is a back story
behind each of these
expansions which comes out.
And that's told through actual
fiction, where you can buy a
really trashy novel.
[LAUGHTER]
But it's also told through
little quotes between--
by significant the characters
in the fiction, also the
images which are presented
on the cards.
So, maybe that's the closest
thing to environmental story
telling in--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yes, yeah.
Magic the Gathering has this
world, and it seems to be very
easy expand it.
I don't know if there's a
bible of the Magic the
Gathering world.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, yeah, there's an
entire creative department
at Wizards of the Coast that's
responsible for maintaining
the story and making sure it's
all consistent and stuff.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So it's
not really something--
it's almost 4:00, so I have
still something, but we can go
through it very fast
if that works?
PROFESSOR: If we run out of
time, we can play these games
on Friday or something.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: OK.
PROFESSOR: If that sounds
like a good idea.
All right.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So, we've
been talking so far
about designing the story of
world, designing the story of
the fictional world.
What we also have, as I was
saying before, the players
also construction a
story as we go.
Things that happen to the
player, things that happen in
the world, because they
happen to the player.
And again, one of the reasons
why I was talking about games
of progressions versus games
of emergence is that in
stories, we have a similar
parallel of stories that have
been designed for the player,
things that they have to do in
role-playing games, and I'm
talking about pen and pencil--
pen and paper role-playing
games, we have the story that
as the end we have designed,
and then there's what the
players are trying to do.
In video games, because
computers don't have the
capacity for improvisation, what
the player has to do is a
lot more constrained in a way.
So what are the bosses
that they have to--
how do they solve a specific
problem, or how do we get over
a specific problem.
So I like giving the example
of Legend of Zelda games,
where we do have a story that
we're completing almost in a
specific order, because if you
don't have certain objects,
you can't go to the next stage
until you have certain
properties.
So even though we have a really
nice, relatively open
world, a world that we can
navigate, we do have a
specific order of events
that we have to follow.
Adventure games, it might be
something like point and click
adventure games, again, things
like Syberia, things like
Myst, where there is a
pre-established sequence of
events that we have
to go settle.
And then, the other extreme, we
have games that are closer
to these games like Once Upon
a Time, or Gloom where the
system itself is producing
stories of
sorts, like in The Sims.
And in The Sims, the fact that
we have a way to record our
own stories and share them is
proof that that's a kind of
system closer to things
like Once Upon a Time.
That is, the system can generate
narratives, and that
playing with the system will
generate some narratives.
So we have ways in which, as
designers, we can provide cues
or ways to design the
story of the player.
And the first one is the
game premise, what is
the goal of the game?
Game events, I don't know if
I'll let that one, because
that was too long.
And we have [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
a narrative.
The game premise is who are
you in the game, what
do you do in it.
It's kind of similar to the
title, but in this case, is
very tied to who is the player,
what is the role of
the player in the game?
So things like Cooking
Mama, for example.
You're Cooking Mama, so who
are you, Cooking Mama?
You're not mama.
Mama's complaining about you.
You are the person who's
cooking for Mama.
That's the title they should
have, Cooking for Mama.
And then now they're getting
pissed off at you because you
didn't do it right.
But it tells you basically
so you're a cook.
Or what is it that you do.
You're trying to please
Mama by cooking
something nice and yummy.
Usually, also kind of weird.
A really good example of
creating the story of the
player by the premise of who you
are in the game is this.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
I love this example.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Because
it's like, who are you?
You're a hacker.
And it gives you--
the cool thing about this
trailer is it gives you a list
of what you do.
This is your story.
You are framing people,
you are framing
innocent people, of course.
Maintaining people's academic
records, building their
devices, and all those are
activities in the game, but
it's also who you are.
That is your story.
Those are the kinds of things
that you're going to be doing
in the game.
So again, we were talking
about Saboteur before.
Well, as saboteur, you already
have a series of actions that
you associated with the
your character.
That is way that we can design
the story of the player, at
least at the higher level,
and give it that cue.
I'm skipping game events because
it's kind of long and
it's very, very strong.
Two basic video games, and
mostly [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
The other example that I
want to make here is
micronarratives.
And again, all these are more
video game things, but
micronarratives are little
events, they're not even cut
scenes, they're just little
events that happen as
reactions to the player's
actions.
In a way, Sonic tapping his foot
is a kind micronarrative.
You're not doing anything,
come on, I want to go.
Or Mario falling asleep
is kind of like a
micronarrative of sorts.
This is one of my favorite
micronarratives
in these video games.
This is the game Jet Set Willy,
which is from 1985,
maybe, something, middle '80s.
It was for Commodore 64.
Well, it was originally
for the--
AUDIENCE: Spectrum.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yes, thank you.
He's prepared a presentation
on the Spectrum, yes.
Commodore 64 and surrounding
this world is Z80 platforms in
the '80s, and this was a
sequel to Manic Miner.
So Manic Miner, you were
Miner Willy, yes?
Miner Willy.
And you go down into the
earth, and you find a
treasure, and you become
immensely rich.
So with the money that you get
from the first game, you throw
a party, and you throw such a
big party that your house
becomes invaded by the weirdest
creatures ever.
There are flying toilet seats,
mutant pigs, I don't know.
AUDIENCE: Sounds like
a good party.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah, such
a good party that you get
people from other worlds
to come to your party.
But the thing was that it was
such a good party, you wanted
to go to bed.
This is Willy.
This is you in the game.
So in Jet Set Willy, this is the
day after, and Willy is is
hungover probably after
the super party.
And he was in a bed.
In the game, to the left, you
have the picture of the bed,
and that's your goal,
go to bed.
But this is your landlady, who's
seen how you trashed the
place, and she doesn't want you
to go to bed until you've
cleaned it up.
So the cool thing, they
really want to get--
and then, the animation here--
is that she has her
arms like this.
She's holding her arms like
this, and whenever
you get near her--
which arm is it?--
her left arm, she
goes like, ha!
Go.
And it's a reaction
to what you do.
With this, it's a few pixels.
It's probably four
or five pixels.
And in four or five pixels, this
game is telling you this
is what you have to do.
Go that way.
This is your goal,
you asked me.
You've gotta come here, go that
way, and clean it up.
And this is eight bit pixels!
And she's telling you all that
with just a few pixels.
You don't really
need that much.
But with that kind of reaction,
we always want to,
again, gives cues.
What is it that the
player has to do?
We don't need a cut scene.
With a few pixels, we know what
we have to do, right?
And it's a very difficult game,
too, for today's standards.
Anyway, so the conclusion
here is that
why do we need stories?
Why do we need fictions?
What do fictional worlds
do for us?
What do themes do for us?
As we were saying, humans have
a tendency the story-icize
everything.
We are natural storytellers.
Some of what these games like
Once Upon a Time or
[? Bloom ?]
are playing with is because we
tell other people what has
happened to us.
If you complain about something,
you're complaining
in the form of a story
if something might
have happened to you.
We understand our experiences
as stories, and there are
different disciplines that
have dealt with this from
computer science
to psychology.
How we are making stories about
ourselves, how we are
making stories about
our worlds.
So having a story, having a
game that has a fictional
world in which a story can
take place is a way of
understanding the underlying
system.
As I was saying, if we have a
game that is called Mafia
Wars, we already have a goal, we
have sets of rules, who we
are, what is it that
we have to do.
We don't need a lot of--
two words have been enough
to evoke a lot of that
information.
So the last thing, and this
applies a bit more to video
games, is that by having a
story, we're also providing
consistency to the world.
When Jesper Juul is talking
about incoherent worlds, he's
really talking about worlds
where there's not really a
story, and there are video games
that have awful stories,
that's true.
But when you're forced, or when
you're thinking about
your world not only as a
fictional world as a
simulation, but also as a world
that has to produce a
story that makes sense, that
is going to provide more
coherence to the world
hopefully.
We have to [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But that means that you can take
the [UNINTELLIGIBLE] for
games, [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And there are things that yes
there are complains about,
like why does Mario
have to realize?
Well, because it's
Mario, right?
Is that part of the story?
That's one of those no-man's
land issues.
Does that undermine the
consistency of the world?
Maybe the anthological level,
the level of the world itself.
But really, it's more about
making sense about the rules.
What is it--
being able to look at the
world in a critical way.
I'm trying to think
of an example of--
apart from the three
lives of Mario--
AUDIENCE: He was a plumber.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: What?
AUDIENCE: I thought you
said he was a plumber.
Oh no, that was in the theme.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: No,
but for example, Kirby.
He eats other creatures
and spits them.
Where does it come from?
Why does it do that?
What is the story of Kirby?
He's kind of cute, but hey, I
would watch out with him,
because he can eat almost
anything, and then
he just dumps it?
AUDIENCE: Kirby's a weirdly
disturbing character.
[LAUGHTER]
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes,
if you think about
it in terms of stories.
But this is kind of wow.
AUDIENCE: Yoshi, too, right?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes.
And I love Yoshi.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, and that's
another video game character--
it seems like one of the reasons
why these arguments
have been raised is because
there have been these huge
piles of inconsistencies.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: But the
inconsistency has become--
I think that when you try
to write the story,
if that makes sense.
So Yoshi eats creatures and--
AUDIENCE: Then he
spits them out.
Each one.
Depends on which Mario you're
talking about, because if it's
Super Mario World--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: I'm
thinking of Yoshi's Island.
AUDIENCE: Okay, yeah,
in Yoshi's Island,
yeah, he poops eggs.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah, and
is like, hm, and then he
throws it, and they're
like bombs?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, he throws
his eggs at--
he uses his eggs as weapons.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah, but
all of those things become
evident the moment that
we start his story
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So who is this person, what do
they do, why do they do this?
Wow, it's kind of
falling apart.
So the incoherence--
and I'm just thinking that I
don't know if you guys will
really like this or not--
but the incoherence comes
from the impossibility--
or not impossibility, but the
problems of trying to make
this into a story and
realizing, well,
this has not been--
this has been thought out as a
cool game, and I love Yoshi's
Island, but as a story, it
kind of falls apart.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: I think one of the
really glaring inconsistencies
in a lot of RPGs in particular
is that in most of these
worlds, there's some kind of
resurrection card, and there
are a lot of plots which revolve
around character dying
and that being a bad thing,
but then you're like, why
don't you just use your
Phoenix Down or--
why do we care if the human is
being assassinated, I've got
this thing in my inventory which
will bring him back.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes, I
wished that about Aeris like a
thousand times, and no, because
this guy kills her?
Then what kind of--
AUDIENCE: The actual conceit
there is you're not dead,
you're just knocked out.
So it's like smelling
salts or something.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: But
there are games like
Planescape: Torment where that
is incorporated in the--
you're immortal, and that's the
thing, figuring out why
you're immortal.
They make fun of you waking
up, and you go like, oh my
goodness, this really hurts,
I feel terrible!
And then making that
problem into an
essential part of the game.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So, with the RPG
thing, the incoherency is how
so many times when you're in
these battles, you're doing
these incredible things.
Like you're summoning asteroids
or jumping in the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But then in the game world,
you get to a ledge, and
they're like, oh,
it's a ledge.
I have to go around.
Or it's a gap like this wide.
I can't step over it because
of a bush, oh no!
What am I going to do?
There's a bush in the way.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
But you're
thinking diagonals, too.
What?
No, I cannot do diagonals.
AUDIENCE: I think another
egregious inconsistency that
comes up a lot is the--
and I think it's explicitly
mentioned in the reading--
that you're the world savior
usually, and on the way,
you're going to pillage, steal,
kill innocent people,
and it's not going
to be a big deal.
And even in games where they
make the endpoint variable, so
all right, you can either save
the world to or be a total
jerk, and that fixes one
problem, they still have the
problem that during the game,
you can alternate back and
forth between being really good
and really bad, and all
it does is it kind of swings
you one way or the other.
It's one dimensional.
So you're sort of just in a
spectrum, and if you do five
really bad things and then
five really good things,
you're back to where
you started.
And that's not necessarily
consistent in terms
storytelling.
AUDIENCE: Well, there's also the
classic inconsistency of
if I don't save the world,
everything will be destroyed,
but you're still going
to charge me 100
gil for this phoenix?
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: It's still
inconsistent.
AUDIENCE: Or, I have to save
the world now because bad
things are happening.
Let me go do these 20
side quests first.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: The
whole world is that--
AUDIENCE: This cat's
stuck in a tree!
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: There're rats
in the cellar,
man, rats in the cellar.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yes, but
the end of the world is nigh.
Like in Final Fantasy, the end
of the world is nigh, but let
me go around--
AUDIENCE: Blitzball!
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: --and get
more random encounters so
that I can bump up my stats.
AUDIENCE: So that actually
reminds me of--
I think it was a web-comic--
that I read around a month ago,
and it was based around,
oh my god, you're our savior!
You know how to solve it!
Yes, I am, and so the whole
time, he's just going on,
like, what are you doing?
They're raping and pillaging
everything, they're destroying
everything, what
are you doing?
Oh, I'll do that in a second,
I just have to get this
really, really cool shield.
And then at one point it's like,
why, what are you doing?
It's like, I'm fishing, so I
can get this lure, so I can
catch another fish.
Why would you ever be doing
this right now when the
world's about to end, and
evil is spreading across
everything?
He's like, don't worry
about it, I'm on it.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Well,
it's very interesting.
And this is my last slide,
so if you want to--
we can go on discussing.
PROFESSOR: Sure.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So at
times, the little cues that
are building world or building
character can also backfire.
So I've been playing one of the
DS Zelda games, and one of
the nicest touches is that
whenever you meet a character,
Link is going to look
at them in the eye.
Hi!
You're walking, and
it's like, hi.
And at times it's super weird,
because the characters look at
each other.
They acknowledge that they're
there, so they feel kind of
alive with a very simple
algorithm, where there's
another character, they
look at each other.
It's like, wow, they're alive,
cool, and they react.
But then, you go into somebody's
house, and they're
looking at you and
you're like, hi!
[BREAKING SOUND]
You know?
You break their pots
to get rupees.
And they're looking at you,
and you're breaking
everything.
And it's just like, this
is kind of weird.
They should react, because
they're looking at you while
you're breaking their house.
And that's, again, is giving a
touch that is making those
characters alive, but it's also
like breaking it, like,
I'm still breaking your pots.
I don't know what's better.
AUDIENCE: I think that
was subverted in--
no, in another Zelda game,
Link's Awakening?
You go into the shop, and the
shop owner is always looking
at you, so if you take something
off the shelf and
try to exit, he says, no,
you can't do that,
you can't steal it.
But if you run around him, he's
not fast enough to keep
his eye on you, so you run
around him until he's looking
away, and you can leave.
But if you come back in, he
says, you're the guy who stole
something, and he shoots
you with a laser.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: And then every
character in the game calls
you "thief" for the
rest of the game.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Ah,
that's really funny.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, it's awesome.
AUDIENCE: I was going to say,
Oblivion and Fallout do the
same, where everyone watches
you if they're within--
if they're acknowledging you,
and then you try to take
something, they're run up and be
like, why the hell are you
taking my stuff, or start
beating you up or whatever.
AUDIENCE: Or shooting you.
AUDIENCE: Or calling
the town guard.
But it's problematic when you're
powerful enough and you
can take the town guard.
Then it's just really annoying
because everywhere you go,
there's guys you can kill that
are kind of there, and you're
like, all right, come on,
get out of my way.
AUDIENCE: So there was a Mega
Man Legends which I don't know
if anybody ever played.
I don't think anyone ever
played that game.
But essentially it was like
Mega Man, but the
RPG style of game.
But it was actually slightly
different from most RPGs.
Most RPGs, you just walk around,
walking into people's
houses, looking for loot.
But you actually couldn't just
walk into people's houses.
Their doors would be locked.
And you could knock and see if
anybody was there, but it was
kind of interesting, because it
was actually consistent, in
the sense that you couldn't
just randomly walk into
somebody's house and
steal their crap.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So one
thing that I wanted to ask--
because all these things in
video games, after a while,
they result in [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
right?
Because we have the possibility
of having a
fleshed out world that we can
interact with, that is
simulated, and the times where
those cracks are showing,
where the system is is showing,
when it's showing
that this is limited, that we've
chosen a specific level
of abstraction to simulate
the world.
But do those incongruencies
bother people in board games
or card games so much?
AUDIENCE: I would argue that
sometimes it's a little bit of
a speed bump to learning
what's going on.
Assuming some [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
assuming
that is incoherent.
It seems like because it's
almost impossible to play a
card game or a board game
without first understanding
the rules, unlike in video games
where you can just jump
right in, that is usually
something that can be
surmounted if people say, oh,
the rules say this, but the
theme says that, OK, I
understand how to play by the
rules, and be able to
step over that.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
and I think that that's an
excellent point, and when we
start playing a board game,
probably what you guys do in
this class, is you get a new
board game.
What do you do?
You pick up the instructions
and you're figuring out the
rules first, and
not the world.
In a lot of video games, we
figure out the world first,
and then by exploring
the world, we're
figuring out the rules.
And even if there are games that
are giving us tutorials
or manuals, who--
I don't know, not many people
read the manuals, if at all.
AUDIENCE: While the game
is installing.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yes, [INAUDIBLE].
But manuals is not
something that--
even though it's going to be the
first thing to look at in
a board game and a card game.
And even, well, as a player, you
also look at the rule book
at least to built your own
character most times.
AUDIENCE: You mean on PC
and computer games?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: On
role-playing games.
AUDIENCE: Oh, are you
talking about table
top role-play games?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yes, table top.
AUDIENCE: Oh yeah, even
table top role-playing
games you try to start.
People start by looking
at their handbooks.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
LARPing might be a
good example of how--
LARPing, you're just
given your
AUDIENCE: Your character
sheet.
You have to read it.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Your
character sheet, which is very
interesting.
AUDIENCE: For role-playing, I
know a lot of people who can't
really be bothered to learn the
rules that thoroughly and
prefer just to experience the
story and have somebody tell
them how to resolve
the mechanics and
that kind of thing.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: But it's
funny, because when you're
building your character in a
table top role-playing game,
you still have to have a look
at what is the race that you
want, what is your religion,
what is your powers that you
want to choose?
Even if you're only playing for
kicks, and you don't care
so much about the rule.
And I'm the type of table top
role-player that prefers the
story, and I don't care
so much about combat.
But you still have to know the
rules even before you start
playing, if that makes sense.
AUDIENCE: There are situations
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] described
where people don't look at the
rules, but then they're
usually relying on the GM to
tell them what's allowed and
what's not allowed, which means
someone read the rules.
It's no different from someone
explaining to you a card game,
as opposed to having
the rules--
AUDIENCE: It actually makes
the experience a bit like
playing a computer game,
that the GM does the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Yeah, the GM is your
computer, and in fact it's
more powerful than a computer,
because a GM can figure out
what you're actually asking.
[LAUGHTER]
[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: I had a question
about the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], actually.
So one thing about card games
and board games is that almost
everything that gets revealed or
that happens in the middle
of the game is usually
a player mechanics.
Sometimes there's some loose
flexibility, like games where
they allow open negotiation
between specific players.
But most of it's actually in the
play of a card, the move
of a piece, something
like that.
And especially when you're
playing cards, you have to
play flavor text, especially for
cards where you can just
play them at any time.
And I've seen micronarratives
done--
at least what I think a
micronarrative seems to be--
done pretty well in
those instances.
In fact, in the example of
cards, right, someone tries to
do something that might win them
the game, but you play
this card, and that denies them
the win, but it is tied
up with some sort of flavor
text, some sort of thematic
element to that card.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Well,
it could be like--
in Monopoly, what is
the type of card?
Those two types of cards.
AUDIENCE: Go to jail?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: No.
AUDIENCE: Community
Chest and Chance?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Yeah,
like the Chance.
There's Chance when there's
something that happens to you,
but there's also--
AUDIENCE: Community Chest.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: --the
Community Chest, thank you,
which is something
that you play.
The differences in
micronarratives here, what it
means is something, it's a
reaction to player's events.
It's not something that the
player chooses to do.
Those reaction cards, those are
also part of the player's
narrative, and in a way, the
player is choosing, this is
going to happen now.
This is what Gloom is about, and
these are what these two
games are about most
of the time.
It's like you're trying to
construct a story, and you're
trying to tamper into somebody
else's story, so it's that
kind of reaction.
Yeah, we would have to
find a name for it.
But yeah, the micronarrative is
referring to something that
happens as reaction.
It's not something that
the player does.
AUDIENCE: It's often in reaction
to what another
player is doing.
So it depends on whose point
of view you are taking.
So, I've got a Community Chest
card, and I'm holding it until
somebody else is about to take
advantage of a position, and
then I deny them that.
So it's still a reaction
to what the
other player is doing.
AUDIENCE: Well, I just wanted
to mention, in terms of
micronarrative, I don't
know, would this
be a possible example?
In the board game that we're
designing, there's a computer
in the center that you want to
hack, and every time someone
tries to hack it,
it gets weaker.
So it's sort of a response to
someone doing an action on it.
Would that count as a
micronarrative, or is that
more of a mechanic?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: It
seems as an event it's
an important event.
It's a change of state.
But I don't know how much
of a story it is.
And there's no science to what
constitutes an event or not.
It's something that's part of
my research, it's something
that I'm going to figure out.
How can we identify what's an
event that is a rule and is
also an event in the story?
Because things like
disconnecting the computer, or
hacking the computer,
yeah, that seems to
be clearly an event.
What if we had each time that
it becomes weaker, there is
something else that
you can do.
So by hacking the computer,
there is a new action.
You get access to new areas
of the game, or you
get a new power up.
Or it's easier--
for example, if--
I'm totally hypothesizing
about what your game is
about-- but if you will have a
computer that is controlling
the security of a place,
whenever you hack a certain
part of the system, it's
letting you move faster
through the board.
In a way, that might be closer
to a micronarrative, because
it's a reaction, but it's
also a consequence.
AUDIENCE: In that case, in
Careers for Girls, when you
choose to go down a path, is
that a micronarrative?
Because the player chooses and
then sort of changes the
state, [INAUDIBLE].
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: I don't
know the choices, but the
events that happen, like what
happens when you land on
something, might be closer.
And again, it's kind of like,
it's a micronarrative?
AUDIENCE: Careers and Careers
for Girls, which I both see as
really, really appalling--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: I agree.
AUDIENCE: Seems to be built on
micronarratives, the whole
idea that everywhere you land,
something's happening--
you're granted something.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: But the
choice-- what I'm saying is
that the choice itself is not
the micronarrative, it's the
landing and what happens
when you land.
Oh wow.
It's almost time.
Anything else?
AUDIENCE: I actually wanted to
make one last comment about
emergent stories, particularly
the example of The Sims.
Is anybody familiar with
Alice and Kev?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so Alice
and Kev was this really
interesting experiment that this
guy did where he created
two homeless Sims,
a father and--
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: Ah, yes!
AUDIENCE: --a daughter.
AUDIENCE: I think we
talked about this--
AUDIENCE: And just did a sort
of a web-comic style display
of the lives of these two
homeless Sims as she grew up
and he got older.
And it almost seemed like it
became a role-playing game,
where the guy playing The Sims
became the dungeon master, who
had created these characters,
and then the AIs were playing
these characters for him.
In particular, there was this
one moment where he gets to a
part of the story where the
daughter has just gotten her
first paycheck, and
she decides to
donate it to charity.
And he keeps trying to keep
her from donating it to
charity, but she keeps
saying I want to
donate it to charity.
So eventually he lets her
And it was almost like it
was the character's
choice to donate it.
At the end of this blog that
he did about this specific
event, he's talking about what
does it mean when a video game
character that you created makes
you question your own
life choices?
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: This is a really
interesting thing.
If you haven't read it, you
should check it out.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Yeah, on what blog?
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: I think
it's aliceandkev.com,
something like that.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: It's
a story of the Sims 3.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA:
Any more?
AUDIENCE: Talking about
non-digital games being very
involved in your character, and
I felt like one game I've
played where I've been very
involved with a character is
Mafia, where there's
not a lot of actual
information given to you.
People are yelling at you, like,
you're the Mafia, the
way you smiled at him!
Clearly you guys--
I don't know.
CLARA FERNANDEZ-VARA: So you
become the character more by
how people see you than
how you play it?
AUDIENCE: I guess you're also
assigning character to other
people, reading into their
actions and things.
PROFESSOR: That's a game where
the roles are designed by the
designer, right?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but there's
only two roles.
It's not like--
AUDIENCE: Well no, there
can be a lot of roles.
AUDIENCE: There's a few roles.
AUDIENCE: I've seen websites
with a whole list of roles,
and some of them
are hilarious.
AUDIENCE: Seems good.
In digital games, I feel like
there are the games where you
have a very defined character,
unlike this.
If you have a very defined
character in a video game, you
tend to get into it more,
whereas Fable, your character
isn't defined, and changes based
on the actions you use.
If you're evil, he becomes
ugly and he gets
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] things.
But I never felt like I
identified with the character
at all versus games that already
give me a very strong
character, and I play
a certain way.
PROFESSOR: That's odd because
that's completely--
that runs against what you
would be trying to do, at
least, that's why they're
marketing games that are
trying to do it, to make you
feel closer to the character
because it's the reflection
of who you are.
AUDIENCE: I think that Bioshock
does a better job of
that, where you never
see the guy.
So you're always just looking
through his eyes, and he has
essentially no personality, at
least, no personality is
displayed in the game.
So it's almost as if
you are directly
interacting with the world.
PROFESSOR: You're given
a space to to be--
AUDIENCE: To actually project
yourself into the game, which
I think is sort of what Fable
was trying to do, but doesn't
really do a good job of it.
Because you see him
right there, and
he's clearly not you.
AUDIENCE: I feel like Torment
is a really--
Planescape: Torment has a really
interesting take on
this, where the character is
essentially who it is that you
play in that, but there's more
to it than that, because
there's also back story to the
character, which you, the
character, have forgotten,
and it's
revealed to you over time.
But you know more of that
character, who your character
was back then, than you know
about your character now.
So your nature changes over
time, and you've gone through
several iterations of this.
And none of them is the truer
or more correct you.
AUDIENCE: The funny thing about
Planescape: Torment,
it's kind of like a
personality test.
I've been playing it again, and
the first time I played
through, I was chaotic good?
And I was trying to
play different.
I'm still chaotic good.
So I'm kind of freaking out.
OK, I'm really trying to do
something different, but I'm
still in the same alignment.
Because a lot of your
definition of--
and actually, your alignment can
also decide items that you
can get or things that
you can do--
but it's based on your choices
and how you tackle a quest.
If you lie, for example, or
if you do crazy things.
It's not something--
once you realize what the effect
of your choices is, you
can kind of control it.
But there's--
playing Planescape is--
it's going to be about you and
how your game playing style is
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] humanity.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, there's
interesting effects in Knights
of the Old Republic if anybody's
played that.
You can explicitly
make decisions to
go to the dark side.
I remember when I played it,
every time it came up with a
decision where I could--
the dark side has all the
awesome powers, right?
So I kept thinking, I'm gonna be
on the dark side, I'm gonna
have all the awesome powers,
it's gonna be grand.
Then you get to the decisions,
and I was almost uncomfortable
with choosing the evil options,
such that I couldn't
actually bring myself to
go to the dark side.
PROFESSOR: We are actually
out of time.
But I wouldn't say that--
the options are thankfully all--
or, actually, let's save
discussion of Knights of the Old
Republic for another class
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
OK, all right, well, thank you.