CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I really just
want to practice matrix
multiplication, which is
potentially something new for
some of you, and maybe some of
you have been doing it for a
while and are very good at it.
But I want to make sure that
everyone is feeling confident
in their ability to
multiply matrices.
So we have three
matrices here.
We have A, B, and C. And what I
want you to do is I want you
to compute what makes
sense below.
I have four products
of matrices below.
a is A times B, b is B times A,
c is B times C, and d is A
times C. So I want you to
multiply the matrices that
make sense to multiply, and then
the ones that don't, make
sure you understand why.
Give yourself a brief
explanation of why you can't
multiply them.
So why don't you work on that,
pause the video, and when you
feel confident in your answers,
bring the video back
up, and you can check them
against my work.
OK, welcome back.
Well, we wanted to make sure
we felt comfortable
multiplying matrices.
So what we're going to do is
look at the four products I
mentioned below, and we're
going to see how they do,
whether or not we can actually
compute them.
So let's first look at a, which
was A times B. So before
I write it down again,
A times B is--
notice A is a 2 by 2 matrix,
and B is a 2
by 3 matrix, right?
And so if I write letter a,
we know we're taking a 2
by 2 by a 2 by 3.
And so the fact that the
interior dimensions agree,
that the number of columns of
A is equal to the number of
rows of B, means that
I can multiply them.
So I can multiply them, and my
result I expect to get is, of
course, the dimensions we
have on the outside.
So I expect to get
a 2 by 3 matrix.
So I'm going to rewrite A and
B here, so that I don't have
to keep walking back and forth,
and then we'll do the
multiplication.
So I have 6, 5, 1, 2, times
2, minus 1, 3, 1, 0, 4.
OK.
So I want to perform this
multiplication.
Now remember that when you are
looking for a value in your
resulting matrix, which I know
is 2 by 3, so I can even make
a little space for myself.
I know it's 2 by 3, so I know
I'm going to have to fill in
these spots.
When I look at this position,
it's row 1, column 1.
That means I take row 1 of
the first matrix, and I'm
essentially just dotting
it with column 1
of the second matrix.
So I'm taking row 1 times column
1 in the way it was
described, which is I take
6 times 2, and I add
it to 5 times 1.
So row 1, column 1 gives me 6
times 2 is 12, plus 5 times 1
which is 5, so I get 17.
And then if I come in to the
next spot, what is this?
And the resulting matrix's
position is row 1, column 2.
So now I take row 1 of the first
matrix and column 2 of
the second matrix, and I get 6
times negative 1 is negative
6, plus 0 times 5, so I
get a negative 6 here.
Negative 6 times 0.
Maybe I should show
you this way.
Negative 6 times 0.
OK.
And then here I am now in the
third spot of the first row,
so I'm in a row 1, column 3.
So that's again, row 1 of the
first, column 3 of the second.
So you see a pattern here about
where we're getting our
things from that we're
multiplying.
For row 1, column 3 of the
resulting, I take row 1 of the
first and column 3
of the second.
So 6 times 3 is 18, plus--
5 times 4 is--
20.
So 20 plus 18 is 38.
OK.
Now I have to do the same
thing on the bottom.
Right?
So I have now here, the row,
notice I'm in row 2, so I'm
always going to use row
2 of ths first matrix.
And then what we saw last time
is I used column 1 in the
first spot, column 2 in the
second spot, column 3 in the
third spot.
Right?
That's what happens over
and over again.
So what do I do?
I take 1, 2, and I multiply
it by 2, 1.
So I take 1 times 2,
plus 2 times 1.
So I get 2 there and 2
there, so I get a 4.
And then the next column:
row 2, column 2.
1 times negative 1
is negative 1--
2 times 0 is 0--
so I get a negative 1.
And then the last column.
1 times 3 is 3.
2 times 4 is 8.
So I get 3 plus 8,
so I get 11.
Hopefully I didn't make any
stupid summing mistakes there,
but if I did, you probably
caught it.
Because I was trying to say
what I did as we went.
So that is the answer to a.
OK.
So now let's think
about what is b.
b was take B times A, which is
just to switch the order.
So let's look at the
dimension matchup.
Now we have a 2 by 3 matrix, and
I'm trying to multiply it
by a 2 by 2 matrix.
Well, I don't have to
do any more work,
because I can't do it.
Because the dimensions
of the insides here--
three columns for B,
two rows for A--
means that I can't actually
multiply them.
OK?
So this isn't even defined.
OK, so that was easy.
That was b.
All right.
Letter c--
I'll give myself a lot
of room to do that--
letter c was B times C. And so
I'm going to write down the
dimensions to see if
I even need to
write down the matrices.
B was two rows by three columns,
and C was three rows
by two columns.
So if I look at the dimensions,
the 3 and the 3
match up, so I am going
to be able to multiply
them, and my result--
as I mentioned before--
should be a 2 by 2.
So let me write down B and C
here, so we don't have to keep
going to the side.
OK.
And then C is 1, 2, negative
1, negative 1, 3, 2.
All right, let me just make
sure I didn't transcribe
anything incorrectly.
I think it looks good.
OK.
So row 1 of B. Row 2 of B.
Column 1 of C. Column 2 of C.
We're going to be dealing with
those, specifically.
So we want to multiply these.
We said our resulting matrix
is going to be 2 by 2.
OK.
Because I'm going to have a lot
of terms, I might write
them down on this one,
and then simplify.
Because I may make a mistake,
so to be more careful, I'll
write down all the pieces.
So here I am in row 1, column
1 of the resulting.
So I take row 1 of the first,
column 1 of the second, and
what do I get when I multiply?
I get 2 times 1-- that's 2.
Plus negative 1 times 2--
that's negative 2.
Plus 3 times negative 1--
that's negative 3.
Right?
That's all we have to do
for the first position.
Then I do, for the second one,
it's row 1, column 2.
So I do row 1, column 2.
So I'll try to keep my
head out of the way.
I realize I keep stepping
in front.
So it's 2 times negative 1.
I get negative 2.
Negative 1 times 3, so
I get negative 3.
And 3 times 2 gives me 6.
OK.
And then the bottom two.
I get row 2, column 1 over
here, and then row 2,
column 2 over here.
So row 2, column 1 is going
to be 1 times 1.
Plus 0 times 2.
Plus 4 times negative 1,
so I get negative 4.
And then here.
Row 2, column 2.
I get 1 times negative 1,
so I have negative 1.
Plus 0 times 3--
plus 0.
And then 4 times 2 is 8.
So if I simplify these, it looks
like in the first spot I
should get a negative 3.
And the second spot,
I should get a 1.
This is just for you to
check your answer.
And the third spot, I
get a negative 3.
And then the fourth
spot, I get a 7.
So hopefully I added correctly
all throughout.
I think I did, so I think
we're good there.
So that is the answer to C.
And again, the reason we can
multiply those, was that the
dimensions--
when you wrote them down in
order-- the dimensions to the
inside agreed, and then the
outside gives us the size of
the resulting matrix.
So there was one more problem,
and that was d.
And I wanted you to take A times
C. And A was a 2 by 2.
And C was a 3 by 2.
And so again, we see we can't
do it, because the two
interior dimensions here--
when I write them
in that order--
don't agree.
OK.
So d is not defined.
All right, so the basic idea of
this whole video is just to
make sure we felt comfortable
multiplying matrices.
We're trying to use some
simple examples
to understand that.
Understand how we can recognize
from the dimensions
whether or not multiplication is
even defined, and then what
size the resulting
matrix will be.
I do want to point
out one thing.
And I want to point out that if
we come over to our example
back in the beginning.
We had AB as our first
example and then BA
as our second example.
And AB-- well, I think,
I got to remember
what they were, yeah--
AB you could multiply,
but BA you could not.
So I think it has been stressed
before, but I think I
should stress it again,
that order matters in
multiplication.
OK?
You can't commute
these things.
You can't switch the order
and get the same result.
So matrix multiplication, you
have to be very careful about
keeping things in the same order
as you're multiplying.
OK, I think that is
where I will stop.