PROFESSOR: Welcome to this
recitation on damped harmonic
oscillators.
So here you're asked to assume
an enforced, overdamped
spring-mass-dashpot that started
at x dot of 0 close to
0, so rest, and to show that
it never crosses the
equilibrium position, x equal
to 0, for t larger then 0.
The second part of the problem
asks you to show that
regardless of the initial
condition, this overdamped
oscillator can not cross the
equilibrium position more than
one time, or more than once.
OK.
So why don't you pause the
video, try to think about this
problem, and I'll
be right back.
Welcome back.
So the system that we're
looking at is a
spring-mass-dashpot that would
be written in this form--
second order differential
equation.
Let's assume that we have
positive constant
coefficients here.
And basically, to solve this,
you would be considering the
methods that we saw before.
And the general solution would
just be written in the form of
c1 exponential lambda 1, the c2
exponential lambda 2, with
c1, c2, just two constants that
would be determined by
the initial condition.
Lambda 1, lambda 2 would be
here the roots of the
characteristic polynomial that
you would have found there.
Given that we're looking
at an overdamped forced
spring-mass-dashpot, you can
actually show that lambda 1
and lambda 2 would be both
real and negative.
And here, we can just say that
basically, lambda 1 and lambda
2 would be less than 1.
And we'll keep that aside for
now, and I'll use this later.
So this is just setting
up the problem.
So now, what was the question?
The question was to show that
if we start this system with
initial condition x dot of 0
equal to 0, which corresponds
to lambda 1 c1 plus lambda 2
c2 equals to 0, then the
system cannot cross the
equilibrium position x equal
to 0 for t larger than 0.
So let's just start by assuming
that the system
crosses the equilibrium
position.
So for example, let's look for
t star such that x of t star
is equal to 0.
So x of t star, we know
its form already.
We have the general form
of x of t star.
That's basically c1 exponential
lambda 1 t star
plus c2 exponential
lambda 2 t star.
And so we can massage this
equation, and basically end up
with minus c2 over c1 equal to
exponential of lambda 1 minus
lambda 2 t star.
So now let's just find our t
star by applying the log of
both sides of this equation.
So we get t star equals to the
log of minus c2 over c1, and
we divide by the lambda
1 minus lambda 2.
So here this tells us that if t
star exists, which means, if
the log is defined, and this
minus c2 over c1 basically is
positive, then we only have one
value of t star possible.
So here, we actually are
answering the second part of
this question, number two,
which was telling us that
regardless of the initial
condition-- so regardless of
the coefficient c1 c2
that we would have--
if t star exists, there
is only one.
And so that means that the
system would not cross this
equilibrium position
more than once.
But I'll come back on that.
But now let's go back to what
we were asked to do in the
first part, where we basically
now go back to our x dot of 0
equals to 0, which basically
gave us that minus c2 over c1
is equal to lambda 1 over
lambda 2, and the way we
define lambda 1 over lambda 2
here gives us that minus c2
over c1 is less than 1, which
means that the log is going to
be negative.
What happens in the
denominator?
Lambda 1 minus lambda
2 would be positive.
So with this initial condition,
we would end up
with a t star that would
be negative.
So basically, x is never equal
to 0 again for t larger than
0, given these initial
conditions.
So that finishes this first
part of the problem.
So I'll go back on the
physics of it in a
moment with a graph.
So starting from this initial
condition, x can never be
equal to 0, because the
only t star we can
find would be negative.
So for t larger than 0,
it does not cross
the equilibrium point.
The second part of
the problem--
so this was 1--
just comes from the fact that,
if I label this star, star
tells us that if minus c2 over
c1, strictly larger than 0,
then only 1 t star exists.
So if we have a solution,
there is only one.
And this is regardless of the
initial conditions that we
would be given.
So the system cannot cross
the equilibrium
position more than once.
So now let's look at what we're
doing here, graphically.
Let's assume that we're, for
example, starting with initial
condition here, where we're
stretching our spring, but we
start with 0 velocity.
So x dot of 0 equal to 0.
That was the system
that we had.
Then this is an overdamped
case where both basically
exponentials are decaying to
0, and so we would have a
solution that would
go to 0 quickly.
It would be damped.
And so this would be part 1.
Now let's look at what would
happen if we started with
other initial conditions.
So for example, starting from
the same point with a much
bigger velocity.
Then the system would go
up, but eventually,
it has to go down.
It wouldn't have this shape, but
basically, it would have
to go down to 0's position.
And when it reaches, you can
show that again, the
derivative of x can
reach 0 only once.
And at that point, you're then
back to the initial conditions
that you had in the first part
of the question, and so you
can then, from here, argue again
that you cannot cross
the zero, the equilibrium
point,
after reaching a maximum.
Now what if we had a stretch
that would be giving a
negative velocity to the
mass, and a very
strong negative velocity?
Then the system also
wants to go back to
0, but could overshoot.
And the overshoot would also
generate a unique time at
which the derivative would be
equal to 0, and after that
point, you would be back to
the same argument we had
before, where the solution would
have to go toward 0, but
never crosses it.
So we can have various
configurations.
And here I start with this
point, but you could also
start with other initial
conditions, where you could
have, as well, something that
would be, for example, a very
strong positive, where again,
here you would have an
overshoot, but then the solution
would be attracted by
the x equal to 0 solution.
And of course you could also
start from the equilibrium.
If you're not imposing any
initial velocity, you just
stay there, because this
is not forced.
But if you're imposing a
velocity, then you would have
other trajectories of the kind,
for example, like this,
where again, it would go up, but
then be attracted back by
the 0 solution.
So that's the typical behavior
for a damped oscillator, where
basically there's no
oscillation, but the solution
is attracted to rest. And you
could have cases of overshoot
when it can show that after the
overshoot, velocity would
reach 0 maximum, and then would
be attracted back to the
0 solution with never
crossing it.
And that ends this recitation.