The damped vibrations applet
illustrates several different
concepts related to differential
equations.
Initial conditions for second
order equations, the phase
plane for autonomous equations,
and damping
conditions for second order
homogeneous linear equations.
The differential we're studying
appears at upper right.
And the parameter names reflect
the fact that this
equation describes a mass spring
dashpot system, with
mass m, dashpot constant b,
and spring constant k.
The right hand side of
the equation is zero.
There's no forcing term.
The equation is homogeneous.
The sliders at bottom control
the values of the system
parameters.
With the selected values for
m, b, and k, solutions are
damped vibrations.
I can let the solution evolve by
grabbing the time slider or
by using the animation
key, which also
serves to stop the animation.
If the value of the solution
gets too small, I can blow the
picture up using the zoom slider
at the upper left.
Moving it to the right squeezes
the solutions.
Moving it to the left
makes them larger.
The window on the left lets you
set the initial condition
of the system.
There are two components to
the initial condition of a
second order equation.
Position and velocity,
that is x and x dot.
Together they form the
coordinates of a
point on this plane.
I can grab the point and change
both x and x prime
simultaneously.
The x-coordinate is written
vertically, because that's how
it's written on the right
hand graphing window.
And you can see that they keep
pace with each other.
The horizontal component is x
dot, the initial velocity.
That's positive when we're
to the right, and becomes
negative when we're
to the left.
The left window represents
phase space.
For any time t, the values
of x and x dot are the
coordinates of a point
in phase space.
And as the solution evolves
through time, that point
follows a path, sweeps out
a path in phase space.
And with these selected choices
of m, b, and k, the
path is a spiral.
This reflects the fact that
both x and x dot undergo a
damped vibration.
The system parameters can be
set using these sliders at
lower left.
Let's suggest the mass to be 1/2
and leave k to be one, and
watch what happens to the
solutions as we vary the
damping constant b.
When b is small, the solution
doesn't damp out as quickly,
and when b is large, it damps
out more quickly.
These things become much clearer
when you think about
them in terms of the roots of
the characteristic polynomial
of this equation.
And we can display those
roots by clicking the
roots button here.
What's shown here is the complex
plane with the roots
of the characteristic polynomial
drawn on it.
Also we have a readout of the
two roots in green over here.
So let's watch what happens
when we adjust b.
I'm going to start with
b equal to zero.
In this case, there's
no damping.
The solutions are sinusoidal,
the roots of the
characteristic polynomial are
purely imaginary, and the
trajectory in phase space
is an ellipse.
Both the solution and its
derivative vary sinusoidally.
As I increase b away from
zero, I get spirals.
And at the same time,
the roots move off
the imaginary axis.
They acquire a negative real
part, which is minus b over
2m, incidentally.
And as I increase b further,
the spiral opens up, the
damping occurs more quickly, the
roots move away from the
imaginary axis.
They increase the size
of their real part.
The damping occurs
more quickly.
And you'll notice that they get
closer and closer to the
real axis as well.
Their imaginary part
is decreasing.
That means that the circular
frequency, the angular
frequency of the solution,
is decreasing.
The period, or pseudo-period of
the solution is decreasing.
You can see that in the graph,
but it's much clearer to see
what's happening to these roots
of the characteristic
polynomial.
There are converging on the real
axis, and eventually they
merge into a double root
on the real axis.
This is critical damping.
From the readout, we see that
the value of b seems to be
about 1.41.
Why don't you take a moment and
calculate what b is for
these values of m and k when
critical damping occurs?
If we continue to increase b
beyond critical damping, now
the roots move out
on the real axis.
There are two exponential
solutions, and the general
solution is a linear combination
of them.
And there's no oscillation
in any solution.