PROFESSOR: Welcome back.
In this session, we're going
to tackle initial value
problem, y dot plus
ty equals to t.
And this initial value problem
is going to be subject to the
initial condition, y
of 0 equals to 3.
We are going to use the method
of integration factor.
And what I want you to use is
both definite integrals and
indefinite integrals.
So why don't you take
a few minutes to
think about the problem?
And we will be right back.
Welcome back.
So I hope that you worked out
the first part of the problem.
So what are we going to
do to solve this ODE.
First, we need to review
what is the method
of integrating factor.
So when we use the integrating
factor, basically, we're
trying to write down our ODE
in a different form by
introducing a function u.
And the goal is to find the
function u such that we can
rewrite this left-hand side
as the derivative of the
product y dot u.
So in this case, if we're
looking at identifying the
function u that would give us
this form, yu dot, we need to
just basically identify
that this is u dot.
And from previous sessions, we
saw that this would give us
classical solution that involves
an exponential of the
integral of the right-hand
side after dividing by u,
which gives us exponential
of t squared over 2.
So integrating factor is just
using a trick so that we
simplify our left-hand side and
write it in the form of
the derivative of
the product, yu.
So now, we identified our
integration factor.
It's u equals exponential
of t squared over 2.
Now, we can go back
to our equation.
And I'm going to just label
it with a star here.
So now, this equation is written
in this form, t, and
the integral of just basically
derivative, which is itself.
So if we use first the
approach of definite
integrals--
actually, we're going to switch
the order, and I'm
going to start with indefinite
integrals first.
So using indefinite integrals,
we'll be
integrating both sides.
And on the left-hand side, we
would just be left with yu,
remembering that u is just
exponential of t
squared over 2.
On the right-hand side, we're
just integrating t exponential
of t squared over 2.
And here, you can recognize
that the derivative of
exponential of t squared
over 2 would have a
t in front of it.
So this is actually a very
simple integration.
But we are in the case of
differential equation where we
need a constant of
integration.
And again, here, we would end
up with two constants of
integration on both sides.
But given that we are dealing
with a first order
differential equation, we can
regroup that in one constant.
And then, we can just find our
solution by dividing this
equation by u.
And u, if you remember, is just
exponential of t squared
over 2, so it's equivalent to
multiplying both sides by
exponential of minus
t squared over 2.
So I'm just going to
write it down.
Then, it just gives us
exponential minus t squared
over 2 multiplied by exponential
t squared over 2,
which is 1 and c exponential
of minus t squared over 2.
So that's our solution.
But remember that we're trying
to solve an initial value
problem they subject to
an initial condition.
And our initial condition is y
of 0 equals to 3, which means
that here, y of 0 would give us
exponential to 0, which is
just a constant.
So we end up with 3 equals
to 1 plus c.
Therefore, c is equal to 2.
And the final form of the
solution would just be 1 plus
2 exponential of minus
t squared over 2.
So we started with the
indefinite integral.
So what if we would do this
using definite integrals?
So we don't need to start
from the beginning.
We just need to take the problem
a few steps before
when we integrated both
sides of the equation.
And here, specify the bounds
of the integral.
So how do we want to specify
the bounds of the integral?
We're given an initial
condition that is
at t equals to 0.
So that's what we want here.
And we're integrating
to the variable t.
But one thing is important when
you do that is that you
have the variable t that is in
the bounds of the integral.
So we want the integrand to not
be written in terms of the
variable of integration.
So it is very important to
change the label of your
variables in the integrand.
That's how you proceed for
different integrals.
So in this case then, we
end up with similar--
so u dot y evaluated at t minus
u dot y evaluated at 0.
And from our initial conditions
in the form of u,
we know the value of this side
of this term in the equation.
And here, we're just again
recognizing that this is just
the derivative of exponential to
s squared over 2 evaluated
between 0 and t.
So here, if I just carry on the
right-hand side and then
go back to left-hand side in the
next step, we would end up
here with just t squared
over 2 minus 1.
Exponential of 0 is 1.
And now, let's deal with
this left-hand side.
So again, we end up with uy
minus u dot y evaluated at 0.
However, u of 0 is just the
function exponential to t
squared over 2 evaluated
at 0, which is one.
And y of 0, we have it because
that was our initial
condition, and this is only 3.
So we have uy minus 1
dot 3, which is just
basically minus 3.
And on the right-hand side, we
have exponential of t squared
over 2 minus 1, which gives us
exponential of t squared
over 2 minus 1.
Now bring in this minus 3 on the
other side, you now have a
plus 3, all of this multiplied
by 1 over u, which was our
exponential of minus
t squared over 2.
And therefore, we end up with a
similar solution that we had
for the different integral,
3 minus 1 is just 2.
So we have minus t squared
over 2 plus 1.
So using both the definite
integrals approach and the
indefinite integrals, we recover
the same results.
And the main point of this
problem was really to practice
using the integration factor
and practice using both
approaches with the definite
and indefinite integrals.
So this ends the problem.
And I'll see you next time.