BEN HARRIS: Hi, and
welcome back.
Today we're going to do a
problem about the four
fundamental subspaces.
So here we have a matrix B. B is
written as the product to a
lower triangular matrix and an
upper triangular matrix.
And we're going to find a basis
for, and compute the
dimension of, each of the four
fundamental subspaces of B.
I'll give you a minute to try
that on your own, to hit
pause, and then I'll be right
back in just a minute and we
can do it together.
OK.
We're back.
Now, the first thing to notice
is that this is an LU
decomposition of B. So we
have L here and U here.
Now let's go one space
at a time.
Let's start with the
column space.
And first, let's just say what
the dimension of the
column space is.
OK, so let's look
at our U matrix.
How many pivots do we have?
We have two pivots, so the
column space has dimension 2.
This is the number of pivots.
Good.
Now how do we find a basis
for the column space?
How do we find that basis?
Well, in lecture Professor
Strang had started with a
matrix B. He did elimination
on it, and then he took the
pivot columns in the
original matrix.
And that's great.
That works.
You can also take the pivot
columns in the L matrix.
You can see by multiplying this
out that it will amount
to essentially the same thing.
So a basis for this column
space, I can just take these
two pivot columns of my L
matrix, 1, 2, -1 and 0, 1, 0.
Good.
OK.
So there's the dimension of and
the basis for the column
space of B.
Next, let's do the null
space together.
OK.
What's the dimension
of the null space?
Well, the dimension of the
null space is always the
number of columns minus
the number of pivots.
Right?
It's the number of
free variables.
So here, that's just one.
Good.
And how do we find this one
vector in the null space?
Well, what we do is we can just
plug in 1 for our free
variable, and we can back solve
to get the other two.
So this equation tells me that
my second number is -1, and
this equation tells me that that
third variable -3/5, if I
can fit it in here.
That's a -3/5, if it's
difficult to
see that on the tape.
Now let's move on.
Next is the row space.
So how do we find the dimension
of the row space?
I'm going to write row space as
column space of B transpose.
How do we find that?
Well, remember that one of our
big facts in this class is
that the dimension of the row
space is the same as the
dimension of the column space.
It's just the number
of pivots.
So that's good.
It's 2.
And how do we find a basis
for the row space?
There are a couple ways of
thinking about this.
One way to think about it is we
got this upper triangular
matrix from B by doing
elimination.
And elimination doesn't
change the row space.
So I can just use the two pivot
rows of the matrix u.
Basis for my row space here is
I just put these two pivot
rows together, and I get a
basis for this row space.
The last one is always the
toughest and the trickiest. We
have to do the left
null space or the
null space of B transpose.
First, let's compute
its dimension.
What's the dimension of
this left null space?
Well, there's a similar formula
to the one we used
when we were computing the
dimension of the null space.
It's just the number of rows
minus the number of pivots.
So there are three rows.
Our matrix is 3 by 3.
And there're other two pivots.
So this is just one dimensional,
again.
We need to compute, now,
this left null space.
Let me go back to our
original matrix.
The way to do this is to take B
equals LU, and invert L, and
get EB equals U. So we need
to move L over to
the left-hand side.
If we do that--
I'm just going to write
that down here.
So what's the inverse
of the L matrix?
We just get 1, -2, 1, 0, 1, 1,
times B, is our U matrix, this
upper-triangular matrix.
Now that I moved L over to the
other side, I can read off the
vectors in my left null space.
Now, I'm looking at not my pivot
variables but my free
variables, because it's some
sort of null space.
but I want to look
at this E matrix.
So the third row of this
E matrix, the third row
corresponds to the three row
here and when I multiply this
by B, I just get zeros,
so this is in
the left null space.
A basis for this left
null space is--
see if I can fit it here--
just this 1, 0, 1.
Good.
So we've found the dimension
of and basis for all of the
four fundamental subspaces.
Before I move on, I just want
to recall which of the L
matrix or the U matrix we used
for each of these subspaces.
So for the column space,
we used the pivot
columns of the L matrix.
For the null space, we looked
at the U matrix.
For the row space we also
looked at the U matrix.
And for the left null space,
we needed to invert the L
matrix and look at
the three row.
We're done with the problem.
But the last thing that's useful
is to draw a picture,
which I have right here.
I know in lecture Professor
Strang has drawn you some sort
of cartoon pictures of what
these subspaces look like.
But here I want to try to
actually draw them in a
special case.
So if you can read my drawing
here, what do we have?
We have the row space here,
and the null space here.
Right?
And so B maps this picture
into this picture.
The null space here--
all the scalar multiples of
this vector-- all go to 0,
because they're in
the null space.
That's exactly what
B takes to 0.
B takes everything else,
including the row space, into
this column space.
And what is B transpose do?
Well B transpose kills this left
null space, kills this
vector, and it take everything
else into the row space, into
the column space
of B transpose.
OK.
Thanks for doing this
exercise together.
I hope this picture is helpful.