Two, two by two formula we
know,
right?
The two by two formula for A
inverse, the inverse of a b c d
inverse is one over the
determinant times d a -b -c.
Somehow I want to see what's
going on for three by three and
n by n.
And actually maybe you can see
what's going on from this two by
two case.
So there's a formula
for the inverse,
and what did I divide by?
The determinant.
So what I'm looking for is a
formula where it has one over
the determinant and,
and you remember why that makes
good sense, because then that's
perfect as long as the
determinant isn't zero,
and that's exactly when there
is an
inverse.
But now I have to ask can we
recognize any of this stuff?
Do you recognize what that
number d is from the past?
From last, from the last
lecture?
My hint is think cofactors.
Because my formula is going to
be, my formula for the inverse
is going to be one over the
determinant times
a matrix of cofactors.
So you remember that D?
What's that the cofactor of?
Remember cofactors?
If -- that's the one one
cofactor, because if I strike
out row and column one,
I'm left with d.
And what's minus b?
OK.
Which cofactor is that one?
Oh, minus b is the cofactor of
c,
right?
If I strike out the c,
I'm left with a b there.
And why the minus sign?
Because this c was in a two one
position, and two plus one is
odd.
So there was a minus went into
the cofactor,
and that's it.
OK.
I'll write down next what my
formula is.
Here's the big formula for the
A -- for A inverse.
It's one over the determinant
of A and then some matrix.
And that matrix is the matrix
of cofactors,
c.
Only one thing,
it turns -- you'll see,
I have to, I transpose.
So this is the matrix of
cofactors,
the -- what I'll just -- but
why don't we just call it the
cofactor matrix.
So the one one entry of,
of c is the cof- is the one one
cofactor, the thing that we get
by throwing away row and column
one.
It's the d.
And, because of the transpose,
what I see up here is the
cofactor of this guy down here,
right?
That's where the transpose came
in.
What I see here,
this is the cofactor not of
this one, because I've
transposed.
This is the cofactor of the b.
When I throw away the b,
the b row and the b column,
I'm left with c,
and then I have that minus sign
again.
And of course the two two entry
is the cofactor of d,
and that's this a.
OK.
So there's the formula.
But we got to think why.
I mean, it worked in this two
by two case, but a lot of other
formulas would
have worked just as well.
We, we have to see why that's
true.
In other words,
why is it -- so this is what I
aim to find.
And, and let's just sort of
look to see what is that telling
us.
That tells us that the --
the expression for A inverse --
let's look at a three by three.
Can I just write down a a b c d
e f g h i?
And I'm looking for its
inverse.
And what kind of a formula --
do I see there?
I mean, what -- the determinant
is a bunch of products of three
factors, right?
The determinant of this
matrix'll
involve a e i,
and b f times g,
and c times d times h,
and minus c e g,
and so on.
So things with three factors go
in here.
Things with how many factors do
things in the cofactor matrix
have?
What's a typical cofactor?
What's
the cofactor of a?
The cofactor of a,
the one one entry up here in
the inverse is?
I throw away the row and column
containing a and I take the
determinant of what's left,
that's the cofactor.
And that's e i minus f h.
Products of two things.
Now,
I'm just making the observation
that the determinant of A
involves products of n entries.
And the cofactor matrix
involves products of n minus 1
entries.
And, like, we never noticed any
of this stuff when we were
computing the inverse by the
Gauss-Jordan method or whatever.
You remember how we did it?
We took the matrix A,
we tucked the identity next to
it, we did elimination till A
became the identity.
And then that,
the identity suddenly was A
inverse.
Well, that was great
numerically.
But we never knew what was
going on, basically.
And now we see what the formula
is
in terms of letters,
what's the algebra instead of
the algorithm.
OK.
But I have to say why this is
right, right?
I still -- that's a pretty
magic formula.
Where does it come from?
Well, I'll just check it.
Having,
having got it up there,
let me -- I'll say,
how can we check -- what do I
want to check?
I want to check that A times
its inverse gives the identity.
So I want, I want to check that
A times this thing,
A times this -- now I'm going
to write in the inverse -- gives
the identity.
So I check that A times C
transpose -- let me bring the
determinant up here.
Determinant of A times the
identity.
That's my job.
That's it, that if this is
true, and it is,
then, then I've correctly
identified A inverse as C
transpose divided by the
determinant.
OK.
But why is this true?
Why is that true?
Let me, let me put down what
I'm doing here.
I have A -- here,
here's A, here's a11 -- I'm
doing this multiplication --
along to a1n.
And then down in this last row
will be an an1 along to ann.
And I'm multiplying by the
cofactor matrix transposed.
So when I transpose,
it'll be c11 c12 down to c1n.
Notice usually that one coming
first would mean I'm in row one,
but I've transposed,
so that's, those are the
cofactors.
This first column are the
cofactors from row one.
And then the last column would
be the cofactors from row n.
And why should that come out to
be anything good?
In fact, why should it come out
to be as good as this?
Well, you can tell me what the
one one entry in the product is.
This is like you're seeing the
main point if you just tell me
one entry.
What do I get up there in the
one
one entry when I do this row of
this row from A times this
column of cofactors?
What, what will I get there?
Because we have seen this.
I mean, we're,
right, building exactly on what
the last lecture reached.
So this is a11 times c11,
a12 times c12,
a1n times c1n.
What does that what does that
sum up to?
That's the cofactor formula for
the determinant.
That's the, this cofactor
formula, which I wrote,
which we got last time.
The determinant of A is,
if I use row one,
let,
let I equal one,
then I have a11 times its
cofactor, a12 times its
cofactor, and so on.
And that gives me the
determinant.
And it worked in this,
in this case.
This row times this thing is,
sure enough,
ad minus bc.
But this formula says it always
works.
So up here in this,
in this position,
I'm getting determinant of A.
What about in the two two
position?
Row two times column two there,
what, what is that?
That's just the cofactors,
that's just row two times its
cofactors.
So of course I get the
determinant
again.
And in the last here,
this is the last row times its
cofactors.
It's exactly -- you see,
we're realizing that the
cofactor formula is just this
sum of products,
so of course we think,
hey, we've got a matrix
multiplication there.
And we get determinant of A.
Great.
But there's one more idea here,
right?
What else, what have I not --
so I haven't got that formula
completely proved yet,
because I've still got to do
all the off-diagonal stuff,
which I want to be zero,
right?
I just want this to be
determinant of A times the
identity, and then I'm,
I'm a happy person.
So why should that be?
Why should it be that one row
times the cofactors from a
different row,
which become a column because I
transpose, give zero?
In other words,
the cofactor formula gives the
determinant if the
row and the,
and the cofactors -- you know,
if the entries of A and the
cofactors are for the same row.
But for some reason,
if I take the cofactors from
the -- entries from the first
row and the cofactors from the
second row,
for some reason I automatically
get zero.
And it's sort of like
interesting to say,
why does that happen?
And can I just check that -- of
course, we know it happens,
in this case.
Here are the numbers from row
one and here are the cofactors
from row two,
right?
Those are the numbers in row
one.
And th- these are the cofactors
from row two,
because the cofactor of c is
minus b and the cofactor of d is
a.
And sure enough,
that row times this column
gives -- please say it.
Zero, right.
OK.
So now how come?
How come?
Can we even see it in
this two by two case?
Why did -- well,
I mean, I guess we,
you know, in one way we
certainly do see it,
because it's right here.
I mean, do we just do it,
and then we get zero.
But we want to think of some
reason why the answer's zero,
some reason that we can use in
the n by n case.
So let -- here,
here is my thinking.
We must be, if we're getting
the answer's zero,
we suspect that what we're
doing somehow,
we're taking the determinant of
some matrix that has two equal
rows.
So I believe that if we
multiply these by the cofactors
from some other row,
we're taking the determinant --
ye, what matrix are we taking
the determinant of?
Here it's, this is it.
We're, when we do that times
this, we're really taking -- can
I put this in little letters
down here?
I'm taking -- let me look at
the matrix a b a b.
Let me call that matrix AS,
A screwed up.
OK.
All right.
So now that matrix is certainly
singular.
So if we find its determinant,
we're going to get zero.
But I claim that if we find its
determinant by the cofactor
rule,
go along the first row,
we would take a times the
cofactor of a.
And what is the -- see,
how -- oh no -- let me go along
the second row.
OK.
So let's see,
which -- if I take -- I know
I've got a singular matrix here.
And I believe that when I do
this multiplication,
what I'm doing is using the
cofactor formula for the
determinant.
And I know I'm going to get
zero.
Let me try this again.
So the cofactor formula for the
determinant says I should take a
times its cofactor,
which is this b,
plus b times its cofactor,
which is this minus a.
OK.
That's what we're doing,
apart from a sign here.
Oh yeah, so you know,
there might be a minus
multiplying everything.
So if I take this determinant,
it's A -- the determinant of
this, the determinant of A
screwed up is a times its
cofactor, which is b,
plus the second guy
times its cofactor,
which is minus a.
And of course I get the answer
zero, and this is exactly what's
happening in that,
in that, row times this wrong
column.
OK.
That's the two by two picture,
and it's just the same here.
That the reason I get a zero up
in there
is, the reason I get a zero is
that when I multiply the first
row of A and the last row of the
cofactor matrix,
it's as if I'm taking the
determinant of this screwed up
matrix that has first and last
rows identical.
The book pins this down more
specific -- and more carefully
than I can do in the lecture.
I hope you're seeing the point.
That this is an identity.
That it's a beautiful identity
and it tells us what the inverse
of the matrix is.
So it gives us the inverse,
the formula for the inverse.
OK.
So that's the first goal of my
lecture, was to find this
formula.
It's done.
OK.
And of course I
could invert,
now, I can, I sort of like I
can see what -- I can answer
questions like this.
Suppose I have a matrix,
and let me move the one one
entry.
What happens to the inverse?
Just, just think about that
question.
Suppose I have some
matrix, I just write down some
nice, non-singular matrix that's
got an inverse,
and then I move the one one
entry a little bit.
I add one to it,
for example.
What happens to the inverse
matrix?
Well, this formula should tell
me.
I have to look to see what
happens
to the determinant and what
happens to all the cofactors.
And, the picture,
it's all there.
It's all there.
We can really understand how
the inverse changes when the
matrix changes.
OK.
Now my second application is to
-- let me put that over here --
is to Ax=b.
Well, the -- course,
the solution is A inverse b.
But now I have a formula for A
inverse.
A inverse is one over the
determinant times this C
transpose times B.
I now know what A inverse is.
So now I just have to say,
what have I got here?
Is there any way to,
to make this formula,
this answer,
which is the one and only
answer -- it's the very same
answer we got on the first day
of the class by elimination.
Now I'm -- now I've got a
formula for the answer.
Can I play with it further to
see what's going on?
And Cramer's,
this Cramer's Rule is
exactly, that -- a way of
looking at this formula.
OK.
So this is a formula for x.
Here's my formula.
Well, of course.
The first thing I see from the
formula is that the answer x
always has that in the
determinant.
I'm not surprised.
There's a division by the
determinant.
But then I have to say a little
more carefully what's going on
up here.
And let me tell you what
Cramer's Rule is.
Let, let me take x1,
the first component.
So this is the first component
of the answer.
Then there'll be a second
component and a,
all the other components.
Can I take just the first
component of this formula?
Well, I certainly have
determinant of A down under.
And what the heck is the first
-- so what do I get in C
transpose b?
What's the first entry of C
That's what I have to answer
myself.
Well, what's the first entry of
C transpose b?
OK.
This B is -- let me tell you
what it is.
Somehow I'm multiplying
cofactors by the entries of B,
right, in this product.
Cofactors from the matrix times
entries of b.
So any time I'm multiplying
cofactors by numbers,
I think, I'm getting the
determinant of something.
And let me call that something
B1.
So this is a matrix,
the matrix whose determinant is
coming out of that.
And we'll,
we'll see what it is.
x2 will be the determinant of
some other matrix B2,
also divided by determinant of
A.
So now I just -- Cramer just
had a good idea.
He realized what matrix it was,
what these B1 and B2 and B3 and
so on matrices were.
Let me write them on the board
underneath.
OK.
So what is this B1?
This B1 is the matrix that has
b in its first column and
otherwise the rest of it is A.
So it otherwise it has the
rest, the, the n-1 columns of A.
It's the matrix with -- it's
just the matrix A with column
one replaced by the
right-hand side,
by the right-hand side b.
Because somehow when I take the
determinant of this guy,
it's giving me this matrix
multiplication.
Well, how could that be?
How could -- so what's,
what's the determinant formula
I'll use here?
I'll use cofactors,
of course.
And I might as well use
cofactors down column one.
So when I use cofactors down
column one, I'm taking the first
entry of b times what?
Times the cofactor c11.
Do you see that?
When I, when I use cofactors
here, I take the first entry
here,
B one let's call it,
times the cofactor there.
But what's the cofactor in --
my little hand-waving is meant
to indicate that it's a matrix
of one size smaller,
the cofactor.
And it's exactly c11.
Well, that's just what we
wanted.
This first entry is c11
times b1.
And then the next entry is
whatever, is c21 times b2,
and so on.
And sure enough,
if I look here,
when I'm, when I do the
cofactor expansion,
b2 is getting multiplied by the
right thing, and so on.
So there's Cramer's Rule.
And the book gives another kind
of
cute proof without,
without building so much on,
on cofactors.
But here we've got cofactors,
so I thought I'd just give you
this proof.
So what is B -- in general,
what is Bj?
This is the,
this is A with column j
replaced by, by b.
So that's -- the determinant of
that matrix that you divide by
determinant of A to get xj.
So x -- let me change this
general formula.
xj, the j-th one,
is the determinant of Bj
divided by the determinant of A.
And now we've said what Bj is.
Well, so Cramer found a rule.
And we could ask him,
OK, great, good work,
Cramer.
But is your rule any good in
practice?
So he says, well,
you couldn't ask about a rule
in mine, right,
because it's just -- all you
have to do is find the
determinant of A and these other
determinants,
so I guess -- oh,
he just says,
well, all you have to do is
find n+1 determinants,
the, the n Bs and the A.
And actually,
I remember reading -- there was
a book, popular book that,
that kids interested in math
read when I was a kid
interested in math called
Mathematics for the Million or
something, by a guy named Bell.
And it had a little page about
linear algebra.
And it said,-- so it explained
elimination in a very
complicated way.
I certainly didn't understand
it.
And, and it made it,
you know, it
sort of said,
well, there is this formula for
elimination, but look at this
great formula,
Cramer's Rule.
So it certainly said Cramer's
Rule was the way to go.
But actually,
Cramer's Rule is a disastrous
way to go, because to compute
these
determinants,
it takes, like,
approximately forever.
So actually I now think of that
book title as being Mathematics
for the Millionaire,
because you'd have to be able
to pay for, a hopelessly long
calculation
where elimination,
of course, produced the x-s,
in an instant.
But having a formula allows you
to, with, with letters,
you know, allows you to do
algebra instead of,
algorithms.
So the, there's some value in
the Cramer's Rule formula for x
and in the explicit formula
for, for A inverse.
They're nice formulas,
but I just don't want you to
use them.
That'ss what it comes to.
If you had to -- and Matlab
would never, never do it.
I mean, it would use
elimination.
OK.
Now I'm ready for number three
in today's list of amazing
connections coming through the
determinant.
And that number three is the
fact that the determinant gives
a volume.
OK.
So now -- so that's my final
topic for -- among these --
this my number three
application, that the
determinant is actually equals
the volume of something.
Can I use this little space to
consider a special case,
and then I'll use the far board
to think about the general rule.
So what I going to prove?
Or claim.
I claim that the determinant of
the matrix is the volume of a
box.
OK, and you say,
which box?
Fair enough.
OK.
So let's see.
I'm in -- shall we say we're
in, say three by three?
Shall we suppose -- let's,
let's say three by three.
So, so we can really -- we're,
we're talking about boxes in
three dimensions,
and three by three matrices.
And so all I do -- you could
guess what the box is.
Here is, here is,
three dimensions.
OK.
Now I take the first row of the
matrix, a11, a22,
A -- sorry.
a11, a12, a13.
That row is a vector.
It goes to some point.
That point will be -- and that
edge going to it,
will be an edge of the box,
and that point will be a corner
of the box.
So here is zero zero zero,
of course.
And here's the first row of the
matrix: a11, a12,
a13.
So that's one edge of the box.
Another edge of the box is to
the second row of the matrix,
row two.
Can I just call it there row
two?
And a third row of the box will
be to -- a third row --
a third edge of the box will be
given by row three.
So, so there's row three.
That, the coordinates,
what are the coordinates of
that corner of the box?
a31, a32, a33.
So I've got that edge of the
box, that edge of the box,
that edge of
the box, and that's all I need.
Now I just finish out the box,
right?
I just -- the proper word,
of course, is parallelepiped.
But for obvious reasons,
I wrote box.
OK.
So, OK.
So there's the,
there's the bottom of the box.
There're the four edge sides of
the box.
There's the top of the box.
Cute, right?
It's the box that has these
three edges and then it's
completed to a,
to a, each, you know,
each side is a,
is a parallelogram.
And it's that box whose volume
is given by the determinant.
That's -- now it's --
possible that the determinant
is negative.
So we have to just say what's
going on in that case.
If the determinant is negative,
then the volume,
we, we should take the absolute
value really.
So the volume,
if we, if we think of volume as
positive, we should take the
absolute value of the
determinant.
But the, the sign,
what does the sign of the
determinant -- it always must
tell us something.
And somehow it,
it will tell us whether these
three is a -- whether it's a
right-handed box or a
left-handed box.
If we, if we reversed two of
the
edges, we would go between a
right-handed box and a
left-handed box.
We wouldn't change the volume,
but we would change the,
the cyclic, order.
So I won't worry about that.
And, so one special case is
what?
A equal identity matrix.
So let's take that special
case.
A equal identity matrix.
Is the
formula determinant of identity
matrix, does that equal the
volume of the box?
Well, what is the box?
What's the box?
If A is the identity matrix,
then these three rows are the
three coordinate vectors,
and the box is -- it's a cube.
It's the unit cube.
So if, if A is the identity
matrix, of course our formula is
right.
Well, actually that proves
property one -- that the volume
has property one.
Actually, we could,
we could, we could get this
thing if we -- if we can show
that the box volume has the same
three properties that define the
determinant,
then it must be the
determinant.
So that's like the,
the, the elegant way to prove
this.
To prove this amazing fact that
the determinant equals the
volume, first we'll check it for
the identity matrix.
That's fine.
The box is a cube and its
volume is one and the
determinant is one and,
and one agrees with one.
Now let me
take one -- let me go up one
level to an orthogonal matrix.
Because I'd like to take this
chance to bring in chapter --
the, the previous chapter.
Suppose I have an orthogonal
matrix.
What did that mean?
I always called those things Q.
What was the point of --
suppose I
have, suppose instead of the
identity matrix I'm now going to
take A equal Q,
an orthogonal matrix.
What was Q then?
That was a matrix whose columns
were orthonormal,
right?
Those were its columns were
unit vectors,
perpendicular unit vectors.
So what kind of a box have we
got now?
What kind of a box comes from
the rows or the columns,
I don't mind,
because the determinant is the
determinant of the transpose,
so I'm never worried about
that.
What kind of a box,
what shape box have we got if
the matrix is an
orthogonal matrix?
It's another cube.
It's a cube again.
How is it different from the
identity cube?
It's just rotated.
It's just the orthogonal matrix
Q doesn't have to be the
identity matrix.
It's just the unit cube but
turned in space.
So sure enough,
it's the unit cube,
and its volume is one.
Now is the determinant one?
What's the determinant of Q?
We believe that the determinant
of Q better be one or minus one,
so that our formula is --
checks out in that -- if we
can't check it in these easy
cases where we got a cube,
we're not going to get it in
the
general case.
So why is the determinant of Q
equal one or minus one?
What do we know about Q?
What's the one matrix statement
of the properties of Q?
A matrix with orthonormal
columns has -- satisfies a
certain equation.
What, what is that?
It's if we
have this orthogonal matrix,
then the fact -- the way to say
what it, what its properties are
is this.
Q prime, u- u- Q transpose Q
equals I.
Right?
That's what -- those are the
matrices that get the name Q,
the matrices that
Q transpose Q is I.
OK.
Now from that,
tell me why is the determinant
one or minus one.
How do I, out of this fact --
this may even be a homework
problem.
It's there in the,
in the list of exercises in the
book, and let's just do it.
How do I get,
how do I discover
that the determinant of Q is
one or maybe minus one?
I take determinants of both
sides, everybody says,
so I won't -- I take
determinants of both sides.
On the right-hand side -- so I,
when I take determinants of
both sides, let me just do it.
Take the determinant of --
take determinants.
Determinant of the identity is
one.
What's the determinant of that
product?
Rule nine is paying off now.
The determinant of a product is
the determinant of this guy --
maybe I'll put it,
I'll use that symbol for
determinant.
It's the determinant of that
guy
times the determinant of the
other guy.
And then what's the determinant
of Q transpose?
It's the same as the
determinant of Q.
Rule ten pays off.
So this is just this thing
squared.
So that determinant squared is
one and sure enough it's one or
minus one.
Great.
So in these special cases of
cubes,
we really do have determinant
equals volume.
Now can I just push that to
non-cubes.
Let me push it first to
rectangles, rectangular boxes,
where I'm just multiplying the
e- the edges are -- let me keep
all the ninety degree angles,
because those are -- that,
that makes my life easy.
And just stretch the edges.
Suppose I stretch that first
edge, suppose this first edge I
double.
Suppose I double that first
edge, keeping the other edges
the same.
What happens to the volume?
It doubles, right?
We know that the volume of a
cube doubles.
In fact, because we know that
the
new cube would sit right on top
-- I mean, the new,
the added cube would sit right
on -- would fit -- probably a
geometer would say congruent or
something -- would go right in,
in the other.
We'd have two.
We have two identical cubes.
Total volume is now two.
OK.
So I want -- if I double an
edge, the volume doubles.
What happens to the
determinant?
If I double,
the first row of a matrix,
what ch- ch- what's the effect
on the determinant?
It also doubles,
right?
And that was rule number 3a.
Remember rule 3a was that if I,
I could, if I had a factor in,
in row one, T,
I could factor it out.
So if, if I have a factor two
in that row one,
I can factor it out of the
determinant.
It agrees with the -- the
volume of the box has that
factor two.
So, so volume satisfies this
property 3a.
And now I really close,
but I -- but to get to the very
end of this proof,
I have to get away from right
angles.
I have to allow the possibility
of, other angles.
And -- or what's saying the
same thing, I have to check that
the volume also satisfies 3b.
So can I --
This is end of proof that the
-- so I'm -- determinant of A
equals volume of box,
and where I right now?
This volume has properties,
properties one,
no problem.
If the box is the cube,
everything is -- if the box is
the unit cube,
its volume is one.
Property two was if I reverse
two rows, but that doesn't
change the box.
And it doesn't change the
absolute value,
so no problem there.
Property 3a was if I mul- you
remember what 3a was?
So property one was about the
identity matrix.
Property two was about a plus
or minus sign that I don't care
about.
Property 3a was a factor T in a
row.
But now I've got property three
B to deal with.
What was property 3b?
This is a great way to review
these, properties.
So that 3b, the property 3b
said -- let's do,
let's do two by two.
So said that if I had a+a',
b+b', c, d that this equaled
what?
So this is property 3b.
This is the linearity in row
one by itself.
So c d is staying the same,
and I can split this into a b
and a' b'.
That's property 3b,
at least in the two by two
case.
And what I -- I wanted now to
show that the volume,
which two, two by two,
that means area,
has this, has this property.
Let me just emphasize that we
have got -- we're getting --
this is a formula,
then, for the area of a
parallelogram.
The area of this parallelogram
-- can I just draw it?
OK, here's the,
here's the parallelogram.
I have the row a b.
That's the first row.
That's the point a b.
And I tack on c d.
c d, coming out of here.
And I complete the
parallelogram.
So this is -- well,
I better make it look right.
It's really this one that has
coordinates c d and this has
coordinates -- well,
whatever the sum is.
And of course starting at zero
zero.
So we all know,
this is a+c,
b+d.
Rather than -- I'm pausing on
that proof for a minute just to
going back to our formula.
Because I want you to see that
unlike Cramer's Rule,
that I wasn't that impressed
by, I'm very impressed by this
formula for the area of a
parallelogram.
And what's our formula?
What,
what's the area of that
parallelogram?
If I had asked you that last
year, you would have said OK,
the area of a parallelogram is
the base times the height,
right?
So you would have figured out
what this base,
the -- how long that base was.
It's like the square root of A
squared plus b squared.
And then you would have figured
out how much is this height,
whatever it is.
It's horrible.
This, I mean,
we got square roots,
and in that height there would
be other revolting stuff.
But now what's the formula that
we now know for the area?
It's the determinant of our
little matrix.
It's just ad-bc.
No square roots.
Totally rememberable,
because it's exactly a formula
that we've been studying the
whole, for three lectures.
OK.
That's, you know,
that's the most important point
I'm making here.
Is that if you know the
coordinates of a box,
of the corners,
then you have a great formula
for the volume,
area or volume,
that doesn't involve any
lengths or any angles or any
heights, but just involves the
coordinates that you've got.
And similarly,
what's the area of this
triangle?
Suppose I chop that off and say
what about -- because you might
often be interested in a
triangle instead of a
parallelogram.
What's the area of this
triangle?
Now there again,
everybody would have said the
area of a triangle is
half the base times the height.
And in some cases,
if you know the base that a,
that's -- and the height,
that's fine.
But here, we,
what we know is the coordinates
of the corners.
We know the vertices.
And so what's the area of that
triangle?
If I know these,
if I know a b,
c d, and zero zero,
what's the area?
It's just half,
so it's just half of this.
So this is, this is a- a b -- a
d - b c for the parallelogram
and one half of that,
one half of ad-bc for the
triangle.
So I mean,
this is a totally trivial
remark, to say,
well, divide by two.
But it's just that you more
often see triangles,
and you feel you know the
formula for the area but the
good formula for the area is
this one.
And I'm just going to -- I'm
just going to say one more thing
about the area of a triangle.
It's just because it's -- you
know, it's so great to have a
good formula for something.
What if our triangle did not
start at zero zero?
What if our triangle,
what if we had this -- what if
we had -- so I'm coming back to
triangles again.
But let me, let me put this
triangle somewhere,
it's -- I'm staying with
triangles, I'm just in two
dimensions, but I'm going to
allow you to give me any three
corners.
And in -- those six numbers
must determine the area.
And what's the formula?
The area is going to be,
it's going to be,
there'll be that
half of a parallelogram.
I mean, basically this can't be
completely new,
right?
We've got the area when -- we,
we know the area when this is
zero zero.
Now we just want to lift our
sight slightly and get the area
when all th- so let me write
down what it,
what it comes out to be.
It turns out that if you do
this, x1 y1 and a 1,
x2 y2 and a 1,
x3 y3 and a 1,
that that works.
That the determinant symbol,
of course.
It's just -- if I gave you that
determinant to find,
you might subtract this row
from
this.
It would kill that one.
Subtract this row from this,
it would kill that one.
Then you'd have a simple
determinant to do with
differences, and it would --
this little subtraction,
what I did was equivalent to
moving the triangle to start at
the origin.
I did it fast,
because time is up.
And I didn't complete that
proof of 3b.
I'll leave -- the book has a
carefully drawn figure to show
why that works.
But I hope you saw the main
point is that for area and
volume, determinant gives a
great formula.
OK.
And
next lectures are about
eigenvalues, so we're really
into the big stuff.
Thanks.