PROFESSOR: Welcome to this
presentation on linearization.
So here we consider a
prey-predator system, where we
have x dot equals x, factorizing
3 minus x minus
xy, and y dot equals y
factorizing 1 minus y plus xy.
So here we can see that x is
the prey, because y is
basically feeding on it.
And y is the predator, because
feeding on x gives a growth of
the predator species, y.
So here, because it's a
prey-predator system, x and y
are assumed to be positive.
So you're asked to interpret
even further this system and
to find the critical points,
linearize and sketch the phase
portrait and then discuss what
your linearization tells you
about the behavior
of this system.
So why don't you pause the video
and take a few minutes
to do that.
I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So I helped you already for
the first question.
We interpreted that x was the
prey and y was the predator.
The other thing that you could
see is that this term here is
basic logistic growth.
So if we didn't have the
predator species around, this
species x of prey would just
grow and eventually reach a
value that corresponds to
the saturation level.
And if we started with a lot of
prey, then eventually they
would die off and go back to
that same carrying capacity
value of prey in that
environment.
Same thing here for
the predator.
We have a logistic growth,
with different growth
coefficients.
And again, if we didn't have the
prey around, we would just
have a logistic dynamic for
this species on its own.
But with the prey, we have
a growth of this species.
So that basically ends
the first part.
For the second part, we need to
find the critical points.
So how do we find the
critical points?
The critical points correspond
to basically f
and g equals to 0.
So f equal to 0 equals to g.
You see from f equals to 0
that we can have either x
equals 0, if we factorize the
x on both terms, and if x is
not equal to 0, then we end up
with y equals to 3 minus x.
For the second part, we can also
here, if g equals to 0,
factorize y.
And we get either y equals to 0,
or we have that x is equal
to y minus 1, where I
just bring that term
to the other hand.
So the critical point would be
either of these two entries.
It would be, for example, x
equals to 0 and this entry,
which would give us y equals
to 1, or we would have y
equals to 0, and then this
entry would give
us x equals to 3.
And then the last combined case,
where we have these two
entries, which corresponds
to 1 and 2, if you do it.
So let's look now at the
stability of the linearization
of the system around each one
of these critical points.
So what do we do to linearize
the system?
Very quickly, we need to compute
the Jacobian around
each critical point-- and we're
just going to build a
table after to do that--
where we basically have f, a
derivative of f around x,
derivative of g around x,
derivative of f around y,
derivative of g around y,
all this evaluated at
the critical point.
And this corresponds to
basically linearizing our
nonlinear system, because you
see here that there are a lot
of nonlinear systems, and
studying the stability around
the neighborhood of the critical
point, like if it was
basically linear around there.
This method has its limitations,
and we'll discuss
them later.
So first I'm going to just here
give you the results of
computation that I did earlier,
where basically you
can repeat this computation.
But I don't want to spend
too much time
with the algebra here.
So we have four critical
points.
(0,0), (0,1), (3,0),
and (1,2).
So this is going to
just replace the
values for the Jacobian.
So here you compute basically
the derivative of f of x with
respect to x.
And you evaluate this at then
the value of (0,0).
And so that would give
you (3,0) (0,1).
For this case, same thing.
We have the expression
for the Jacobian.
We evaluate it at critical
point (0,1).
And that gives us
(2,0) (1,-1).
For this one similarly,
we evaluate
the Jacobian at (3,0).
And we get this Jacobian
value.
And for this last critical
point, we have
this Jacobian value.
So now what's next?
So the Jacobian basically gives
us the expression around
the critical point to look at
the system, like if it was
linear around there.
So from this point, we're back
to the linear methods we
learned before.
We need to compute the
eigenvalues of the Jacobian
around each critical point,
and then determine the
structure around each critical
point of the structure of
basically the phase portrait.
So what are the eigenvalues?
The eigenvalues are (3,1), and
you can compute that and
verify for yourself.
Plus or minus root of 7pi and
the whole thing over 2.
So here basically,
we have two real
eigenvalues, both positive.
So we're going to have,
basically, an instability,
unstable node.
And it's just basically the
local stability around the
critical point.
Here we would have this one
positive, one negative.
So this is a saddle, which
would be unstable.
The (-3,4) would give
us another saddle.
And these complex eigenvalues
would basically give us a
spiral with the real part going
to 0, with the real part
being negative.
So a spiral that's stable
and [? symbiotical ?].
So let's just do the
diagram here.
And I'll continue
the discussion.
So let's consider only the
case where x and y are
positive, because we're talking
about populations.
And let's place our
critical points.
So we have a first critical
points here at (0,0).
We have a second critical
point here at (0,1).
We have a third critical point
at (3,0), and the last
critical points at basically
(1,2), or
something around there.
So now, based on the information
we have on this
table, we have the
eigenvalues.
We could also compute the
corresponding eigenvectors.
And you can compute that.
And I'm not going to get into
the details here, but
basically the values of the
eigenvectors would be
important to give you,
for example, the
direction of your spiral.
But we will do that on
the diagram as we go.
So here at the (0,0) point
is an unstable node.
So basically, the solutions are
going away from this point
in the x and y.
This point, (0,1) is a saddle.
So we basically are
on the ray here.
You would compute that the
eigenvector that corresponds
to this negative eigenvalue
would actually be in the
direction (0,1) and would
converge toward this solution.
And you can compute that
the other eigenvector
corresponding to the eigenvalue
2 would have a
direction this form.
So here we neglect what's
happening here, but it would
be in this direction.
And the solutions would
be basically
going away from here.
And we would have locally
something like that.
For this point, which
corresponds to an unstable
mode, basically the solution
would be going away.
For this point, which
corresponds to (3,0), we have
a saddle again, which
is unstable.
And here you can compute that
the eigenvector corresponding
to the negative eigenvalue would
basically be parallel to
the x-axis.
So it would have coordinates
(1,0).
And the eigenvector
corresponding to the
eigenvalue 4 would be directed
in this direction.
And basically, the solution
would be fleeing from there.
So locally, we would have
something like that, like we
did before.
So we'll complete the graph.
Now, let's focus on the last
critical point, (1,2).
So this point corresponds
to a spiral.
And it's a stable spiral --
asymptotically stable, because
these eigenvalue's negative.
So the solutions are going
toward this point.
And you can look at the lower
entry here of the matrix,
which is positive, which means
that we would be going
counterclockwise.
So we would have something there
would be looking like
this, going toward this point.
So that's roughly what we
would have for the three
critical points.
Am I missing one?
For the four critical points.
And so now we can complete our
diagram by basically linking
to different localized phase
portraits together.
And so what will we have here?
So for example, we would have a
solution here that would be
escaping, if we start in this
neighborhood, would be
escaping from this
critical point.
But then eventually, it would
get attracted by this other
critical point, which when
it enters its basin of
attraction, given that it's
symptotically stable would be
attracted by it and go here.
If we started from a very high
y value, we would be going
down and then eventually getting
close to this critical
point that would then basically
cause this directory
to, again, escape and go feed
this spiral by reaching the
basin of attraction
of this point.
If we look at the critical point
(3,0), then if we start
with a population x that is
very large and we approach
this point, then we would have
a solution that basically
would eventually continue
parallel to this ray of the
unstable part of the critical
point (3,0), follow this ray
and eventually basically just
be far more parallel to this
trajectory that links this
linear (3,0), critical point
to the (1,2) critical point.
And so we can complete
the diagram by having
something like this.
Now for this point,
what do we have?
So for this point, we also have
the solutions that would
be basically fleeting from the
point (0,0), and eventually
could be attracted to
the spiral as well.
So that we give us then
something like this, a
trajectory that would be
looking like that And
basically these trajectories
would be looking like that.
And I'm not going to complete
the parts where y and x are
not positive.
So we can complete the phase
diagram of this nonlinear
system in this way.
So now, how do we
interpret this?
What does this mean?
Well, if we remind ourselves
of what this is actually
modeling, and if we just look
at, for example, the different
axes, what does the y equals
0, x equals 0 point mean?
It means that basically we have
0 population of prey, 0
of predator.
And so it makes sense that we
have basically an unstable
point here, an unstable critical
point, because as
soon as we add one prey or one
predator, we would have an
increase of the prey population,
eventually the
predator would grow, and so we
would have a solution that
basically escapes the
area around the
critical point (0,0).
What would happen if we just
looked at the axis y equals to
0? y equals to 0 corresponds
to dynamics where we don't
have the predator population.
So the prey is just
leaving its life,
growing at logistic growth.
And so basically, it's attracted
by the carrying
capacity that would
be here set at 3.
And so if we start with a lot
of prey, eventually they die
out until they reach
population 3.
And if we start with not enough,
they grow and they
reach population 3, without
the predator around.
Same thing for the predator
on its own.
Now if we put the two together
then we have a spiral, which
means that we have
oscillation.
If we have a lot of predators,
we have very few prey.
And eventually the predators
start dying off as well.
But then, because they start
dying off, the prey population
starts increasing, which
then gives an
increase of the predator.
So we get, eventually, an
oscillation that goes to this
attractor, (1,2), where the
system will stabilize
eventually, where we would have,
basically, one prey for
two predators.
So that ends the interpretation
of the system.
And the idea here was to
basically use what we learned
for the linear systems, in terms
of the phase portrait,
and to see how we can apply that
to the nonlinear cases,
after linearlizing the system
around each one of the
critical points.
What I should also mention
here is that in all these
cases that we looked at,
we had cases that were
structurally stable, which means
that in our determinant
trace diagram, we weren't at
any borderline case where a
little perturbation could make
the structure around the
critical point change
radically.
So all these points are
structurally stable, and the
linearization therefore
is valid around them.
And that ends this recitation.