We have here some area in which
we have a magnetic field
which is pointing in
the blackboard.
We have an initial field
pointing in the blackboard
which is 0.8 Tesla.
And we have a 'Db/ dt', the
magnetic field is gradually
becoming smaller and smaller,
weaker and weaker.
That's why we have
the minus sign.
Of 0.045 Tesla per second.
The field is decaying,
so to speak.
So if you want to know what 'B'
is at any moment in time,
you would have plus 0.8, if
I call plus going into the
paper, minus 0.045 times 'T'.
And if you wait long
enough then the
field will even reverse.
It will come out of the paper.
We have right here concentric
a wire loop.
The while loop has
a radius 'R'.
Oh that's actually a terrible
thing to do.
Let's not do that.
Let's give it a radius 'd.' And
let's give the resistance
of this wire a capital 'R'.
Otherwise we get too
much confusion.
This is point 'a' and this is
point 'b' on that wire.
Well, the resistance of the wire
is uniformly distributed
and we are now asked what is
the induced current in this
loop when this magnetic field
is slowly decaying?
First of all, what is the
meaning of this minus sign in
this equation?
We also refer to that minus sign
sometimes as Lenz's law.
The meaning is the following,
and once you understand the
meaning you can actually in your
calculations completely
forget the minus sign,
you will see why.
The meaning is the following:
the magnetic field in this
case in the paper is gradually
decreasing.
The induced current in this loop
will now try to oppose
the change.
And the changes that the
magnetic field, which is in
down direction, gets weaker
and weaker and weaker.
The system opposes that, and
therefor the system will try
to keep the field pointing in
the paper as much as possible.
And the only way it can do that
is by driving an induced
current in clockwise direction,
because that will
give you an induce 'B' field in
this direction, which will
oppose to change.
Namely, that the 'B' field
becomes weaker
and weaker and weaker.
So inside this wire there must
be an electric field that must
be building up which will
be driving this current.
Now, we're now going to
apply Faraday's law.
A big moment in our life.
Closed loop integral
of 'E dot dl'.
This is my loop.
What is my surface?
Open service attached
to the loop?
I might as well choose
this one.
Radius little 'd'.
This now, we call that the
EMF, acts like a battery.
There's no battery in there,
but yet there's an electric
field that is generated and
there's a current flowing.
We call that the EMF.
Electromotive force.
That now equals minus 'dB/
dt' times 'pi d squared'.
Times this surface, because
'B' is the same everywhere
inside this surface
so it's very easy
to execute the integral.
That also equals 'E', which is
the electric field, times '2
pi' times 'd'.
Because when I go around 'E
dot dl', E is the same
everywhere, so you get
'E' times '2 pi d'.
I would suggest that you forget
about minus signs, that
you take absolute values
everywhere, because we already
know that the induced current
is in this direction.
There's really no need
to carry any
further these minus signs.
You know what 'dB/ dt' is.
You know what 'B' is.
So you calculate what
the EMF is.
You can calculate what 'E'
because you know what 'd' is.
Now you have the EMF, you can
now calculate that the induced
current is that EMF
divided by the
resistance 'R' of the wire.
This allows you to calculate
what current is going to flow.
So far, so good.
I don't think you're
going to have a
problem up to this point.
Now comes the part where it
becomes very non-intuitive.
Young is asking you what is
the potential difference
between point 'a'
and point 'b'.
And that is a nonsense question
because it depends on
the routing, how you
go from 'a' to 'b'.
I would like to make a different
drawing to make my
point as clear as
I possibly can.
Here is only that inner loop.
Here is point 'a' and
here is point 'b'.
And the electric field, I'll put
it in red now, is in this
direction, this direction, this
direction, this direction.
Notice that the integral
of 'E dot dl' is not 0.
It's a non-conservative field.
Kirchhoff's Law no
longer holds.
But now comes the non-intuitive
part.
If I march from a to b along
this line, then the integral,
in going from 'a' to 'b' of
'E dot dl' is positive.
You can see 'E' and 'dl' are
in the same direction.
And it happens to be,
if I did not make a
mistake, plus 0.7 minivolts.
If, however, I walk in this
direction notice that my 'E'
and my 'dl' are in opposite
directions.
So the dot product will give
me a minus sign and so here
the integral in going
from 'a' to 'b' of
'E dot dl' is negative.
It happens to be minus
0.7 minivolts.
Suppose I walk this way.
Exactly through the middle, then
the integral of 'E dot
dl' from 'a' to 'b' equals 0.
If I put the line slightly here
the trajectory, the path,
will be larger than 0.
If I put it on this side it'll
be smaller than 0.
So, you see, it is completely
ill defined.
I can go even further
and show you the
absurdity of Young's question.
If I have here point 'a' and I
have here point 'b', and if I
choose a closed loop, which
starts at a and goes around
and around and around and around
and around and around
and around and around and
finally attach it to point
'b', then it's a closed loop
and I do 100,000 windings.
Then the integral from 'a' to
'b' of 'E dot dl', believe it
or not is plus 700 volts.
That's to say if I start
in this direction.
If I start in this direction,
than it is minus 700 volts.
Can you now say that 'a'
is at a 700 volt
potential higher than 'b'?
That's nonsense.
Because you go this way, then
it is 700 volts below 'b'.
How real is this 700 volts?
Can you actually measure
these voltages?
And the answer is yes.
If, for instance, in my previous
example, if I had a
wire here, and I had a volt
meter here straight through
the middle, this volt
meter would read 0.
If I had a wire here and a volt
meter here and attach it
here this volt meter would
read plus 0.7 minivolts.
Was it 0.7?
It was 7.
If I had a volt meter here in
this line, then this one would
read minus 7 minivolts.
And if I put a volt meter here
in this line which has 100,000
windings, that volt meter would
read plus 700 volts.
That's the whole idea
behind transformers.
So, I hope it will stick that
the concept of potential
difference between two points is
no longer defined when you
deal with a non-conservative
field.
And that's always the case
when the magnetic flux,
through a surface, attached to
closed loop is changing.
And it is sad, truly sad,
that Young does
not understand that.