That brings me now to the last
problem, which is Problem 5,
which is 30-42, my
last problem.
A little bit of a mathematical
problem perhaps, I have a
current 'i' here, and I have,
here, a loop, and the loop has
length 'l'.
This distance is little 'a',
this distance is little 'b',
and I have a changing current,
'di/dt.' Well, first of all
the current 'i' will produce
a magnetic field pointing
everywhere on this side, in the
paper and everywhere on
this side out of the paper,
but we're only
concerned on this side.
The 'di/dt' will make the
current grow, and so 'i', as a
function of time, equals some
'i0', time equals 0, plus
'di/dt' times 't'.
It's growing linearly.
Lenz's Law, Faraday's Law,
says I don't like that.
I don't like this magnetic field
in the paper to grow; I
don't like the magnetic flux
through this surface to grow,
and so what does it do?
It creates a 'B induced'
in this direction.
How can you get a 'B induced'
in this direction?
It's only possible if you have
an 'i induced' in this loop in
this direction.
Therefore, electric fields
in the wires that contain
resistance in this direction.
Now, how are you going
to go about it?
The growing magnetic fields
will give a growing flux
through this surface, and
that gives you, then, a
counterclockwise induced
current.
To calculate the change of the
magnetic flux, we have the
closed loop integral
of 'E dot dl'--
I'm only worried about
magnetic flux,
about absolute values.
I don't care about
minus signs.
That is 'd/dt' times the
integral of 'B dot dA' over
that open surface.
And now, what I have to do to
calculate this properly, I
have to take a slice
out of here.
I take a slice out of here at
distance 'r', and the width of
the slice is 'dr'.
And the magnetic field at that
position 'r', away from this
wire with current 'i', is
something that you, by now,
know by heart, is 'mu 0 i'
divided by '2 pi r'.
So the magnetic flux, the
teeny-weeny, little magnetic
flux going through this small
narrow ribbon, of which 'dr'--
'd phi r', this is the magnetic
flux at location 'r'--
is the magnetic field times
the surface area--
since this was 'l'--
which is 'ldr'.
And so, if I do an integral of
the magnetic flux; then I have
to do an integral all the way
from 'a' to 'b' of that
magnetic field 'ldr'.
Here's the surface area.
I integrate 'r' from 'a' to
'b', and what do I find?
'Mu 0' times 'i' times 'l'
divided by '2 pi' times the
logarithm of 'b/a' , because
remember 'Br' is inversely
proportional to 'r'.
I think we're done, because all
you now have to do, and
you are perfectly capable of
doing that yourself, you now
have to take the time derivative
of phi that gives
you the phi dt.
And once you know the phi dt,
you know the integral E dot
dl, and you can calculate
the induced current.
So it's simply a matter now, of
taking the time derivative
of this one, and what you are
going to see is that what is
very important is the magnitude
of 'di/dt' .
The larger 'di/dt'
, the larger the
induced emf in the system.