PROFESSOR: Problem 4 is 30-21.
Here, linear axis: 0, 'L',
'2L', '-L', '-2L'.
And here in space, perhaps a
little bit artificial, I have
an area '2L' by '2L', which has
a magnetic field pointing
in the paper, and the
magnetic field is
constant in the paper.
Here I have a loop, which has
sides, capital 'L', and that
loop is being moved by me with
a certain velocity, 'v',
dragged into this
magnetic field.
And I'm being asked now, what is
the induced current in this
loop as a function of position,
and what is the
force of this loop as a
function of position.
I, Walter Lewin, have
to drag it in.
Is it positive force to
the right or is it a
force to the left?
Do I have to push it?
Maybe it sucks in itself.
I will use this point 'P'
as my reference point
relative to this axis.
Follow me closely.
Before 'P' reaches this point,
there is no magnetic flux
change; it's 0, so there cannot
be any induced current.
The moment that 'P' hits '-L'
there is going to be an
increased magnetic flux
through this surface.
This is the surface attached
to my loop, it's an open
surface; and therefore, there
will be an induced current.
The magnetic flux is increasing,
and therefore,
there will be an induced
current.
If the magnetic flux is
increasing in this direction,
the current that will flow
will try to oppose that
increase, and so it will create
an induced magnetic
field in this direction, so
that the flux in the paper
doesn't grow so fast. Once the
loop is completely inside,
that means once point 'P'
reaches 0, there is no longer
any flux change, and so there
is no longer any induced
current, and the current
will stop once it
reaches this point.
And all the way from here to
here, 'P' being here to here,
the magnetic flux
will not change.
But the moment that 'P' emerges
here, the magnetic
flux, which is in this
direction, is changing again.
It's losing magnetic flux,
so something is
going to happen again.
I will do the early part of the
problem, and you will then
do the second part
of the problem.
Well, the magnetic flux change,
'd phi dt', when 'P'
begins to move into the magnetic
field equals 'vBL'.
Every second the magnetic flux
increases with a value, which
is 'B' times the increase in
surface area, and the increase
in surface area is 'vL', and so
the closed loop integral of
'E dot dl' along the loop
that I have chosen--
and let's not worry about signs,
because we know the
direction anyhow--
equals 'vBL', and we already
determined that in the loop
when it starts to enter the
magnetic field the induced
current will be in this
direction, so the induced
electric field will be
in this direction.
That's the 'E' field in this
loop, and if you want to know
what the induced current is,
well, that is the EMF value,
which is 'vBL' divided by the
resistance of this circuit, if
'R', capital 'R' is the
resistance of that circuit.
What is the force
on this loop?
Well, there are two ways
that you can do this.
One way is to say, aha, I have
this wire here, which has
length 'L', I'll make
a new drawing.
This wire, which has length 'L',
it has a current flowing
through it, which is 'i
induced', which we just
calculated.
It has a magnetic field, 'B'--
I should really make
it black--
'B', in the paper, which is this
external field, and so
the force on the wire equals
'i' times 'L' times 'B'.
This is part of Assignment
5, and that
force is in this direction.
Remember, it is the
cross-product between 'i',
'L', and 'B', and if you take
that into account, you'll see
that it is in this direction.
But I, Walter Lewin, have to
push this in, have to pull it
in, so my force, 'F', Walter
Lewin, is in magnitude the
same, but it is to the right.
And therefore, notice that
I do positive work.
I do positive work, because the
force is to the right, and
I'm dragging it to the right.
That's one way of doing it.
There's another way, which I
like, and that is: as the
current is flowing in here,
there is power dissipated in
that loop, which has a
resistance 'R', and that power
is 'i squared R'.
That's the amount of work per
second that is released in the
form of heat in this
whole loop.
Now, who is going to provide
that work per second?
That's Walter Lewin; so this
must be the force by Walter
Lewin by the velocity with
which I drag it through.
Remember this is also power,
and if you solve this
equation, you will find
exactly the same
value for my force.
It must give the same answer,
and I think you should
convince yourself, both methods
give the same answer.
If I make a drawing, a sketch,
of the induced current as a
function of this linear
dimension: 'L', '2L', 0, '-L',
'-2L', and if I draw here, 'i
induced', then we would agree
that when point 'P'-- this is
all relative to point 'P'--
when 'P' is outside
capital 'L', there
is no induced current.
Instantaneously, when 'P'
penetrates a magnetic field,
it goes to a value 'BvL' divided
by 'R', and I called
this negative, but it's really
a counter-clockwise current,
and I would like to call a
clockwise current positive.
Then while it's inside all the
way from 0 to 'L', there is,
again, no flux change--
I stress that point,
here it is, again--
when the loop is in here, all
the way marching up to here
there is no flux change, so the
induced current goes to 0,
and this, now, is the part all
the way on the right side,
here, you do.
I think you have all the
ingredients, now.
You should have no problem.