PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
Today what I want to do is
something maybe a little bit
more theoretical, but the goal
is to show that something that
you are going to be repeatedly
doing when you use quadratic
approximations is,
in fact, true.
So I'm going to explain the
situation, give a quick
example, and then show you what
we're setting out to do.
So the situation is as follows
we're going to--
any time you see a Q of f,
that's going to represent the
quadratic approximation
to f at x equals 0.
So what I've done is say, Q of
f I'm going to define to be
the thing on the right, which
is exactly the formula you
were given in class for the
quadratic approximation of a
function f at x equals 0.
So f is approximately the thing
on the right near 0.
Our goal is to show that if I
want to take the quadratic
approximation of a product of
two functions, that I can do
it in a different way.
I can do it in the way written
on the right hand side, which
actually looks more complicated
in this notation,
but is, in fact, easier
in reality.
So let me explain what's
happening and then I'll give
you an example.
If I wanted to take the
quadratic approximation of a
product of two functions, what
I want to show is that
instead, I could take the
quadratic approximation of
each individual function,
multiply those together, and
then take the quadratic
approximation of
what I get as a result.
So let me give you
an easy example.
For instance, let's let f of x
equal e to the x and let's let
g of x equal sine x.
Then what is Q of f?
Q of f is the quadratic
approximation to e to the x at
x equals 0.
And that's going to be 1 plus x
plus x squared over 2-- your
already knew this.
And g, the quadratic
approximation of
sine x, is just x.
So if I wanted to find the
quadratic approximation to e
to the x sine x, what
I could do--
what this is claiming
I can do--
is instead I can take the
quadratic approximation of
this function times
this function.
So instead I can take the
quadratic approximation of--
f was the e to the x--
1 plus x plus x squared
over 2 times x.
That's not a 4, sorry.
That's a parentheses.
1 plus x plus x squared
over 2 times x.
And what is that?
The quadratic approximation
to that is the quadratic
approximation to x plus x
squared plus x cubed over 2.
And at x equals 0, if I have
a polynomial, the quadratic
approximation to a polynomial at
x equals 0 is just all the
terms up to the quadratic
term.
So I drop off higher order
terms. So I just
get x plus x squared.
So that's the idea.
The idea is I have a product of
two functions, I know their
individual quadratic
approximations, and so what I
want to do is I want to find the
quadratic approximation of
this product by exploiting the
fact that I already know their
individual ones, and explain
the fact that quadratic
approximation of polynomials
at x equals 0 is very easy.
So that's the example,
that's the idea.
So now let's see if
we can do it.
OK.
So we have a cheat sheet
up here that I'm going
to refer back to.
I didn't want to use it again
and I didn't want to have to
derive this for you, but we
have the product rule-- fg
prime is equal to what's on the
right, and fg double prime
is equal to what's
on the right.
So my goal here is to show,
remember, that the quadratic
approximation--
let me point over here again.
The goal is to show the
quadratic approximation of fg
is equal to the quadratic
approximation of quadratic
approximation of f times the
quadratic approximation of g.
So let's do, well let's do the
right hand side first because
that's a little nicer.
And then we'll show the right
hand side and then we'll show
the left hand side and we'll
show they're equal.
So let me start here with
the right hand side.
OK?
So, let's look at what's the
quadratic approximation of f
and what's the quadratic
approximation of g and then
we'll take their final quadratic
approximation.
So Q of f, we have exactly
what we need there.
f of 0 plus f prime of 0 times
x plus f double prime of 0
over 2 x squared.
Q of g is equal to g of 0 plus
g prime of 0 times x plus g
double prime at 0 over
2 x squared.
So now what I'm going to do is
multiply those two together.
And I'm actually going to swing
this way a tiny bit, if
that's OK, to write Q of f
times Q of g because it's
going to be a little long.
And I'm going to group them
carefully so that I have all
the higher order terms
at the end.
OK?
So I'm going to get
f of 0 g of 0 by
multiplying these two together.
And then I'm going to get two
terms involving an x.
I'm going to get an f prime
times g and a g prime times f.
Actually, if you'll allow me,
we'll know that anywhere we
see an f or a g or an f prime
or a g prime, or an f double
prime or g double prime, they're
all evaluated at 0.
So I'm going to drop the
0's from here on out.
Anywhere you see those, I'm
evaluating them at 0.
Otherwise this will
be way too long.
So let me write this
just as fg.
I can even write just a single
one evaluated at 0.
It's the product evaluated at 0
and then I have f prime g--
so I'll just evaluate it at 0
at the end of the product--
plus fg prime evaluated at 0.
This whole thing is times x.
I get an x here, I
get an x here.
Now I need to figure out what
terms give me an x squared.
OK?
So the terms that give me an x
squared are f of 0 times g
double prime over 2.
That gives me an x squared.
f double prime times g gives
me an x squared.
And f prime g prime gives
So let's write out those terms.
I get fg double prime
at 0 over 2--
from those two--
plus g f double prime
at 0 over 2--
from those two--
plus f prime g prime at
0 all times x squared.
So there's an x times
an x there--
gives you an x squared.
x squared there, x
squared there.
Now I could keep going, and I
will mention the higher order
terms, but I'm not going to
write them all the way out
because of what we're
about to do.
Let me show you where
they come from.
You get an x cubed term
from here and an x
cubed term from here.
Maybe I'll write the x cubes,
but I won't write
the x to the fourth.
So the x cubed terms are f prime
g double prime 0 over 2
plus g prime f double
prime at 0 over 2.
And those are my
x cubed terms.
And then I got some x to the
fourth terms. And where do the
x to the fourth terms
come from?
They come from this product.
Right?
But I want to point
out something.
What I'm going to do, I'm
going to work some
magic on the board.
This is a quadratic
approximation of f times a
quadratic approximation of g.
Let me come over here and remind
you that I want the
quadratic approximation
of that product.
So what I'm going to do is go
back and look at what I need
from there to be the quadratic
approximation of that product.
So we come back over here.
If I apply the quadratic
approximation to this thing,
which means then I'm applying it
to this whole giant thing,
what do I actually get?
This is actually a polynomial.
I have something--
I have a linear term, I have an
x, I have an x squared, I
have an x cubed, I have
an x to the fourth.
So if I apply that quadratic
approximation,
let's see what stays.
This term stays.
I'm going to erase what
disappears because I don't
want us to get confused
by that.
So these two terms disappear.
Why?
Because again, this
is a polynomial.
I have linear--
or I have constant, I'm sorry,
I think I called this maybe
linear earlier-- constant
linear quadratic term.
And what I need is just those if
I'm looking for a quadratic
approximation.
So constant linear quadratic
term, I immediately drop the
cubic and the quartic term
when I'm looking at a
quadratic approximation
of a polynomial at 0.
So if I want the right hand
side, I just need what's
underlined in blue.
So now I'm going to put a big
box around that because that's
going to be important.
Whatever else happens,
we don't lose that.
So now we've done the
right hand side.
And now let's write out what
is the left hand side.
And that's just going
to be plugging it
straight into the formula.
And using our cheat sheet.
So Q of fg, let me write out the
definition and then we'll
use the cheat sheet.
It's fg at 0--
again, this is f at 0,
g at 0, that's what
this notation means--
plus fg quantity prime at 0
times x plus quantity fg
double prime at 0 over
2 times x squared.
And now what we're hoping,
remember, is that what's in
the box is what shows
up over here.
Because this is the long
way to do the problem.
This would be if I took either
the x sine x and I took all
the derivatives.
And this, in fact, even though
it looks more confusing in
evaluating such a quadratic
approximation, this way would
be the easier way.
We just want to show we don't
lose anything by doing what
would be the easier way.
So I get fg at 0.
And that's good-- we can see we
already have one of those,
so that's nice.
What do I get here?
I get f prime g at 0 plus
g prime f at 0 times x.
That comes-- let me remind you,
I'll walk over here--
comes from the cheat sheet.
The first thing.
fg prime is f prime
g plus g prime f.
We know that one pretty well,
but just to remind you.
So that's where this
term comes from.
This looks promising because
if we come back to our
quadratic of quadratic of f
times quadratic of g, it looks
exactly like the second
term here.
So now we're hoping that the x
squared term looks like this.
The only thing that might make
you nervous is this doesn't
have an over 2, but if you were
paying attention to the
cheat sheet you'll probably
see where that's coming.
And I'll point it out
in one moment.
So fg double prime--
using the cheat sheet--
is f double prime g plus
g double prime f
plus 2 g prime f prime.
I should have put
0's in there.
Just to be consistent let me
put these 0's in there.
2 f prime g prime at 0.
And then I have to divide the
whole thing by 2 because
there's a divided by 2 there,
and then times x squared.
So let me move out of the
way for a moment.
So this numerator came from the
cheat sheet for the second
derivative.
And if you need,
we can go back.
Let me just remind
you, here it is.
You can work it out
for yourself.
You can just take the derivative
of the first
derivative.
But that's where this
comes from.
So let me go back and we're
almost done with the problem.
So what do we see?
Well, we see that
we get fg at 0.
We get the second term we want,
f prime g at 0 plus g
prime f at 0 times x.
And then the third term is, in
fact, exactly what we want
because we get f double prime
g at 0 over 2 plus g double
prime f at 0 over 2 plus--
the 2's divide out--
and I get f prime g prime
at 0 time x squared.
And if we look at this last
term and we look at the
squared term in the box
we see, in fact, they
are exactly the same.
So let me summarize because this
was kind of a long video.
So I'm going to go back to the
beginning, give you the
example, and tell you what we
were really trying to do here.
So let's come back over here.
And let me remind you, the goal
was to show that if I
wanted to take a quadratic
approximation of a product of
two functions, if I already
knew their individual
quadratic approximations, you
were told that you could take
those two quadratic
approximations, multiply them,
and drop off the higher
order terms. The
higher order, then 2.
So we had an example.
We knew these two quadratic
approximations.
And you've been told that
quadratic approximation of
their product is just the
quadratic approximation of the
product of their quadratic
approximations.
And so our goal today was to
show that you don't drop any
of the terms that you get if you
do it by this method or by
this method.
And we've done that.
So I think I'll stop there.