JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome to recitation.
In lecture, you started learning
about vectors.
Now vectors are going to be
really important throughout
the whole of this course.
And I wanted to give you one
problem just to work with them
in a slightly different context
than what we're going
to do in the future.
So this is the context of
Euclidean geometry.
So some of you have probably
seen this problem that we're
going to solve, but you probably
haven't seen it
solved with vectors.
So let's take a look at it.
So what I'd like you to do is
show that the three medians of
a triangle intersect at a point,
and the point is 2/3 of
the way from each vertex.
So let me just remind you
of some terminology.
So in a triangle, a median is
the segment that connects one
vertex to the midpoint
of the opposite side.
So here, this point M is exactly
halfway between B and
C.
So OK.
So every triangle has three
medians-- one from each vertex
connected to the midpoint of the
opposite side-- and what
I'm asking you to show is that
these three medians all
intersect in the same point.
And also, that this point
divides the median into two
pieces, and the big piece
is twice as large
as the small piece.
So this is 2/3 of the median,
and this is 1/3 of the median.
So, why don't you take a few
minutes, work that out-- try
and do it using vectors
as much as possible--
pause the video, come
back, and we
can work on it together.
So hopefully you had some luck
working on this problem.
Let's get started on it.
So to start, I actually want
to rephrase the question a
little bit.
And I'll rephrase it to an
equivalent question that's a
little bit more clear about how
we want to get started.
So another way to say this
problem is that it's
asking us to show--
so for each median, say this
median AM here, where M is the
midpoint of side BC--
there exists a point on the
median that divides it into a
2:1 ratio, so the point that's
2/3 from the vertex to the
midpoint of the opposite side.
So for example, you know,
there's a point--
so, let's call it P,
say, at first--
so there's a point P such
that AP is twice PM.
OK?
And similarly, there's some
point-- maybe called Q--
that's 2/3 of the way from B to
the midpoint of this side.
And there's some point that's
2/3 of the way from C to the
midpoint of this side.
And so an equivalent formulation
of the question is
to show that these
three points are
really the same point.
That they're all in
the same place.
So one way we can do that is
that we can compare the
position vectors of those
three points.
And if those three points all
have the same position vector,
then they're all in exactly
the same position.
So in order to do that
we need some origin.
And it happens that for this
problem, it doesn't matter
where the origin is, and so
I'm not going to draw an
origin, but I'm going
to call it O.
So we're going to set up a
vector coordinate system with
origin O. And now I want to look
at what the vector from O
to P is in terms of the vectors
connecting O to A, B,
and C. Right?
Those are the vectors
that determine the
vertices of the triangle.
And so I want to relate the
location of P to the locations
of A, B, and C.
So the first thing
to do is that--
well, in order to talk about
where P is, I know how P is
related to A and M and I know
how M is related to B and C.
So let's first figure out what
the position vector of M is in
terms of the position vectors
of A, B, and C, and then we
can use that to figure out
the position vector of P.
So M is the midpoint
of the segment BC.
So I think we saw
this in lecture.
What this means is that the
position vector OM is exactly
the average of the position
vectors of B and C. It's 1/2
of the quantity OB plus OC.
All right?
So it's easy to express the
position vector of the
midpoint of a segment in
terms of the position
vectors of the endpoints.
You just add the position
vectors of the endpoints and
divide by 2.
So if you like, this is
equivalent to the geometric
fact that the diagonals of a
parallelogram bisect each other.
So that's the position
vector of M.
Now we have to figure out what
the position vector of P is.
So in order to do this we can
note, that in order to get
from the origin to point P,
well, what we have to go from
the origin-- wherever it is--
to A, and then we have to go
from A 2/3 of the way
to M. All right?
So the vector OP is equal to OA
plus 2/3 of the vector AM.
Right?
Because we go 2/3 of the way
from A to M in order to get
from A to P. This is because
we've chosen P to be the point
that divides segment AM into
a 2:1 ratio so that
AP is 2/3 of AM.
OK.
So good.
So now we need the vector AM.
Well, we know what the position
vector of A is.
It's just OA.
And we also know what the
position vector of M is.
It's OM.
So that means that AM is
just the difference
of those two vectors.
It's going to be OM minus OA.
Another way to say this is that
if you add OA to both
sides, you have that OA
plus AM equals OM.
In other words, to go from O to
M, first you can go from O
to A, and then go from
A to M. All right.
And I've just subtracted OA
onto the other side here.
So we can write AM in
terms of OM and OA.
And we also, we have an
expression for OM here in
terms of OB and OC.
So that means we can get an
expression for AM in terms of
OA, OB, and OC.
So let's do that.
So that's just by substituting
from here into here.
So if I do that, I get that AM
is equal to-- so OM is 1/2 OB
plus 1/2 OC, and now
I just subtract OA.
All right.
So that's what AM is, putting
these two equations together.
I get that that's AM.
And so now I need to figure
out what OP is.
So for OP, I just need to
substitute in this new
expression that I've
got for AM.
So I have OP is equal to, well
it's equal to OA plus 2/3 of
what I've written just
right above--
2/3 of AM.
So that's 1/2 OB plus
1/2 OC minus OA.
OK.
And so now you can multiply this
2/3 in-- you know, just
distribute the scalar
multiplication across the
addition there-- and then
we can rearrange.
We'll have two terms involving
OA and we can combine them.
So we'll see we have a
plus OA minus 2/3 OA.
So that's going to be
equal to 1/3 OA.
And then we have, OK so
2/3 times 1/2 OB.
So that's plus 1/3
OB plus 1/3 OC.
So this gives us a simple
formula for the position
vector of P--
that vector OP--
in terms of the position vectors
of A, B, and C. So in
particular, it's actually
because P is the special
point, it's 1/3 of their sum.
Of the sum OA plus OB plus OC.
OK, so that's where P is.
Now to finish the problem, I
just have to show that this is
the same location as
the point that
trisects the other medians.
So how would I do that?
Well, I could go back to my
triangle and I could do
exactly the same thing.
So I could-- maybe I'll give
this point a name, also.
I'll call this midpoint
N, say.
So I could let Q be the point
that lies 2/3 of the way from
B to N. And then I could write
down the position vector of N
in terms of OA, OB, and OC.
And then I can use that to write
down the position vector
of Q in terms of OA, OB, and
OC, and I'll get some
expression.
And what will happen
at the end--
I hope if I'm lucky--
that expression will be equal
to this expression that I
found over here.
OK?
So you can go through and do
that, and if you do that, what
you'll find is that
in fact it works.
So there's actually a sort
of clever, shorter
way of seeing that.
Which is that this formula is
symmetric in A, B, and C.
So that means if I just relabel
the points A, B, and
C, this expression
for the position
vector doesn't change.
So rather than going through
that process that I just
described, you can also say,
well, in order to look at, say
Q, instead of P, what I need to
do is I just need to switch
B and A. I need to do exactly
the same thing but the roles
of A and B are interchanged.
Well, if the roles of A and B
are interchanged, then in the
resulting formula, I just have
to interchange the roles of A
and B, but that won't change the
value of this expression.
So by symmetry, the point
I get really is
going to be the same.
If you don't like that argument,
I invite you to go
through this computation
again in the case
of the other medians.
In either case, what you'll find
is that the points that
trisect the three medians all
have position vector 1/3 OA
plus 1/3 OB plus 1/3
OC, but that means
they're the same point.
So what we've shown then, is
that the points that trisect
the three medians-- that
trisect-- that divide them
into 2:1 ratios from the vertex
to the midpoint of the
opposite side, that those three
points all have the same
position vector.
So in fact, they're the same
point, and that's what we
wanted to show, right?
We wanted to show that there's
one point that trisects all
three of those medians.
So we've shown that the three
points that trisect them are
actually the same.
So that's the same conclusion,
phrased differently.
So I think I'll end there.