The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation, or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: We'll start with a
little bit of recap from two
Fridays ago.
But just a reminder of things to
keep in mind while you guys
are testing.
On one hand, most of you are
pretty much the most expert
players in your game at this
point in time, [INAUDIBLE]
You know the game better
than anybody else.
And the kind of things that--
that means you suck
as a tester.
That means you still have a
role to play as testers.
You can be looking for the
degenerate strategies, and you
can be looking for exploits.
Sometimes it takes more
imagination than a
sleep-deprived MIT student has
available to them, to be able
to see these exploits.
But, because you know the
systems better than anyone
else, you're in a good position
to spot that.
The kinds of things you're
looking for are obviously
value [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
strategy.
I mentioned that the last time
we were in this room.
But also, look for those
strategies were, like, OK, I
have two [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
those decision points where I
could do decision A or I could
do the decision B, but if I
change my strategy, and nobody
else has changed their strategy,
I'm screwed.
And that makes it really really
hesitant for someone to
say, well, Strategy B could be
really interesting, I can go
for this kind of play, but on
the assumption that the only
way how this is going to be
beneficial is if everybody
else also changes
their strategy.
Now you have a situation where
nobody wants to try that
second option.
That's one way to think
about cyberpunks.
It's like, if you change your
position and the only way that
you can change your position is
at a cost to yourself, then
the benefits of changing that
position is going to be lower
than the risk that you're taking
on, then you've got a
situation where it's very
difficult to break out of one
dominant strategy.
So if you've got a situation
where there are three dominant
strategies, then none of them
are dominant anymore that's
great, now I have an
option of different
things they can choose.
So that's just one thing to keep
in mind if all you guys
are looking at a game.
If everyone just ends up
adopting the same strategy,
and you're just hoping for a
chance of drawing the right
cards, in order to win your
game, then [UNINTELLIGIBLE],
then you've got a game where
the individual player's
decisions aren't quite that
influential on the outcome.
And I still need to play your
games to be able to see what
you guys are going for.
But, for the most part, it looks
like you guys are not
going for a purely chance-based
game.
You're looking for something
where someone's decision
actually matters.
So that's one reminder from the
game theory point of view.
And the other one I never really
got time to talk about
games or system of conflict,
and we don't have a huge
amount of time because
we have today's
readings to go through.
But if you think about games as
games where multiple people
are striving for some sort of
goal, and there are going to
be winners and there are going
to be losers, then the idea of
thinking of games as some kind
of conflict makes sense.
If you think of them as, are
games competitive, or are
games cooperative, for
throughout some games that are
known to be cooperative
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
there are certain modes in
certain different games that
flip it from competitive
to cooperative.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: But it is designed
for four people to play, all
going for the same goal.
AUDIENCE: Gears of War
PROFESSOR: Gears of War
multiplayer, yeah.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] interesting,
yeah.
Because it's kind of the
risk of cooperation.
Pandemic is you against
the board, actually.
You against the game rules.
And actually, that leads into
today's lecture a bit.
So hang onto that idea
of Pandemic.
But there is one argument that
all games are competitive.
Even games like Left for Dead,
where you're playing against
the computer, or Pandemic, when
you're playing against
the game rules.
Or--
AUDIENCE: Shelter
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
a bit--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: You're mostly playing
against the game rules.
Unless there's a trader,
there's not
always one in the game.
PROFESSOR: But the basic idea is
that even in a game that's
generally assumed to be
co-op, you're still
playing against the world.
So as competitive against the
world, just not here,
computing against the
other human people
that are playing it.
If they're competing against.
Anyone is probably going to
decide who set it up, to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So that's one way to think of
all games as competitive.
Obviously, the games that people
generally think of as
competitive, real-time games
like chess, for instance.
There's one winner, there's one
loser, and if there's a
draw then nobody wins.
Or, those games people
generally think of as
competitive.
But then, the other way to think
about cooperation is
that all games are
also cooperative.
Because if you don't agree
on the rules--
if you're all in fact not
playing the same rules, then
you don't actually
have a game.
So you all have to cooperate
to play.
We have the same set of rules
and we're going to play
according to them.
That's not necessarily the
same thing as saying that
everyone knows all the rules.
There are plenty of games,
especially computer games,
where you're going
into the game not
knowing all the rules.
You're going to try to figure
out the rules as the one
system lets you.
Role-playing games, where
you start off like,
I want to do this.
I want to-- you know,
get drunk now,
and how do I do that?
And then the GM tells
you the rules.
Roll against your--
AUDIENCE: Constitution.
PROFESSOR: Constitution,
is it constitution?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
but.
Drunkenness.
PROFESSOR: Always good.
Possibly.
And then you get
told the rules.
And then you go and do it.
Live-action role-playing
games.
I know there's a bunch of people
here who play them.
You usually get a subset of
all the rules that were
written for the game.
You get the subset that
pertains to you.
And you assume that everybody
else has the subset that
pertains to them.
And that they're playing
according to it.
There's a strong honor system,
and even in a game, especially
the kinds that are played in
MIT, which are fiercely
competitive.
There's literally
assassin games.
You literally want to lead
someone into a dark alley and
shoot them.
Even then, you have to assume
that whatever rules that
person, who you're leading down
a dark alley in order to
shoot them.
Whatever rules [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
they're
playing by those rules.
They're not going to say--
if you shoot them, they can
say, that didn't work.
You have to assume that actually
didn't work, because
they have rules that tell them
when it works and when it
didn't work.
So it's still cooperative,
even though
it's competitive play.
And, some terminology now.
There's systemic cooperation,
which is what I'm describing.
It's the, you are agreeing
that the system works.
And you are agreeing how
the system works.
These are the ways
how I'm going to
interact with the system.
If I'm going to be playing--
Goldeneye or [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
on the split screen.
Or Halo on the split screen.
And you agree not to look at
somebody else's screen.
Then, that's a systemic rule.
You might also decide, no, it's
on the screen, I can't
avoid seeing it, therefore
we can all look at
each others' screens.
That would be a systemic rule.
Even though the goals are the
same, let's shoot each other.
And then there's clear
cooperation, which is a little
bit more like the games like
Pandemic and Left for Dead,
where you're explicitly trying
to help each other in your
team in a shared goal.
And I'm just trying to
differentiate them.
Because it's useful sometimes
to sort of try to figure out
the differences.
There's a game that I don't
think we're making you play,
called The War on Terror.
That we have in the lab.
And one of the things about this
game is that it actually
doesn't end.
If you look at the rules,
it seems that there are
conditions for the game end,
but they're really, really
hard to reach.
And if you're interested in
seeing how the game ends, I'll
be happy to pass you to Cory,
and he can try to figure it
out, or play it.
But of course, that's the point
that they're trying to
make, right?
It's a War on Terror, it
never really ends.
It'll keep going.
It perpetuates yourself, and
it's designed to be a
competitive game.
Everybody tries to take down
all the other states.
The other nation states, by
sponsoring terrorist activity,
or trying to defend themselves
from terrorist activity.
Which means everybody's
responsible for terrorism in
the end, in that game.
But in the end, what you're
hoping is at some point in
time, the players are going to
cooperate, because this game's
not going to end.
That's the whole point
of the game.
And the entire group coming to
that conclusion in a shared
way, is what the game
designers were
trying to go for.
It's a funny game.
Anybody who played Crunch, it
was done by the same folks.
But it's a little bit more of
the, we have an opinion and we
want you to share it, then
this is a game that you
actually want to try to win.
It's funny.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
So, that's some opinions about
cooperation, and that is,
systemic cooperation, where
you're agreeing on the rules,
or you agree that the
system works.
And that's their cooperation,
where players are actually
agreeing towards some
sort of shared goal.
And there are games where
it flips between player
cooperation and player
competition.
It's like--
Castle Crashers, who's played
Castle Crashers?
It's a great game, xBox
Live arcade game.
You run around, it's a side
scrolling game, where a little
knight with a sword--
AUDIENCE: It's a sword?
AUDIENCE: No, it
can be an axe.
It can be a fish.
PROFESSOR: Some sort of
bludgeoning device.
Fish is awesome.
And in general, if you're
playing with three other
people with controllers right
to you on the couch, you're
pretty much going for
the same goal.
There are you four, and there
are a whole bunch of baddies
on screen, and you're trying
to kill it all.
But then, as soon as you beat
the last one, the game
switches from defeat all the
baddies to save the princess.
And, wait a minute--
AUDIENCE: No, you've already
saved the princess.
It goes to get the princess.
PROFESSOR: It becomes
get the princess.
There's one princess, there's
four knights, and it becomes a
competitive game.
All of a sudden, everything that
you were using against
the baddies becomes
something that
you use on your teammates.
And there are games that
flip-flop between that.
Diplomacy is a really fluid
game in that sense.
You have to assume everybody's
competitive in that game.
But the only way to obtain your
goals is to cooperate
occasionally.
And so you can adapt.
All that's clear cooperation.
No-one's disagreeing on rules.
So that's systemic cooperation
all the way through, but then
there's player competition
and cooperation
going back and forth.
So, that's cooperation.
Finally, think a little bit
about level playing field and
what it means in your games,
whether they're
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
In many of your games,
especially card games, they're
going to start with
some sort of deal.
They're going to start with some
sort of hand, or maybe a
drawing in some sort
of systematic way
from a shuffled deck.
That pretty much means that
you're starting out with
something that's effectively
random.
But then it could be also
influenced by your knowledge
of the game, by your
skill at the game.
And you want to see how--
at what point, how do you want
to balance it between
someone's skill, familiarity
with the game,
against pure chance.
And a level playing field means
different things to a
lot of different people.
For some people, it may mean,
no matter what skill level I
am, I have a chance
at winning.
So you're sort of biasing
towards chance.
For some people a level playing
field is, no matter
what hand I get given, there
is a valid strategy.
Or the goals that get set
in a way that allows
me to obtain it.
A lot of trick-kicking games,
especially games with bidding,
actually have an automatic
ranking system.
In various lives that you
only bid a game that you
think you can win.
And the whole idea is, the game
is to push your opponent
to bid on something which they
couldn't actually get.
So, that's a level
playing field.
I can have a crappy hand, but
that's not chance so much as
the decisions that
you're making.
So, what I would advocate,
in this class, if
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
is, when you're trying to
balance it out towards
whatever your interpretation
of a level playing field is
going to be, try to pick
decisions that push you in the
direction of meaningful
decisions.
Things that players can make a
decision on, and can see the
consequences.
They can understand how
those consequences
play out in the game.
And the outcome of the
overall game is going
to be resolved then.
That is, again, not necessarily
the only
definition.
So I want to be very
very clear.
What I'm asking of you here is
not necessarily the only
definition of a well-designed
game.
Because designing a game to be
played from ages 3 to 90, you
probably want a game where
making a meaningful decision
isn't going to bias the game
to the point where
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] people, or
really smart because that's
just not [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And this particular task.
Try and bias it so that, in that
competitive sense, you
want everyone to feel like they
have a chance of winning.
But I want you to bias your
game towards the--
and whether you win or lose is
going to be based on the
outcome of these decisions.
Clearly understanding the
outcome of the decision that
you make in the game.
Not necessarily just what you
wish , or what you were dealt.
You can still use those
things in your game.
Sometimes it's the whole idea of
the, oh my God, I hope it's
the right card, aargh.
But then there's things
like probability.
There's, how much information
are you giving to the player
about what the probability that
you have the right card
going to be.
Are you letting them look at
the deck ahead of time?
Are you giving them information
about how many of
those cards are in the deck, so
that you can actually make
guesses on-- all right, we
played through half this deck
and we haven't seen any of those
cards yet, that means
the probability of that card
showing up has now gone up.
And now we come to a decision
that you can make.
Do I draw, do I hold--
that sort of thing.
So that's my suggestion
for this class.
I would love to be able to see
those kinds of games come out
of this class.
So that's all the things
that [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
So, actually, before we move
on, does anyone have any
questions regarding that?
One point of administration.
Who here needs to print on
the Gambit printers?
Or who here has access to other
printers that you guys
are fairly confident about using
for your assignment?
You need a printer?
AUDIENCE: No, did you say that
you need a printer or that you
have access.
Because you said both?
PROFESSOR: Oh, right.
So who here needs to use
Gambit printers?
Who absolutely needs to
use Gambit printers.
Because we don't actually have
computers set up for
everybody to log in.
So I would suggest not using any
of the computers in this
lab because [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
lab work on it.
So you've all got access to
printers, that's awesome.
I think you sent out an e-mail
about card stock.
AUDIENCE: That card stock's
actually out of stock.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: I went to order and
I was like, oh, shit.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Is there like a
Staples somewhere near here?
PROFESSOR: Harvard
has a Staples,
downtown has a staples.
AUDIENCE: CopyTech has--
AUDIENCE: I went to CopyTech and
they said they can print
and cut your cards for you.
PROFESSOR: They have a pretty
awesome card printer.
Their cutter is harsh, harsh.
AUDIENCE: What does that mean?
PROFESSOR: Well, first of all,
it's really pointy on the
corners, which is kind of
cool if that's what
you're going for.
But [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Can they round it
or do we have to use--
AUDIENCE: I don't
think they can.
PROFESSOR: They can't.
I have a rounder.
I have a corner punch that, you
have to do it four times
for each card, but--
AUDIENCE: We'll do it.
We can do it.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Just ask me and
you can borrow it.
You may want to do it on some
test cards before you really
get a sense of how it works.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
And I wouldn't suggest
punching more than
one card at a time.
The other thing is, if you're
printing it on a, not like
CopyTech, where they obviously
know what kind of paper works
best with their printers.
If you're printing it on
something like a Laserjet, if
you go to the paper
manufacturer's website, a lot
of them actually specifically
state Laserjet compatible.
And the problem is actually
the width of the card.
There's not the folding
of the paper as it
goes through the printer.
It's whether the toner will
bond to the paper.
Like, does the paper get
hot enough, and open up
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Does the paper get hot
enough for the
toner to actually bind.
And a lot of card stocks
actually don't, because
they're so thick that the heat
doesn't transfer well.
And as a result of that, after
print it looks great when it
comes out and it
starts leaking.
So, that's the problem
with the card stock.
Some card stocks will jam your
printer, but the majority of
the modern Laserjets actually
deal pretty well with that.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: Did you want us to
print on card stock for
Wednesday, or was that
for when it's due?
PROFESSOR: When it's due.
AUDIENCE: OK.
So Wednesday--
PROFESSOR: And in fact, printing
card stock for when
it's due is not necessary.
It is much appreciated.
It was a great thing for you
to do for yourself, if you
want to make copies for your
friends or your team, that you
actually want to
end up playing.
To be perfectly honest,
if you say--
if our printer wasn't working
and all we could do were these
regular white papers, if I also
cut them in the right
shape, so then we could just
play the game, that's fine.
We're not going to take the
weight of your paper and do
the [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the deck first, erm.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Has anyone played,
what was it, High Society
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Yes.
AUDIENCE: Those are awesome.
PROFESSOR: They were like
kids' books, you know?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: If anyone does have
issues printing, before you
jump straight into the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
talk to Jason and I. Jason
usually has room by the TV
lounge, my room is just
down the corridor.
And we might be able to
help you with that.
But in general, if you've got
access to other printers, go
right for it.
Because going through
us is a bottleneck.
Again, not for Wednesday.
For Wednesday just have
something testable so that we
can [UNINTELLIGIBLE] before
the date it's due, try to
print something.
You don't want to wait until the
last minute and you don't
want to suddenly realize that
your paper doesn't work very
well with the printer
at the last minute.
So, today's reading was Bartle
and Chapter 11, I think, of
the [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And in general, both of them are
asking the same question.
Which is, who are you designing
your game for?
On the assumption that
you're not designing
the game for yourself.
Of course, realistically, if
you're going to get a job
making games, the majority of
the games that you're going to
design are not games for
yourself, they're going to be
games for some other
demographic.
And the Bartle paper is a little
bit more influential in
how people think about games,
because it shifted the
question from, what's the age
group, what's the demographic,
what are people out there
who are already buying
games going to want?
And you fit that into, what
sort of things are people
looking for in a game?
He doesn't actually take
it to the next
step, which is where--
I think he wrote that
in the 70s or late
80s, does anyone remember?
AUDIENCE: In the 90s.
AUDIENCE: I think it
was in, like, 1990.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: But a lot
of the ideas come
from the 70s, actually.
Because that's when he
made the first MUD.
RIchard Bartle [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: What exactly
is a MUD?
They never actually
described it.
They just assumed everyone
knew what a MUD was.
PROFESSOR: MUD stands for
Multi-User Dungeon.
Anyone want to describe one?
AUDIENCE: It's like, an online
text-adventure thing, where
everyone's interacting
with the same
text-based dungeon thing.
AUDIENCE: The best way to
describe it is, imagine if WoW
was presented entirely
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I found that kind
of annoying in the text.
He just assumed everyone
knew what a MUD was.
But never actually said,
this is what a MUD is.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
Because the whole sort of,
reading the article, actually
I believe he formatted
that for a forum
post for for community.
So there's an assumption.
But yeah, apologies for that.
Actually, if you're interested--
and here he does
define it right at the bottom.
Which is right at the end
of the article here.
He talks about specifically,
this is what I mean by MUD.
Somewhere in the
footnotes--these text
adventures, text-style online
games where multiple people
are interacting.
And if you look at the rest of
the website, there's actually
a bunch of stuff about
how MUDs work.
But, for the most part, that was
sort of online multiplayer
gaming, back when he started.
He's credited for having
built the first MUD.
And, frankly, not all
that different from
MMOGs you get today.
The difference being that
they were all text.
But you still went out
hunting monsters.
They call them mobiles,
or mobs.
And in fact there's
still some of that
terminology going around.
They drop loot.
You will pick up loot
and show it off.
And sometimes, some games
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
loot.
Most games let you
exchange loot.
And then you would use your
loot to go and kill other
monsters and get better loot.
Sometimes you'd do it
with other people.
Sometimes you attack
other people.
Sometimes you just hang around
and chat and talk about things
that are completely not in game,
like what did I have for
lunch today.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
And sometimes it will
take multiple
people to take a monster.
And it was just handled
on a how fast can you
type kind of thing.
Attack monster, attack
monster.
I think you can just hit repeat
and but, the behaviors
are also not all
that different.
And how he describes it is, a
game will sight itself in a
position where it is variably
appealing to
various kinds of players.
And that's how he
described it.
Where game studies has kind of
gone on to since then, is the
realization that just
because you're--
some people through all the
four types that you--
AUDIENCE: Explorer.
Killer.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: So, there are these
four types of players.
And just because you're an
achiever in one game doesn't
necessarily mean that you're
going to be an achiever in
another game.
Different people play different
games, or possibly
even different types
of the same game,
for different reasons.
And that's where we go back to
earlier concepts that we
brought up, is [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
kinds of fun.
What are people trying to get
out of their game playing?
So, but he was--
if you're looking at the content
of any one of MUD, and
a little slice of what you saw
of somebody's personality,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and all the things that
they were doing.
And the kinds of things that you
tended to keep doing every
time you logged in, it was very
easy to stereotype them
into somewhere along
those lines.
Even he acknowledges that
nobody's really all the way on
one of these layers.
Griefers, I think, are the words
that I hear generally
used for killers nowadays.
But even then, that's
not quite the way
that he's using it.
He's actually using it as
somebody who's generally still
playing by the rules
of the game.
They are there to cause misery
to other people, but they're
not there to break the game.
There is a class of people
called griefers, who are
deliberately trying to find ways
to exploit the system, to
just make the game just
kind of silly.
But all the other dynamics
that he draws on
are very much there.
You get a whole bunch of
socializers together.
People who want to do nothing
but chat and have a good time,
they don't really care about the
game, and there's going to
be a whole bunch of people going
right after them, saying
these are great people
to grief.
Because they are enjoying
themselves so much.
We could end that.
Second Life gets a lot of this,
because Second Life has
that whole, you can do
anything you want.
And socializing is one
of the big things.
Personalizing is one
So, do keep in mind that the
way that he's talking about
it, sounds like all of these
different personalities are
somewhat mutually exclusive when
really the discussion has
now come to, how do you cater
to all of these different
desires at any given time?
I may be an achiever today, I
may be an explorer tomorrow.
And he even talks about
explorers thinking that
achievers are beginner
explorers, because it's like,
once you've already beaten the
game, what else is there left
to do but explore what
else you can do?
So he himself acknowledges that
there's some personality
transfer that can happen.
But it's kind of interesting
how he talks about the
feedback loops of people.
You'll get a whole bunch of
achievers, and you get a whole
bunch of socializers.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
killers, and achievers--
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
you've got the competition
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
But he also makes this weird
assumption that there is a
finite pool of people who are
going to be playing the game.
Which is actually true, even in
a 10-20 million player game
like in World of Warcraft.
All those things have to be--
we don't have 20 million people
logging onto one server.
They say, I have
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
or something.
AUDIENCE: Exactly, exactly.
AUDIENCE: And I'm like,
once [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
you can start [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
that are just really
big numbers.
Like, 25-- it's currently
25 is the highest.
They used to go to 40.
But yeah, and you just
kill bigger monsters
and get lots of loot.
And then there's PvP,
which you go--
the main thing right
now is arenas.
And you have the team of two
or three or five, and you
fight other players with your
gear by doing battlegrounds
and [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
arena.
And it's basically, WoW.
PROFESSOR: I can't remember.
Are there role-playing
servers?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
There are role-playing
servers.
I have actually never visited
one, so I can't really talk
about that.
AUDIENCE: That's a
lot of dancing.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
slash dance, maybe, or your
character dances.
And it was those things that
really is popular among
socialized type players
all over--
and Diablo.
But it's not just
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I mean, slash dance means
other things now.
It could mean I'm bored.
It's like, I have nothing to do
right now, I have to wait
for this stupid thing to
respawn, slash dance.
It's more fun than just
standing there.
But there is a group in WoW.
And I guess--
maybe not a group.
There are folks who play World
of Warcraft and they engage
you to think on theory crafts.
Which is, how we optimize the
way how you build a character.
And the things that you equip a
character for, to make that
character really, really
good at doing one or
two different things.
So as you're building up a
character that's designed to
heal, what class should they be,
what race should they be,
what equipment should they be
getting, depending on what
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] you
are in the game.
And they're going to try to
derive as much of the math of
the cause and effect in the
game as they possibly can.
There is actually
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
which is--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
It's actually kind of funny.
The Elitist Jerks' forums had
one guy who just happened to
write a forum post about
dressing up in real life.
Like, this is how you get really
nice [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
because he worked at a
men's fashion place.
And it it turned out that that
community was really, really,
really interested in learning
more about that.
Which is actually not
all that weird.
It's like, you care about what
armor you get in the game.
You care about what you
wear in real life.
Especially if it might have some
impact on your real life.
What job that you're
looking for.
OK, you know.
So, I would actually put
those more in the
explorers part of things.
Sure, they're looking
to optimize.
They're looking to
do their best.
But they're not looking to be
necessarily rewarded by the
game system.
They're using the game system
to test their ideas against.
It's like, I'm looking for a
better way to suck up more
damage, because I'm a tank.
I'm supposed to be absorbing
all the damage.
Or the other as they call it.
Or the attentions of the
characters being controlled by
the computer, while the rest of
my folks put out a lot of
damage, can do their job.
But I am not interested in what
the system has deemed to
be, you have absorbed tons
of damage, good job.
I don't care what
the system says.
I care how the system operates,
so that I could
optimize it through some sort
of metric that I've figured
out and my friends have figured
out and the community
has figured out.
So I want to understand
the system.
Again, that's what
it comes down to.
The metric that they're using
is, how do I optimize it.
But for the most part, people
who engage in that kind of
theory craft, it's like about
this armor combined with those
pants, I've proven something,
those are well in the area of
explorers even though their
behavior seems very much,
that's the best solution.
Whereas achievers are very much
focused on, how do I get
to level-- it's like, how do
I get the coolest mount.
In World of Warcraft you can
ride around and every once in
a while, Blizzard, the company
that makes it, will release
some new stuff.
And the achievers will say,
I've got to get that.
Because the space
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
it takes a lot of effort and a
lot of money to be able to get
one of those things.
But to be able to get it,
it gives you some
recognizable status.
You will see someone with
the limited edition of
some kind of mount.
And you'll know that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] is to spend a
heck of a lot of time in this
game and play the game really
well, that's the kind
of recognition
they're looking for.
So that's the difference
between
achievers and explorers.
So I want to try one
little activity.
Which is, I've got the chart
that Bartle lays out.
The whole player versus--
interacting and acting,
player and the world.
And he uses this to describe
where your game could be at
any given time.
If you're acting on players
that your game's biased
towards killers.
If you're designing your game
to be more about interacting
with other players, then you're
somewhat biasing it
towards socializers.
Interacting with the world is
more for the achievers.
Acting on the world is more
for the achievers.
Given these quests, I've
beaten all the quests.
I have 100% of the
quests complete.
That's achievers.
And interacting with the world
is more of the explorers.
It's like, what else can
you do in this world?
There are these goals that
are set, that's great.
But how does this world work
that I can do cool stuff.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
distinction between acting and
interacting, incredibly
[UNINTELLIGIBLE], I didn't
really understand what
he was trying to say.
PROFESSOR: It was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I think he came across
those terms because
they sounded cute.
Acting, interacting,
is like a--
AUDIENCE: I mean, can you
interact without action?
PROFESSOR: Well,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: What does that mean?
And, like, the really classic
example he gives.
Like, the acting on a play is
like a pure [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the other player fights back.
There's an interaction there.
PROFESSOR: Sure.
But the thing about it--
AUDIENCE: But the difference
there--
PROFESSOR: So I believe what he
means by that is that the
killer is actually less
interested in what the player
does back to him.
In some sense, they are
interacting because they're
trying to see what sort
of response they get.
It's like, I'm going to do
something to this player.
This player's either going to
die, or fight back, or whine
about the fact that I'm
hitting him so much.
But they're not looking for
the competitive bit.
They're not really interested in
the, and now that person's
going to turn around
and attack me.
AUDIENCE: I know, but the whole
point is supposed to be
that killers are griefers, so
they really care about how
people respond to them.
He says later on that one of the
most annoying things you
can do to a griefer is
just ignore them and
not rise to the bait.
So interacting seems to
be the crucial thing.
Again, I feel like his--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I kind of see it as,
does the person care about how
the other works, in a sense?
And so it is the case that
a griefer wants to
get a certain reaction.
But beyond that it
doesn't matter.
So in the same case within the
game system, I want it to do
this thing, I want it to give me
points but why it did that
or how the mechanic works
is kind of irrelevant.
And that's how I
understood it.
AUDIENCE: Well, in particular,
with the interacting, when
somebody is like trying to
player kill or something, the
reaction is not necessarily--
the reaction they're looking
for is to piss somebody
off, right?
And that reaction is not
necessarily part of the game.
So, it is acting on them because
you are taking what
the game allows you to do, and
using this against a person.
But you don't care about
what they use in the
game against you.
You more care about this
abstract idea.
So I think the interaction is
not actually part of the game.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
specifically to do with game
mechanics, whereas interacting
is to do with something
which is--
so maybe acting is something
mechanical, whereas
interacting is something
dynamics-related?
Or?
AUDIENCE: Well, I see is as
like, acting is sort of like a
single direction
with mechanics.
So, for example, the mechanic
there is being able to hit
somebody in the head with
your [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Whereas interacting would be the
case where you are hitting
each other on each others'
heads with your swords.
Which is an entirely
different thing.
And it's more of a competitive
thing rather than the, I just
want to make you angry.
AUDIENCE: I think the
unidirectional perspective
makes sense.
You could think of it
as going with the
hitting on the head example.
If I'm acting, then I care
that information
is flowing one way.
I am dealing damage to you.
If I'm interacting, I'm curious
as to how that is
computed and what that means
for me in return.
Does that make sense?
AUDIENCE: So like, if I'm really
bad at terminology--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: A bunch of other
examples of things that you do
to maximize interacting
versus acting.
There might be interesting
examples of things like make
super [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And then the acting ones are
like, make [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: So, in the context
of a MUD, a puzzle is often
like a door.
So you've got to solve this
puzzle if you want to get into
a new area.
Because that's really
the only thing--
sometimes you get your loot.
And the idea behind that is, you
are either privileging it
to getting people to talk with
each other more and socialize
with each other more.
Or you're privileging it to
getting people to look at the
world more, see more
of the world and
understand how it works.
Then in a sense, you don't want
to put too many barriers
between the people who've been
in for a very long time and
the people who just started
playing, the people who are in
one area of the world
and people in
another area of the world.
You kind of want quick flow.
So in MUDs, that's one thing
where the definition of
puzzles is very specific.
It's like, but I have to move
this set of levers.
AUDIENCE: Another point that
I've found that's really
strange, because I would expect
an explorer, who is
supposed to be a world
interacting person to really
enjoy deep puzzles, which reward
them for knowing more
about the world.
PROFESSOR: But a problem with
puzzles in MUDs is that
they're usually simple
solutions.
So there's less pleasure to be
found in a very difficult
puzzle, because all that
told you was, you just
solved this one thing.
There is still some
pleasure there.
The interest that explorers are
way more compelled by--
kind of the latent dynamics--
is understanding the interaction
of how mechanics--
especially [UNINTELLIGIBLE] in a
way that might not have been
originally designed that way.
That's what they're
looking for.
They're not looking for, what
is the solution that was
designed in the game.
They're looking for, how am I
going to get this game to do
something that it might not
have been designed to do
originally, but would be cool
once I figure it out.
So that, unfortunately--
you are definitely right.
But that one suffers from the
very specific terminology of
what a puzzle is in a MUD, as
opposed to the more general
definition of what
a puzzle is.
The reason why, at least for
achievers, hard puzzles are
very important, because if you
make a puzzle that most people
aren't going to be able to get,
being able to get that
puzzle gives you some
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] status.
Usually some sort of visible
reward, even.
You are now in a location not
everybody else can get to, or
you now have a piece
of equipment
that no-one else has.
Whereas explorers, they will
probably have an advantage in
solving difficult puzzles.
But they're not necessarily the
sort of thing that makes
them want to interact
with the world.
Lots of the mechanics that
interact with each other in
and new and interesting ways,
are more likely to be
interesting to an explorer.
But you're right, acting and
interacting are crappy, crappy
terminology sort of thing.
AUDIENCE: Are you talking about
how griefers are more
like actors, where they just try
to get people to interact
with them, or try to get people
to get annoyed by them.
I've definitely seen,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
game design.
But [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
300.
Where we watched a video of
griefers in Team Fortress 2,
where there's a certain door
where, if they stand in a
certain spot, it won't open.
So this person started making
everyone interact.
OK, we're going to play
a game today.
If you want to leave, you have
to answer correctly.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, what
is the capital of--
AUDIENCE: That I see as more
of an explorer things.
Like, you bounce some weird
combination of the interaction
with the mechanics that allows
you to do something new, which
is turn Team Fortress
2 into a game show.
AUDIENCE: It was pretty funny.
AUDIENCE: But people
who can't play.
AUDIENCE: Griefers and explorers
are a combination of
bottle types, if you're going
to be a successful griefer.
PROFESSOR: And that's
absolutely true.
If your personality's oriented
one way, you may have to
engage with some other behaviors
in order to be able
to maximize that core behavior
they're looking for.
So there are people who are
looking at exploits and trying
to understand how the world
works so they can cause
maximum damage and maximum
grief to other people.
That's definitely one good
way of doing it.
But what I find is that as soon
as they find it, they are
not interested in finding
more ways until that
first way gets boring.
Or gets fixed.
So, people are going to say,
there's a lot of teleporting
you directly in front of a
turret, stuff like that.
Teleporting your own teammates
in front of a turret, that
sort of thing.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: I don't understand.
PROFESSOR: You don't
understand?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
PROFESSOR: It's fun.
AUDIENCE: Griefers.
AUDIENCE: No, it's not.
AUDIENCE: So, I'm going
to mess with you.
Just for the hell of it.
AUDIENCE: I remember in Sims
Online, an effective way to
grief would be to organize a
band of people and arrive on
that property.
Since there was a population
limit of 12 people or
something on any given lot.
In that lot, was a business that
required a lot of people
to come through.
And then you just had
12 of your people
show up and mill around.
And say a lot of profanities.
You could tag the place and
lock it up and no-one else
could go there and visit it,
sometimes including owners and
stuff like that.
It was very frustrating.
PROFESSOR: In fact, some of
the behavior they did got
towards organized crime level.
Actually, I mean it wasn't real
crime, it was virtual.
But there are actually a good
number of articles about the
Sims Online mafia.
Because that game had so
much built in for--
actually for socializers--
to be able to communicate,
express themselves.
I mean if you played the
original Sims, there's a whole
range of different expressive
things that you can do to
communicate how you're feeling
and to be able
to chat with people.
And someone, I think it might
have been Maxis itself,
actually charted out the web of
influence of all the players.
And there was one alpha player
who was in charge of
everything.
And if she decided that this
person wasn't wanted, she
didn't want, spending too much
time [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
because of how it pissed her off
or piss one of her friends
off or something, she'd organize
something like that.
Effectively.
It was called the Sims mafia.
and you get that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
And it's kind of interesting
to see how different worlds
respond to that.
Even though in [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
which is--
actually, one thing I'd like
to do is, I'd like to throw
different games up
on that chart.
So I am looking mostly
at multiplayer games.
Preferably online multiplayer
games.
But, and I don't know all the
games that are out there.
So, I'd like people
to call-out games.
And tell me roughly what
I should put up.
If you disagree, then by all
means put up your hand and
suggest that it should
be moved.
AUDIENCE: Minecraft should go
definitely toward world
interaction andexplorer type.
AUDIENCE: Like, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
far, far.
AUDIENCE: So what
is Minecraft?
I've heard of it, I just don't
know what exactly it's about.
AUDIENCE: You basically go
around mining things and
creating objects, and you can
create your own worlds.
AUDIENCE: So it's like--
I guess?
AUDIENCE: EVE is definitely
world interacting as well.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So that's
same as EVE.
AUDIENCE: I would say EVE
is also player to player
interacting.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I'd see it as
in the middle, then.
AUDIENCE: In EVE you have to
form corporations with bunches
of people in order
to do anything.
PROFESSOR: That's true.
You have to be really good in
your social skills, actually.
It's one of the games that's
most ruthlessly
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: If you interact
with the people
and the world a lot.
AUDIENCE: I think it's more
strongly player attracting and
is world attracting
than most games.
PROFESSOR: You cannot
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: But there's also a
huge amount of achievement and
player versus player conflict
in this kind of stuff.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: You can die far down
the interacting scale.
I mean, consider things in
Second Life instead.
Which would be way further down
the interacting end of
the spectrum than EVE
Online, surely.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Assuming that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I'm not sure
it's hacking.
Like, PvP is the opposite
of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I mean it's not--
AUDIENCE: I think it's
definitely player interaction
more than player action.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I believe
it's interaction.
AUDIENCE: Something like having
PvP tournaments, I
think, would be definitely
a lot of interaction.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
I think that's the distinction
between griefing and like
people fighting each other.
AUDIENCE: Griefing can be
an [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: What I got from this
article is that acting is
like, I go and kill someone
and ha, I killed
them and that's it.
Or I go through the world, it's
like, I killed a monster,
I killed a monster.
And you just have a goal.
If you want to get the
goal instead of
diverting from your goal.
So, I don't know.
I definitely think griefing
can be hugely interactive.
But there could be a
whole bunch of--
in EVE if you infiltrate
someone's company and you--
AUDIENCE: Steal ten thousand
dollars' worth of their money.
AUDIENCE: Exactly.
That's hugely interactive
griefing.
AUDIENCE: I don't think
that's griefing.
AUDIENCE: Consider Team
Fortress, right.
There's Team Fortress
player interaction.
Because that means it's
a socializer game.
PROFESSOR: I personally do not
think Team Fortress falls
under player interacting
with team.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: But Left
for Dead is.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: There's definitely
interaction happening--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I'd say probably
more-- it depends on what
you're doing
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: So with Left for Dead
you can play-- you're
interacting, but then you're
also online and you can go
against other players
who are actually the
zombies, against you.
PROFESSOR: Right.
So let's talk about the basic
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: So the basic, most
common mode is going to be
four players playing
cooperatively
against the game world.
AUDIENCE: That's just
interacting with the world.
AUDIENCE: And there is a lot
of interaction that goes on
between players, because you
cannot basically survive
unless you get each
others' backs.
AUDIENCE: So I would
say it's--
AUDIENCE: And there's
built-in functions
to help other people.
So someone might get back up
on a ledge and he'll be
holding on and you have
to pull him back up.
AUDIENCE: Or smokers.
AUDIENCE: At the same time,
there's also an intelligent
engine that plans that level
for you and places zombies
specifically to maintain you
in a state of nervousness.
And so it's different every
single time you play.
So those balance out and
probably place it somewhere in
the middle.
Maybe a little bit more player
biased than world biased,
because you really have
to stick together.
PROFESSOR: So, it's weird
because it's almost like, you
want to have like a plane.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I think the big
problem with this sort of
graph is that you can't really
necessarily separate games
into one of these quadrants.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: And that
is actually also--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It might be a little
more useful to actually draw
areas within the graph to
represent a game, I guess.
Draw the area that encompasses
all the pieces the game
represents.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Like Halo co-op and
Halo multiplayer, and player
versus player.
That will probably be a little
refinement, if I create some
sort of scatter chart
or Venn diagram.
AUDIENCE: Because I could
definitely see there being a
game where there's a lot of
acting on the world and
interacting with players.
And if you're just separating
these into distinct points,
that isn't possible
with this graph.
PROFESSOR: So that's another
problem, is the assumption
that acting and interacting
are--
AUDIENCE: Mutually exclusive?
PROFESSOR: They're mutually
opposite.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Do people generally
accept this?
AUDIENCE: No, no.
They do less acting
than interacting.
AUDIENCE: If you just warp
space, then you can have
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I think if you had
different values for player
world interacting
and acting would
necessarily be connected.
I think EVE definitely in world
is very high, and in
player is very high.
PROFESSOR: World very high,
player very high.
But I mean, player is
interacting and world is
acting on the world.
AUDIENCE: On the world still.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: I mean, because--
you're exploring the world
spatially a lot.
Are you exploring the systems
of the world a lot?
Or are you really exploring the
systems set up by people?
AUDIENCE: That's true.
PROFESSOR: The nice thing about
things like EVE Online--
also [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
EVE Online [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
game basically, where you
start off as a captain.
Correct me if I'm
wrong with this.
AUDIENCE: It's a super-sandbox
game.
PROFESSOR: But for the
most part, you're
traveling in space.
AUDIENCE: Can you get out of
your ship and walk on foot?
AUDIENCE: Have they added that,
because I know they
wanted to add an expansion where
you could actually walk
on planets.
Last time I heard,
they hadn't.
AUDIENCE: Last I heard
AUDIENCE: Dust 66 or something
like that.
PROFESSOR:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
AUDIENCE: It's a
separate game.
PROFESSOR: No, you're traveling
through space.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
But the whole idea is that it's
all built around this
economy, where [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
mining,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
cash.
But the real power in the game
comes when players start to
ally with each other.
Form armadas, form
trade groups.
Form areas that you can
patrol and control.
And areas where you want to
agree that if you don't get
along with the people who are in
control of this space, you
will die when you
fly in there.
And the only thing that's making
that happen are other
players deciding that this
social contract is
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So it's pretty damn amazing.
What some folks were talking
about earlier was a big story
about how, basically, one person
got into a very, very
powerful position in
one of these clans.
And decided to defect.
Take a majority of one clan's
financial resources with him.
And-- remember, this is a
fairly modern massive
multiplayer online game.
In-game assets can now be
traded for real money.
AUDIENCE: It's illegal
so that--
PROFESSOR: It's illegal.
AUDIENCE: Like, in-game.
So you can get your
account banned.
So what happened, if I'm talking
about the one that
you're talking about.
Someone got to a really
powerful place in
this banking clan.
And then took all of
their assets and
traded it for real money.
So he got $10,000 by
selling it off.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: One was a guy who
infiltrated the clan
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] that
much money.
One was like a parent who was
going into financial trouble
and held a fifth of the assets
of the major bank, and cashed
it in for $6,000 to help pay off
part of his house and his
kids' medical bills.
And then posted an apology on
the board and quit the game.
AUDIENCE: I thought he got
banned from the game.
AUDIENCE: He was banned
from the game, but he
also quit the game.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: He was like, I'm
sorry, everybody, but this is
kind of important.
AUDIENCE: The amazing one
was the guy who actually
infiltrated the company and
just took it down as a
years-long operation--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
thought he was a
friend and all that.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Trying to get in and then
managed to take down this
gigantic in-game corporation.
AUDIENCE: How many active
players are
there on EVE Online?
A hundred thousand?
AUDIENCE: No.
I feel like the active
players are--
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: At any moment?
PROFESSOR: No, I mean active
current players who have
active accounts.
AUDIENCE: Do they
have new players
arriving regularly, or--
AUDIENCE: Occasionally.
AUDIENCE: They don't have
a game that's been--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It's like
a ridiculous
learning curve, yeah.
AUDIENCE: It's like four
months or something.
It's insane.
PROFESSOR: But the interesting
thing about the particular
case where someone infiltrated,
took all the
money and basically decimated
this clan deliberately, was
that that person
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: The most recent
one that I read about,
theoretically had in the tens of
thousands of US dollars of
assets in the game and did not
cash in any of it for real
money because there is no
authorized mechanism.
And the article that I read,
basically, the end note was,
no-one knows what he
can do with it.
He's technically rich but
there's no legal mechanism
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I don't think he got banned
at all because--
PROFESSOR: Its part
of the game.
At least for the definition
of EVE.
Stories like that tend
to have earned its
reputation in a way.
This is lawless in space.
We're trying to encourage this
kind of player to player.
And [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
So I'm not entirely sure
if [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
griefing.
It was an incredibly
smart tactical--
AUDIENCE: See, I would not
call that griefing.
It may have been done to annoy
the people who were running
the company that he took down.
But see it as exploration.
I'm going to try and--
it's [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
player interaction.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I started a major
corporation all by myself.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, might
actually be--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Do you put that
on your resume?
Single-handedly [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
been hired by a lawyer.
PROFESSOR: So, what
I would actually
like to end this with--
we've got about 15 minutes.
Is to spend some time--
I would say, how many
of you have we got?
One, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, 10,
11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.
So, groups of four.
And what I'd like
folks to do--
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] --
I'd like folks to come
up with other axes.
Not necessarily anything
having to do with
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Give me two things that you feel
are diametrically opposed
but in describing a game,
or any series of games.
You can place games
on other sub-axes.
If we have time, we can talk
about an attitude difference.
But something to help describe
two people, OK, this game is
on the hard extreme of one,
this game's on the hard
extreme of the other.
The goal here is to come up with
terms that will help you
identify who this game might
be target towards.
What kind of player might
this game be targeting?
Not necessarily using Bartle's
terminology at all.
Bartle's terminology, as we have
said, is kind of weak, so
let's throw out some
other words to
describe games already.
If that fails, because you
haven't really thought about
it, to come up with
some new words.
Real game-ish words.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Random versus
strategy.
PROFESSOR: Oh, very good.
AUDIENCE: Original
versus copy.
PROFESSOR:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
I'd rather use more chance or
random to get the point across
pretty clearly.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Right.
So I think that axis should be
random, deterministic and/or
reactive and deliberative.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: It's fancy.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Say that one again?
AUDIENCE: Reactive.
AUDIENCE: So reactive
and delibrative.
AUDIENCE: Reactive
and deliberative.
AUDIENCE: Or random
and deterministic.
AUDIENCE: So you can definitely
still have
randomness and have strategy.
AUDIENCE: Right.
AUDIENCE: But random
and deterministic.
AUDIENCE: They would be
somewhere on the axis, right?
AUDIENCE: So the problem is, you
can have incredible amount
of randomness but if you
can just figure out the
probabilities, you
can still have an
optimum strategy, right?
AUDIENCE: But then that's
less random.
PROFESSOR: In doing this, you
can't have a system that is so
complex yet deterministic that
there's no way you can predict
what's going to happen next.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Killer robot.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: It's theoretically
possible, but this is--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Player versus
system agency?
PROFESSOR: Player versus--
also system--
player versus system agency
is kind of your--
AUDIENCE: It's distributed.
PROFESSOR: It's the name
of your tactics, right?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: You also had a low
learning curve versus high
learning curve.
You're definitely not on both
ends of that, and--
AUDIENCE: Fast versus slow.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: I like that idea.
Fast versus slow.
AUDIENCE: So, another axis you
may have was you could call it
freedom and predetermined
paths in the game.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Huh?
AUDIENCE: Freedom versus
constraint.
AUDIENCE: I can't remember the
terms, but ludus and pitheus,
something like that.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So one more that
I use here often,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: 13 hours
of Final Fantasy--
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: For 60 hours.
PROFESSOR: Sandbox, I would
say, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
is a very broad one.
It's one that people generally
understand as embodying a sort
of freedom.
You get to dick around,
basically.
You get to play Grand Theft
Auto totally not
following the storyline.
And-- actually, it kind of goes
on, it becomes a little
bit less of that, you can get
to do , you get to play but
the whole idea is that that
world has ramps everywhere, so
that you can drive cars and
vehicles [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Anything else?
AUDIENCE: There's realism
versus attraction.
AUDIENCE: Oooh.
AUDIENCE: What?
AUDIENCE: So the difference
between EVE Online, for
example, which is supposed
to be very
realistic, simulating something.
Whereas poker, for example,
is just cards and numbers.
AUDIENCE: Something on the
freedom sandbox versus
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] on rails,
there's a very interesting
thing in [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
there's a feature in one of the
games where you were told
you need X amount of money to
be able to pay for the ship
out of here.
And you're placed in a sort
of sandbox environment.
And you're given--
you're not told, but--
whatever ways you can think of
to make that amount of money.
The amount of money
you need to leave
that part of the game.
So it's a predetermined
sandbox .
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
a lot of adventure games, a lot
of roleplaying games, are
largely [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
areas of freedom.
Even in a game like Final
Fantasy, it is not something
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] in other games
in the series, the story
is largely predetermined.
But what you do in combat
is very, very fluid.
And that's kind of like
the dichotomy that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Square Enix, or Square in
the past, have decided
that that was OK.
This helps us cater to people
who want some flexibility in
how they're going to play, by
making the combat system fluid
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
they want.
But also lets us cater to people
who really want that
long, over-arching,
epic narrative.
And we can only pick one.
We can't branch
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
Are there others?
AUDIENCE: I mean,
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
a lot of [UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
puzzle games there's only one
way to do it, whereas
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: I mean, you
could have multiple
solutions, I guess.
AUDIENCE: Multiple and single.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: I'm not so sure
if that tells you
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
if I tell you something about
the constraints on
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] budget of--
AUDIENCE: I prefer games
that are much more
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
And I guess it goes back
to [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Because the
interesting thing about
multiple solutions and single
solutions is that multiple
solutions-- it could
be all design.
I could design in the game-- in
fact, now, if you play Deus
Ex, or any of the sequels, they
specifically stated that
they made this game with
multiple solutions in mind.
And with the data sets to, they
designed it so that they
thought, this puzzle needs
to have three solutions.
And they actually will design
an environment for it.
So, while the game kind of tells
us, you get to play with
the system, you get to figure
out how all these things
combine and come up with
solutions on your own.
Really, they tried to design it
so that you have three very
clear options at
any given time.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
And so you can have multiple
solutions.
Whereas this is like freedom
sandboxing, kind of applies
not necessarily to design.
You've got lots of little things
that you can do and
lots of different spaces that
you can explore and design.
It's not like you've got one
obstacle and three different
ways to solve it.
You've got all kinds of
different things that you
could be doing.
You could be like
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
So these are different axes.
I just want to point out that
these are different ways of
doing different things.
AUDIENCE: You can have, in terms
of rule changing games,
whether it's dynamic rules
or static rules.
AUDIENCE: Hmm.
So, hyper-dynamic, static,
and then [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Are the rule going to
change if [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: There are some games
where the whole point is
changing rules.
AUDIENCE: Like Flux.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: And assuming basically
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Timescale
of decisions.
PROFESSOR: So, short model?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, like twitch
games versus thought games.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
decisions.
Sort of like that are
contemplative and reactive.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: Are you guys going
for basically the same thing.
Like, reactive means things are
coming at you and you have
to respond really,
really quickly.
Maybe [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
about it.
And deliberative is like
a trivia game.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Doesn't necessarily
mean that.
The kind of turn-based game
is very fast-paced.
Because the weight of any given
decision is not going to
be so deep.
So, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I'm just going to put this up
here because I'm running out
of space [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
that's one way of describing
a game, reactive versus
deliberative.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
I bet you could take two of
these and put them on an axis
and then we could
talk about them.
On a [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
but every once in a while
we find a game that
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Which is fine.
Which is part of
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] to talk about
these games.
These are really, really
useful terms.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
it's a little bit more boxing,
it's a little bit more
restrictive than
predetermined.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
sandbox and rails are more like
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]