So that's the i j entry.
Right there is C i j.
We always write the row number
and then the column number.
So I might -- I might -- maybe
I take it C 3 4,
just to make it specific.
So instead of i j,
let me use numbers.
C 3 4.
So where does that come from,
the three four entry?
It comes from row three,
here, row three and column
four, as you know.
Column four.
And can I just write down,
or can we write down the
formula for it?
If we look at the whole row and
the whole column,
the quick way for me to say it
is row three of A -- I could use
a dot for dot product.
I won't often use that,
actually.
Dot column four of B.
But this gives us a chance to
just, like, use a little matrix
notation.
What are the entries?
What's this first entry in row
three?
That number that's sitting
right there is...
A, so it's got two indices and
what are they?
3 1.
So there's an a 3 1 there.
Now what's the first guy at the
top of column four?
So what's sitting up there?
B 1 4, right.
So that this dot product starts
with A 3 1 times B 1 4.
And then what's the next -- so
this is like I'm accumulating
this sum, then comes the next
guy, A 3 2, second column,
times B 2 4,
second row.
So it's b A 3 2,
B 2 4 and so on.
Just practice with indices.
Oh, let me even practice with a
summation formula.
So this is -- most of the
course, I use whole vectors.
I very seldom,
get down to the details of
these particular entries,
but here we'd better do it.
So it's some kind of a sum,
right?
Of things in row three,
column K shall I say?
Times things in row K,
column four.
Do you see that that's what
we're seeing here?
This is K is one,
here K is two,
on along -- so the sum goes all
the way along the row and down
the column, say,
one to N.
So that's what the C three four
entry looks like.
A sum of a three K b K four.
Just takes a little practice to
do that.
Okay.
And -- well,
maybe I should say -- when are
we allowed to multiply these
matrices?
What are the shapes of these
things?
The shapes are -- if we allow
them to be not necessarily
square matrices.
If they're square,
they've got to be the same
size.
If they're rectangular,
they're not the same size.
this might be -- well,
I always think of A as m by n.
m rows, n columns.
So that sum goes to n.
Now what's the point -- how
many rows does B have to have?
n.
The number of rows in B,
the number of guys that we meet
coming down has to match the
number of ones across.
So B will have to be n by
something.
Whatever.
P.
So the number of columns here
has to match the number of rows
there, and then what's the
result?
What's the shape of the result?
What's the shape of C,
the output?
Well, it's got these same m
rows -- it's got m rows.
And how many columns?
P.
m by P.
Okay.
So there are m times P little
numbers in there,
entries, and each one,
looks like that.
Okay.
So that's the standard rule.
That's the way people think of
multiplying matrices.
I do it too.
But I want to talk about other
ways to look at that same
calculation, looking at whole
columns and whole rows.
Okay.
So can I do A B C again?
A B equaling C again?
But now, tell me about...
I'll put it up here.
So here goes A,
again, times B producing C.
And again, this is m by n.
This is n by P and this is m by
P.
Okay.
Now I want to look at whole
columns.
I want to look at the columns
of -- here's the second way to
multiply matrices.
Because I'm going to build on
what I know already.
How do I multiply a matrix by a
column?
I know how to multiply this
matrix by that column.
Shall I call that column one?
That tells me column one of the
answer.
The matrix times the first
column is that first column.
Because none of this stuff
entered that part of the answer.
The matrix times the second
column is the second column of
the answer.
Do you see what I'm saying?
That I could think of
multiplying a matrix by a
vector, which I already knew how
to do, and I can think of just P
columns sitting side by side,
just like resting next to each
other.
And I multiply A times each one
of those.
And I get the P columns of the
answer.
Do you see this as -- this is
quite nice, to be able to think,
okay, matrix multiplication
works so that I can just think
of having several columns,
multiplying by A and getting
the columns of the answer.
So, like, here's column one
shall I call that column one?
And what's going in there is A
times column one.
Okay.
So that's the picture a column
at a time.
So what does that tell me?
What does that tell me about
these columns?
These columns of C are
combinations,
because we've seen that before,
of columns of A.
Every one of these comes from A
times this, and A times a vector
is a combination of the columns
of A.
And it makes sense,
because the columns of A have
length m and the columns of C
have length m.
And every column of C is some
combination of the columns of A.
And it's these numbers in here
that tell me what combination it
is.
Do you see that?
That in that answer,
C, I'm seeing stuff that's
combinations of these columns.
Now, suppose I look at it --
that's two ways now.
The third way is look at it by
rows.
So now let me change to rows.
Okay.
So now I can think of a row of
A -- a row of A multiplying all
these rows here and producing a
row of the product.
So this row takes a combination
of these rows and that's the
answer.
So these rows of C are
combinations of what?
Tell me how to finish that.
The rows of C,
when I have a matrix B,
it's got its rows and I
multiply by A,
and what does that do?
It mixes the rows up.
It creates combinations of the
rows of B, thanks.
Rows of B.
That's what I wanted to see,
that this answer --
I can see where the pieces are
coming from.
The rows in the answer are
coming as combinations of these
rows.
The columns in the answer are
coming as combinations of those
columns.
And so that's three ways.
Now you can say,
okay, what's the fourth way?
The fourth way -- so that's --
now we've got,
like, the regular way,
the column way,
the row way and -- what's left?
The one that I can -- well,
one way is columns times rows.
What happens if I multiply --
So this was row times column,
it gave a number.
Okay.
Now I want to ask you about
column times row.
If I multiply a column of A
times a row of B,
what shape I ending up with?
So if I take a column times a
row, that's definitely different
from taking a row times a
column.
So a column of A was -- what's
the shape of a column of A?
n by one.
A column of A is a column.
It's got m entries and one
column.
And what's a row of B?
It's got one row and P columns.
So what's the shape --
what do I get if I multiply a
column by a row?
I get a big matrix.
I get a full-sized matrix.
If I multiply a column by a row
-- should we just do one?
Let me take the column two
three four times the row one
six.
That product there --
I mean, when I'm just following
the rules of matrix
multiplication,
those rules are just looking
like -- kind of petite,
kind of small,
because the rows here are so
short and the columns there are
so short, but they're the same
length, one entry.
So what's the answer?
What's the answer if I do two
three four times one six,
just for practice?
Well, what's the first row of
the answer?
Two twelve.
And the second row of the
answer is three eighteen.
And the third row of the answer
is four twenty four.
That's a very special matrix,
there.
Very special matrix.
What can you tell me about its
columns, the columns of that
matrix?
They're multiples of this guy,
right?
They're multiples of that one.
Which follows our rule.
We said that the columns of the
answer were combinations,
but there's only -- to take a
combination of one guy,
it's just a multiple.
The rows of the answer,
what can you tell me about
those three rows?
They're all multiples of this
row.
They're all multiples of one
six, as we expected.
But I'm getting a full-sized
matrix.
And now, just to complete this
thought, if I have -- let me
write down the fourth way.
A B is a sum of columns of A
times rows of B.
So that, for example,
if my matrix was two three four
and then had another column,
say, seven eight nine,
and my matrix here has -- say,
started with one six and then
had another column like zero
zero, then -- here's the fourth
way, okay?
I've got two columns there,
I've got two rows there.
So the beautiful rule is --
see, the whole thing by columns
and rows is that I can take the
first column times the first row
and add the second column times
the second row.
So that's the fourth way --
that I can take columns times
rows, first column times first
row, second column times second
row and add.
Actually, what will I get?
What will the answer be for
that matrix multiplication?
Well, this one it's just going
to give us zero,
so in fact I'm back to this --
that's the answer,
for that matrix multiplication.
I'm happy to put up here these
facts about matrix
multiplication,
because it gives me a chance to
write down special matrices like
this.
This is a special matrix.
All those rows lie on the same
line.
All those rows lie on the line
through one six.
If I draw a picture of all
these row vectors,
they're all the same direction.
If I draw a picture of these
two column vectors,
they're in the same direction.
Later, I would use this
language.
Not too much later,
either.
I would say the row space,
which is like all the
combinations of the rows,
is just a line for this matrix.
The row space is the line
through the vector one six.
All the rows lie on that line.
And the column space is also a
line.
All the columns lie on the line
through the vector two three
four.
So this is like a really
minimal matrix.
And it's because of these ones.
Okay.
So that's a third way.
Now I want to say one more
thing about matrix
multiplication while we're on
the subject.
And it's this.
You could also multiply --
You could also cut the matrix
into blocks and do the
multiplication by blocks.
Yet that's actually so,
useful that I want to mention
it.
Block multiplication.
So I could take my matrix A and
I could chop it up,
like, maybe just for
simplicity, let me chop it into
two --
into four square blocks.
Suppose it's square.
Let's just take a nice case.
And B, suppose it's square
also, same size.
So these sizes don't have to be
the same.
What they have to do is match
properly.
Here they certainly will match.
So here's the rule for block
multiplication,
that if this has blocks like,
A -- so maybe A1,
A2, A3, A4 are the blocks here,
and these blocks are B1,
B2,3 and B4?
Then the answer I can find
block.
And if you tell me what's in
that block, then I'm going to be
quiet about matrix
multiplication for the rest of
the day.
What goes into that block?
You see, these might be -- this
matrix might be -- these
matrices might be,
like, twenty by twenty with
blocks that are ten by ten,
to take the easy case where all
the blocks are the same shape.
And the point is that I could
multiply those by blocks.
And what goes in here?
What's that block in the
answer?
A1 B1, that's a matrix times a
matrix, it's the right size,
ten by ten.
Any more?
Plus, what else goes in there?
A2 B3, right?
It's just like block rows times
block columns.
Nobody, I think,
not even Gauss could see
instantly that it works.
But somehow,
if we check it through,
all five ways we're doing the
same multiplications.
So this familiar multiplication
is what we're really doing when
we do it by columns,
by rows by columns times rows
and by blocks.
Okay.
I just have to,
like, get the rules straight
for matrix multiplication.
Okay.
All right, I'm ready for the
second topic,
which is inverses.
Okay.
Ready for inverses.
And let me do it for square
matrices first.
Okay.
So I've got a square matrix A.
And it may or may not have an
inverse, right?
Not all matrices have inverses.
In fact, that's the most
important question you can ask
about the matrix,
is if it's -- if you know it's
square, is it invertible or not?
If it is invertible,
then there is some other
matrix, shall I call it A
inverse?
And what's the -- if A inverse
exists -- there's a big "if"
here.
If this matrix exists,
and it'll be really central to
figure out when does it exist?
And then if it does exist,
how would you find it?
But what's the equation here
that I haven't -- that I have to
finish now?
This matrix,
if it exists multiplies A and
produces, I think,
the identity.
But a real -- an inverse for a
square matrix could be on the
right as well -- this is true,
too, that it's -- if I have a
-- yeah in fact,
this is not -- this is probably
the --
this is something that's not
easy to prove,
but it works.
That a left -- square matrices,
a left inverse is also a right
inverse.
If I can find a matrix on the
left that gets the identity,
then also that matrix on the
right will produce that
identity.
For rectangular matrices,
we'll see a left inverse that
isn't a right inverse.
In fact, the shapes wouldn't
allow it.
But for square matrices,
the shapes allow it and it
happens, if A has an inverse.
Okay, so give me some cases --
let's see.
I hate to be negative here,
but let's talk about the case
with no inverse.
So -- these matrices are called
invertible or non-singular --
those are the good ones.
And we want to be able to
identify how -- if we're given a
matrix, has it got an inverse?
Can I talk about the singular
case?
No inverse.
All right.
Best to start with an example.
Tell me an example -- let's get
an example up here.
Let's make it two by two -- of
a matrix that has not got an
inverse.
And let's see why.
Let me write one up.
No inverse.
Let's see why.
Let me write up -- one three
two six.
Why does that matrix have no
inverse?
You could answer that various
ways.
Give me one reason.
Well, you could --
if you know about determinants,
which you're not supposed to,
you could take its determinant
and you would get -- Zero.
Okay.
Now -- all right.
Let me ask you other reasons.
I mean, as for other reasons
that that matrix isn't
invertible.
Here, I could use what I'm
saying here.
Suppose A times other matrix
gave the identity.
Why is that not possible?
Because -- oh,
yeah -- I'm thinking about
columns here.
If I multiply this matrix A by
some other matrix,
then the --
the result -- what can you tell
me about the columns?
They're all multiples of those
columns, right?
If I multiply A by another
matrix that -- the product has
columns that come from those
columns.
So can I get the identity
matrix?
No way.
The columns of the identity
matrix, like one zero -- it's
not a combination of those
columns, because those two
columns lie on the -- both lie
on the same line.
Every combination is just going
to be on that line and I can't
get one zero.
So, do you see that sort of
column picture of the matrix not
being invertible.
In fact, here's another reason.
This is even a more important
reason.
Well, how can I say more
important?
All those are important.
This is another way to see it.
A matrix has no inverse -- yeah
-- here -- now this is
important.
A matrix has no -- a square
matrix won't have an inverse if
there's no inverse because I can
solve -- I can find an X of -- a
vector X with A times -- this A
times X giving zero.
This is the reason I like best.
That matrix won't have an
inverse.
Can you -- well,
let me change I to U.
So tell me a vector X that,
solves A X equals zero.
I mean, this is,
like, the key equation.
In mathematics,
all the key equations have zero
on the right-hand side.
So what's the X?
Tell me an X here -- so now I'm
going to put -- slip in the X
that you tell me and I'm going
to get zero.
What X would do that job?
Three and negative one?
Is that the one you picked,
or -- yeah.
Or another -- well,
if you picked zero with zero,
I'm not so excited,
right?
Because that would always work.
So it's really the fact that
this vector isn't zero that's
important.
It's a non-zero vector and
three negative one would do it.
That just says three of this
column minus one of that column
is the zero column.
Okay.
So now I know that A couldn't
be invertible.
But what's the reasoning?
If A X is zero,
suppose I multiplied by A
inverse.
Yeah, well here's the reason.
Here -- this is why this spells
disaster for an inverse.
The matrix can't have an
inverse if some combination of
the columns gives z- it gives
nothing.
Because, I could take A X
equals zero, I could multiply by
A inverse and what would I
discover?
Suppose I take that equation
and I multiply by -- if A
inverse existed,
which of course I'm going to
come to the conclusion it can't
because if it existed,
if there was an A inverse to
this dopey matrix,
I would multiply that equation
by that inverse and I would
discover X is zero.
If I multiply A by A inverse on
the left, I get X.
If I multiply by A inverse on
the right, I get zero.
So I would discover X was zero.
But it -- X is not zero.
X -- this guy wasn't zero.
There it is.
It's three minus one.
So, conclusion -- only,
it takes us some time to really
work with that conclusion -- our
conclusion will be that
non-invertible matrices,
singular matrices,
some combinations of their
columns gives the zero column.
They they take some vector X
into zero.
And there's no way A inverse
can recover, right?
That's what this equation says.
This equation says I take this
vector X and multiplying by A
gives zero.
But then when I multiply by A
inverse, I can never escape from
zero.
So there couldn't be an A
inverse.
Where here -- okay,
now fix -- all right.
Now let me take -- all right,
back to the positive side.
Let's take a matrix that does
have an inverse.
And why not invert it?
Okay.
Can I -- so let me take on this
third board a matrix -- shall I
fix that up a little?
Tell me a matrix that has got
an inverse.
Well, let me say one three two
-- what shall I put there?
Well, don't put six,
I guess is -- right?
Do I any favorites here?
One?
Or eight?
I don't care.
What, seven?
Seven.
Okay.
Seven is a lucky number.
All right, seven,
okay.
Okay.
So -- now what's our idea?
We believe that this matrix is
invertible.
Those who like determinants
have quickly taken its
determinant and found it wasn't
zero.
Those who like columns,
and probably that --
that department is not totally
popular yet -- but those who
like columns will look at those
two columns and say,
hey, they point in different
directions.
So I can get anything.
Now, let me see,
what do I mean?
How I going to computer A
inverse?
So A inverse -- here's A
inverse, now,
and I have to find it.
And what do I get when I do
this multiplication?
The identity.
You know, forgive me for taking
two by two-s,
but --
lt's good to keep the
computations manageable and let
the ideas come out.
Okay, now what's the idea I
want?
I'm looking for this matrix A
inverse, how I going to find it?
Right now, I've got four
numbers to find.
I'm going to look at the first
column.
Let me take this first column,
A B.
What's up there?
What -- tell me this.
What equation does the first
column satisfy?
The first column satisfies A
times that column is one zero.
The first column of the answer.
And the second column,
C D, satisfies A times that
second column is zero one.
You see that finding the
inverse is like solving two
systems.
One system, when the right-hand
side is one zero -- I'm just
going to split it into two
pieces.
I don't even need to rewrite
it.
I can take A times -- so let me
put it here.
A times column j of A inverse
is column j of the identity.
I've got n equations.
I've got, well,
two in this case.
And they have the same matrix,
A, but they have different
right-hand sides.
The right-hand sides are just
the columns of the identity,
this guy and this guy.
And these are the two
solutions.
Do you see what I'm going --
I'm looking at that equation by
columns.
I'm looking at A times this
column, giving that guy,
and A times that column giving
that guy.
So -- Essentially -- so this is
like the Gauss -- we're back to
Gauss.
We're back to solving systems
of equations,
but we're solving -- we've got
two right-hand sides instead of
one.
That's where Jordan comes in.
So at the very beginning of the
lecture, I mentioned
Gauss-Jordan,
let me write it up again.
Okay.
Here's the Gauss-Jordan idea.
Gauss-Jordan solve two
equations at once.
Okay.
Let me show you how the
mechanics go.
How do I solve a single
equation?
So the two equations are one
three two seven,
multiplying A B gives one zero.
And the other equation is the
same one three two seven
multiplying C D gives zero one.
Okay.
That'll tell me the two columns
of the inverse.
I'll have inverse.
In other words,
if I can solve with this matrix
A, if I can solve with that
right-hand side and that
right-hand side,
I'm invertible.
I've got it.
Okay.
And Jordan sort of said to
Gauss, solve them together,
look at the matrix -- if we
just solve this one,
I would look at one three two
seven, and how do I deal with
the right-hand side?
I stick it on as an extra
column, right?
That's this augmented matrix.
That's the matrix when I'm
watching the right-hand side at
the same time,
doing the same thing to the
right side that I do to the
left?
So I just carry it along as an
extra column.
Now I'm going to carry along
two extra columns.
And I'm going to do whatever
Gauss wants, right?
I'm going to do elimination.
I'm going to get this to be
simple and this thing will turn
into the inverse.
This is what's coming.
I'm going to do elimination
steps to make this into the
identity, and lo and behold,
the inverse will show up here.
K--- let's do it.
Okay.
So what are the elimination
steps?
So you see -- here's my matrix
A and here's the identity,
like, stuck on,
augmented on.
STUDENT: I'm sorry...
STRANG: Yeah?
STUDENT: -- is the two and the
three supposed to be switched?
STRANG: Did I -- oh,
no, they weren't supposed to be
switched.
Sorry.
Thanks.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
And there -- I've got them
right.
Okay, thanks.
Okay.
So let's do elimination.
All right, it's going to be
simple, right?
So I take two of this row away
from this row.
So this row stays the same and
two of those come away from
this.
That leaves me with a zero and
a one and two of these away from
this is that what you're getting
-- after one elimination step --
Let me sort of separate the --
the left half from the right
half.
So two of that first row got
subtracted from the second row.
Now this is an upper triangular
form.
Gauss would quit,
but Jordan says keeps going.
Use elimination upwards.
Subtract a multiple of equation
two from equation one to get rid
of the three.
So let's go the whole way.
So now I'm going to -- this guy
is fine, but I'm going to --
what do I do now?
What's my final step that
produces the inverse?
I multiply this by the right
number to get up to ther to
remove that three.
So I guess, I -- since this is
a one, there's the pivot sitting
there.
I multiply it by three and
subtract from that,
so what do I get?
I'll have one zero -- oh,
yeah that was my whole point.
I'll multiply this by three and
subtract from that,
which will give me seven.
And I multiply this by three
and subtract from that,
which gives me a minus three.
And what's my hope,
belief?
Here I started with A and the
identity, and I ended up with
the identity and who?
That better be A inverse.
That's the Gauss Jordan idea.
Start with this long matrix,
double-length A I,
eliminate, eliminate until this
part is down to I,
then this one will -- must be
for some reason,
and we've got to find the
reason -- must be A inverse.
Shall I just check that it
works?
Let me just check that -- can I
multiply this matrix this part
times A, I'll carry A over here
and just do that multiplication.
You'll see I'll do it the old
fashioned way.
Seven minus six is a one.
Twenty one minus twenty one is
a zero, minus two plus two is a
zero, minus six plus seven is a
one.
Check.
So that is the inverse.
That's the Gauss-Jordan idea.
So, you'll -- one of the
homework problems or more than
one for Wednesday will ask you
to go through those steps.
I think you just got to go
through Gauss-Jordan a couple of
times, but I --
yeah -- just to see the
mechanics.
But the, important thing is,
why -- is, like,
what happened?
Why did we -- why did we get A
inverse there?
Let me ask you that.
We got -- so we take --
We do row reduction,
we do elimination on this long
matrix A I until the first half
is up.
Then a second half is A
inverse.
Well, how do I see that?
Let me put up here how I see
that.
So here's my Gauss-Jordan
thing, and I'm doing stuff to
it.
So I'm -- well,
whole lot of E's.
Remember those are those
elimination matrices.
Those are the -- those are the
things that we figured out last
time.
Yes, that's what an elimination
step is it's in matrix form,
I'm multiplying by some Es.
And the result -- well,
so I'm multiplying by a whole
bunch of Es.
So, I get a -- can I call the
overall matrix E?
That's the elimination matrix,
the product of all those little
pieces.
What do I mean by little
pieces?
Well, there was an elimination
matrix that subtracted two of
that away from that.
Then there was an elimination
matrix that subtracted three of
that away from that.
I guess in this case,
that was all.
So there were just two Es in
this case, one that did this
step and one that did this step
and together they gave me an E
that does both steps.
And the net result was to get
an I here.
And you can tell me what that
has to be.
This is, like,
the picture of what happened.
If E multiplied A,
whatever that E is -- we never
figured it out in this way.
But whatever that E times that
E is, E times A is -- What's E
times A?
It's I.
That E, whatever the heck it
was, multiplied A and produced
I.
So E must be -- E A equaling I
tells us what E is,
namely it is -- STUDENT:
It's the inverse of A.
STRANG: It's the inverse of A.
Great.
And therefore,
when the second half,
when E multiplies I,
it's E --
Put this A inverse.
You see the picture looking
that way?
E times A is the identity.
It tells us what E has to be.
It has to be the inverse,
and therefore,
on the right-hand side,
where E -- where we just
smartly tucked on the identity,
it's turning in,
step by step --
It's turning into A inverse.
There is the statement of
Gauss-Jordan elimination.
That's how you find the
inverse.
Where we can look at it as
elimination, as solving n
equations at the same time --
-- and tacking on n columns,
solving those equations and up
goes the n columns of A inverse
Okay, thanks.
See you on Wednesday.