PROFESSOR: Hi there.
My name is Ana.
Welcome to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about how to multiply
matrices, and how to think about
that multiplication in
different ways, and also about
when a matrix is invertible or
not, and how to compute the
inverse when it is invertible.
And that's what today's
problem is about.
We have a matrix A that
has variables a and
b instead of numbers.
And the question is what are the
conditions on a and b that
make that matrix invertible?
And when it is invertible,
what is A inverse?
Why don't you hit Pause and work
on it for a little while.
And then we'll come back and
work on it together.
And we're back.
I hope you had success
in solving that.
Let's do it ourselves.
So, remember from lecture,
we talked about--
well, Professor Strang talked
about how it's easy to spot--
some easy tests to spot when
a matrix is not invertible.
Those were if you have a column
of 0s or a row of 0s,
then the matrix is
not invertible.
But if you have two columns that
are the same, or two rows
that are the same, the matrix
is also not invertible.
So let's see if this matrix
satisfies any of those easy
conditions.
Well, here you have
a row of a's.
If a is equal to 0, you have a
row of 0s, the matrix is not
invertible.
So a is--
What was the other one?
Two of the same column
or of the same row.
Well, if a is equal to b, then
all the entries in the matrix
are the same.
So all the rows are the same,
all the columns are the same,
the matrix is not invertible.
So that's the other
easy condition.
A is not invertible if a is
equal to 0 or a equals to b.
There's not any other easy
condition that I can spot.
So we have to do it in a
more systematic way.
So to do that, actually what we
do is we start with a, we
try to find its inverse, and if
in the process we run into
something fishy, those
are our conditions.
So remember how to find the
inverse of a matrix?
You start by writing a giant
matrix that has A and the
identity next to it.
And then you perform elimination
steps until--
let's put dots here, because
there's lots of steps--
and you stop once you've reached
the identity matrix on
the left side.
And when you do that, what you
have on the right side will be
your A inverse.
Easy enough.
So let's do the computations.
a, b, b, a, a, b, a, a, a, and
my identity matrix next to it.
And now I know you learned about
elimination in the past
recitation.
So I'll do the first few steps
slowly, and then I'll just
write the solution for
the last steps.
So we want to eliminate
this a.
We want to turn into 0.
So let's subtract the first
row from the second.
Let's do row 2 minus row 1, and
write it instead of row 2.
So a, b, b, 1, 0, 0, 0, so a
minus a, a minus b, b minus b
is 0, 0 minus 1, 1 minus
0, 0 minus 0.
And then we want to do the
same with the third row.
So let's do row 3 minus row 1.
0, a minus b, it doesn't fit.
a minus b.
Can you understand that?
And then 0 minus 1, 0
minus 0, 1 minus 0.
All right.
Let's continue up here.
Now I want to eliminate
this a minus b.
I want to turn it into a 0.
So the first row
stays the same.
a, b, b, 1, 0, 0, 0, a
minus b, 0, -1, 1, 0.
And now 0 minus 0, a minus
b minus a minus b is 0.
a minus b minus 0,
that's easy.
-1 minus -1, 0 again.
-1 and 1.
Almost there.
We already have 0s down here.
It's looking more and more
like the identity matrix.
So we have to turn all these
diagonal entries into one, so
let's do that now.
1, b over a, b over-- oh.
I'm dividing by a.
a better not be 0.
Let me signal that here.
a different from 0.
1 over a, 0.
0.
I want to make that into a 1.
So 1 over a minus b, and--
you guessed it-- a minus b has
to be different from 0.
0 minus -1 over a minus b.
1 over a minus b.
0, 0, 1, 0, -1 over a minus b.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Someone's
pointing a mistake.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, the (2, 2)
entry, you should have a 1.
PROFESSOR: Oh, you're
absolutely right.
Thank you.
All right.
So not much left to do.
We only have to eliminate
b over a and b over a.
That's a little bit
computationally heavy.
So what do you have to do?
You just have to basically
subtract--
replace row 1 by row 1 minus b
over a times row 2 plus row 3.
Let me write that down.
row 1 minus b over a times
row 2 plus row 3.
You want that to go
into your row 1.
These stay the same.
-1 over a minus b.
1 over a minus b.
This is where I'm going to go to
my notes and tell you that
these numbers are 1 over
a minus b, 0 minus b
over a, a minus b.
That looks pretty awful.
But that is A inverse.
And we're done.
Except it looks terrible.
So let me just write
it in a nicer way.
A inverse equals-- see, you're
dividing everything by a minus
b, so pull out that factor.
1, 0, minus b over a,
-1, 1, 0, 0, -1, 1.
Looks much better now.
So here's your A inverse.
And the other question was what
are the conditions on a
and b for the matrix
A to be invertible?
Well, a has to be non-zero,
and a has to be
different from b.
And we're done.
That's it for today.
See you next time.