NIKOLA KAMBUROV: Hi everyone.
In this video, we're going to
explore briefly the concept of
a vector subspace.
This is the problem
we're going to do.
We're given these four different
subsets of R3, and
we are asked to figure out which
of these is, in fact,
the subspace.
So I'll give you a few moments
to try to do this on your own,
and then please come back to
see whether you were right.
So hi again.
So before we start, let's
briefly recall what a vector
subspace is.
Well vector subspace, of
course, it's a subset.
In this case, a subset of R3.
But it behaves like a vector
space itself, meaning that if
we take linear combination of
element in the subset, what we
get is still something
in that subset.
And in class, professor Strang
showed you a few specific
examples of subspaces, which
are related to matrices.
One of them was the null space
of a matrix, all the vectors
that the matrix sends to 0,
and the column space of a
matrix, which is the span of
the column of a matrix.
So let's see if we can apply
what we've learned in lecture
to our problem.
Number one, we are given a
linear equation relation
between b1, b2, and b3.
Once we have something linear,
this is a philosophy that
you'll learn in this class, we
can always write this as a
matrix equation.
So in particular, b1 plus b2
minus b3 equals 0, we can just
write it as the matrix 1, 1
negative 1, and b1, b2, b3
equal to 0.
So therefore, b1, b2, and b3
precisely describe the null
space of 1, 1 negative 1.
And thus, what we are
given in the first
question is a subspace.
What about the second one?
Again, we are given the relation
between b1, b2, b3,
but it's not linear.
b3 is the product
of b1 and b2.
So right, your guts tell you
that this shouldn't be a
vector space.
But we need to prove why.
Well, see that the vector 1,
1, 1 is inside this subset,
because the third entry is
the product 1, is the
product 1 and 1.
If the subset were a subspace
itself, then we would have 2,
2, and 2 in it as well.
Right, because any multiple of
a vector in the subspace is
inside the subspace.
But is 2, 2, 2 described
by this equation?
Well no, because the third
entry 2 is not
equal to 2 times 2.
So the example in number
2 is not a subspace.
Let's try 3.
And first, so we are given the
subset in question 3 is given
as the linear span of these two
vectors, 1 0 negative 1
and 1, 0, 1.
Plus the vector 1, 0, 0.
So let's think about
this geometrically.
We know that the linear span
of two linear independent
vectors, and these are
obviously linearly
independent, is a plane in R3.
So we have the plane, and we add
a vector to the point on
this plane.
So what if the vector were
lying on the plane?
Well we're not going to
change the plane.
We're still going to remain
in the plane.
What I'm hinting at is
the following thing.
That, in fact, 1, 0, 0 is a
linear combination of 1, 0
negative 1 and 1, 0, 1, and
it's fairly obvious to see
which linear combination of
these two vectors it is.
It's 1/2, 1, 0, negative 1
plus 1/2 times 1, 0, 1.
So we can write the whole
relation here in
the following way.
b1, b2, b3 is 1, 0, 0, which
we can write this.
Plus 1, 0 negative 1,
and c2, 1 0, 1.
Let me continue this here.
So b1, b2 and b3 is precisely c1
plus 1/2 of 1, 0, negative
1 plus c2 plus 1/2 of 1, 0, 1.
So indeed, the points b1, b2,
and b3 are described by the
linear span 1, 0, negative
1, and 1, 0, 1.
So it is a vector
subspace itself.
And finally, let's
look at number 4.
So we have a similar
situation.
I mean it's almost the
same situation.
We again have the linear span of
precisely the same vectors
as in question 3.
But this time we add
the vector 0, 1, 0.
Now, 0, 1, 0 is not in the span
of these two vectors.
So the argument that we just
showed for 3 doesn't work.
But what we know about
vector subspace is
the following thing.
Almost treated from the axioms
that 0 needs to be inside the
subset in order for it
to be a subspace.
It's a necessary condition.
Well is 0 inside this subset?
Meaning can we find coefficients
c1 and c2 plus 0,
1, 0 to equal 0 vector?
And the answer is no.
And why is this?
There's a very easy
way to see it.
Well we just look at the second
entry of the vector is,
and we see that any multiple.
So the linear span of these two
vectors will have as its
second entry 0.
And when we add it to 1, we can
never get a 0 entry here.
So the subset in 4 is
not a subspace.
So I hope this was useful and
just getting an intuition
which subsets of R3
are subspaces.
I'll see you guys later.