PROFESSOR: Welcome to this
recitation on matrix
exponential.
So here, we're given matrix
A with entries 6, 5, 1, 2.
And we're asked to compute
the matrix exponential,
exponential At, and to use it
to solve the initial value
problem u prime of t equals
Aut, where here, u are
basically vectors with initial
condition, u of 0 equals 4, 1.
So why don't you pause
the video,
work through the problem?
And I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So first, to go ahead and
compute the matrix
exponential, we need to identify
the eigenvalues of
matrix A and its eigenvectors.
So this is a matrix--
I'll just rewrite here--
that we saw before.
And its eigenvalues are again,
solution of 6 minus lambda 5,
1, 2 minus lambda equals to 0,
which gives us 6, 2 minus
lambda minus 5 equals to 0
lambda squared minus 8 lambda.
And we have a 12 minus 5.
So you can verify that the
eigenvalues would be 1 and 7.
Lambda 1 equals to 1.
And lambda 2 equals to 7.
So now, we need to seek the
eigenvectors associated to
each one of the eigenvalues.
So the idea here is to basically
move toward a
diagonalization of the matrix
A. So let's seek the
eigenvectors.
And here, I'm just going to give
them to you, and you can
verify the calculation.
And this calculation was
performed in a previous
recitation.
So the eigenvectors, V1
associated to the eigenvalue
lambda 1 was, for example,
1 minus 1.
And the other one that we found,
again, this is one form
of the eigenvector,
was 5 and 1.
So these are from the notes
of a previous recitation.
So you can verify that these
are the two eigenvectors.
And from this point, then we can
rewrite this solution, if
you recall.
I'm just going to go through
the steps toward getting to
the definition of the
exponential matrix.
So here, if we didn't know
anything about the exponential
matrix, we would be able to
write the solution as C1
exponential t V1 plus C2
exponential 7t V2, which
basically gives us here, if I
write it in this form, for
example, an exponential t minus
exponential t and an
exponential 5t multiplied by the
entry of this vector, an
exponential 7t here multiplying
C1, C2.
So this is where the
idea of the matrix
exponential comes from.
We're basically introducing the
matrix phi of t for which
we can write u equals phi of
t multiplied by this C1, C2
general constant.
So phi of t would then be
equal to this matrix.
But what we want is to be able
to solve an initial value
problem for which e of A of
0 applied to our initial
conditions would give us back
our initial condition.
So we're seeking for a form for
this exponential matrix
that would allow
us to do this.
So the way that we define the
matrix exponential give us
exponential At.
Now, I'm going to the proof, but
we're just going to check
it together, multiplied
by phi of 0 minus 1.
So let's check that if we use
this form of the matrix
exponential, we would have e.
We will have that at
0 applied to u0.
We have phi 0, phi 0 minus
1 applied to u0.
This is a matrix with
its inverse, which
gives us the identity.
And so basically, this gives
us back u of zero.
I mean you don't need to do that
when you're asked to find
the matrix exponential.
But just to remember where it's
coming from, you write
down your system
in matrix form.
You identify the matrix
phi of t.
And then you recall why you want
the matrix exponential to
have this form, basically to be
able to solve initial value
problems for which the value u
of t is projected to u of 0
when we take t equals 0 for
the matrix exponential.
So now let's go back
to our problem.
So let's compute this
matrix exponential.
We have phi of t.
So now from this formula, we
know that we need phi of 0.
So that give us, basically,
exponential of 0, 5,
minus 1, and 1.
We need to find its inverse.
So recall that the inverse
of a two-by-two matrix is
basically just the determinant,
minus B minus C
and reversing the diagonal
entries.
So we can just apply this to
get our phi of 0 minus 1.
So here, our determinant
is basically 1 plus 5,
which is 1 over 6.
And then the entries are simply
1, 1, minus 5, and 1.
So now, we're just left with
the multiplication of two
matrices to get our matrix
exponential.
So our matrix exponential would
give us this one sixth.
And we now have to multiply
the entries.
So I'm not going to rewrite
everything.
I'm just going to use
this space here.
So we have exponential t
multiplying 1 plus 5
exponential 7t.
Then, we have exponential t dot
minus 5 for this entry.
5 exponential t multiplying
our 7t.
Then for the second entry,
we basically have minus
exponential t1 exponential 7t1
minus exponential t minus 5
and exponential 7t1.
So we're done with the
matrix exponential.
So now we were asked to solve
for the initial value problem
with initial condition
4 and 1.
So how do we go about that?
Well, recall that I just
reminded you what did we want
to use this matrix
exponential for.
And what we wanted it for is
to be able to basically
project an initial condition
into a solution u of t, t
times later.
And we constructed this matrix
to be able to basically give
us this solution by just
multiplying the matrix by the
initial value vector.
So basically, to find the
solution of this initial value
problem, we simply need to
multiply this matrix by the
initial vector that
we were given.
And I'm just going to write it
here to not have to rewrite
everything.
And it was 4 and 1.
And this is u of 0.
So let me just do a dash here
just so that we can do the
computation.
And we would end up
with a solution--
I'm going to keep it in
matrix form for now.
So we end up with 4 exponential
t minus 5
exponential t, so minus
1 exponential t.
And we have a one sixth.
Here, 5 exponential 7t, so we
have 20, plus 5, so 25,
exponential 7t.
Then for the second entry of the
vector solution, we have
minus exponential here minus 4
that we add to a 5, and here,
a 7 multiplied by 4 that
we add to a 1.
So we have basically plus
5 exponential 7t.
And that basically gives
us one way of
writing this solution.
And we can split this down, if
we will, into two vectors,
plus t, minus 1, 1 exponential
7t, 25, 5.
And this form is as valid.
Yes, thank you.
So that ends the laborious
calculations.
But basically, the key point
here was just to remember
where is the matrix exponential
coming from,
basically, from the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors
of the original matrix present
in the system, and where is
the definition coming from, why
do we define it as phi of
t phi minus 1 of 0, and how
to use it then to give the
solution to an initial
value problem.
So that ends this recitation.