PROFESSOR: Hi everyone.
So today, I'd like to talk
about frequency response.
And specifically, we're going
to take a look at a couple
different differential
equations.
And we're asked to graph
the amplitude
response for each equation.
And you'll note that these
equations a, b and c have
varying amounts of damping.
So for part a we're asked to
plot the amplitude response
for x dot dot plus 4x equals
f knot cosine omega t.
For part b it's the same
equation, however we have an x
dot term added.
For part c, again we've
increase the damping.
So now we have 6x dot.
And then lastly for part d,
we'd like to discuss the
resonance for each system.
So I'll let you work out
this problem, and I'll
be back in a moment.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So for part a, we're asked to
graph the amplitude response
to the differential equation x
dot dot plus 4x equals f not
cosine omega t.
And from a previous recitation,
we already wrote
down the particular response to
this differential equation.
So I'm just going to write down
the particular response,
which has the form f not
4 minus omega squared
cosine omega t.
Now the amplitude response is
defined as a ratio, and
specifically it's the ratio of
the output amplitude of a
differential equation to the
input amplitude of a
differential equation.
So in the case at hand, we
have the output is a
sinusoidal function whose
amplitude is f not divided by
4 minus omega squared.
So it's the output divided
by the input.
These are both amplitudes.
And in our case, we have
f not divided by
4 minus omega squared.
This is the output amplitude.
And the input amplitude
is just f not.
So we see when we compute this
ratio the f0's divide out.
And at the end of the
day, we're left with
4 minus omega squared.
So I'm going to draw the
amplitude response now.
So we have omega.
And we see that when
omega is equal to
2, there's an asymptote.
When omega is equal
to 0, we have 1/4.
And specifically, we have
this tent-like function.
So this is the amplitude
response.
So notice how when we drive the
system with frequency two,
the amplitude response
goes to infinity.
As a result, we call
this frequency
the resonant frequency.
So this concludes part a.
For part b, we have a
differential equation with
damping now.
And to compute the particular
solution, we follow the
standard procedure of first
complexifying the right-hand
side and then using the
exponential response formula.
So I'm just going to write down
the particular solution.
If we follow these steps, we
find that it's the real part
of the right-hand side
complexified, which is f not e
to the i omega t divided by the
characteristic polynomial
evaluated at i omega.
And in this case, the
characteristic polynomial p of
s is s squared plus s plus 4.
p of i omega is then 4 minus
omega squared plus i omega.
And when we put the pieces
together, we end up with a
particular solution, which looks
like the real part of 1
over 4 minus omega squared plus
i omega f not upstairs e
to the i omega t.
So we're asked to compute the
amplitude response graph.
And if we take a look at this,
we see that the denominator
here is really just
a complex number.
So we can convert it into the
form of r,e to the i phi.
Now, the amplitude response is
defined as the ratio of the
output divided by the input.
And so the output amplitude is
going to be the magnitude of
this complex number.
So as a result, the amplitude
response is just the magnitude
of 1 over the characteristic
polynomial
evaluated at i omega.
This is also sometimes
referred to
as the complex gain.
Moreover, this term right here
contains two pieces of
information.
Not only does it contain the
amplitude response, but it
also contains the phase
information.
When we take the absolute value,
we're throwing out the
phase information, and we're
just remembering
the amplitude response.
So what is this amplitude
response look
like for this case?
Well, we have 1 over and it's
the magnitude of this complex
number, which is 4 minus omega
squared plus i omega.
So I just take the real part,
square it, add it to the
imaginary part squared,
and square
root the whole quantity.
Now there's a question
of how to graph this.
And we see that first off,
the square root's
an increasing function.
And we see that we're 1 over
So there's a trick, which
is to just look first at
sketching this piece which is
under the radical sign.
And if you look at trying to
maximize this function--
so finding the critical
points--
we'd see that in this case, we
have one maximum, to 4 minus
omega squared plus
omega squared.
And this is at 1 omega equals
the square root of 7/2.
Sorry.
This is a minimum.
So when I go to sketch this now,
we have omega, we have
the amplitude response.
Now, I'm going to draw in 2
from our previous diagram.
Now, the square root of 7/2
is just below 2, so
square root of 7/2.
So we end up with a maximum
at 7/2, and
then a decay to infinity.
And again, this is going to
be 1/4 when omega is 0.
So this is the peak amplitude
response.
So note that in this case, by
adding damping, what we've
done is we no longer have an
asymptote at omega equals 2.
But we now have a finite
amplitude, which occurs at
omega equals the square
root of 7/2.
So I'm just going to clean up
the board, and I'll be back
with part c in a second.
For part a, we have an amplitude
response diagram,
which looks like a
tent function.
And at 2, omega equals 2,
we have a resonance.
So the amplitude response
diverges.
Just like to point out, I made
a small error before.
I forgot to include
absolute values on
the denominator here.
The amplitude response function,
it's always a
positive quantity.
We always throw out any phase
information and leave that for
the phase in the description
of the response
of the linear system.
So the amplitude response
is always positive.
For part b, we added dampening
to the system.
And we see that there's actually
a peak point which is
at the square root of 7/2.
And the amplitude response is
bounded at this point, but it
achieves a maximum.
And then again it decays
to infinity.
So I'd like now to take
a look at part c.
And in part c, we have the
differential equation x dot
dot plus 6x dot plus 4x equals
f not cosine omega t.
And again, the amplitude
response is going to equal 1
over the absolute value
of p of i omega.
And in this case, p of i omega
is going to be 1 over--
Well, we still have the 4 minus
omega squared term.
Instead of x dot, we
now have 6x dot,
which gives us 6i omega.
And then again, we want to take
the absolute value of
this complex number.
And when we take the absolute
value, we just get the sum of
the real parts squared plus the
sum of the imaginary parts
squared, which in this case is
going to be 36 omega squared,
the whole quantity squared
rooted, and then we have 1
over this value.
So now if we'd like to plot this
function, we can still do
the same trick and try to
maximize or find the critical
points of the denominator
under the radical.
And if we did this, in this case
we would find that the
only critical point is when
omega is equal to 0.
Secondly, if we look at omega
going to infinity, we see that
the denominator goes
to infinity.
So this whole quantity
must go to 0.
So if I were to go back here to
the amplitude response for
part c, again, when omega is
equal to 0 it's going to start
off at 1/4.
I've just argued that
it goes to 0 as
omega goes to infinity.
And since there are no critical
points, we must
smoothly paste the function
between the two.
And in fact, it's always
decreasing.
So the amplitude response,
in this case, is just a
decreasing function.
So this concludes part c.
And now I'll take a
look at part d.
Discuss the resonance
for each system.
So in part a, we
had no damping.
And we saw that there was a
resonance at omega equals 2.
And the resonance manifested
itself in the amplitude
response graph with a divergent
asymptote at omega
is equal to 2.
So as you drive the system close
to omega equals 2, the
amplitude of the system
starts to diverge.
In case two we introduced
damping into the system.
So we still have a very large
amplitude response at omega
equals the square root
of 7/2, however
it's no longer infinite.
And then lastly, when we
increased damping even further
so we had the 6x dot term,
the presence of a peak
disappeared.
And in fact, the amplitude
response just monotonically
decayed from 1/2 to infinity.
So just constantly
decreased to 0.
So I'd just like to conclude
there, and I'll
see you next time.