PROFESSOR: Welcome to the
applet, Amplitude and Phase
Second Order II.
This applet is a sibling of
the applet, Amplitude and
Phase First Order, which I
used to introduce the MIT
Mathlet collection.
It's color coding, placement
conventions, and it's
functionalities are identical
to that one.
This applet represents a
mechanical system driven by
the motion of the far
end of the dashpot.
Let's begin by animating the
system to see how this works.
You can see the dashpot
is moving up and down
sinusoidally, driving
a mass in yellow.
And the mass is also constrained
by a spring at the
top, attached to a fixed
wall at the top.
Perhaps we should animate this
again, so you can see the
whole thing at work.
This applet, and its siblings,
show only the steady state or
periodic solutions to
these equations.
They don't allow you to pick
initial conditions.
They don't represent the
effect of transients.
In the applet, x represents the
position of the mass, and
you can see it read
off on this scale.
It's represented in yellow on
the graphing window here.
And we declare x to be zero when
the spring is exerting no
force on the mass.
It's at rest.
We declare x to be the
output signal of the
system in the mathlet.
Y denotes the position of the
plunger, and it's read off by
this scale here.
We declare y to be the input
signal of the system.
Now the force exerted by a
dashpot is proportional to the
relative velocity of the
cylinder and the piston
sliding inside of it.
The proportionality constant
is called b.
As a consequence, the right-hand
side of the
equation controlling
the position of the
mass is b,y dot --
b times the time derivative
of y.
This is a good example in which
the right-hand side of a
linear equation in standard
form is not
just the input signal.
In this case, it's not even a
multiple of the input signal.
It's a multiple of
the derivative
of the input signal.
The most important case to study
is that in which the
input signal is sinusoidal,
and that's what
is represented here.
In the applet, we take the
amplitude of the input
signal to be one.
If the amplitude of the input
signal is doubled, so is its
derivative, and so by
superposition the amplitude of
the output signal would
also be doubled.
So setting the input's amplitude
equal to one isn't
really a restriction.
In this situation, when the
input amplitude is one, the
output amplitude is the same
as the gain of the system.
We can see how this output
amplitude depends upon the
input frequency by opening the
Bode Plot window here.
This opens two windows.
The top one represents the
amplitude of the system
response, the gain, as
a function of omega.
And we can start with
omega small.
When omega equals zero, the
plunger isn't moving at all,
and the mass has no reason
to move either.
So x equals zero, the spring is
relaxed, there's no motion.
When omega increases,
the system
response becomes greater.
But you'll notice something
interesting.
In this system, when omega is
small, the system response
leads the input signal.
That is to say, the phase
lag is negative.
And that's represented here.
This is a little confusing.
This is a graph of the negative
of the phase lag or
the phase gain.
And that's a positive
angle, in this
system, for omega small.
You can see the effect.
The mass seems to be pulling the
plunger, although that's
not actually what's happening.
When omega increases, the
amplitude of the system
response increases until a
critical moment when omega
takes on some critical value.
This is the resonant frequency
of the system.
And at this point, the system
response is identical to the
input signal.
Shall we see what this looks
like by animating the system?
Now the plunger seems to be
locked to the piston.
That's not actually the case,
but the system is simply
operating in harmony here.
It's the resonant frequency.
When omega increases still
further, then the system
response falls off.
The phase lag becomes positive,
the response falls
behind the input signal.
And that's all visible from
the Bode plot pictures.
As I look at this, I notice
something interesting.
When the system response
reaches a maximum or a
minimum, that's exactly the same
moment as when the system
response curve crosses the
input signal curve.
So in other words, the amplitude
of the output signal
equals the value of the
input signal at the
moment when they cross.
Let's see if that is always
the case when I change the
frequency here.
That always seems
to be the case.
Very interesting.
And in fact, perhaps we should
change the values of b and k
to see whether that continues
to be the case.
Yes it just seems to drag
up and down there.
And similarly, if I change the
value of the spring constant,
k, again that peak seems to
move up and down along the
blue curve.
Very odd.
We'll come back to that.
Here are some further
observations that you can see
from experimenting
with this applet.
First of all, let's watch what
happens if I change the value
of the damping constant, b.
I'm going to watch the Bode
plot over here, the
amplitude Bode plot.
Well, it changes, but one thing
that doesn't change is
the position of the resonant
peak there.
In other words, the resonant
frequency seems to be
independent of the value of b,
of the damping constant.
The second thing you can observe
as I vary b is when b
is large, the resonant hump is
quite broad, but as b becomes
smaller, that spike becomes
narrower and
narrower and narrower.
And the third thing you can
notice from looking at this is
as b gets to be small, the
flip between phase lag of
close to minus pi over 2 to a
phase lag of close to plus pi
over 2 happens more and more
abruptly as I change the
frequency from something small
and cross through that
resonant peak.
Now the system response is ahead
of the input signal.
But it very quickly flips to
being behind it as you cross
the resonant frequency.
And that transition happens
more and more rapidly as b
gets to be small.
Each one of these three
observations can be verified
by calculation.
The relationship between the
gain and the phase lag can be
illustrated very well using the
Nyquist plot, which I'll
open using this key.
This is a plot of the complex
plane, and on it is drawn a
complex number in yellow.
And that complex number has
a magnitude and an angle.
The magnitude is the gain.
This yellow strut is the same
length as this radius vector.
And the angle is the negative
of the phase lag.
It's the phase gain.
So when the angle's positive
here, it goes through zero
here and becomes negative down
here, when the phase lag
becomes positive.
So you can see why it is that
the resonant peak occurs at
exactly the same instant as when
the phase lag is zero.
That says that this trajectory,
this Nyquist plot,
goes through this point, which
is the point 1 in the complex
plane, where the angle is zero
and the magnitude is 1.
This trajectory is in fact
independent of either or both
of the system parameters.
If I change them, many things
change, but the shape of this
trajectory, the Nyquist plot,
is independent of those two
system parameters.
And in fact, it's a circle of
radius 1/2 and center 1/2.
You can verify that by
calculation as well.
That fact explains the
observation we made earlier,
that the amplitude of the system
response, the gain,
seems to be equal to the value
of the input signal when that
maximum is achieved.
In other words, the claim is
that the gain equals the
cosine of the phase lag.
The gain is the cosine
of the phase lag.
This curve is given by the
equation, the radius equals
the cosine of the angle.
r equals cosine theta is a
polar equation for this
particular circle.
And so the fact that this is a
circle is the same as the fact
that we observed earlier, that
the solution curve crosses the
input curve just when
it reaches a
maximum or a minimum.
Well, in addition to the spring
system shown in this
applet, this very same equation
models the response
of an A/M radio receiver.
The input signal is the incoming
radio signal, which
contains electromagnetic waves
of many different frequencies.
The output signal feeds
to the amplifier.
You tune the radio to a
particular angular frequency
by adjusting k, the spring
constant, which in the circle
model is the capacitance, so
that the resonant frequency is
the desired frequency that
you want to tune to.
Then the output generated by the
other frequencies is much
less than the output generated
by frequency omega r.
How much less depends on how
sharp the resonance spike is.
The sharper the spike, the
better the tuning.
You can make the spike sharper
by decreasing the value of b,
which in the A/M radio model,
is the resistance.