CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, what I'd like
us to do is work on
understanding simply connected
regions in three dimensions.
Well, there's one
two-dimensional one, but the
rest are three dimensions.
So what I want you to do is for
each of the following--
there are six different
regions--
determine whether or not each
of them is simply connected.
So the first one is R3.
The second one is if
I take R3 and I
remove the entire z-axis.
The third one is if I take
R3 and I remove 0.
The fourth one is if I take
R3 and remove a circle.
The fifth one is R2 minus
a line segment.
And the sixth one is
a solid torus.
So a solid torus looks like a
doughnut, and it includes the
inside of the doughnut.
This looks like a doughnut,
hopefully, to you.
And it's not hollow.
It includes the inside.
So what I'd like you to do,
again, is determine whether or
not each of these regions
is simply connected.
And why don't you pause the
video while you work on that.
And then bring the video back
up when you're ready
to check your work.
OK, welcome back.
So again, what we're interested
in doing is
understanding simply
connectedness in another dimension.
We did something already
a while back with two
dimensions, and so now we want
to understand it better in
three dimensions.
So let's work through these.
Well, I'm not going to write
anything down for number one,
because you should
already know that
R3 is simply connected.
But if you weren't sure about
it, you could think, for any
closed curve I draw in R3, I can
certainly get all of the
inside of it contained in R3.
Another way to think about it is
that I can take that curve
and I can collapse it down to
a point, and remain in R3.
So then the first one is
an easy yes to simply
connectedness.
OK?
So let's start on the second
one, and I'm going to draw a
little picture for us.
So the second one is R3.
I should go this way.
This is x, y, and z, but then
I remove the entire z-axis.
So I should make this really
dark so we know we're removing
that part from R3.
And I'm removing it all the way
up to minus infinity in
the z-direction and plus
infinity in the z-direction.
Now, the question is can I find
any closed curve, that
when I try and compress that
closed curve down to a point,
I can't do it while remaining
inside this region that is all
of R3 minus the z-axis.
And the answer is there
is a whole family of
curves that do this.
If I take a curve that goes
around the z-axis, you'll
notice that there's something
on the inside of it--
regardless, of whether I slide
it up or down-- there's a
point on the inside of this
curve that is not in the
region I'm interested in.
The region, again, is
R3 minus the z-axis.
So there are two ways
to think about this.
You can think about if I were to
take this curve and I were
to put a surface across this
curve so it was like a disk,
there would be a point
on the z-axis that
would intersect it.
Or you can think about it as
saying, I have this curve and
if I try and squeeze it down to
as small as I can get it, I
can't get it as small is I
want without hitting the
z-axis at some point.
The z-axis is kind of
in the way, right?
Now, number three is a little
different situation.
Because in number three, I think
this exact same picture,
but instead of removing the
whole z-axis, I just remove
the origin.
So let me try and draw
a picture of that.
So I'm going to make this a big
open circle at the origin.
That's not included
in our region.
So our region is all of
R3 except the origin.
And in two-dimensional space,
this was not simply connected.
But in three-dimensional space
it is simply connected.
So this is a little different
situation than what you had
previously.
And so the idea is here, if I
take a curve, even if I take a
curve that's sitting in the xy
plane that goes around the
origin, the point is I can
keep this curve in
three-dimensional space, and I
can wiggle it around, so that
I can shrink it down to a point,
and the origin doesn't
get in the way.
It doesn't keep me
from doing that.
So actually, this region, even
though in two-dimensional
space it was not simply
connected, in
three-dimensional space it is.
And let's see if we understand
the difference.
The difference is in
two-dimensional space, if I
drew a curve on the xy plane
around the origin, and I
wanted to squish it down to a
point, the only way to do that
would be to bring the curve
somehow through the origin.
Right?
I would be stuck having to pass
the curve through the
origin to shrink it
down to a point.
But in three space, I have
another dimension.
So a curve that sits on the xy
plane, I can just kind of lift
it a little bit away from the
origin, and then I can shrink
it down to a point without the
origin getting in the way.
So having that extra dimension
means even though I remove one
point, it's still actually a
simply connected region.
So maybe this is the first place
we see that in the three
dimensions we have a different
case than we had in two
dimensions removing the
same kind of object.
So I realize now I haven't
been writing down whether
these are simply connected
or not.
So I should write down this
is simply connected.
And maybe for number two I
should go back and formally
write not simply connected.
So that we have this
for posterity.
Now the fourth one is
R3 minus the circle.
So let me see if I can draw
a picture of that.
And for the circle, it doesn't
really matter where it is.
I'm just going to draw
one somewhere.
So here's my circle.
So everything is in my region
except this circle.
And the question: is it
simply connected?
And the answer is: no, the
region is not simply
connected, because of one
particular problem.
It's actually the same kind of
problem you have when you
remove the z-axis.
And that is, if I draw a curve
that goes around this circle--
any curve that goes around
this circle--
notice that any way I try and
move this curve and shrink it
down to a point, this circle is
going to get in the way for
the same reason that the
z-axis got in the way.
Because this circle is closed,
I can't slide the curve I'm
interested in away from
the circle and
then shrink it down.
OK.
There's some sort of obstruction
right here.
And so it's fundamentally
different than the case where
we just had the origin, because
we could take any
curve and we could move it away
from the origin, and then
shrink it down to a point.
And the origin didn't
get in the way.
But here, anywhere I try and
move this curve, it's going to
have to hit the circle if I want
to move it away so I can
shrink it to a point
in my region.
So this circle is preventing
me from shrinking it down.
OK, and then there
are two more.
And the fifth one is R2
minus a line segment.
So now we're in two-dimensional
space.
OK, and let me just
pick a segment.
OK.
Now, this one is interesting.
Oops.
Again I did it.
I forgot to write whether it's
simply connected or not.
Let me come back over to
four for posterity.
Not simply connected.
OK, sorry about that.
For the fifth one, because I'm
in two dimensions, it's going
to be not simply connected,
but if I add a third
dimension, it would become
simply connected.
So I want to explain why it's
not simply connected here, and
then I want to show you why in
a third dimension it becomes
simply connected.
OK?
The problem curves are the
curves that do this, that go
around this line segment.
Because notice, if I want to
try and contract this curve
down to a point and I don't want
to intersect that line
segment, in order to do it I'd
actually have to move it away
from the line segment.
I'd have to pass through
the line segment.
At some point, this curve would
intersect that segment
in order to be able to shrink
it to a point in the region
I'm interested in.
So this segment is getting in
the way-- we can think of it
that way-- of allowing me to
contract this down to a point.
Actually also, when we talked
about simply connectedness in
two dimensions, it was easier.
Because we could say, if we take
any curve and we look at
the disk that's spanned by the
boundary of this curve, and we
look at the region the curve
encloses, notice that this
segment is in that region.
And there's no way of drawing
this kind of curve without the
segment being in that region,
and that's how we know it's
not simply connected.
Now, in three dimensions,
what happens?
What if I took this exact same
picture and I just made the
z-axis come out from
the board?
Why is that suddenly simply
connected, whereas in the
two-dimensional case it's not?
And the reason is because in
this same picture, I could
take this same curve, and I
could take this shaded thing,
and I could push the shaded
thing out of the xy plane.
And so I'd still have the same
boundary curve, but I'd have
the shaded portion not
hitting the segment.
And so I can find some surface
with this boundary that
doesn't have this segment in the
interior of the surface.
And that's another way of
thinking about simply
connectedness.
So in the two-dimensional
case, it is not simply
connected, but if I were to add
a third dimension, this
region would become
simply connected.
OK.
Because I would have no problem
for any curve finding
some surface that had that
curve as a boundary that
didn't intersect that segment.
So I could keep the surface
in the region I
was interested in.
OK.
So that would tell me it
was simply connected.
And then the last one
is a solid torus.
OK, and this one, we might not
have dealt with solid tori
before, but this is an
interesting problem.
OK, so there are
fundamentally--
we say in math-- that there are
two classes of curves that
are interesting.
We won't get into the exact
terminology of what's
happening, but there are two
types of curves on the torus.
One type of curve is the kind
that goes around right here.
OK.
So it loops around the doughnut
in that direction.
But that type of curve is nice,
because notice, that if
I look at the surface in there,
it's all inside the
solid torus.
So that's good.
So that seems like that's a
curve that is not telling us
it's not simply connected.
We'll say that.
But there's another class
of curves in the torus.
And that's the class of curves
that goes around--
this is a little harder
to draw--
the top, but around the hole.
OK?
Around the hole.
Now any surface I have
that I try to draw--
any surface that's
going to have
that curve as a boundary--
is at some point forced to
leave the solid torus.
And the reason is really
because of
the hole in the middle.
Right?
That's really the reason
it happens.
OK.
And so you can see the part
right in here is on the
surface, but it's not
in the solid torus.
So because I have a curve that
any surface I draw that has
that curve as a boundary is
forced to leave the solid
torus, it's a non-simply
connected region.
So we say not simply
connected.
OK.
So I'm going to go back through
real quickly and just
remind us what was happening.
And maybe use the language
I was using at the end to
describe the first examples,
because that might help a
little better.
So let's go back to the
first examples.
OK, in the R3 example, again,
number one, we know it's
simply connected.
We're not going to
worry about it.
OK.
But let me draw number two.
Maybe if I draw some shaded
region, this will help us
understand it a little
bit better.
Number two we established was
not simply connected.
And if you think about it, if
you have a curve that goes
around the z-axis, and you want
to look at a surface that
has that curve as its boundary,
this surface
certainly intersects
the z-axis.
The question is, can I keep this
curve the way it is, and
pull the surface away and have
it not intersect the z-axis?
And the answer is no.
Any way I move the inside of
the curve-- basically, what
looks like a disk--
it's still going to intersect
the z-axis somewhere.
Right?
And so it's definitely
not simply connected.
And the thing I was trying to
point out in number three is
that it is simply connected.
If I shade the boundary of a
curve sitting in the xy plane,
and then I take that shaded
disk and I push it up a
little, then it no longer
hits the origin.
And I haven't fundamentally
changed my curve at all.
And so that's a way of
understanding that it is
actually simply connected.
OK?
So there are a couple of
ways to think about it.
And without being incredibly
mathematically precise, these
are some of the best ways we
have of thinking about
understanding simply connected
or not simply connected.
So again, we had six examples.
Removing the z-axis from R3
was not simply connected.
Removing the origin from R3 was
still simply connected.
Removing a circle from R3 was
not simply connected for the
same reason as the z-axis
problem, because here was my
disk, and any way I try to move
this shaded surface, I
can't keep it from intersecting
this circle.
And then number five was
R2 minus a segment.
It was not simply connected,
but if I add another
dimension, it is simply
connected, for the same kind
of reason that R3 minus
the origin was.
And then number six was
the solid torus.
Which now, it's kind of hard
to see what the solid torus
looks like.
But we said, there's one curve
that behaves fine, but the
curve that goes all the way
around the hole shows it's, in
fact, not simply connected.
So hopefully that was
informative, and
that's where I'll stop.