Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture you've been
learning about vector
calculus, Stokes' theorem,
all sorts of cool
stuff like that, curl.
So I have a nice problem
here for you.
So let F be the following
vector field.
So it's the vector field whose
direction is xi hat plus yj
hat plus zk hat, but in addition
I want to multiply it
by rho to the n.
So this is your usual rho from
spherical coordinates.
This is the square root
of x squared plus y
squared plus z squared.
And n can be any number.
So it might be positive, it
might be negative, it might be
0, doesn't have to
be an integer.
Some number, though,
it's some constant.
So what I'd like you to do is
to show that for this field,
regardless of what the value of
n happens to be, that it is
a gradient field.
So it is the gradient
of some function.
So why don't you pause the
video, have a go at that, come
back and we can work
on it together.
So recall that for something to
be a gradient field, what
that means--
well, first of all, that means
that there is some function
that has it as the gradient,
and we know a lot of other
characterizations of it.
And one of them that we know
involves the curls.
So let's talk about that one.
So in order to look at the curl
of this field, I'm going
to want to take partial
derivatives of its components.
And so I'm going to want
to take partial
derivatives of rho.
So let's just remember or
recall that partial rho
partial x equals z over rho.
And similarly, partial rho
partial y is y over rho.
And partial z partial--
sorry, partial rho partial
z is z over rho.
So you can just check that using
the fact that you know
what rho is.
Et cetera.
I'm going to write et cetera
because it's the same
for the other two.
So let's call-- for
shorthand--
let's call F, Mi plus
Nj plus P times k.
So M, N, and P are
its components.
If F is this, then we know
that curl F is equal to--
what is it?
So it's P, the y partial
derivative of P, minus the z
partial derivative of
N, i hat, plus--
OK, so it's the z partial
derivative of M minus the x
partial derivative of
P, j hat, plus--
it's going to be, what's
the last one?--
the x partial derivative of N,
minus the y partial derivative
of M k hat.
So if this is our formula for
F, then this is our formula
for the curl of F. And OK, so
now we just have to compute
these various different partial
derivatives in order
to see what the curl is.
And then hopefully
that'll tell us
something about this field.
So let's see.
So Py.
In our case, so M is equal to
rho to the little n times x.
Big N is equal to rho to
the little n times y.
And big P is equal to rho
to the little n times z.
So let's look at our
components here.
So P sub y--
well, z is a constant
with respect to y.
So this is just rho to the n.
Well, z times the y partial
of rho to the n.
So that's by the chain rule, so
we got n rho to the n minus
1 times y over rho times z.
So we can rewrite this as nyz
rho to the n minus 2.
And similarly, so that
was P sub y, so let's
look at N sub z.
So N is rho to the n times y.
So you take the z partial
derivative, so y is a constant.
So we need to look
at the z partial
derivative of P to the n.
So this is, again, it's n--
sorry, I think I said
P to the n.
But of course this isn't
a P, this is a rho.
So it's n rho to the n minus 1
times partial rho partial z.
So that's z over rho times y.
And again, this is equal to
nyz rho to the n minus 2.
OK, so P sub y, the y partial
of P is nyz rho
to the n minus 2.
And the z partial of n is nyz
rho to the n minus 2.
And they're the same.
So what does that mean?
So that means the first
component of curl of F is 0.
So if you do a little bit more
arithmetic of exactly the same
sort, you have two more
components to check.
What you're going to
find is that the
other ones are 0 also.
I'm not going to do out all
those partial derivatives for
you, but I trust that you can
compute the similar looking
partial derivatives that appear
in these other two
components--
this j should have had a hat--
the other partial derivatives
that appear in these
components and show that they're
all also equal to 0.
So in our case, curl of F is
just equal to 0 vector.
OK, great.
So what does that mean?
Well, we want to show that
something is a gradient field.
So we know that we
can do that.
We know that that happens
precisely when its curl is 0
if it's defined on a simply
connected domain.
On a simply connected region.
So we know that a function is
a gradient field if it's
defined on a simply connected
domain and has curl 0.
Well, let's see.
So where is this
thing defined?
Where is F defined?
Well, if n is bigger than
or equal to 0--
well, I guess I want strictly
bigger than 0 just to be on
the safe side.
If n is positive,
this is defined
everywhere and we're great.
If n is negative, then we
have a problem at 0.
Because then we have
division by rho.
So we don't want
to divide by 0.
So if n is negative, there's
a problem at the origin.
So in the worst case,
F is defined
everywhere except the origin.
But that's simply connected.
Because we're in space.
If we were in the plane, this
would be a different story.
But in space, just removing a
point doesn't destroy simply
connectedness.
So this field F is defined
everywhere, except the origin
perhaps, so we're in a simply
connected region.
So when you have curl F in a
simply connected region, your
field is, in fact,
a gradient field.
Now I leave it as an exercise
to you to come up with the
actual function, or one of the
actual functions, of which
this is a gradient.
But we've just shown that
because its curl is 0, and
because it's defined in a simply
connected region of
space, that this field really
is the gradient
field of some function.
So I'll stop there.