I'm Walter Lewin.
My lectures will in general not
be a repeat of your book but
they will be complementary to
the book.
The book will support my
lectures.
My lectures will support the
book.
You will not see any tedious
derivations in my lectures.
For that we have the book.
But I will stress the concepts
and I will make you see beyond
the equations,
beyond the concepts.
I will show you whether you
like it
or not that physics is
beautiful.
And you may even start to like
it.
I suggest you do not slip up,
not even one day,
eight oh two is not easy.
We have new concepts every week
and before you know you may be
too far behind.
Electricity and magnetism is
all around us.
We have electric lights.
Electric clocks.
We have microphones,
calculators,
televisions,
VCRs, radio,
computers.
Light
itself is an electromagnetic
phenomenon as radio waves are.
The colors of the rainbow in
the blue sky are there because
of electricity.
And I will teach you about that
in this course.
Cars, planes,
trains can only run because of
electricity.
Horses need electricity because
muscle contractions require
electricity.
Your nerve system is driven by
Atoms, molecule,
all chemical reactions exist
because of electricity.
You could not see without
electricity.
Your heart would not beat
without electricity.
And you could not even think
without electricity,
though I realize that even with
electricity some of you may have
a problem with that.
The modern picture of an atom
is a nucleus which is very small
compared to the size of the
atom.
The nucleus has protons which
are positively charged and it
has neutrons which have no
charge.
The mass of the proton is
approximately the same as the
mass of the neutron.
It's about six point seven
times ten to the minus
twenty-seventh kilograms.
One point seven.
The positive charges here with
the nucleons,
with the neutrons,
and then we have electrons in a
cloud around it.
And if the atom is neutral the
number of electrons and the
number of protons is the same.
If you take one electron off
you get a positive ion.
If you add an electron then you
get a negative ion.
The charge of the electron is
the
same as the charge of the
proton.
That's why the number is the
same for neutral atoms.
The mass of the electron is
about eighteen hundred thirty
times smaller than the mass of
the proton.
It's therefore negligibly small
in most cases.
All the mass of an atom is in
the nucleus.
If I take six billion atoms
lined up touching other,
I take six billion because
that's about about the number of
people on earth.
Then you would only have a
length of sixty centimeters.
Gives you an idea of how small
the atoms are.
The nucleus has a size of about
ten to the minus twelfth
centimeters.
And the atom itself is about
ten thousand times larger.
The cloud of electrons.
Which is about ten to the minus
eight centimeters.
And if you line six billion of
those up you only get this much.
Already in six hundred BC,
it was known that if you rub
amber that it can attract pieces
of dry leaves.
And the Greek word for amber is
electron.
So that's where electricity got
its name from.
In the sev- sixteenth century
there were more substances known
to do this.
For instance glass and sulfur.
And it was also known and
written that when people were
bored at parties that the women
would rub
their amber jewelry and would
touch frogs which then would
start jumping of desperation
which people considered to be
fun, not understanding what
actually was happening to the
amber nor what was happening to
the frogs.
In the eighteenth century it
was discovered that there are
two types of electricity.
One if you rub glass and
another if you rub rubber or
amber for that matter.
Let's call one A and the other
B.
It was known that A repels A
and B repels B but A attracts B.
And it was Benjamin Franklin
without any knowledge of
electrons and protons who
introduced the idea that all
substances are penetrated with
what he called electric fluid,
electric fire.
And he stated if you get too
much of the fire then you're
positively charged and if you
have a deficiency of that fire
then you're
negatively charged.
He introduced the sign
convention and he decided that
if you rub glass that that is an
excess of fire and he called
that therefore positive.
You will see later in this
course why this choice he had
fifty percent chance is
extremely unfortunate but we
have to live with it.
So if you take this fluid
according to Benjamin Franklin
and bring it from one substance
to the other then the one that
gets an excess becomes
positively charged but
automatically
as a consequence of that the
one from which you take the
fluid becomes negatively
charged.
And so that's the whole idea
behind the conservation of
charge.
You cannot create charge.
If you create plus then you
automatically create minus.
Plus and plus repel each other.
Minus and minus repel each
other.
And plus and minus attract.
And Benjamin Franklin who did
experiments also noticed that
the more fire you have the
stronger the
forces.
The closer these objects are to
each other the stronger the
forces.
And there are some substances
that he noticed which conduct
this fluid, which conduct this
fire, and they are called
conductors.
If I have a glass rod as I have
here and I rub it then it gets
this positive charge that we
just discussed.
So here is this rod and I rub
it
with some silk and it will get
positively charged.
What happens now to an object
that I bring close to this rod
and I will start off with taking
a conductor.
And the reason why I choose a
conductor is that conductors
have a small fraction of their
electrons which are not bound to
atoms but which can freely move
around in the conductor.
That's characteristic for a
conductor, for metals.
That's not the case with
nonconductors.
There the all electrons are
fixed to individual atoms.
So here we have a certain
fraction of electrons that can
wander around.
What's going to happen that
electrons want to be attracted
by these positive charges.
Plus and minus attract each
other.
And so some of these electrons
which can freely move will move
in this direction and so the
plus stay behind.
This process we call induction.
You get sort of a polarization.
You get a charge division.
It's a very small effect,
perhaps only one in ten to the
thirteen electrons that was
originally here will end up here
but that's all it takes.
So we get a polarization and we
get a little bit more negative
charge on the right side than we
have on the left side.
And so what's going to happen
is since the attraction between
these two will be stronger than
the repelling force between
these two because the distance
is smaller and Franklin had
already noticed the
shorter the distance the
stronger the force.
What will happen is that if
this object is free to move it
will move towards this rod.
And this is the first thing
that I would like you to see.
I have here a conductor that is
a balloon, helium-filled
balloon.
And I will rub this rod with
silk.
And as I approach that balloon
you will see that the balloon
comes to the rod.
I will then try to rub with
that rod several times on that
balloon.
It will take a while perhaps
because the rod itself is a very
good nonconductor.
It's not so easy to get charge
exchange between the two.
But if I do it long enough I
can certainly make that balloon
positive.
Then they're both positive.
And then they will repel each
other.
But first the induction part
whereby you will see the balloon
come to the glass rod.
These experiments work best
when it is dry.
In the winter.
They don't work so well when it
is humid so it's a good time to
teach eight oh two in the
winter.
OK there we go this should be
positively charged now.
And the balloon wants to come
to the glass.
You see that?
Very clearly.
Come on baby.
OK.
So now I will try to get this
balloon charged a little so
there is a change of electrons
that go from the balloon to the
glass.
And the glass doesn't it's not
a conductor itself so it is not
always so easy to get charge
exchanges.
OK let's see whether I have
succeeded now in making the
balloon positively charged as
well as the glass rod.
If that's the case then the
balloon is not going to like me.
The balloon will now be
repelled.
And you see that very clearly.
To show you now that there are
indeed two different kinds of
electricity if I now rub with
cat fur by tradition we do that
with cat fur I don't know why by
tradition we use silk for the
glass.
So if we do this with cat fur
now then this becomes negatively
charged.
Remember there were two types
of electricity.
And since that balloon is
positively charged now the
balloon will come to me.
And there it is.
Now it comes to me.
So you've seen
for the first time now clearly
that there are two different
kinds of electricity.
The positive charge is chosen
by Franklin on the glass rod and
the negative charge on the
rubber.
So now you may think that if I
approach a nonconducting balloon
with a glass rod and I have a
nonconducting balloon here you
may think now that this balloon
will not come to the glass rod
because there are no free
electrons.
So these electrons cannot
freely move and so you don't get
this polarization.
You don't get this induction.
But that is not the case.
And this is actually quite
subtle.
You have to look now at the
atomic scale.
If I take an atom like you have
here.
You have positive charge and
you have the electrons here in a
cloud
around the positive nucleus.
If I bring a glass rod
positively charged nearby then
these electrons which are stuck
to the atoms,
they cannot freely move like in
conductors, however will spend a
little bit more time on the side
where the glass rod is because
they feel attracted by the glass
rod, whereas the nuclei if
anything want to go away from
the glass rod,
so what you're going to see is
that
in a way if I started off with
a spherical atom let's suppose
this were a spherical atom or a
spherical molecule then what
will happen is that you get sort
of a shape like this and the
electrons spend a little bit
more time here than they spend
here and that means that I have
actually polarized that atom.
If the electrons spend more
time on this side of the atom
than on this side I have also
created the phenomenon of
induction and I therefore expect
that this side
becomes more negative than that
side.
And I can show you that in a
nice way with a transparency
whereby I have plus and minus
signs and I have equal number of
plus and minus signs.
So they represent neutral
atoms.
There you see them.
Boy.
It's a little dirty but maybe
see I can
clean it a little.
OK.
So here we go.
So notice there are equal
amount of pluses and minuses,
so think of the plus and the
minuses as one neutral atom.
Just a representation.
Now I'm holding a glass rod on
this side which is positively
charged.
And so each atom the electrons
want to go a little bit to this
side and so the nucleus stays
behind.
And if each atom does that this
is what's going to happen.
And now notice what you end up
with.
In the middle of the substance
plus and minuses cancel each
other out again.
But on the right side you have
created a negatively charged
layer and on the left side you
have created a positively
charged layer.
And so in a way you have again
induction.
So even in the nonconducting
objects this side will turn
negative and this side will turn
positive and therefore if I
approach a nonconducting balloon
with a glass
rod I will also see the balloon
come to me.
And so I can easily show you
that.
It doesn't make any difference
whether I choose glass or
whether I choose rubber.
I can do it with both.
Nonconducting balloons always
have a potential problem.
The potential problem is that
they can be charged by
themselves just like the metal
balloons can be charged by
themselves.
However, if I touch the metal
balloon then any charges there
will immediately flow through me
to the earth we will understand
that later.
Because this is a conductor.
That remember the electric
fluid is conducted by a metal
but not by a nonconductor.
So with this it's more
difficult.
Even if I kiss it and touch it
it's not clear that I can take
all the charge off.
In fact by doing that I may
even make it worse.
Let's hope that it is not
charged
too much and let's approach it
with this glass rod and see
whether I can convince you that
indeed it's coming to the rod
not because of the free
electrons but because of that
process.
Oh boy.
Ho.
And it should also do the same
with rubber I hope.
If it were negatively it'd go
away.
Ha it does go away so it is
negatively charged you see that.
By touching it I actually
probably charged it and there's
not much I can do about it.
Very difficult to get charge
off.
I already had a suspicion when
I approached it with the glass
it was too eager to come to the
glass.
Still negatively charged.
That's the way it goes.
It's not because the
demonstration
failed but it's because the
balloon is charged and doesn't
want to give it up because it's
a it is a nonconductor.
Friction can cause electric
charge and that's exactly what
happened when I touched this
balloon and tried to discharge
it.
Through friction I may actually
have charged it.
If I take these party balloons
that all of you may have seen
and you just rub them on your
shirt on your trousers they
stick to my hand.
They have charge on them.
Whether it's positive or
negative I don't know,
I don't even remember.
It's not important.
And so when I bring them to my
hand, my hand is not a good
conductor but you get induction,
this phenomenon that we just
discussed and so the two attract
each other.
The positive and the negative
side attract each other.
And you can stick them on the
ceiling.
Or you can stick them on the
board.
You can decorate your room that
way.
Very pretty isn't it.
All that you can do now because
of eight oh two.
Now these heavy balloons may be
a little bit more difficult.
Also I'm wearing cotton.
If you wear nylon or polyester
it's much better.
It's much easier to get oh
that's good, that's a nice one,
I think we need a blue one.
There we go.
So you see friction causes
electricity.
That's of course why the silk
when we rubbed the glass and the
cat fur we rub the rubber then
we create charge on one.
Of course if you make the glass
positively charged your silk
will be automatically negatively
charged.
When you comb your hair you may
have noticed with dry weather
that you hear some cracking
noise.
Cracking noise means sparks.
And you will learn all about
sparks
in this course though not
today.
But you can hear it if you're
very quiet.
And as you do that you charge
the comb.
I can hear the cracking.
Interesting.
So the comb is now charged.
Probably so am I and there it
comes.
See.
It's not as good as the glass
but same idea.
If you take your shirt off and
you make it and you make it dark
in your dormitory and you stand
in front of a mirror an amazing
experience.
And I'd be happy to do it for
you because but I told you I
really wear cotton and it
doesn't work with cotton so
well.
You really have to do it with a
nylon shirt.
And when you take that nylon
shirt
off not only do you hear the
cracking but you actually see
the glow of these teeny weeny
little sparks.
You actually are like a light
bulb.
It is an experiment that you
cannot miss.
And I would suggest you try
that this weekend.
Do it with a friend.
That's even more fun.
We'll all perhaps remember when
you just walk around.
Do your normal things during
the day.
There are rugs in rooms and
you want to leave the room and
you touch the doorknob and you
get a shock.
It's a spark that flies over.
It's electricity.
Even when you touch a person
you sometimes feel this shock.
When you cook and you take
saran wrap off these rolls the
damn stuff just doesn't want to
come off because as you roll it
off there is friction and it
gets charged and it often gets
crumpled up and it's very bad,
very difficult to handle it.
You've all experienced that.
Also cellophane around boxes
with chocolate the same thing
happens.
As you take it off you charge
it, whether you like it or not.
I now want to do an experiment
and I need a volunteer.
I need a student who actually
is wearing preferably not all
cotton but I think Simon you
have a beautiful wonderful nylon
parka.
So if you are willing to
sacrifice a
little bit for the sake of
science and come over here and
sit down here.
Just relax.
Make sure that your feet are
off the ground.
OK.
So what I'm going to do now
Simon I'm going to beat you with
cat fur.
And as I beat you with cat fur
you
will get charged and since I
don't want you to be the only
person who suffers under this
experiment I will also stand on
an insulated stool so if you
become for instance positively
charged I don't know whether
it's positive or negative I
would get the other amount of
charge.
So we share in the charge.
And as I beat you you will
charge up more and more and I
will charge
up more and more and then we
will have to convince the class
that that we are both charged.
And we will do that in a way
that will be hopefully rather
convincing.
I let me just start beating you
a little bit.
To make you feel at home.
We know each other right.
OK.
Now of course as I mentioned to
you these experiments work well
when it is dry and so if you are
too wet it won't work.
But let's see if you sweat a
little bit too much then it
doesn't work too well.
So we ready?
I have here in my hand a neon
flash tube.
And although we don't know
yet what voltage is because we
will learn about that in this
course, to get a good flash out
of these you need about a few
thousand volts.
And so we will see and we'll
make it dark shortly and I will
hold the flashlight,
the flashlight in one hand,
the neon discharge tube,
and then Simon will touch it on
the other side.
And if we've succeeded then you
may see some light.
So Simon look at me first,
don't touch it yet,
because we're going to make it
all the way dark.
You know where it is,
it's there, OK,
make it darker Marcos.
Touch it.
OK, try it again,
touch it again.
OK.
Thank you.
Can we have some light.
[applause] Thank you very much.
Equal charges repel each other.
I've shown that,
the demonstration with the
balloons.
Here we have an instrument
which is called the Vandegraaff.
It's named after Professor
Vandegraaff, who invented it.
It was an MIT professor.
And this instrument,
which I will not discuss in any
detail though but you will
understand it later on in the
course, I'll tell you all about
it later.
Just think of this instrument
as a super amber rod.
And although we don't know yet
what voltage is,
I mentioned already the twenty
thousand volts between Simon and
me, in this instrument you have
to think in terms of several
hundred thousand volts.
So this instrument is not
without danger.
But that of course makes it
more exciting to work with it.
So it's a super amber rod and
what I will do first now is to
put some confetti on top and
when we turn on the Vandegraaff
the confetti may at first go to
the charged dome,
it is already on top of it,
and when it picks up some of
the charge it will then spread
out because it it will repel.
So let's get some some light on
there which will make it a
little bit better to see.
Let me put some of this
on top.
It's just regular confetti,
pieces of paper.
All right now all I have to
remember is how to start the
most of the action has already
occurred.
I will put a little bit more
on.
[laughter] If you see sparks
don't worry yet.
[laughter] Put some more on.
More and nothing left for the
second
class.
[laughter] Make it perhaps a
little darker.
Ah that's too dark.
[laughter] OK.
We'll try it once more give it
a zap so look at the confetti on
top.
And I think it's quite
convincing.
Some of the confetti will stay
there.
Well that's the reason that
it's not a good conductor and
so it get it first sucked in and
if it doesn't get charge of the
Vandegraaff then it will not
spread out.
All right.
So now let's try for the first
time to be a little bit more
quantitative.
If I take two charges and we
use in
general we use for charge the
symbol Q.
So here we have Q one.
And here we have Q two.
And let's say they're separated
by a distance R.
And the unit vector in the
direction from one to two I call
that R roof one-two.
The roof stands for unit
vector.
These charges are equal,
both minus or both plus,
then they will repel each other
and so here there is a force F
which I call one-two.
It is the force on two due to
number one and since action
equals minus reaction force here
is to one equal in magnitude but
a hundred eighty degrees in
opposite direction.
Coulomb, the French physicist,
who did a lot of research on
this in the nineteenth
eighteenth century actually.
Coulomb found the following
relationship.
That the force is proportional
to the product of the two
charges.
So it's Q one times Q two.
Times a constant which nowadays
we call Coulomb's constant,
K.
Divided by the distance between
these charges squared.
And it is in direction of the
unit vector that goes from one
to two.
This is the force on number two
due to one.
And notice that this equation
is sign sensitive.
Because if Q one and Q two are
both negative the source is in
the the force is in this
direction and if they are both
positive it's also in this
direction as I have it.
However if the if one is
positive and one is negative you
get minus
this direction so this force
flips over and that one then
obviously also flips over.
In the SI units in this course
we will use for the unit of
charge the coulomb named after
this great man.
One coulomb charge is a
horrendous amount of charge.
More than you will ever see in
your lifetime.
We normally work with
microcoulombs,
sometimes even less than that.
The charge of one proton,
which is exactly the same as
the charge of one electron,
is approximately one point six
times ten to the minus nineteen
coulomb.
So one coulomb is something
like six times ten to the
eighteen protons or electrons if
the charge is negative.
This constant K in SI units is
nine times ten to the
ninth.
And the unit you can find out
because you know that this is
newtons, this is coulomb squared
and this is square meters.
So the unit is newton square
meters newtons square meters
divided by square coulombs.
But that's not so important.
No one ever thinks of it that
way.
For historical reasons which
may at
times be a pain in the neck for
you we write for K one divided
by four pi epsilon zero.
There is nothing magic about
that.
It's just a historical reason.
And so one divided by four pi
epsilon zero is nine times ten
to the ninth.
That's all that matters.
This epsilon zero has a name
it's called the permittivity of
free space.
But you can forget about that.
It's not important the name.
Notice that there is a clear
parallel with gravity.
Newton's law of gravity that
the force, which in that case is
always attracting,
gravity never repels,
is the product of two masses
and then you have here the
gravitational constant and again
you have the distance squared.
So there is an enormous
parallel between the two.
There's a great beauty that
electricity acts in a way that
is
very parallel to the way that
gravity works.
If I added a third charge,
for instance here,
Q three, and if now I want to
know what the force is on Q two,
then I use the superposition
principle which we've used many
times in eight oh one,
and we say OK the net force on
number two is the force due to
number one plus the force from
number three.
If number three if this is
positive and this is positive
and this were negative then this
force would be in this
direction, F one,
F three two and then the net
force on number two would be the
vectorial sum of these two.
Is it obvious that the
superposition principal works?
Not at all.
It's not at all obvious.
Do we believe in it?
Yes we do.
Why do we believe in it?
Because it's consistent with
all experiments that we have
done.
But the superposition principle
which is very powerful is really
not a matter of course.
But it works.
We can always use it.
And we will.
If you compare eight oh one
with eight oh two thereby
comparing electricity with
gravity you will
see that electric forces are
way more powerful than
gravitational forces.
And the way I can best show you
that is by taking two protons
which are a distance D apart.
Here is a proton and here is a
pro- proton and they are
separated by a distance D.
They repel each other.
And the force by which they
repel each other is of course
extremely easy to calculate.
We know Coulomb's law.
That law is called after
Coulomb.
And so the force,
the electric force with which
they repel each other,
this is just the magnitude now
of the force,
is the charge of the proton
which is one point six times ten
to the minus nineteen but I have
to square that,
I have to multiply it by
Coulomb's constant,
which is nine times ten to the
ninth, and I divide it by D
squared.
That's the electric force.
If I want to know the
gravitational force,
which is the force with which
they attract each other,
these are repelling forces,
but I just want magnitudes
here, then I have to take the
mass of the proton,
which is one point seven times
ten to the minus twenty-seven I
have to square that remember M
one
times M two times the
gravitational constant.
The gravitational constant in
SI units is six point seven
times ten to the minus eleven
and I divide that by D squared.
If now I compare the electric
force with the gravitational
force, so I divide one by the
other, notice that the D
cancels.
They both have D squared
downstairs.
And so you will easily be able
to
show that this ratio is roughly
ten to the thirty-six.
So the electric force is
thirty-six orders of magnitude
more potent than the
gravitational attraction.
This teaches you some respect
perhaps for eight oh two.
If these were the only forces
that acted on the protons and
you bring them in the nucleus
which has a size
of only ten to the minus
twelfth centimeters then the
acceleration that the proton
will experience is the electric
force divided by the mass of the
proton.
F equals MA.
Basis of eight oh one.
And if you take this electric
force when you make D ten to the
minus twelfth centimeters which
is ten to the minus fourteen
meters and you calculate this
ratio you will find
that it is twenty-six orders of
magnitude higher than the
gravitational acceleration on
earth.
Twenty-six orders of magnitude
higher.
So you wonder what the hell
holds the nucleus together.
If there is such a tremendous
force on these protons.
Well, what is holding them
together are the nuclear forces,
which we do not fully
understand, but thank goodness
the nuclear forces are not part
of eight oh two so I will leave
that alone for now.
So what holds our world
together?
Well on the nuclear scale ten
to the minus twelve centimeters
very important are the nuclear
forces.
On an atomic scale up to
thousands of kilometers,
it's really electric forces
that hold our world together.
But on a much larger scale,
planets and stars and the
galaxy, it is gravity that holds
our world together.
And now you may say ah that's
very inconsistent with what you
just told us because didn't you
tell us that D
cancels if you compare gravity
with electricity.
Yes, however,
most objects are neutral or
very close to neutral and so if
you take the earth it is very
unlikely even that the earth as
a whole would have a charge of
more than ten coulombs.
That probably is already an
exaggeration.
So if I take the earth and I
take the moon and I put on both
a charge of ten
coulombs, here's the earth and
here's the moon,
and I put say just arbitrarily
ten coulombs here and that is
put on here either minus,
minus ten coulombs,
so they will attract each
other, but given their distance,
it's almost nothing.
The force is negligibly small.
But of course the force of
gravity, which is proportional
to their masses,
wins and in this particular
case if you take the earth and
the
moon the gravitational force
wins over the electric force by
twenty-five orders of magnitude.
So even though our immediate
surroundings are dominated by
electric forces,
including your own body for
that matter, the behavior of the
universe on a large scale is
dictated by gravity.
We will use various instruments
to measure charge in a
quantitative way
and one of the instruments that
you will see we will use it
often in the lectures that are
to come, is called an
electroscope.
It's a very simple instrument.
In general it is just a
conducting rod.
It could be aluminum,
metal, and at the end are two
pieces of tinsel,
two pieces of aluminum foil,
and often there is a nice knob
here, and if I touch this with a
charged object,
then because this can conduct
electricity, this can conduct
the fire, as defined by Benjamin
Franklin, if I touch it with an
object which is positively
charged, then this object will
become positively charged.
If I touch it with an object
which is negatively charged it
will become negatively charged.
And you see now here these two
very light pieces of aluminum
foil will repel each other.
And so you will see that this
shows a certain angle,
and the more charge there is
the larger that angle.
Sort of gives us a way of doing
some quantitative measurements.
There are other electroscopes
which are not too different.
There's one central rod and
they would have one leaf hanging
there and when you charge that
one up then
this leaf will go out and if
the charge is more it will go
out even further.
I don't have an electroscope
now here.
But what I want you to see that
if I charge myself up and I hold
in my hands these Christmas tree
tinsels, that in a way if I get
enough charge on me,
then these tinsels will
spread out.
It's an idea that immediately
follows from the fact that you
get a certain amount of charge,
whether it's negative charge
from me, or whether I'm
positively charged,
that doesn't make any
difference, these tinsels will
spread out.
And of course the best way I
can do that is if I charge
myself with the Vandegraaff.
And as I said earlier
experiments of this nature are
not entirely without risk.
And so there's always the
possibility of course that I
don't survive this
demonstration.
[laughter] But don't worry
because in that case there will
be someone else who will lecture
eight oh two except he is not
likely to show this
demonstration again.
[laughter] So you might as well
take a close look because this
may be the only time you will
ever see it.
So I will give you some nice
light on the Vandegraaff and
it's always a
scary moment for me,
sleepless nights about the
Vandegraaff.
Am I going to turn it on,
Marcos, or you have the courage
to turn it on?
You will turn it on?
OK, hold it Marcos,
this is too close for comfort.
You ready?
Are you nervous?
Feel.
[laughter] So look at the
tinsels and try not to look at
me please.
Go ahead.
I am now a living electroscope.
[laughter] If the if the
weather is cooperating today and
if I had long hair you might
even see that my hair would
start to act like
an electroscope.
We can try that too.
Why don't you throw it.
[laughter] [applause]
Is it working?
OK, well, this weekend make
sure you take this nylon shirt
off in front of the mirror and
enjoy your enjoy the experiment
at home.
Don't try this ever.
See you Friday.
[applause]