I'll tell you what a Markov
matrix is, so this matrix A will
be a Markov matrix and I'll
explain how they come in
applications.
And -- and then if I have time,
I would like to say a little
bit about Fourier series,
which is a fantastic
application of the projection
chapter.
Okay.
What's a Markov matrix?
Can I just write down a typical
Markov matrix,
say .1, .2, .7,
.01,
.99 0, let's say,
.3, .3, .4.
Okay.
There's a -- a totally just
invented Markov matrix.
What makes it a Markov matrix?
Two properties that this --
this matrix has.
So two properties are -- one,
every entry is greater equal
zero.
All entries greater than or
equal to zero.
And, of course,
when I square the matrix,
the entries will still be
greater/equal zero.
I'm going to be interested in
the powers of this matrix.
And this property,
of course, is going to -- stay
there.
It -- really Markov matrices
you'll see are connected to
probability ideas and
probabilities are never
negative.
The other property -- do you
see the other property in there?
If I add down the columns,
what answer do I get?
One.
So all columns add to one.
All columns add to one.
And actually when I square the
matrix, that will be true again.
So that the powers of my matrix
are all Markov matrices,
and I'm interested in,
always, the eigenvalues and the
eigenvectors.
And this question of steady
state will come up.
You remember we had steady
state for differential equations
last time?
When -- what was the steady
state -- what was the
eigenvalue?
What was the eigenvalue in the
differential equation case that
led to a steady state?
It was lambda equals zero.
When -- you remember that we
did an example and one of the
eigenvalues was lambda equals
zero, and that -- so then we had
an E to the zero T,
a constant one -- as time went
on, there that thing stayed
steady.
Now what -- in the powers case,
it's not a zero eigenvalue.
Actually with powers of a
matrix, a zero eigenvalue,
that part is going to die right
away.
It's an eigenvalue of one
that's all important.
So this steady state will
correspond -- will be totally
connected with an eigenvalue of
one and its eigenvector.
In fact, the steady state will
be
the eigenvector for that
eigenvalue.
Okay.
So that's what's coming.
Now, for some reason then that
we have to see,
this matrix has an eigenvalue
of one.
This property,
that the columns all add to one
-- turns out -- guarantees that
one is an eigenvalue,
so that you can
actually find the eigenvalue --
find that eigenvalue of a Markov
matrix without computing any
determinants of A minus lambda I
-- that matrix will have an
eigenvalue of one,
and we want to see why.
And then the other thing is --
so the key points -- let me --
let me write these underneath.
The key points are -- the key
points are lambda equal one is
an eigenvalue.
I'll add in a little -- an
additional -- well,
a thing about eigenvalues --
key point two,
the other eigenval- values --
all other eigenvalues are,
in magnitude,
smaller than one -- in absolute
value, smaller than one.
Well, there could be some
exceptional case when -- when an
eigen -- another eigenvalue
might have magnitude equal one.
It never has an eigenvalue
larger than one.
So these two facts --
somehow we ought to -- linear
algebra ought to tell us.
And then, of course,
linear algebra is going to tell
us what the -- what's -- what
happens if I take -- if -- you
remember when I solve -- when I
multiply by A time after time
the K-th thing is A to the K u0
and I'm asking what's special
about this -- these powers of A,
and very likely the quiz will
have a problem to computer s- to
computer some powers of A or --
or applied to an initial vector.
So, you remember the general
form?
The general form is that
there's
some amount of the first
eigenvalue to the K-th power
times the first eigenvector,
and another amount of the
second eigenvalue to the K-th
power times the second
eigenvector and so on.
A -- just -- my conscience
always makes me say at least
once per lecture that this
requires
a complete set of eigenvectors,
otherwise we might not be able
to expand u0 in the eigenvectors
and we couldn't get started.
But once we're started with u0
when K is zero,
then every A brings in these
lambdas.
And now you can see what the
steady state is going to be.
If lambda one is one -- so
lambda one equals one to the
K-th power and these other
eigenvalues are smaller than one
-- so I've sort of scratched
over the equation there to -- we
had this term,
but what happens to this term
-- if the lambda's smaller than
one,
then the -- when -- as we take
powers, as we iterate as we --
as we go forward in time,
this goes to zero,
right?
Can I just -- having scratched
over it, I might as well scratch
further.
That term and all the other
terms are going to zero because
all the other eigenvalues
are smaller than one and the
steady state that we're
approaching is just -- whatever
there was -- this was -- this
was the -- this is the x1 part
of un- of the initial condition
u0 -- is the steady state.
This much we know from general
-- from -- you know,
what we've already done.
So I want to see why -- let's
at least see number one,
why one is an eigenvalue.
And then there's actually -- in
this chapter we're interested
not only in eigenvalues,
but also eigenvectors.
And there's something special
about the eigenvector.
Let me write down what that is.
The eigenvector x1 -- x1 is the
eigenvector and all its
components are positive,
so the steady state is
positive, if the start was.
If the start was -- so -- well,
actually,
in general, I -- this might
have a -- might have some
component zero always,
but no negative components in
that eigenvector.
Okay.
Can I come to that point?
How can I look at that matrix
-- so that was just an example.
How could I be sure -- how can
I see that a matrix --
if the columns add to zero --
add to one, sorry -- if the
columns add to one,
this property means that lambda
equal one is an eigenvalue.
Okay.
So let's just think that
through.
What I saying about -- let me
ca- let me look at A,
and if I believe that one is an
eigenvalue, then I should be
able to subtract off one times
the identity and then I would
get a matrix that's,
what, -.9, -.01 and -.6 -- wh-
I took the ones away and the
other parts, of course,
are still what they were,
and this is still .2 and .7 and
-- okay, what's -- what's up
with this matrix now?
I've shifted the matrix,
this Markov matrix by one,
by the identity,
and what do I want to prove?
I -- what is it that I believe
this matrix -- about this
matrix?
I believe it's singular.
Singular will -- if A minus I
is singular, that tells me that
one is an eigenvalue,
right?
The eigenvalues are the numbers
that I subtract off -- the
shifts -- the numbers that I
subtract from the diagonal -- to
make it singular.
Now why is that matrix
singular?
I -- we could compute its
determinant, but we want to see
a reason that would work for
every Markov matrix not just
this particular random example.
So what is it about that
matrix?
Well, I guess you could look at
its columns now -- what
do they add up to?
Zero.
The columns add to zero,
so all columns -- let me put
all columns now of -- of -- of A
minus I add to zero,
and then I want to realize that
this means A minus I is
singular.
Okay.
Why?
So I could I --
you know, that could be a quiz
question, a sort of theoretical
quiz question.
If I give you a matrix and I
tell you all its columns add to
zero, give me a reason,
because it is true,
that the matrix is singular.
Okay.
I guess actually -- now what --
I think of -- you know,
I'm thinking of two or three
ways to
see that.
How would you do it?
We don't want to take its
determinant somehow.
For the matrix to be singular,
well, it means that these three
columns are dependent,
right?
The determinant will be zero
when those three columns are
dependent.
You see, we're --
we're at a point in this
course, now, where we have
several ways to look at an idea.
We can take the determinant --
here we don't want to.
B- but we met singular before
that -- those columns are
dependent.
So how do I see that those
columns are dependent?
They all add to zero.
Let's see, whew -- well,
oh, actually,
what -- another thing I know is
that the -- I would like to be
able to show is that the rows
are dependent.
Maybe that's easier.
If I know that all the columns
add to zero, that's my
information, how do I see that
those three rows
are linearly dependent?
What -- what combination of
those rows gives the zero row?
How -- how could I combine
those three rows -- those three
row vectors to produce the zero
row vector?
And that would tell me those
rows are dependent,
therefore the columns are
dependent,
the matrix is singular,
the determinant is zero --
well, you see it.
I just add the rows.
One times that row plus one
times that row plus one times
that row -- it's the zero row.
The rows are dependent.
In a way, that one one one,
because it's multiplying the
rows,
is like an eigenvector in the
-- it's in the left null space,
right?
One one one is in the left null
space.
It's singular because the rows
are dependent -- and can I just
keep the reasoning going?
Because this vector one one one
is --
it's not in the null space of
the matrix, but it's in the null
space of the transpose -- is in
the null space of the transpose.
And that's good enough.
If we have a square matrix --
if we have a square matrix and
the rows are dependent,
that
matrix is singular.
So it turned out that the
immediate guy we could identify
was one one one.
Of course, the -- there will be
somebody in the null space,
too.
And actually,
who will it be?
So what's -- so -- so now I
want to ask about the
null space of -- of the matrix
itself.
What combination of the columns
gives zero?
I -- I don't want to compute it
because I just made up this
matrix and -- it will -- it
would take me a while -- it
looks sort of doable
because it's three by three but
wh- my point is,
what -- what vector is it if we
-- once we've found it,
what have we got that's in the
-- in the null space of A?
It's the eigenvector,
right?
That's where we find X one.
Then X one, the eigenvector,
is in the null space of A.
That's the eigenvector
corresponding to the eigenvalue
one.
Right?
That's how we find
eigenvectors.
So those three columns must be
dependent -- some combination of
columns --
of those three columns is the
zero column and that -- the
three components in that
combination are the eigenvector.
And that guy is the steady
state.
Okay.
So I'm happy about the -- the
thinking here,
but I haven't given -- I
haven't completed it because I
haven't found x1.
But it's there.
Can I -- another thought came
to me as I was doing this,
another little comment that --
you -- about eigenvalues and
eigenvectors,
because of A and A transpose.
What can you tell me about
eigenvalues of A -- of A and
eigenvalues of A transpose?
Whoops.
They're the same.
They're -- so this is a little
comment -- we -- it's useful,
since eigenvalues are generally
not easy to find -- it's always
useful to know some cases where
you've got them,
where -- and this is -- if you
know the eigenvalues of A,
then you know the eigenvalues
of A transpose.
eigenvalues of A transpose are
the same.
And can I just,
like, review why that is?
So to find the eigenvalues of
A, this would be determinate of
A minus lambda I equals zero,
that gives me an eigenvalue of
A -- now how can I get A
transpose into the picture here?
I'll use the fact that the
determinant of a matrix and the
determinant of its transpose are
the same.
The determinant of a matrix
equals the determinant of a --
of the transpose.
That was property ten,
the very last guy in our
determinant list.
So I'll transpose that matrix.
This leads to -- I just take
the matrix and transpose it,
but now what do I get when I
transpose lambda I?
I just get lambda I.
So that's -- that's all there
was to the
reasoning.
The reasoning is that the
eigenvalues of A solved that
equation.
The determinant of a matrix is
the determinant of its
transpose, so that gives me this
equation and that tells me that
the same lambdas are eigenvalues
of A transpose.
So that, backing up to the
Markov case, one is an
eigenvalue of A transpose and we
actually found its eigenvector,
one one one,
and that tell us that one is
also an eigenvalue of A -- but,
of course, it has a different
eigenvector,
the -- the left null space
isn't the same as the null space
and we would have to find it.
So there's some vector here
which is x1 that produces zero
zero zero.
Actually, it wouldn't be that
hard to find,
you know, I -- as I'm talking
I'm thinking,
okay, I going to follow through
and actually find it?
Well, I can tell from this one
-- look, if I put a point six
there and a point seven there,
that's what -- then I'll be
okay in the last row,
right?
Now I only -- remains to find
one guy.
And let me take the first row,
then.
Minus point 54 plus point 21 --
there's some big number going in
there, right?
So I have -- just to make the
first row come out zero,
I'm getting minus point 54 plus
point 21, so that was minus
point 33 and what -- what do I
want?
Like thirty three hundred?
This is the first time in the
history of linear algebra that
an
eigenvector has every had a
component thirty three hundred.
But I guess it's true.
Because then I multiply by
minus one over a hundred -- oh
no, it was point 33.
So is this just -- oh,
shoot.
Only 33.
Okay.
Okay, so there's the
eigenvector.
Oh, and notice that it -- that
it turned -- did turn out,
at least, to be all positive.
So that was,
like, the theory -- predicts
that part, too.
I won't give the proof of that
part.
So 30 -- 33 -- point six 33
point seven.
Okay.
Now those are the ma- that's
the linear algebra part.
Can I get to the applications?
Where do these Markov matrices
come from?
Because that's -- that's part
of this course and absolutely
part of this lecture.
Okay.
So where's -- what's an
application of Markov matrices?
Okay.
Markov matrices -- so,
my equation,
then, that I'm solving and
studying is this equation
u(k+1)=Auk.
And now A is a Markov matrix.
A is Markov.
And I want to give an example.
Can I just create an example?
It'll be two by two.
And it's one I've used before
because it seems to me to bring
out the idea.
It's -- because we have two by
two, we have two states,
let's say California and
Massachusetts.
And I'm looking at the
populations in those two states,
the people in those two states,
California and Massachusetts.
And my matrix A is going to
tell me in a -- in a year,
some movement has happened.
Some people stayed in
Massachusetts,
some people moved to
California, some smart people
moved from California to
Massachusetts,
some people stayed in
California and made a billion.
Okay.
So that -- there's a matrix
there with four entries and
those tell me the fractions of
my population -- so I'm making
-- I'm going to use fractions,
so they won't be negative,
of course, because -- because
only positive people are in-
involved here -- and they'll
add up to one,
because I'm accounting for all
people.
So that's why I have these two
key properties.
The entries are greater equal
zero because I'm looking at
probabilities.
Do they move,
do they stay?
Those probabilities are all
between zero and one.
And the probabilities add to
one because everybody's
accounted for.
I'm not losing anybody,
gaining anybody in this Markov
chain.
It's -- it conserves the total
population.
Okay.
So what would be a typical
matrix, then?
So this would be u,
California and u Massachusetts
at time t equal k+1.
And it's some matrix,
which we'll think of,
times u California and u
Massachusetts at time k.
And notice this matrix is going
to stay the same,
you know, forever.
So that's a severe limitation
on the example.
The example has a -- the same
Markov matrix,
the same probabilities act at
every time.
Okay.
So what's a reasonable,
say -- say point nine of the
people in California at time k
stay there.
And point one of the people in
California move to
Massachusetts.
Notice why that column added to
one, because we've now accounted
for all the people in California
at time k.
Nine tenths of them are still
in California,
one tenth are here at time k+1.
Okay.
What about the people who are
in Massachusetts?
This is going to multiply
column two, right,
by our
fundamental rule of multiplying
matrix by vector,
it's the -- it's the population
in Massachusetts.
Shall we say that -- that after
the Red Sox, fail again,
eight -- only 80 percent of the
people in Massachusetts stay and
20 percent
move to California.
Okay.
So again, this adds to one,
which accounts for all people
in Massachusetts where they are.
So there is a Markov matrix.
Non-negative entries adding to
one.
What's the steady state?
If everybody started in
Massachusetts,
say, at -- you know,
when the Pilgrims showed up or
something.
Then where are they now?
Where are they at time 100,
let's say, or maybe -- I don't
know, how many years since the
Pilgrims?
300 and something.
Or -- and actually where will
they be, like,
way out a million
years from now?
I -- I could multiply -- take
the powers of this matrix.
In fact, you'll -- you would --
ought to be able to figure out
what is the hundredth power of
that matrix?
Why don't we do that?
But let me follow the steady
state.
So what -- what's my starting
-- my starting u Cal,
u Mass at time zero is,
shall we say -- shall we put
anybody in California?
Let's make -- let's make zero
there, and say the population of
Massachusetts is --
let's say a thousand just to --
okay.
So the population is -- so the
populations are zero and a
thousand at the start.
What can you tell me about this
population after -- after k
steps?
What will u Cal plus u Mass add
to?
A thousand.
Those thousand people are
always accounted for.
But -- so u Mass will start
dropping from a thousand and u
Cal will start growing.
Actually, we could see -- why
don't we figure out what it is
after one?
After one time step,
what are the populations at
time one?
So what happens in one step?
You multiply once by that
matrix and, let's see,
zero times this column -- so
it's just a thousand times this
column, so I think we're getting
200 and 800.
So after the first step,
200 people have -- are in
California.
Now at the following step,
I'll multiply again by this
matrix -- more people will move
to California.
Some people will move back.
Twenty people will come back
and, the -- the net result will
be that the California
population will be above 200 and
the Massachusetts below 800 and
they'll still add up to a
thousand.
Okay.
I do that a few times.
I do that 100 times.
What's the population?
Well, okay, to answer any
question like that,
I need the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors,
right?
As soon as I've -- I've created
an example, but as soon as I
want to solve anything,
I have to find eigenvalues and
eigenvectors of that matrix.
Okay.
So let's do it.
So there's the matrix .9,
.2, .1, .8 and tell me its
eigenvalues.
Lambda equals -- so tell me one
eigenvalue?
One, thanks.
And tell me the other one.
What's the other eigenvalue --
from the trace or the
determinant -- from the -- I --
the trace is what -- is,
like, easier.
So the trace of that matrix is
one point seven.
So the other eigenvalue is
point seven.
And it -- notice that
it's less than one.
And notice that that
determinant is point 72-.02,
which is point seven.
Right.
Okay.
Now to find the eigenvectors.
This is -- so that's lambda one
and the eigenvector -- I'll
subtract one from the diagonal,
right?
So can I do that in light let
-- in light here?
Subtract one from the diagonal,
I have minus point one and
minus point two,
and of course these are still
there.
And I'm looking for its --
here's -- here's -- this is
going to be x1.
It's the null space of A minus
I.
Okay, everybody sees that it's
two and one.
Okay?
And now how about -- so that --
and it -- notice that that
eigenvector is positive.
And actually,
we can jump to infinity right
now.
What's the population at
infinity?
It's a multiple -- this is --
this eigenvector is
giving the steady state.
It's some multiple of this,
and how is that multiple
decided?
By adding up to a thousand
people.
So the steady state,
the c1x1 -- this is the x1,
but that adds up to three,
so I really want two -- it's
going to be two thirds of a
thousand and one third of a
thousand,
making a total of the thousand
people.
That'll be the steady state.
That's really all I need to
know at infinity.
But if I want to know what's
happened after just a finite
number like 100 steps,
I'd better find this
eigenvector.
So can I --
can I look at -- I'll subtract
point seven time -- ti- from the
diagonal and I'll get that and
I'll look at the null space of
that one and I -- and this is
going to give me x2,
now, and what is it?
So what's in the null space of
-- that's certainly singular,
so I know my calculation is
right,
and -- one and minus one.
One and minus one.
So I'm prepared now to write
down the solution after 100 time
steps.
The -- the populations after
100 time steps,
right?
Can -- can we remember the
point one -- the -- the one with
this two one eigenvector and the
point seven with the minus
one one eigenvector.
So I'll -- let me -- I'll just
write it above here.
u after k steps is some
multiple of one to the k times
the two one eigenvector and some
multiple of point seven to the k
times the minus one one
eigenvector.
Right?
That's --
I -- this is how I take -- how
powers of a matrix work.
When I apply those powers to a
u0, what I -- so it's u0,
which was zero a thousand --
that has to be corrected k=0.
So I'm plugging in k=0 and I
get c1 times two one and c2
times minus one one.
Two equations,
two constants,
certainly independent
eigenvectors,
so there's a solution and you
see what it is?
Let's see, I guess we already
figured that c1 was a thousand
over three, I think -- did we
think that had to
be a thousand over three?
And maybe c2 would be -- excuse
me, let -- get an eraser -- we
can -- I just -- I think we've
-- get it here.
c2, we want to get a zero here,
so maybe we need plus two
thousand over three.
I think that has to work.
Two times a thousand over three
minus two thousand over three,
that'll give us the zero and a
thousand over three and the two
thousand over three will give us
three thousand over three,
the thousand.
So this is what we approach --
this part, with the point seven
to the k-th power is the part
that's disappearing.
Okay.
That's -- that's Markov
matrices.
That's an example of where they
come from, from modeling
movement of people with no gain
or loss, with total -- total
count conserved.
Okay.
I -- just if I can add one more
comment,
because you'll see Markov
matrices in electrical
engineering courses and often
you'll see them -- sorry,
here's my little comment.
Sometimes -- in a lot of
applications they prefer to work
with row vectors.
So they -- instead of -- this
was natural for us,
right?
For all the eigenvectors to be
column vectors.
So our columns added to one in
the Markov matrix.
Just so you don't think,
well, what -- what's going on?
If we work with row vectors and
we multiply vector times matrix
-- so we're multiplying from
the left -- then it'll be the
then we'll be using the
transpose of -- of this matrix
and it'll be the rows that add
to one.
So in other textbooks,
you'll see -- instead of col-
columns adding to one,
you'll see rows add to one.
Okay.
Fine.
Okay, that's what I wanted to
say about Markov,
now I want to say something
about projections and even
leading in -- a little into
Fourier series.
Because -- but before any
Fourier stuff,
let me make a comment about
projections.
This -- so this is a comment
about projections onto --
with an orthonormal basis.
So, of course,
the basis vectors are q1 up to
qn.
Okay.
I have a vector b.
Let -- let me imagine -- let me
imagine this is a basis.
Let -- let's say I'm in n by n.
I'm -- I've got,
eh,
n orthonormal vectors,
I'm in n dimensional space so
they're a complete -- they're a
basis -- any vector v could be
expanded in this basis.
So any vector v is some
combination, some amount of q1
plus some amount of q2 plus some
amount of qn.
So -- so any v.
I just want you to tell me what
those amounts are.
What are x1 -- what's x1,
for example?
So I'm looking for the
expansion.
This is -- this is really our
projection.
I could -- I could really use
the word expansion.
I'm expanding the vector in the
basis.
And the special thing about the
basis is that it's orthonormal.
So that should give me a
special formula for the answer,
for the coefficients.
So how do I get x1?
What -- what's a formula for
x1?
I could -- I can go through the
projection -- the Q transpose
Q, all that -- normal equations,
but -- and I'll get -- I'll
come out with this nice answer
that I think I can see right
away.
How can I pick -- get a hold of
x1 and get these other x-s out
of the equation?
So how can I get a nice,
simple
formula for x1?
And then we want to see,
sure, we knew that all the
time.
Okay.
So what's x1?
The good way is take the inner
product of everything with q1.
Take the inner product of that
whole equation,
every term, with q1.
What will happen to that last
term?
The inner product --
when -- if I take the dot
product with q1 I get zero,
right?
Because this basis was
orthonormal.
If I take the dot product with
q2 I get zero.
q1 I get one.
So that tells me what x1 is.
q1 transpose v,
that's taking the dot product,
is x1 times q1 transpose q1
plus a bunch of zeroes.
And this is a one,
so I can forget that.
I get x1 immediately.
So -- do you see what I'm
saying -- is that I have an
orthonormal basis,
then the coefficient that I
need for
each basis vector is a cinch to
find.
Let me -- let me just -- I have
to put this into matrix
language, too,
so you'll see it there also.
If I write that first equation
in matrix language,
what -- what is it?
I'm writing --
in matrix language,
this equation says I'm taking
these columns -- are -- are you
guys good at this now?
I'm taking those columns times
the Xs and getting V,
right?
That's the matrix form.
Okay, that's the matrix Q.
Qx is v.
What's the solution
to that equation?
It's -- of course,
it's x equal Q inverse v.
So x is Q inverse v,
but what's the point?
Q inverse in this case is going
to -- is simple.
I don't have to work to invert
this matrix Q,
because of the fact that the --
these columns are orthonormal,
I know the inverse to that.
And it is Q transpose.
When you see a Q,
a square matrix with that
letter Q, the -- that just
triggers -- Q inverse is the
same as Q transpose.
So the first component,
then -- the first component of
x is the first row times
v, and what's that?
The first component of this
answer is the first row of Q
transpose.
That's just -- that's just q1
transpose times v.
So that's what we concluded
here, too.
Okay.
So -- so nothing Fourier here.
The -- the key ingredient here
was
that the q-s are orthonormal.
And now that's what Fourier
series are built on.
So now, in the remaining time,
let me say something about
Fourier series.
Okay.
So Fourier series is -- well,
we've got a function f of x.
And we want to write it as a
combination of -- maybe
it has a constant term.
And then it has some cos(x) in
it.
And it has some sin(x) in it.
And it has some cos(2x) in it.
And a -- and some sin(2x),
and forever.
So what's -- what's the
difference between this type
problem and the one above it?
This one's infinite,
but the key property of things
being orthogonal is still true
for sines and cosines,
so it's the property that makes
Fourier series work.
So that's called a Fourier
series.
Better write his name up.
Fourier series.
So it was Joseph Fourier who
realized that,
hey, I could work in function
space.
Instead of a vector v,
I could have a function f of x.
Instead of orthogonal vectors,
q1, q2 , q3,
I could have orthogonal
functions, the constant,
the cos(x), the sin(x),
the s- cos(2x),
but infinitely many of them.
I need infinitely many,
because my space is infinite
dimensional.
So this is, like,
the moment in which we leave
finite dimensional vector spaces
and go to infinite dimensional
vector spaces and our basis --
so the vectors are now
functions -- and of course,
there are so many functions
that it's -- that we've got an
infin- infinite dimensional
space -- and the basis vectors
are functions,
too.
a0, the constant function one
-- so my basis is one cos(x),
sin(x), cos(2x),
sin(2x) and so on.
And the reason Fourier series
is a success is that those are
orthogonal.
Okay.
Now what do I mean by
orthogonal?
I know what it means for two
vectors to be orthogonal -- y
transpose x equals zero,
right?
Dot product equals zero.
But what's the dot product of
functions?
I'm claiming that whatever it
is, the dot product -- or we
would more likely use the word
inner product of,
say, cos(x) with sin(x) is
zero.
And cos(x) with cos(2x),
also zero.
So I -- let me tell you what I
mean
by that, by that dot product.
Well, how do I compute a dot
product?
So, let's just remember for
vectors v trans- v transpose w
for vectors, so this was
vectors, v transpose w was v1w1
+...+vnwn.
Okay.
Now functions.
Now I have two functions,
let's call them f and g.
What's with them now?
The vectors had n components,
but the functions have a whole,
like, continuum.
To graph the function,
I just don't have n points,
I've got this whole graph.
So I have functions -- I'm
really trying to ask you what's
the inner product of this
function f with another function
g?
And I want to make it parallel
to this the best I can.
So the best parallel is to
multiply f (x) times g(x) at
every x -- and here I just had n
multiplications,
but here I'm going to have a
whole range of x-s,
and here
I added the results.
What do I do here?
So what's the analog of
addition when you have -- when
you're in a continuum?
It's integration.
So that the -- the dot product
of two functions will be the
integral of those functions,
dx.
Now I have to say -- say,
well, what are the limits of
integration?
And for this Fourier series,
this function f(x) -- if I'm
going to have -- if that right
hand side is going to be f(x),
that function that I'm seeing
on the right,
all those
sines and cosines,
they're all periodic,
with -- with period two pi.
So -- so that's what f(x) had
better be.
So I'll integrate from zero to
two pi.
My -- all -- everything -- is
on the interval zero two pi
now, because if I'm going to
use these sines and cosines,
then f(x) is equal to f(x+2pi).
This is periodic -- periodic
functions.
Okay.
So now I know what -- I've got
all the right words now.
I've got a vector space,
but the vectors are functions.
I've got inner products and --
and the inner product gives a
number, all right.
It just happens to be an
integral instead of a sum.
I've got -- and that -- then I
have the idea of orthogonality
-- because, actually,
just -- let's just check.
Orthogonality -- if I take the
integral -- s- I -- let me do
sin(x) times cos(x) -- sin(x)
times cos(x) dx from zero to two
pi -- I think we get zero.
That's the differential of
that, so it would be one half
sine x squared,
was that right?
Between zero and two pi --
and, of course,
we get zero.
And the same would be true with
a little more -- some trig
identities to help us out -- of
every other pair.
So we have now an orthonormal
infinite basis for function
space, and all we want to do is
express a function in that
basis.
And so I --
the end of my lecture is,
okay, what is a1?
What's the coefficient -- how
much cos(x) is there in a
function compared to the other
harmonics?
How much constant is in that
function?
That'll -- that would be an
easy question.
The answer a0 will come out to
be the average value of f.
That's the amount of the
constant that's in there,
its average value.
But let's take a1 as more
typical.
How will I get -- here's the
end of the lecture,
then -- how do I get a1?
The first Fourier coefficient.
Okay.
I do just as I did in the
vector case.
I take the inner product of
everything with cos(x) Take the
inner product of everything with
cos(x).
Then on the left -- on the left
I have -- the inner product is
the integral of
f(x) times cos(x) cx.
And on the right,
what do I have?
When I -- so what I -- when I
say take the inner product with
cos(x), let me put it in
ordinary calculus words.
Multiply by cos(x) and
integrate.
That's what inner products are.
So if I multiply that whole
thing by
cos(x) and I integrate,
I get a whole lot of zeroes.
The only thing that survives is
that term.
All the others disappear.
So -- and that term is a1 times
the integral of cos(x) squared
dx zero to 2pi equals -- so this
was the left side and this is
all that's left on
the right-hand side.
And this is not zero of course,
because it's the length of the
function squared,
it's the inner product with
itself, and -- and a simple
calculation gives that answer to
be pi.
So that's an easy integral and
it turns out to be pi,
so that a1 is one over pi times
there -- times this integral.
So there is,
actually -- that's Euler's
famous formula for the -- or
maybe Fourier found it -- for
the coefficients in a Fourier
series.
And you see that it's exactly
an expansion in an orthonormal
basis.
Okay, thanks.
So I'll do a quiz review on
Monday and then the quiz itself
in Walker on Wednesday.
Okay, see you Monday.
Thanks.