PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, I'd like to tackle a
problem in Markov matrices.
Specifically, we're going to
start with this problem which
almost has a physics origin.
If we have a particle that jumps
between positions A and
B with the following
probabilities--
I'll just state it--
if it starts at A and jumps to
B with probability 0.4 or
starts at A and stays at A with
probability 0.6 or if it
starts at B then it goes to A
with probability 0.2 or stays
at B with probability 0.8,
we'd like to note the
evolution of the probability of
this particle over a long
period of time.
So specifically the problem
we're interested today is if
we have a particle and we know
that it starts at position A,
what is the probability that
it is at position A and the
probability that it's at
position B after one step,
after n steps, and then finally
after an infinite
number of steps?
So I'll let you think about this
problem for a moment and
I'll be back.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So the main difficulty with
this problem is that it's
phrased as a physics problem.
And we need to convert it into
some mathematical language to
get a handle on it.
So specifically, what we'd like
to do is to convert this
into a matrix formulism.
So what we can do is we can
write this little graph down
and describe everything in this
graph using a matrix.
So I'm going to call this matrix
A, and I'm going to
associate the first row of A
with particle position A and
particle position B. And I'll
associate the first and second
columns with particles positions
A and B. And then
what I'm going to do is I'm
going to fill in this matrix
with the probability
distributions.
So, specifically what's going to
go in this top left corner?
Well, the number 0.6, which
represents the probability
that I stay at position A, given
that I start at position
A. What's going to go here in
the bottom left hand corner?
Well, we're going to put 0.4,
because this is the
probability that I wind up at
B, given that I start at A.
And then lastly, we'll fill in
these other two columns or the
second column with
0.8 and 0.2.
So I'll just state briefly
this is what's
called a Markov matrix.
And it's called Markov, because
first off, every
element is positive or 0.
And secondly, the sum of the
elements in each column is 1.
So if we note 0.4 plus 0.6
is 1, 0.8 plus 0.2 is 1.
And these matrices come up all
the time when we're talking
about probabilities and the
evolution of probability
distributions.
OK.
So now once we've encoded this
graph using this matrix A, we
now want to tackle
this problem.
So I'm going to introduce the
vector P, and I'm going to use
a subscript 0 is to denote the
probability that the particle
is at time 0.
So we're told that the particle
starts at position A.
So at time 0, I'm going to use
the vector 1, 0 again.
I'm going to match the top
component of this vector with
the top component of this matrix
and the first column of
this matrix.
And then likewise the second
component of this vector with
the second row and second
column of this matrix.
And we're interested in how does
this probability evolve
as the particle takes
many steps.
So for one step, what's the
probability of the particle
going to be?
Well, this is the beauty of
introducing matrix notation.
I'm going to denote P1 to be
the probability of the
particle after one step.
And we see that we can write
this as the matrix A
multiplied by P0.
So the answer is 0.6 and 0.4.
And I achieve this just by
multiplying this matrix by
this vector.
OK?
So this concludes part one.
Now part two is a
little trickier.
So part two is n-steps.
And to tackle this problem,
we need to use
a little more machinery.
So first off, I'm going to note
that P1 is A times P0.
Likewise, P2--
so this is the position of
the-- the probability
distribution of the particle
after two steps.
This is A times P1, which
is A squared times P0.
And we note that there's
a general trend.
After n-steps--
so Pn--
the general trend is it's going
to be this matrix A
raised to the nth power,
multiply the vector P0.
So how do we take the
nth of a matrix?
Well, this is where we use
eigenvectors and eigenvalues.
So recall, that we can take
any matrix A that's
diagonizable and write it as
U D U inverse, where D is a
diagonal matrix and this matrix
U is a matrix whose
columns correspond to the
eigenvectors of A.
So for this problem I'm, just
going to state what the
eigenvalues and eigenvectors
are.
And I'll let you
work them out.
So because it's a Markov matrix,
we always have an
eigenvalue which is 1.
And in this case, we have
an eigenvector U
which is 1 and 2.
In addition, the second
eigenvalue is 0.4.
And the eigenvector
corresponding to
this one is 1, -1.
And I'll just call these
U1 and U2, like that.
OK, we can now write this big
matrix U as 1, 2, 1, -1.
D is going to be--
now I have to match things up.
If I'm going to put the first
eigenvector in the first
column, we have to stick 1 in
the first column as well and
then 0.4 like this.
And then lastly, we also have
U inverse which I can just
work out to be -1/3, one over
the determinant, times -1, -1,
-2, and 1, which simplifies
to this.
OK, so now if we take A and
raise it to the power of n, we
have this nice identity that
all the U and U inverses
collapse in the middle.
And we're left with U, D to
the n, U inverse, P0.
Now raising the a diagonal
matrix to the power of n is a
relatively simple thing to do.
We just take the eigenvalues
and raise them to
the power of n.
So when we compute this product,
there's a question of
what order do we do things?
Now these are 2 by 2 matrices,
so in theory we could just
multiply a 2 by 2 matrix, 2 by
2 matrix, 2 by 2 matrix, and
then on a vector which
is a 2 by 1 matrix.
But if you're in a test and
you're cramped for time, you
want to do as little
computations as possible.
So what you want to do is you
want to start on the right
hand side and then
work backwards.
So if we do this, we end up
obtaining 1, 2, this is going
to be to the power
of n, 1/3, 1, 2.
OK, so for this last part, I'm
just going to write down the
final answer.
And I'll let you work out the
multiplication of matrices.
So we have for Pn, 1/3, 2 times
0.4 to the n, plus 1,
-2, 0.4 to the n, plus 2.
And this is the final
vector for P of n.
So this finishes up Part 2.
And then lastly for Part
3, what happens
when n goes to infinity?
Well, we have the answer
for any n.
So we can just take the limit
as n goes to infinity.
Now, specifically as n goes to
infinity, 0.4 raised to some
very large power vanishes.
So these two terms drop off.
And at the end of the day,
we're left with P
infinity is 1/3 1, 2.
OK?
So just to recap, we started off
with a particle starting
at A, and then after a very long
time, the particle winds
up with a probability
distribution which
is 1/3 1 and 2.
And this is quite characteristic
of Markov
matrix chains.
Specifically, we note that 1/3
1, 2 is a multiple of the
eigenvector corresponding
to eigenvalue 1.
So even though the particle
started at position A, after a
long period of time, it tended
to forget where it started and
approached, diffused into this
uniform distribution.
OK.
I'd like to finish up here.
And I'll see you next time.