Welcome back to recitation.
What I'd like us to do in
these two problems is to
understand how to compute the
flux in three dimensions-- the
flux of a vector in
three dimensions--
across a surface, without
maybe doing a lot of
calculations.
So we're going to see if we can
figure out how to do these
problems without doing
a lot of computation.
So the first one is to find
the flux of the vector k
through the infinite cylinder
x squared plus y
squared equals 1.
So notice this doesn't depend
on z, but in fact at every
height it is a unit circle.
So it's an infinite cylinder.
And then the second problem I'd
like you to think about
and to try is to to find the
flux of the vector j through
one square that has side length
1 in the x-z plane.
So you pick any square in the
x-z plane of side length 1 and
find the flux of j through
that square.
And so I think that that's
enough information.
So why don't you try both of
those problems, pause the
video, and then when you're
ready to see my explanation of
how they work, bring
the video back up.
OK, welcome back.
Again, what we're trying to do
is to understand the flux of a
vector field across a surface.
And we're hoping to do it
with the least amount of
calculation possible for these
particular problems. So
obviously it's going to be
helpful if you can draw a
picture to draw a picture.
So I'm going to draw the surface
that is the infinite
cylinder first and then I'm
going to look at the
vector field k.
So let me draw my picture
first. If these are my
coordinate axes, I get--
I think you have something
usually like this.
This is x, this is
y, and this is z.
This is how you do them
in your class.
And so it's not going to be a
great picture but I'm going to
try and make it look like a
cylinder up here coming down.
So this is in fact going to be
infinitely long, going down
forever, but I'll stop it
somewhere down here.
And then so every slice in the
z at a fixed height for z is
going to be a circle.
I should think about these are
intersecting the x and y axes
at (1, 0) and (0, 1).
So there's actually a sort of
unit circle down here as well.
Now that's the surface.
Now what does the vector
field look like?
Well, in general what does the
vector field look like? k is
just a constant vector field
that points in this direction.
This is k.
So k at every point on the
surface is just the vector
that's pointing straight
up in this direction.
And the normal to the surface,
if you think about it, the
normal to the surface
is independent of z.
It doesn't depend on z at all.
It is always going to be a
vector that is in the x-y
direction only.
It's going to be--
essentially at every point it's
going to be sitting in
the plane z equals
the constant.
Because if you think about what
you have, you have a unit
circle at every height.
And it doesn't vary in the z
direction at all, with the
bending of that unit circle.
So in fact the normal is always
going to point straight
out from the unit circle.
There's going to be
no z component.
Or I should say the
z component's 0.
Maybe that's the best
way to say it.
So that means that the
normal dotted with k
is going to be 0.
And so the answer to the first
question is the flux of k
through the infinite cylinder
is actually 0.
So the answer to part a is 0.
Been getting a lot of zeroes
in my video so far.
The next one is to find the flux
of the vector j through
one square in the x-z plane
where the squares
have side length 1.
So I can draw any
square I want.
That seems to imply that maybe
it'll be the same answer
everywhere.
So let's see what we get.
Let me draw a picture
for part b.
Label this first maybe.
Let me label my axes.
And I'm going to draw the
simplest one I can.
That does not look like
a square but I'm
not great at this.
There we go.
So this is my surface sitting
in the x-z plane.
This side length is 1 and
this side length is 1.
So what is the normal
to that surface?
Well, we have two choices and
so we will actually have a
possibility of two answers.
So let me point out that the
normal to the surface-- well,
what direction does
it point in?
Because this plane is in the x-z
plane, the normal to the
surface is either j
or it's minus j.
And so if I'm integrating j
dotted with the normal over
the surface--
I'll just call this surface
capital R--
if I'm integrating over R j
dotted with the normal dS, j
dotted with the normal
is going to be
either 1 or minus 1.
And hopefully that makes
sense because j--
let me draw this--
j is pointing
exactly in the y direction.
And the normal is either in
this direction or in the
opposite direction.
Up to how I choose to
orient the surface.
And so j dotted with n is either
plus or minus 1, and so
I just get the area of R with
a plus or minus-- ooh, that
doesn't look like a plus
or minus-- with a
plus or minus in front.
Depending on whether j dotted
with n is 1 or whether j
dotted with n is minus 1.
So the solution for this
computation is just the area
of R or minus the area
of R. Well, what's
the area of the region?
The area, it's a square
of side length 1,
so it has area 1.
So the final answer is
just plus or minus 1.
So again, let me remind you
what we're trying to do.
We're trying to determine these
fluxes of vector fields
across surfaces without doing
a lot of calculation.
And in the first case we had a
vector field that pointed in
the z direction only, and
the normal was only
in the x and y direction.
And so the flux was 0, even
though it was a vector field
on an infinite cylinder,
the flux was still 0.
And in the other case, I had
actually here, I had a surface
that was exactly in
the x-z plane.
And so its normal was exactly
either in the same direction
as j or 180 degrees
around from j.
So j dotted with the normal was
either plus or minus 1.
And so I only had to know
the area of the region.
Which is why it didn't
matter where I
moved this unit square.
I didn't tell you where the
unit square had to sit so
that's where you can see
why it didn't matter.
Because it's just the area.
OK, I think that's
where I'll stop.