CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video I would like us
to use Green's theorem to
compute the following integral
where it's the integral over
the curve c, where c is
the circle drawn here.
So the circle is oriented so
the interior is on the left
and it's centered at the point
where x equals a, y equals 0.
So the integral--
you can read it but I will read
it also for you-- it's
the integral of 3x squared y
squared dx plus 2x squared
times the quantity
1 plus xy dy.
So you are supposed
to use Green's
theorem to compute that.
And why don't you pause the
video, give it a shot, and
then when you're ready to see my
solution you can bring the
video back up.
OK, welcome back.
Well, what we're going to do,
obviously to use Green's
theorem to compute this--
because I gave you a big hint
that you're supposed to use
Green's theorem because we
have an integral over
a closed curve.
And what we're going to do is
now take the integral of
another certain integrand--
obviously related in
some way to this--
over the region that
I will shade here.
So we're interested in this
shaded region now.
So let me write down what
Green's theorem is and then
we'll put in the important
parts.
OK, so just to remind you, I'm
not going to write down all
the hypotheses of Green's
theorem that we need, but the
point that I want to make is
that if we start the integral
over this closed curve c of
mdx plus ndy we can also
integrate over the region that
C encloses of N sub x minus M
sub y dy dx.
So that is ultimately what
we're going to do.
And so in this case again, as
always, m is going to be the
function associated with
the dx portion.
It's the ice component
of the vector field.
And n is going to be the
function associated
here with the dy.
That's standard obviously.
So now what we want to do is
transform what we have there
into something that
looks like this.
So the region--
I'm just going to keep calling
it R for the moment--
but the region R you'll notice
is the thing that I shaded in
the drawing.
And so now let's compute
what this is--
well you have the capacity
to do that.
That's just some straight
taking derivative.
So I'm just going to write down
what it is and not show
you all the individual pieces.
So I'll just write down what
you get and then the
simplified version.
So you get 6x squared y
plus 4x is N sub x.
And then M sub y is negative
6x squared y.
And I'm going to call dy dx, I'm
just going to refer to it
now as dA, because that makes
it a lot easier to write.
Oh, I guess I should
call this--
well, dA, this is the area.
The volume form there.
So this simplifies and I just
get the integral of 4x over
this region dA.
Now this-- you saw an example
of this in lecture of how to
deal with these types of
problems. At this point, if I
really wanted to I could figure
out what the bounds are
in that region in terms of x and
y, and I could do a lot of
work and integrate it
all, or I could
remember one simple fact.
Which is that if I have--
I think you see it in class as
x bar-- the center of mass
should be equal to 1 over the
volume of the region times the
integral of x dA over
the region.
That's what we know.
This should be-- this maybe
doesn't look like a v. But so
in this case volume
is area, isn't it?
Maybe I should write area, that
might make you nervous.
So if I take the area--
I could just say A of R-- if
I take the area, 1 over the
area, and then I multiply by the
integral of x over R with
dy dx with respect to dA, then
I get the center of mass.
Well, let's look at what in
this picture-- what is the
center of mass here?
If I want to balance this thing
on a pencil tip, if I
want to balance this disc--
assuming the density is
everywhere the same on a pencil
tip-- where am I going
to put the pencil?
I'm going to put it right
at the center.
The x value there is a, the
y value there is 0.
So if I had the y center of
mass, I would want 0.
But I want the x center
of mass, so I want a.
This x bar is actually
equal to, from the
picture, is equal to a.
And now let's notice
what I've done.
I have taken--
I had this quantity here--
I've taken this quantity except
for the 4 and I have a
way of writing explicitly what
this quantity is without
actually doing any of
the integration.
I haven't done any sophisticated
things at this
point except know what the
center of mass is.
So also what is the area
of the region?
I'm going to need that.
The area of the region-- it's
a circle of radius a.
So the area is pi a squared.
So this quantity is
pi a squared.
And all this together tells me
that the integral of x over R
dA, if I solve for this part,
I get a times pi a squared.
So I get pi a cubed.
And that only differs from
our answer by one thing.
There's a scalar--
you multiply by 4 and that
gives us what we want.
I said differs from
our answer.
Differs from what we
want by one thing.
We just multiplied by 4 there,
so we multiply by 4 here.
So in fact--
maybe there looks like there
was a little magic here, so
let me point out some of the
key points at the end.
I started off knowing I was
trying to integrate 4x over
the region R. And R in this case
was a circle centered at
(a, 0) and of radius a.
And then I said, well,
I don't want to do a
lot of work for this.
So I'm going to not cheat, but
I'm going to use my knowledge
of the center of mass
to make this easier.
So the center of mass is equal
to 1 divided by the area of
the region times the integral
of x over the region.
So I want to find the integral
of x over the region, I just
solve for the integral
of x over the region.
I just solve for that part.
The center of mass-- from just
looking at the picture and
understanding what the center of
mass means-- the center of
mass in the x component is a.
The area is pi a squared.
So I end up with a pi a
cubed when I solve for
the integral of x.
And then because I wanted the
integral of 4x, I just
multiply by 4.
And so the final answer is
actually 4 pi a cubed.
So what I was trying to find,
if you remember, was I was
trying to find the value when
I integrated over this curve
of a certain vector field.
And that one was going
to be a little messy
to do it that way.
But Green's theorem, actually
there's a lot of cancellation
which makes it much easier, and
then the center of mass is
a nice little trick
to use at the end.
And then the calculation
is quite simple.
So I think that's
where I'll stop.