The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
Some content in this audio is
not covered under a Creative
Commons license.
For more information see the
course materials on the MIT
OpenCourseWare website.
GUEST SPEAKER: --to Abe, who
is going to give us a guest
lecture on art games.
And today's reading, the proctor
reading is kind of
like part two of a lot of the
things that Jason maybe talked
about when we did simulations.
If you guys remember, is a
quality reading that a
[INAUDIBLE] question, where
that came from.
One thing that I think was of
interest was that there are a
couple of responses
to that article.
If you scroll all the way down
to the bottom of the article
that these responses
vary [INAUDIBLE]
back to them.
And those are kind of
interesting, because it just
carries on a conversation.
People actually just turning his
article into basically a
blog post and then
write on it.
And they were pretty good.
But a lot of that was kind
of the state of art game
discussion back in 1999, I
think, I think a pretty old
article, where they were very
much thinking about games have
to be simulations.
Games and narratives, blaaach.
Storytelling is like some
other mediums' domain.
It's all about the simulation.
Arguably at that time there
wasn't a big discussion of an
art games movement.
There were other games
movements, like new games
which were really more about
people interacting with you,
trying to get games to where
people were more cooperative,
less competitive, and
less cutthroat.
There were other movements
about people--
they were probably advertising
game movements.
And there was a lot of work
in people making months of
computer games that effectively
made it
unplayable, but made really
pretty images in the process.
So that [UNINTELLIGIBLE], for
instance, where everything
becomes black and white
and is striped,
including the monsters.
There's no way you can see what
the hell's going on, but
they look pretty cool.
AUDIENCE: Have you seen--
I think it's 96 kilobytes--
there was a competition in full
game [INAUDIBLE]-- no
it's 4 kilobytes, I think.
It's a 4-kilobyte game in full
3-D, with multiple levels,
extremely clever, including
the music and everything.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, yeah.
AUDIENCE: Have you ever heard
of this or seen this?
GUEST SPEAKER: There are
a couple of those.
A lot of those come up
with the demoscene.
Demoscene, which I will put
off to some other time--
AUDIENCE: It's very
impressive, too.
It's like very--
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, yeah.
It's kind of this weird thing
of computer hacking, really,
really fast and really, really
compact coding, and visualized
statics and music, which
goes more like a
digital music video.
Only there were some people who
added mouse control, and
game play into it and made
these kind of games.
But that's very different from
the art game scene that we
have today, or at least
what's commonly
described as art games.
So I'd like Abe to talk about
what happened since then,
since 1999.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, yeah.
Hi, guys.
I'm Abe.
I work here at the lab.
I play a bunch of your games.
I've met a bunch of you.
It's nice to be here.
Phillip asked me to come
in to talk about,
quote/unquote, art games.
I think largely because it's a
kind of, I'll say, sector of
game development that my work
at Gambit tends to intersect
with, especially recently.
And I think, too, that it's--
AUDIENCE: Sorry.
I was choking from--
GUEST SPEAKER: I think, too,
that it's a sector that's a
little bit confusing--
and possibly confusing, too.
And so, just to give
you guys a sense--
when you asked me about this
it actually made me think,
like, oh, yeah, cool, I'll
talk about this art games
movement or whatever,
but that of course--
ooh, wait.
I'm locked into some kind
of weird mode right now.
Sorry.
OK.
That brings up this question,
which is, are games art?
And just to give you a sense
for how this little talk
thing, whatever, is going to go,
I'm going to talk a little
bit about this question, give
you examples of what people
have said about this, and
opinions that I think are
particularly important,
particularly
valid on this subject.
I also after that want to show
you some examples, some
historical and then kind of
moving forward examples.
I'm actually going to get some
of you guys to just come up
here and maybe even play some of
these examples that I think
are particularly important.
And I'd really like it if we
can keep this less of a me
talking at you and you engaging
me as you have
questions on this.
Because me blabbing at you as
you fall asleep is maybe good
for a nap, but less useful for
getting anything out of this.
So we'll try to structure this
as a conversation, and then
I'll try to pull back, hearken
back, to any of my teacher
instincts and see if I
can get you engaged.
But we'll see.
So are games art?
I hate this question.
Let's start off by saying that
I fundamentally find it
abhorrent, and I hear
it all the time.
And it's aggravating to me
because I think it's
incontrovertibly yes.
I think that you can't possibly
come up with any
other answer other than yes,
games are art, games have art,
yes, yes, yes, right?
But it keeps coming up.
And it keeps becoming a
question-- and I should say,
too, that this is a wholly
biased and slanted talk.
This is my perspective on this,
and hopefully by the
time-- you'll be like, wow,
he's absolutely right.
There's no way that games could
be anything but art.
Or at least they are
art, and then some.
So this guy, who's a little
hard to see right now, but
he's handily brought up,
recently brought into the
fore, and that's Roger Ebert
of Siskel and Ebert fame.
Or since you guys are, some of
you, younger than me, probably
Ebert and Roeper.
He had some interesting,
controversial comments recently.
And I pulled this quote,
"Nevertheless, I'm being
convinced that in principle--"
I love that
he put that in italics.
"--video games cannot be art.
Perhaps it is foolish for me to
say never, because never as
Rick Wakeman informs us,
is a long, long time.
Let me just say that no video
gamer now living will survive
long enough to experience the
medium as an art form."
So apparently we should all be
dead already, according to
Ebert, because we wouldn't
have lived long enough to
experience the medium
as an art form.
But here's a guy who, even
though I don't think he's a
particularly good film critic,
is a popular film critic.
And he's weighing in on a
medium that he doesn't
particularly understand.
And I think it's important to
look at what exactly is he
doing when he makes
this statement.
He's in this business of
classification, right?
He's in this business of saying,
all right, we've got
this subject called art.
What can we say falls under that
subset and what does not?
So he says things like painting,
sculpture, dance,
opera, literature, film can all
be classified as art and
that games are not.
Probably some other things.
I don't know where he stands
on comic books.
I don't think he's written about
it yet, but I'm sure
he'd probably--
I don't know what he thinks
about pornography.
Although, since it's in
film form, maybe he
does think it's art.
It's unclear.
He hasn't weighed
in on that yet.
But the interesting
thing about this
is, this is not new.
This is like a high-culture,
low-culture debate that's been
going on for a really
long time.
And I think it's particularly
hilarious because
he would use films.
And films had to fight out of
the low-culture phenomenon to
gain respect as a high-culture
medium.
So he's working--
reviewing a medium that was once
conceived as low culture,
had to work really hard to be
considered high culture.
And now he's saying, look, my
films are high culture, your
video games are low culture.
Which is totally hilarious
because in the past 50 years,
this has been completely
collapsed by post-modernism.
That's a whole 'nother
talk altogether.
Maybe high culture
and low culture
don't even exist anymore.
So Ebert brings us all back.
And you get everybody upset.
And a bunch of trolls are on
his website saying really
terrible things about him
and about what he said.
But he kind of reinvigorated
this talk.
And so new scientists, inspired
by this Ebert
controversy and looking for con
tips on CultureLab asked
the question, can
games be art?
And they sent it out to a bunch
of game scholars saying,
what is your opinion on this?
Ian Bogost is a very smart
guy and says some really
interesting things.
This is really why I'm not gonna
read the whole thing,
but in the first paragraph he
brings up things like Fountain
by Marcel Duchamp, which is a
urinal in a museum, for those
of you who don't
know about it.
And that was a statement, a
piece of art that he was
literally trying to confront,
what high culture defines as
art by taking, literally, a
urinal, putting it upside down
on a pedestal, entitling it
Fountain, and putting it in a
museum, which is the pinnacle
of high culture.
If you can make it in a
museum, you're art.
And so this is something
that--
He mentions Yoko Ono's
performance art, where she's
sitting in a chair, and she has
scissors next to her and
the audience is invited to come
cut her clothes off one
piece at a time.
A lot of this kind of stuff.
Andy Warhol pop culture
paintings,
Mondrian's abstract paintings.
And he says a lot in that
first paragraph.
But I think this interesting
part that I've
pseudo-highlighted down
here is interesting.
I'm starting in the middle.
He says if the purpose of art
is indeed to force us to see
something we thought we
understood in a new light,
perhaps the most fundamental
move video games have made in
the artistic tradition is in
the very eliciting of the
question, can video
games be art?
I think that's really
interesting.
So the fact that people are
even asking this question
suggests that video games are
doing something that we
traditionally conceive
of art doing.
That's, I think, a really
powerful statement, that we're
even having this discussion
renders the question moot in
some senses, which
is I would say
classic Bogostian wordplay.
I think I just made something
up called Bogostian.
I should tweet all about it.
John Sharp, from the Savannah
College of Art and Design, has
had a lot of thoughts on this.
He's actually a great person to
talk about this, because he
studies video games, but he does
it from an art history
background as well.
That's pretty good and useful.
He talks about some interesting
things here.
Similarly to what Ian is doing,
he's talking a bit
about how video games and art
are doing some similar things
at times, and yet games have
certain affordances that other
media do not.
He says at the end here, which
I think is interesting, all
this poses the question of why
are we concerned with giving
video games the status of art?
This is one of the reasons
why I hate this question.
Are we simply trying
to legitimize them?
Does being called, quote/unquote
art change the
qualities of video games.
Only if we can answer these
questions can we move the
conversation forward.
I think he's reacting here
to the question itself.
Actually, he and Ian both are
reacting to the question, Ian
saying the question invalidates
itself and John
Sharp now saying that this
question, it's not helping us.
Asking how does calling it art,
what does that do for the
medium, that's the important
question.
Here's some thoughts about the
question and some more
evidence for why I think the
question, are video games art
is just quite wrong.
Mary Flanagan takes it as being
assumed that video games
are art, which I think
is actually great.
In Critical Play she doesn't go
to great lengths to define
video games as art.
She just looks at art and
she looks at games
and compares them.
She just assumes that
this is so.
I think this is a really nice
quote from the beginning of
her Critical Play book, which
is that, "Critical Play is
built on the premise that, as
with other media, games carry
beliefs within their
representation systems and
mechanics." This is really
important. "Artists using
games as a medium of
expression--" Again, good use
of italics.
"--,then, manipulate elements
common to games--
representation systems and
styles, rules of progress,
codes of conduct, context of
reception, winning and losing
paradigms, ways of interacting
in a game-- for they are the
material properties of games,
much like marble and chisel or
pen and ink bring with them
their own intended
possibilities, limitations,
and conventions."
It's a great point.
You would have a really hard
time making a painting with a
chisel and no paint, like you
were using marble and a
chisel, a you were trying
to make a painting.
Two different things.
Both are art.
It's the same thing
with games.
Games have rule sets, games
have systems, games have
win-and-loss paradigms.
They have all these things
that are conventions and
things that we associate with
even our definition of what a
game is, which is
at times faulty.
But those are our tools.
Those are how we communicate
things.
I think her first sentence
is really important.
I'm guessing with the stuff
that you've been talking
about-- them and Gonzalo
Frasca--
that's coming through.
I actually see that
in your games.
You're trying to-- so, for
example I play-tested that
FedEx game, and I play-tested
the game about marriage.
There's all kinds of meaning in
those systems and meanings
in those choices that you get
that are being communicated.
And that's very similar to what
an artist would do with
any other medium.
You're communicating a message
through those.
And sometimes we do
it accidentally.
It's not always explicit.
We make something--
I would say that the graveyard
and when you get divorced and
you put your divorced person
in the graveyard is an
interesting choice for me,
because it was creating an
equivalence between divorce and
death, which I think is
kind of interesting.
That's just one interesting
example.
So Mary Flanagan in her book
talks about this art movement
called Fluxus.
Before I go into--
any kind of thoughts
or questions?
Does anybody else think-- does
anybody think video games
aren't art still?
It's okay.
Oh, crap, we're gonna fight.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] when we
were designing art, so our art
project now is you have
to choose a real-world
system and relate it.
That's what we're
all working on.
And one of the big things that
really helped us get started
is, what is the message we want
to get across to each set
of ablutions?
What is a bad ablution?
Do you want to say that's
random, do you want to say
that's this?
And how do we express that,
which [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Totally.
And it gets even crazier
when you take--
when you try to look at
systems that are not
particularly tangible.
You maybe looked at it, but
Elude is a game about
depression.
There aren't exactly tangible
kind of road maps the way
there are with FedEx systems,
for clinical depression.
And yet you're looking at
things like emotions,
feelings, stuff like that, that
we might call abstract,
or just not immediate.
How do you communicate
those in systems?
It's really tricky.
AUDIENCE: I have friends that
talk about all their games
which are like more --genic
or more abstract.
Does Ebert [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
art?
GUEST SPEAKER: I mean, it's
a really good question.
AUDIENCE: What would
he say about that?
GUEST SPEAKER: I think that
falls along the same lines as,
like I said, does Ebert consider
pornography art?
It's a really difficult
question.
That's a much larger art history
debate, about has high
culture and low culture
completely collapsed?
Has mass-media proliferation
deteriorated conceptions of
what really high culture art
are, versus low culture.
I don't have particularly
good answers for that.
I think just as all of the other
media that we looked at,
does a Jerry Bruckheimer
film count as art?
Just like we would look at that
and ask that question, we
don't then deny the entire
medium of film from the
possibility of being artistic.
There seems to be this desire,
because the majority of games
in our sector--
which I actually do,
too, because if you
go far enough back--
I should say video games--
Because most video games are
commercially intended and
involve fairly similar things,
does that preclude the medium
from the possibility
of being artistic?
I go back to that Ebert comment
about he says they
can't possibly be, or at least
he says never is a long time.
But not in our lifetime, it
apparently is impossible.
It's a good point.
AUDIENCE: There's actually
interesting effects with the
game we're designing which is
essentially city building and
city creation in the time
of the Roman Empire.
And we actually didn't
intend to instill any
meaning in the game.
But once we actually designed
the mechanics and stuff, we
realized that it was essentially
a game about the
rich getting richer and trying
to control the board.
So it's like there's almost
this inherent meaning that
came out from just designing
the game.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, yeah.
You almost can't help but have
it happen in some instances.
It reminds me of a good thing
that Brenda Brathwaite put in
one of her talks once, which
was about the game
Civilization, the mod
Colonization for sig IV, which
is a great mod in which you
play one of the European
colonizers and you come
over to the New World.
And there's indigenous
peoples there.
You have to negotiate with them
at first, but eventually
you just beat them up and take
their land, or they just give
it to you because you're more
powerful than they are.
And she was making the point,
there's this great box art,
the Native Americans in the
corner and the Conquistador in
the middle, the Spanish,
and the Dutch.
And it's like, if you were a
Native American how would you
respond to this game?
And I'm like, yeah, I'm totally
making America again.
And other people would be like,
oh my god, you basically
just wiped out my ancestors,
thanks.
So it's true, sometimes you
falling into meaning.
It's something.
And I think, again, a lot
of art does that, right?
And some art did it quite
purposely, where they weren't
divulging the meaning, they were
inviting readings on it.
So, Fluxus.
Fluxus is this really
interesting
mid-20th-century art--
they rejected the term
"movement," they called it an
"attitude"--
that Mary Flanagan talks
about a bit in her
Critical Play book.
It's actually quite
interesting.
It really starts out early
with John Cage.
Have you guys heard of
him, the composer?
He's most famous for this piece
of music that he wrote
where, I forget the duration,
AUDIENCE: 4'33".
GUEST SPEAKER: 4'33", yeah.
it's 4 minutes and 33 seconds
of not, well, not playing.
AUDIENCE: He rests.
GUEST SPEAKER: He rests.
Exactly.
So you'd sit down
at the piano.
You'd pull out the music and
everyone would hush.
And then for 4 minutes and 33
seconds you'd sit there,
possibly with your hands
on the keys.
And then after the time, you
would stand up, and you'd take
your bow, and the audience
would erupt
into incredible applause.
He was really testing the idea
of what they eventually called
scores, or event scores.
This idea that music is an art
form where you can write it
down, and then it becomes
performable.
It becomes this thing that
someone can engage with.
We don't think of paintings
that way.
We don't think of paintings as
having a score, having some
kind of, how do I engage
with this?
It sounds kind of like games,
in figuring out how does
interactivity work in
artistic mediums.
Really interested in
indeterminacy, too.
I think you'll see in some of
these examples, they're really
kind of pushing on the
boundaries of what art has
been doing to this point.
They call it intermedia, meaning
that the more multiple
modes that you can use for
communicating it was really
important to the attitude.
Simplicity was really
big, having basic
systems and basic scores.
And then this idea of play
was really important.
Yoko Ono, it's funny we sort
of just attach her to John
Lennon, but she was an artist
before she was in a
relationship with him.
She's actually well known as
one of these kind of Fluxus
practitioners.
This is interesting.
This is the Fluxus manifesto.
I wanted to put this up because
I think you can get a
little bit of a sense for what
they were trying to go for.
They were taking the word
"flux" and putting
definition-- but then they
were mending it here, so,
purge the world of Bourgeois
sickness, intellectual,
professional, and commercialized
culture.
Purge the world of dead art,
imitation, artificial art,
abstract art, illusionistic
art, mathematical art.
I like this, purge the
world of Europeanism.
I don't think that's a word.
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Promote
a revolutionary
flood and tide in art.
Promote living art, anti-art,
non-art reality.
These things sound
totally crazy.
I love the, "to be fully
grasped," but then it crosses
out "fully." I don't doubt
that was completely
intentional, or if they wrote
fully grasped and were like,
oh, this is gonna be great.
I'm crossing it out so
you can see that I
crossed out fully grasped.
We want it to be not
fully grasped.
We want it to be partially
grasped by all people.
Not only critics feel this
class is professional.
It's just a really interesting
thing, and it sort of screams
the avant-garde.
They were trying to push
against boundaries.
They're trying to figure out
what is the edge of the medium
and then how can we
jump way off it?
Some of the classic Fluxus works
were these things called
Flux boxes or Flux kits.
Flux kits tended to
have event scores.
This is one of the most
famous called Water
Yam by George Brecht.
And basically this is a box
with 70 event scores.
These are an example of
these event scores.
It's interesting.
The event scores really seem
like rule systems.
They're like the instructions
to your board game, except
they're kind of whacky.
If you look at air conditioning,
the rule is move
through the place.
Which is really interesting.
If you encounter this game and
you're like, all right, I'm
gonna play Water Yam.
And you're like, move
through the place.
I think that's pretty
characteristic of movement,
right, present you with some
sort of objective or some sort
of requirement, but one that
is abstract or nebulous, or
just kind of strange.
This one's even better.
On a white chair, a great tape
measure, alphabet, flag,
black, and spectral color.
In this instance, it's not
even clear what you're
necessarily supposed to do.
Are you supposed to compile
these things on a white chair?
Are you supposed to sit on a
white chair and hold all of
these things?
It's not particularly clear.
This is the playfulness
of this movement.
This is the energy of this
of avant-garde movement.
You can see the relationship,
I hope, between
rule systems and these.
The next example is, I think,
an even better one.
But you can see how
they're playing
around with these ideas.
At least they're incorporating
interactivity
into these art movements.
And keep in mind, these are
being shown in galleries These
are being shown in
high-art places.
These are being sent out to
their friends as works of art.
This one's great.
This is White Chess
by Yoko Ono.
It's often depicted on its own
and you have to imagine what
the rules are.
But I actually think her rules
as they are written are
actually pretty important
to it.
She says, play it for as long
as you remember who is your
opponent and who is
your own self.
Very interesting wordage.
What are the complications
with white chess.
Anyone.
Any thoughts?
Based on your perceptions
of non-white chess or
white-and-black chess?
AUDIENCE: You'd get into arguing
about is that my pawn
or your pawn?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes, you
definitely-- it will be hard
to keep track of,
I would think.
That's why she said, "as long
as you can remember." Any
other weirdness from this?
AUDIENCE: Who is friend
and who is enemy?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah,
certainly.
This sort of like, wait,
was that my piece?
Was that your piece?
Not only does that complicate
your relationship to the other
player, but now it's like, to
the game itself, it's like,
wait, what was the strategy
I was doing?
AUDIENCE: Friendly or
unfriendly fire?
GUEST SPEAKER: I mean, it's
really hard to keep track of
stuff in chess.
What about the board?
AUDIENCE: He writes off the king
and the queen by mistake
because you don't have to--
AUDIENCE: There's not really any
actual boxes on the board.
AUDIENCE: There are boxes--
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah,
they're all white.
That complicates things a little
bit, too, because you
need to remember how
you were moving.
AUDIENCE: How large is--
GUEST SPEAKER: This
one's really big.
This is like a garden
installment of White Chess.
And I think the cool thing, too,
this is another example
of the movement.
As long as you have
the components you
could play this game.
You could create
this art piece.
I think the intent
is not go play my
installation of White Chess.
It's that this is the
rules, these are the
pieces, it can be played.
That screams game,
that screams that
portability of a game.
Again, this wasn't considered
anything but art, except
probably by people who
turned their nose at
this sort of thing.
they've Any thoughts on
what White Chess could
be about, in a--
AUDIENCE: Two different
sides merging to one.
And so you eventually get,
why am I fighting?
Who is my enemy in
this situation?
GUEST SPEAKER: Sure, sure.
Any other thoughts?
AUDIENCE: Racial relations.
GUEST SPEAKER: Sure,
racial relations.
AUDIENCE: It's probably a whole
antiwar thing of, like,
are we actually destroying
ourselves?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, and that's
an interesting thing.
Yoko Ono was a decidedly antiwar
activist at the time
she was making this
in the early '60s.
One thing-- you can't take
anything for granted, but the
pieces aren't all black,
they're all white.
So I think the race thing
does play a factor.
The inability to remember
who you're attacking and
who you are, even.
I think that's actually why
I really like her words.
Because, "for as long as you
can remember who's your
opponent and who is your own
self," there's something about
incorporating your own self in
there, not just saying what
your pieces are.
She's not saying can you
remember what your pieces are.
She's saying remember who you're
playing against versus
who you are.
That's very different
verbiage.
I think it's very much
a game about who are
you fighting, anyway?
What is the point of war, what
is the purpose of war?
And how does war particularly
function?
And in the rhetoric of
the time it makes a
lot of sense, right?
So that's Yoko Ono's White
Chess, which is part of the
Fluxus [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Yes, it's pretty cool.
Actually, Fluxus and artists in
this period have a really
interesting relationship
with chess.
There's like some quote,
and I'm gonna
butcher it, but it's--
I think it was Marcel Duchamp
saying that not all chess
players are artists, but all
artists are chess players, or
something like that.
He is particularly fascinated
with chess, and you can see
elements of chess in
his work, ought to
be painted or whatever.
AUDIENCE: He was completely
obsessed with chess.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: He played
it really hard.
He wasn't necessarily
a very good player,
but he played a lot.
GUEST SPEAKER: Very into it.
So now I'm gonna move out
of this Fluxus movement.
I just wanted to show you
a couple examples.
But I think this next one is
actually an interesting-- this
is a current theme that I'm
really excited about, which is
called Sixteen Tons.
This is a game I unfortunately
have not been able to play
yet, but I've witnessed
play because it's a
game for four players.
This was created by Eric
Zimmerman and Nathalie Pozzi.
It's a really interesting
game.
It's a little hard to see
from these pictures.
But it's this giant circle, I
would say almost the size of
this room, of corrugated
cardboard, maybe even bigger,
a little bit bigger
than this room.
Inside you've got this array
of colored and circles in
these pretty hefty steel
tubes that have color.
Let's go through the rules.
The first thing you notice is
that they contextualize the
title, Sixteen Tons, with a
quote from the song, "You load
16 tons, and what do you get?
Another day older and
deeper in debt."
This is doing an interesting
thing that John Sharp, who you
can see in the middle, thinks
is actually particularly
important for games and games
that are working this art
movement is that they declare
their intentionality.
Whether they declare what
they're meaning is or not is
less important.
To be taken seriously, you take
yourself seriously, I
think was one of
things he said.
And I think this is another
good example when you talk
about how games maybe in the
digital space do this.
But right now they're already
priming you for reading the
rules in a way that is different
than just, ooh,
let's play.
Could you imagine if Monopoly
had some sort of Marxist quote
in the front of it, or something
like that, your
experience of it would be
completely different.
You set up, you put the pieces
in this array, you stand on a
number and that indicates
what color you are.
And this is great, you
take out $3.00.
Although you can see in this
second picture they're playing
what Eric the designer has
deemed high stakes.
Sixteen Tons where you pull out
three five-dollar bills.
It says, how to win.
You win when the two pieces
of your color are directly
adjacent to each other.
So diagonally adjacent does
not count for a win.
The way you play is, players
take turns, starting with
player one.
When it's your turn, you
say, put me to work.
Players may then offer to
pay you one or more
dollars in any order.
So anyone can just say,
I'll give you this.
You have to accept the highest
payment, except
if there's a tie.
Because with specific
denominations there is very
likely to be a tie.
Then you get to choose
which of the highest
bidders you can take.
The person who pays then tells
you what move to make.
And if no one offers to
pay you, you get to
decide what to do.
And then it's the next player's
turn, and you would
continue until one
player wins.
Just off the top of your heads,
having not even played
it-- it's tough to critique
games when you haven't played.
But just looking at the
rules and hearing
about it and even--
I love that picture on the left,
because it embodies some
of the spirit of
the play, too.
What are some interesting things
about this rule set of
that you notice?
AUDIENCE: You play with money,
but you won't win money?
GUEST SPEAKER: Well, that's
an interesting question.
What happens to the money
at the end of the game?
AUDIENCE: Who knows?
Do you keep it?
AUDIENCE: It's unclear.
GUEST SPEAKER: Very unclear.
That's one of the things that's
really great about this
game, is that it puts you to
into these social situations
where now you're playing
with real currency
that was your own.
And now it's like, what
happens to this?
It says you win if your piece--
but maybe you feel
like you win if you moved those
pieces and you have the
most money at the
end of the game.
You've got this kind of
weird economy in here.
I think the fact that
it's not explicit in
this rule set is great.
That's what creates this
potential for an interesting
social dynamic.
Other things that are
interesting about this game?
AUDIENCE: If you're the only
person who has money, then you
can basically win.
GUEST SPEAKER: You can basically
win if you're the
only person who has
money, yeah.
So it does require a little
bit of strategy, too.
AUDIENCE: Technically,
from that set of--
could you win on the first turn,
because it seems you
only have two pieces
of a certain color.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but
the right is still
the starting position.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, Iknow.
And so on your turn, you could
take one-- your piece and have
it be moved to the square
right next to yours.
AUDIENCE: No.
AUDIENCE: Move to
any adjacent--
AUDIENCE: Oh, you have
to move it--
AUDIENCE: Read the rule
in the red there.
AUDIENCE: Oh, any adjacent
number,okay.
I didn't read the
adjacent part.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, it's any
adjacent or empty square.
AUDIENCE: It's actually
really interesting.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, it's
a really weird--
I also think you're not-- the
agency you have in the game to
win is not by moving your own
pieces, it's by paying someone
to do the work for you.
So then we get back to this
quote at the beginning, "You
load 16 tons and what
do you get?
Another day older and
deeper in debt."
It's like, what is
this game about.
It could be about
a lot of things.
And we honestly probably
shouldn't dissect it until
we've played it.
I think, too, the corrugated
cardboard, it gets hot inside
of there, if you're
not outside.
And that's a really interesting
thing, too.
You're in there, it's hot, it's
sweaty, you've got dirty
money in your hands, you're
moving around these sizable--
they have weight to them.
That was really important,
too.
This could have been played
around a table with go-pieces
or something, painted
go-pieces.
But these are substantial steel
pieces that you've got
to pick up and move.
Obviously the song was
about manual labor.
So this is a really
interesting game.
This was released at the
Art History of Games
conference last year.
And it did well at IndieCade
this year.
It won the Developers
Choice Award.
And it's really cool.
I want to try to get it
up to MIT so that we
can all play it.
AUDIENCE: It occurs to me that
if you went by rules where you
keep the money you get to the
end of the game, you basically
could throw the game to
get all the money.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah,
you could try.
But people are gonna know
what you're doing.
Because they're going
to see you're shiny.
So it's--
AUDIENCE: I'm not gonna
pay you back.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, the
multiplayer gets--
the multiplayer, the
game gets in it.
Just cycling back to
what we're talking
about, is this art?
It would be hard for me to call
it much of anything else.
So this is one of my
favorite games.
It's certainly my favorite
that Jason's ever made.
Who's played Gravitation here?
A couple of games?
Alright, cool.
And a bunch of you haven't.
That's awesome.
So I'll get one of
you to play it.
One thing I want to point out
with this-- we can talk after
someone's played Gravitation,
a little bit about what we
think about the game itself.
But I think this quote
is interesting.
He has artist statements
with all of his games.
Some of them say more, some
of them say less.
This one responded briefly
'cause this was after Passage
was released.
And I think you guys have
all seen Passage, right?
You can immediately identify
the aesthetic similarities
because the character
is exactly the same.
He was responding to criticism
from people about his pixel
art, and why did he
go for Pixel art.
He says, "I now see ultra-low
res pixel art as a kind of
digital cartooning.
It stands right on the line
between the symbolic and the
representational, leaving plenty
of room for viewer
interpretation.
Why draw sideburns when the
viewers can imagine sideburns
on their own.
You just need to give them
something to pin their
imagination on, something
to guide them a bit.
Cartoons are perfect for that.
I think it's a really
interesting point.
And I think what he's also
suggesting here, which is
maybe not clear, is that this
is doing a similar thing to
what that quote from
the music does.
It's priming your experience
of the play.
You load up this game, you see
that it's got this low-res
pixel art that we now associate
with this kind of
art game movement, and
you're ready to read
this in another way.
If I gave you a first-person
shooter and told you nothing
about it except that it was
gonna be the fastest,
awesomest, multiplayer
first-person shooter
experience, but it looked like
this, would you be inclined to
read it like an art game?
I don't know.
But certainly in this instance
with these kind of little
games, this pixel-art aesthetic
that you see being
duplicated in a lot of places,
is sort of priming the pump.
It's establishing some sort
of context in which you
can read this game.
So who wants to play
Gravitation?
Oops, no, that's not what's
supposed to happen.
Why did it click on link.
Oh, 'cause I clicked on my
screen, not on this screen.
All that does is take
me out of here.
Yay.
AUDIENCE: Me not being here,
it might be a problem.
Let's see.
Let's see what screen
it's logged up on.
One.
GUEST SPEAKER: Hold
on one sec.
I've got a mirror
on my screen.
I should not be choosing
who plays.
Who wants to--
I can't make the choice.
Who wants to do it?
AUDIENCE: Interesting that
it's a version zero.
You have to explicitly
make that the case.
GUEST SPEAKER: Anybody.
It's free to download, so if you
don't play it now, you can
play it on your own.
AUDIENCE: We have a
few games, right?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah,
we have a few.
We have a few opportunities, so
anybody jump over and play.
AUDIENCE: Just talk with Jason,
and then we'll do join
me in Dubai--
GUEST SPEAKER: And actually, if
you wouldn't mind talking
about your experience to play
Gravitation as you play it.
Let's play, but live, say.
[GAME MUSIC]
AUDIENCE: I seem to
have a restricted
view, and it's falling.
I caught it.
AUDIENCE: She stole your ball.
GUEST SPEAKER: She seemed to
like you, but she stole it for
the moment.
Now she seems to be playing,
which is better.
AUDIENCE: We seem to-- he bats
it back and forth and my
screen gets bigger whenever
I especially do so.
And it's getting brighter.
AUDIENCE: It gets bigger
when she loves you.
AUDIENCE: It changes this fiery
thing and it seems to be
batting the ball more.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: You're on fire.
AUDIENCE: I'm on fire.
This seems bad.
Now I'm really confused.
AUDIENCE: You should
go to the furnace.
AUDIENCE: Oh, now you're
not on fire.
That makes sense.
Whoa!
AUDIENCE: Wait, can you bounce
the ball up there?
I didn't see anything
that showing me
how to get up there.
Oh, here we go.
AUDIENCE: Isn't that
always the case?
AUDIENCE: What's that star?
Uh-oh.
Well, now you can bounce
the ball up here.
AUDIENCE: Oh, you can jump
higher when she loves you.
AUDIENCE: --the size
of the screen.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, that's how
high you can jump .
OK, so--
I guess maybe bounce it
more to get higher?
AUDIENCE: You're losing her.
AUDIENCE: I'm on fire again.
Oh, but you're gonna be
on fire in a while.
She's not gonna love
you very soon.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, apparently
getting the
stars is also good.
AUDIENCE: It seems it goes
faster and faster the higher
up you get, I think.
Or maybe the more
stars you eat.
AUDIENCE: And that's all ice.
Oh, yes.
She seems happier when
I bounce the ball.
I guess--
so I don't have a which is I
think the start of it because
the stars into the fire so that
they melt or something.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Oh, now it's a star.
Interesting.
AUDIENCE: Well, there's
been [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: What?
AUDIENCE: All right.
Look what's [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
into the fire.
AUDIENCE: Otherwise, he's
gonna have a hammer.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you're dead.
AUDIENCE: The numbers of the
stars are all going down.
The ball can't get to you.
It's [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: OK, now I can--
--push the ice into the fire?
AUDIENCE: And the number on
the top goes up every time
you-- yeah, the numbers on
the star corresponds
to how many, like--
AUDIENCE: You know, fire seems
like it would be bad.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Try to get
rid of the ice--
AUDIENCE: But she doesn't
want to play.
AUDIENCE: That's because
I got rid of the ice.
He was happy I think.
AUDIENCE: Oh, it's getting
icy, though.
It's getting colder.
There's no way to recharge
my thing, though.
GUEST SPEAKER: I think you
just have to go higher.
This is where you were
last time, I think.
Yeah, there.
AUDIENCE: That was
really like--
AUDIENCE: Do you think
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] too fast, and
your hair's burning, that means
you just gave him too
much love, and he starts
falling really fast.
AUDIENCE: Oh, no.
AUDIENCE: But there's a a
counter on the ice blocks of
the stars, and you get more
points if you get them into
the furnace faster.
I think they went down
and he started
warming up in the furnace.
The warmer the world, the less
points you get for de-icing?
AUDIENCE: Is this about
global warming?
AUDIENCE: I think
he's on drugs.
He gets love from this girl, and
then the ice and the stars
make you happy, but only
for a little bit.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So if I'm on fire it
seems to reduce at a much
faster rate.
[INAUDIBLE]
said
AUDIENCE: I think it's
about drugs.
I think everything's
I mean, yeah, obviously.
AUDIENCE: You can actually
catch the purple
guy into that cave.
AUDIENCE: Oh, no.
AUDIENCE: It's a really stupid
design, going all the way back
down there.
GUEST SPEAKER: There's a
[INAUDIBLE] on the right, you
can fall faster.
AUDIENCE: The higher you climb,
the further you fall.
AUDIENCE: Ooh, poetic.
AUDIENCE: Now I probably have a
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] stars, so I
think they need to play--
AUDIENCE: She's gone.
AUDIENCE: She's dead.
You killed her.
AUDIENCE: So sad.
And it's not the fire left.
AUDIENCE: Oh, no.
AUDIENCE:And the fire isn't
bringing things back.
AUDIENCE: Oh, my god.
You didn't get any stars
for her, so she died.
She eats stars.
AUDIENCE: Oh, there you go.
Is she there now?
The fire started warming
you again.
AUDIENCE: Nope.
She's gone forever.
You can't play ball alone.
AUDIENCE: When she's gone.
Maybe she only comes
in the spring.
Maybe winter's too cold.
So maybe if I wait
by the fire.
AUDIENCE: Does is go
faster right there?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, why is
it getting bigger?
AUDIENCE: 'Cause he's
by the fire.
It's getting warmer.
AUDIENCE: That wasn't
working earlier.
AUDIENCE: Now it is.
AUDIENCE: He's at rock bottom.
AUDIENCE: Looks like
it's spring.
AUDIENCE: But when she--
AUDIENCE: How high can
you jump right now?
AUDIENCE: Can you
hit the ball?
AUDIENCE: Pretty high.
That's a lot of jumbos.
AUDIENCE: No, I can't
hit the ball.
AUDIENCE: Only she
can hit the ball.
AUDIENCE: While you're
increasing, you should
probably go up and get--
AUDIENCE: Go up.
Go up.
AUDIENCE: Ah, there you go.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
stop [INAUDIBLE].
It stopped contracting, too.
AUDIENCE: You're on fire now.
AUDIENCE: He's on fire.
AUDIENCE: Can you go
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
high if he's on fire?
AUDIENCE: Uh-oh.
Whoa.
Four stars.
AUDIENCE: Are you getting
all of them?
AUDIENCE: That might have
been a bit of overdose.
AUDIENCE: You totally OD'd
on stars just there.
AUDIENCE: Or, or, you can only
hold four, and then it
retracts and you get four
that turn to ice blocks.
AUDIENCE: What?
That was intense.
AUDIENCE: That's a
lot of falling.
AUDIENCE: There was
so much energy.
AUDIENCE: Wait.
No.
AUDIENCE: You won.
Yay!
Now what you won is
a good question.
GUEST SPEAKER: That's
Gravitation.
Actually, I'm not
even kidding.
That's certainly my favorite
Jason Rohrer game.
It's one of my favorite games.
And I think even just the
example of you guys playing is
great, because you're just
shouting out all these
different ideas for what
it could be about.
There's some clear
intentionality in his design
with this game, in terms of
the system's trying to
communicate something that's
other than just
engagement or fun.
Was it fun?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
GUEST SPEAKER: Oh, all right.
Cool.
Yeah, it's pretty good.
Thoughts on what it's about?
I heard a couple people
be like, drugs.
AUDIENCE: It's definitely
drugs.
I saw tons of analogies.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, it's
kind of like drugs.
AUDIENCE: Or love.
Or both.
AUDIENCE: Love is a drug.
AUDIENCE: Your relationship
versus whatever you're trying
to do for your career.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah.
I think it's like the
ultimate MIT game.
If I told you that this was his
daughter, would it change
your interpretations
of the game?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
GUEST SPEAKER: So now, if you
know that that's his daughter,
what do you think it's about?
AUDIENCE: Neglect.
AUDIENCE: Job versus family.
GUEST SPEAKER: He says
explicitly, before you play,
that this is a game
of motivation.
He doesn't go too far into
telling you what the game is
specifically about.
I think playing through
it a couple times--
I will tell you the first time
I played and I came back down
and she was gone, it was
very upsetting for me.
I was like, and I don't know
if it's just I was ready to
play it that way, or my life
stage or something like that.
But the idea of he's playing
with his daughter, that
inspires him, he travels, and
then one of these days if
you're gone too long,
she grows up.
I don't know if she
dies, but--
AUDIENCE: He didn't bring
her any money.
Because she had no money,
she dies [INAUDIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: So I think
this is a really--
AUDIENCE: What did they say,
it's a game about motivation?
GUEST SPEAKER: It is, yeah.
AUDIENCE: Or she
OD'd on drugs.
GUEST SPEAKER: It's free.
If you just Google-search
Gravitation Jason Rohrer,
you'll find the links to it.
You'll find his artist
statement, which I think is
really good to read.
Again, with John Sharp's point
about declare your
intentionality.
Whatever you say what game's
about is important.
I think this qualifies, at
least for me, as art.
It's doing things that I see
other piece of art doing.
GUEST SPEAKER: OK, so
Paolo Pedercini--
how many over time?
Oh, good.
Paolo Pedercini is one
of my favorite game
designers right now.
This game actually is one of his
newest ones, and I think
it's hilarious and great.
It's called Memory Reloaded
The Downfall.
Test your concentration with
Memory Reloaded matching game
for these unstable times.
History may be different from
that which you remember.
Who would like to play
Memory Reloaded?
I'm laughing already,
because it's funny.
Has anybody played it?
I need somebody who's
not played it.
OK, good.
Do you [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: Sure.
GUEST SPEAKER: Awesome.
OK.
You're up.
AUDIENCE: I will click.
AUDIENCE: Don't do it.
Oh, you're on.
AUDIENCE: You're done.
You lost already.
AUDIENCE: --go away.
It's kind of scary.
I could already see
what they can do.
You're gonna play a
game switch on me.
Afghan Freedom Fighters.
He's gonna be a terrorist
later.
Migrant Workforce.
Migrant workforce.
Iraqi Oil.
Afghan Freedom Fighter.
AUDIENCE: I bet if you grab
Iraqi Oil before Afghan
Freedom Fighter, it
becomes terrorist.
Global Inequality.
Peace in Palestine.
Yes.
Global Inequality.
GUEST SPEAKER: All right.
AUDIENCE: I'm doing well.
Ruthless Banker.
Loan shark.
Was Iraqi Oil here?
No.
Universal Health Care.
Man-made Global Warming.
Natural Global Warming.
Ha!
Hey, not cool.
Universal Health Care.
Sweet.
Oh.
One over.
There.
Peace in Palestine.
There we go.
Wait.
Needy Banker.
Ruthless Banker.
Does it matter, the order
you click them in?
Ruthless Banker.
What?
What did the other one
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
There we go.
Nice.
So that means now--
He's never a satisfied banker.
What the hell?
Oh, dear.
Did we?
Shoot.
Better move.
GUEST SPEAKER: This--
[INAUDIBLE]
Natural Climate [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Oh, I get it.
That's fun.
Is that the entire game?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yes, that
is the whole game.
Of course, you get different
outcomes.
Yeah, that's the idea.
I think you guys have seen some
of the Molleindustria's
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
You guys saw Every Day
the Same Dream?
AUDIENCE: I like that one.
GUEST SPEAKER: Which
is interesting.
Yeah, that one's also one
of my favorite games.
This is looking at another kind
of sector of art, the
activist political statement
sector of art is doing that
through games, and it's
something-- this music too
[INAUDIBLE]--
something that he does
particularly
well with his games.
And I think this one's
particularly interesting and
kind of funny.
I love the reworking of a really
classic game mechanic.
The entire point of memory is
your expectation that they
would be the same the second
time you turn it over.
And when it changes on you, it
really worsens that kind of
perspective, I suppose
imbalance, that can exist when
you're not just turning over
Toadstools and Bowsers, but
actual, interesting things.
I love the crying, sweating
polar bear with a beach chair.
It actually cracks me up.
Humor is actually
something that
shouldn't be ignored here.
If we remember, that was one of
the central Fluxus things,
this idea of satire.
Humor is important.
So I think Paolo Pedercini's
work is really awesome.
Again, for me, it's certainly
arcing up.
This game's really cool.
Who's played Love?
A few people who's
played Love?
All right, cool.
I'd love someone who has not
played Love to play for a
little bit.
I don't know if we can
play the whole game.
This is actually a game that I
really don't like, but I like
the things that it does, if
that makes any sense.
It bothers me for some reason.
And yet--
it's such an articulate
statement, this
game bothers me--
but I think it's worth looking
at, because he's doing a
particularly interesting
thing, Alexander Ocias.
I suppose it's a
soft C, Ocias.
I have the sound turned off.
I'm sorry, top right.
[GAME MUSIC]
AUDIENCE: If you say, yes,
will he like not
teach you how to play?
AUDIENCE: Don't touch
the buttons.
It's like [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER: There's
two paths.
AUDIENCE: Can you find them?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I'm not gonna listen--
AUDIENCE: It says travel
the lower paths.
AUDIENCE: Who's gonna be able
to listen to all this?
AUDIENCE: What's appearing?
GUEST SPEAKER: Weird slowdown.
AUDIENCE: You [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
disobey him.
AUDIENCE: What?
I can't hit the red
blocks now?
AUDIENCE: Disgusting.
[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Just give us not
only art, it's all so
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Patience.
Yay.
AUDIENCE: Those are red.
AUDIENCE: I know.
That means they can't
touch him.
AUDIENCE: Don't do it.
Don't do it, dude.
AUDIENCE: Do it.
AUDIENCE: You're just gonna have
to go back to the part
that was just hard.
AUDIENCE: You get red blocks
when you disobey.
AUDIENCE: You still
can't touch them.
AUDIENCE: So if you disobey, it
hides from you what things
actually are.
Or if you obey, they're
getting the victory.
AUDIENCE: It's so funny.
Just that little--
AUDIENCE: What are the
controls for this?
AUDIENCE: You should disobey.
AUDIENCE: What?
Can you no longer jump?
AUDIENCE: I'm just
screwing around.
AUDIENCE: He's [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: Oh, I thought
that was bad.
GUEST SPEAKER: This game is
well aggravatingly tuned,
because it's difficult enough.
AUDIENCE: Are you doing
that intentionally?
AUDIENCE: I just like to.
GUEST SPEAKER: It's actually
a pretty long game.
I encourage you guys to--
it's pretty- it's
all flash-based.
AUDIENCE: What's the message?
GUEST SPEAKER: It's a really
good question.
Let me just jump in and go back
to that place where--
thank you for playing.
Thank you for playing.
AUDIENCE: Disgusting.
AUDIENCE: You are a changed
person because of it.
So the question then becomes
what's the point, which
already we're in a position
now where we're asking
questions like that.
Which is, if you were playing
Modern Warfare II, you might
say what's the point, and
be like, to blow a lot
of stuff up, right?
This is the response he had in
one of his interviews he gave
after his release and said, I
wanted to get people to wake
up and think about the games
they are playing.
Much of the industry appears to
be pushing in the opposite
direction, as we'll have
tutorials, holding your hand
from beginning to end in
subtext, screens for pointless
exposition.
It is treating players
like idiots.
It is absolutely infuriating.
When you think about it in terms
of the tutorial, if this
is the tutorial for playing the
game, it's pretty obnoxious.
But it's not that much different
than the kind of
tutorials we encounter in
a lot of games that just
basically hold your hand and
tell you how to do everything.
I think he's really
confronting that.
I guess if I were to say the
reasons that I don't like this
game, I think the control
scheme is
actually, it's a weakness.
The game is so hard that, I
mean, you saw you couldn't
even get to the things that he
was trying to communicate.
It gets weirder, the further
along you get,
I can promise you.
It's just you have to get really
skilled at doing it.
There's kind of like a play
barrier for entry on it.
It's also, for me, I think dare
I say, it almost gets too
abstract for me at
certain points.
Clearly he's trying to say
something, but there's nothing
I can latch onto to understand
what it is.
That's entirely his prerogative,
but for me, I'm
just like, what?
I have no clue what this
is about at all.
So that's a little tricky,
not fully grasping.
Clearly I'm not--
I'm partially, so it's
like the perfect
Fluxus piece of art.
OK, so I've only got a couple
more to talk about.
I've got about 15 minutes.
This, I think, is actually one
of the most important games we
can talk about today, which
is Cow Clicker.
Who's played Cow Clicker?
Yay.
This is by Ian Bogost-- that's
the guy we saw earlier.
And he said, Cow Clicker
is a Facebook game
about Facebook games.
It's partly a satire and partly
a playable theory of
today's social games, and partly
an earnest example of
that genre.
So this is kind of like
a classic sort of
art thing to do.
You take something that you're
going to satire, and you make
a version of that, that maybe
does something differently,
but it's fundamentally what
you are satiring.
It's like the Andy Kaufman
comedic kind of style.
You just assume that kind
of character or role.
It's something that I think is
like joyfully subversive in
doing satire.
So hopefully I'm logged into
Facebook so you can see.
I haven't clicked recently,
so you guys can
witness one of my clicks.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
Facebook is down.
Facebook is canceled forever.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
[LAUGHTER]
It actually has no friends.
It's also possible that
the wireless--
the wireless in that corner
is kind of bad.
GUEST SPEAKER: Should I switch
to Google Guest?
I can actually, before we can
see it, I can talk a little
bit about the sort of
interesting controversy that
Cow Clicker is creating.
It's making money.
Let me try Google Guest.
I'm not connected.
How about now?
It seems to be working better.
AUDIENCE: You're still not--
GUEST SPEAKER: The last part of
his statement is about an
earnest effort at a game.
It is fundamentally
a Facebook game.
You can see I've got 5 mooney
and my next click is in a
minute and 40-- ah, man, I
missed one of my clicks.
But maybe if we wait while I
talk about it you can witness
one of my clicks.
Oh, wait, I actually have
some clicks left.
I've got one this week.
AUDIENCE: That's in two hours?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, it
looks like that's when
I get my next one.
So basically you can
click your cow.
Why can I not click
my cow here.
But you can click your cow, and
then you can-- oh, it's
because I'm on scroll?
Anyway, you can click your cow,
and then you can use your
mooney to buy new cows that
are fundamentally the same
thing as other cows, just with
aesthetic differences.
So plain cow.
These are the cows I have.
I have a plain cow
and a steel cow.
I haven't been playing
a lot of Cow Clicker.
If I go to buy a cow,
I can buy a new cow.
So you can see lots
of different cows.
They cost you in
game currency.
AUDIENCE: Paisley cow.
GUEST SPEAKER: Holy cow.
Oil cow [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
It's got a BP logo.
Cute.
Like the [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
cows.
That's pretty good.
So there's lots of
different cows.
You can buy cows, you can give
cows, you can invite a cow,
there's cow rankings.
AUDIENCE: You can buy a cow.
GUEST SPEAKER: So you can see,
mooney's actually pretty
inflated at this point.
You can get 10 mooney for 50
cents, which is pretty good,
1,000 for $10, which
is awesome.
And collect a lot of cows.
You can trade cows.
And you can go to your friends
barns and see how
many cows they have.
And you can click on your cows
when you make your appointment
to actually visit a cow.
So I think you can see how he's
poking fun at things like
FarmVille things like Ravenwood
Fair, which I'm
obsessed with now, actually,
these kind of games where all
you're fundamentally doing is
clicking and acquiring an
in-game currency that's
you can then
use for in-game goods.
But then, of course, you reach
this barrier where you don't
have enough in-game currency
and you use moo currency.
Of course the interesting thing
is there are 500,000
people playing this.
I don't know if it's
that many.
It's a lot.
If you go to the Cow Clicker
front page it'll tell us.
It just [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Where does it say how many
players there are?
AUDIENCE: Ranking, probably
in ranking.
He's milking the cow clicker.
You can see this person's--
Monica's--
AUDIENCE: Is the cow--
AUDIENCE: Is that their
all-time clicks
or this week's clicks?
AUDIENCE: Is there a--
GUEST SPEAKER: Here
we go, yeah, yeah.
12,000 monthly active users.
That's 500,000 in a business
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
But that's a lot of people.
And he's making some interesting
money on it.
And I think one of the things
that was important that he did
is there's an active
forum where people
can talk about it.
So it is a little bit weirdly
controversial, 'cause he made
this game that is poking
fun at Facebook games.
And yet it is a Facebook game
and presumably making some
money, too.
But I think it's really good.
This is the kind of art that's
also important, where it's
taking what we do and purposely
looking at how is it
constructed and how it's set up
and forcing us to kind of
be introspective about the
things that we do and the way
that we engage.
So this is a kind of subversive
game design that I
think along the lines of Paolo
Pedercini's work and even
Gonzalo Frasca if forcing us
to look at how we interact.
And Cow Clicker--
So that's that one.
And I've got like 15 minutes.
Phillip asked me to talk a
little bit about some work
that I'm doing in this space.
So I'm gonna talk to you
about a game, it's
still a work in progress.
It's tentatively entitled
Before and
Now, and it's by me.
And the idea from it is it's
inspired by Fluxus boxes and
those Flux kits.
I'm really interested in
physically tangible games.
I don't know why I'm all
of a sudden obsessed
with holding something.
But I was at IndieCade and I
heard again-- and this is the
question that drives me more
nuts than the are video games
art question, although they're
interestingly related.
But it's when will we have the
Citizen Kane in video games?
It drives me absolutely nuts.
I think 80% of the time people
who say that have never seen
Citizen Kane.
I don't really know that.
But I heard it for the umpteenth
time at IndieCade.
I wanted to throw the television
out of my hotel
room window.
And I was going nuts.
And I was like, all right, what
is Citizen Kane about?
I don't want to spoil it.
Who's seen Citizen Kane
in this room actually?
All right, good.
So I see Citizen Kane and it's
about this very interesting
idea about presents and mementos
and happiness in a
very kind of real way.
And the temporality
of happiness, like
are you happy now?
Were you happy then?
Do you remember being happy?
When is happiness?
And so I was like, well, I'm
going to make a Citizen Kane
in video games, but it's not
gonna be known for being
epically innovative with
camera movement.
It's going to be about
the things I think
Citizen Kane are about.
So it's basically in this form,
although I'm rethinking
what kind of box it's
gonna be in.
But in this form it's a box.
And inside of it are various
objects that start out as--
the starting objects of the box
are the things that have
personal significance to me.
One of the rules of the game,
in fact, I think the most
important rule of the
game is this one.
Rule number one, you may
permanently exchange an object
of personal significance for
any object of equal value.
So when you're playing this
game, you can take something
that belongs to you, and you can
exchange it for anything
in the box.
And of course, the interesting
thing is these objects in the
box are of varying degrees
of interactivity.
You can [INAUDIBLE]
so you can draw something
on the Etch A Sketch.
The rules are kind of veiled
at this moment now, where's
there's like a couple
other rules that
are causing to reflect.
This is actually an extension
of Yup on Word which is a
project we worked on in the
summer, which was a game that
as you're playing it's a
platform where you're typing,
and the game stops and asks
you personal questions.
What I really liked about that
is it was doing something that
I was referring to as a mechanic
of reflection, where
the activity of playing is
reflecting, is thinking, is
contemplating.
It's not interactive in a very
active way as we think of it,
it's more reflective.
I liken it to the moments
in chess where you're
planning your move.
There's not a lot of
action in chess.
But it's a lot of contemplation
in chess.
So if it's personal--
what if that were personal.
And so what I didn't
particularly care about with
Yup on Word it inspires you to
reflect, but it doesn't do it
with tremendous grace.
It just asks you a question.
It just comes up out of the blue
and and says, hey, when
was the last time you lied?
Sometimes you're surprised by
that, and that's a good
effect, but it's also
not subtle.
So I'm trying to explore how
can we be subtle in causing
reflection.
So there are a few
things here.
The value question
is interesting.
How do you know what the value
of the object is in the box?
Do you think of it as
monetary value?
Do you think of it as value in
terms of significance to the
person who put that in there?
Why is it significant to the
What is this thing?
You can look at it
and reflect.
And then when you leave a trace
of yourself in this box,
the next person who comes and
plays is going to see that.
And they're going to wonder
what was that.
So I'm also kind of interested
the organicness, the kind of
never-ending, interminable
nature of a game that carries
the effect of the person who's
played it on and on and on.
The next iteration of this that
I want to do-- actually
this was an idea that Jason
Bean gave me was to use an
apothecary chest.
Because one of the things that
we play-tested it here with--
I left it out for two weeks
and people-- you
probably saw it.
It's right there.
People were engaging in--
this is a photo with objects
that people had left in.
So it was really fun for me
after two weeks to go into
this box and be like, what
is all this stuff.
What got left?
I was actually surprised the
Etch A Sketch was left.
And then I was like,
what is this stuff?
And to give you one really good
example, one person at
the lab put in a Nintendo DS
flash card, which was really a
wrapped DS flash card.
So now there's this kind
of next level.
The game has changed with
another level of
interactivity, where it's like,
if I want to get at what
was the significance of this
object to this person, I need
to get a DS and play this.
So I open up the-- it's got
folders, and it's got a copy
of the game Lemming.
It's got some music in it.
So now it's kind of like you've
uncovered this next layer.
And it's like the interesting
traces of the people who
played this game are now marked
onto this box forever.
Marley even said to me--
I was talking to her about her
play after she had done it,
and I was like--
She told me she wanted to
take the instructions.
She wanted to take the rules.
That's one of the objects that
she could take out of that.
And I told her I had thought
about that actually when I was
designing it, that someone might
be like, ha, I'm going
to take the rules.
And I was going to put in
a rule that said you can
permanently exchange for an
object that's not the rules,
so that the game
could persist.
But I didn't want to
artificially impose that.
If someone takes the rules
because that's what they want,
and now the game has changed.
And maybe someone comes along
later and modifies it.
And maybe they put something in
that makes it a whole new,
different game.
And I really liked the idea that
you could encounter this
game and that it's gonna be in
this state of flux, I guess
you could say.
That's what I'm working
on now.
And like I said, I think one of
the things I didn't like is
that all of the objects are
accessible all at once.
So if it's an apothecary chest
with lots of drawers, this was
Jason Bean's idea, then you have
to do a little exploring.
And maybe the rules are in
one of those drawers.
And maybe you see
the rules first.
Maybe you see the rules
way after you've
looked at a lot of stuff.
And now you've seen all this
stuff and played with it all
and you really like something.
And now it's like, ooh,
what do I trade?
And yeah, I also am trying to
find a way to give the box a
history as well.
I've contemplated some ideas
of putting in some kind of
clues that you could then, if
you felt, if you thought about
it or looked it up, you might
be able to find a
story to this box.
Like if you did an Internet
search you might come up on a
fake website-- well, it wouldn't
be fake, it'd just be
a website-- but a website with
a fake story that tells you a
little bit about this box, and
then it gives you a few more
hooks into what the meaning of
this game or the inspiration
for this game was.
And so this is one of my
projects that I'm working on
right now, like I said, I'm
interested in essentially.
But you can see where a lot of
the other things that I was
talking about are inspiring
this work.
And so we come back to that
question of, are games art?
Of course we only have
five minutes.
I don't know if you guys have
administrative stuff
afterwards.
But this is, like I said,
this is my viewpoint.
It's certainly shared with
a lot of people.
But it's not guaranteed truth.
This is an opinion that
I have just shared.
Any thoughts you guys have about
this subject or these
ideas or these games?
Anything at all?
Yesterday's football game?
AUDIENCE: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
GUEST SPEAKER: Well, cool.
I hope this was useful.
I hope it was helpful.
I think if, at the very least,
it causes you to continue to
think about your own games that
you're developing and how
meaning can be embedded in the
play that you might not even
realize is there.
And also just to count the
possibility space.
I really am excited by--
I'm discouraged by the safe
choices that a lot of
independent game developers
make and excited when some
game developers really
push on the edge.
I don't think we have a clear
understanding of what the
rules are or what even
constitutes a game.
Or what degree of interactivity
is appropriate
for a quote/unquote game.
And I think some of these
designers are really testing
the waters of the medium,
you know, what can we
really do with this?
Where can we go?
How edgy and satirical and
avant-garde can we be?
I think that's always good.
'Cause I'm a revolutionary,
crazy person.
AUDIENCE: Crazy person.
AUDIENCE: Hope 7 played yet one
more this year, which were
some of the games that Abe
worked with the team on over
the summer.
Those are all on our GAMBIT
website, just until 2010 and
as yet [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
which we're
booked about this summer.
This sounds like tri-season
will be digital work.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, and please
play them and give us
feedback, too, right?
Because that's the
other thing.
These are not perfect
articulations of game as the
pure art form.
We're constantly evolving and
trying to improve, so any
feedback you can give us on
this stuff is greatly
appreciated.
AUDIENCE: Do you still have
that box, like somewhere?
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, yeah.
It's in my office.
Yeah, totally.
I have the box and the other
part of it is when I do the
second version of it in the
apothecary kind of chest--
The one thing that's important
to me is that each of the--
For the prototype I just sort
of threw some reasonably
meaningful objects in there.
But I want it to be populated
with objects that are
personally significant to myself
or symbolic to myself.
And populating that box at the
outset with meaningful objects
I think is important, because
once it's released into the
world for play that it's
constantly changing.
So that first instantiation of
the game is the one that's
about me in some sense, and
about my experiences and then
it becomes the world's
to just play.
AUDIENCE: So the way that your
game kind of reminds me of is
I'm pretty sure I heard
somewhere that some
person had a pen.
He started with a pen
and kept trading--
AUDIENCE: The red paper--
AUDIENCE: No.
This is a different one.
Not the red paper
clip for a car.
I think someone started with
a pen or something and kept
trading it.
And over the course of a
year or two, he'd got--
From that initial pen,
he was able to trade
for a house or something.
GUEST SPEAKER: It was
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And that was sort of
an interesting--
I think it was on eBay, too,
or something like that.
And that's even using a pretty
well-designed game system--
'cause eBay is totally
a game--
and using a game system and
subverting the system itself
to do something really
interesting.
Yeah, that's a really great--
it's a game inside of a game.
I love that.
It's kind of like the Cow
Clicker, like making a game
inside of the game
that subverts--
AUDIENCE: Are you familiar
with the concept of
geo-caching?
When I first saw--
the game you were talking about
using [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
reminded me of it.
So initially what it was, was
when GPS's first came out,
people were like, oh, hey,
this is really cool
technology.
We should think of something
fun to do with it.
So what they did was, these
people started hiding empty
tins of little trinkets and
stuff on various hiking trails
or other locations.
And you would look up the
coordinates on your GPS
finder, and you would
find this box.
And then you'd trade trinkets,
and you get them.
And you keep traveling
to these other--
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, and in
that sense this whole
worldwide game becomes--
There's some shared ideas with
some location-based games that
do some really interesting
things with that, whether it's
alternate reality, but not
even with the narrative.
There was one I was reading
about that was, come out and
play, I think, in New York
City at one point.
It was Cruel to be Kind,
it was called.
It was a game where you don't
know who's playing, you don't
know who's on what team, but you
get missions and you get a
weapon that's a complement, like
to kill someone who's on
the other team, mistake them
for a celebrity, or
something like that.
So you're using these random
acts of kindness-- you know,
helping somebody across
the street--
and you don't know, it's in New
York City, so you don't
know if someone's playing
the game.
So now all of a sudden you're
wandering around doing really
nice things for people on the
chance, on a hunch that you
have that maybe they're
playing the game.
And maybe they're not, so you've
just helped somebody
across the street, which
is totally nice.
And it comes to this massive
conclusion where you just have
these two giant teams who meet
up in a location to "nice"
each other to death,
basically.
There's a lot of really, really
interesting stuff,
especially in the
location-based, around.
Big games are really cool.
There's a lot of people
doing really neat
stuff with big games.
AUDIENCE: I think in particular
with the box and
the geo-caching idea, and
talking about the
paperclip-for-a-house thing,
it's really interesting how
people value things.
In particular, you have this
very vague rule, and it just
says something of equal value.
And what does it
actually mean?
Like what someone is willing to
trade for something else.
GUEST SPEAKER: Yeah, those are
the kind of implicit rules
like you see in Sixteen Tons,
where it's like, what happens
with the money?
Jason Bean really pointed it
out, 'cause he was thinking
about value when he was
doing the trading.
And it's such a good word,
because value is such a
different thing to
different people.
Someone might see the flash card
for the DS, which has a
very clear, higher monetary
value than an Etch A Sketch.
And yet, maybe you played with
an Etch A Sketch when you were
a kid, and all of a sudden it
floods back these memories
that you have.
There's also a component to it
that I didn't really talk
about, which is the sacrificing
of an object.
And I think, too, that we tend
to be beholden to our material
objects too much.
In giving it up, in sacrificing
it to this game so
that you don't have it anymore,
if it's something of
personal significance, you're
letting go and being able to
say, OK, the memory
is one thing.
I don't need to--
And that's how it relates a
bit back to Citizen Kane,
which is a movie you should
see, because it is good.
It's everything they said it is,
depending on who they are.
Cool.
Thanks, guys.