MARTINA BALAGOVIC: Hi.
Welcome to recitation.
Today's this problem is
about change of basis.
It says the vector space of
polynomials in x of degree up
to 2 has a basis 1,
x, and x squared.
That's the obvious basis that
you would write for that
vector space.
But today we're going to
consider another basis, w1,
w2, and w3.
And we don't know what w1, w2,
and w3 are explicitly.
What we know is that their
values at x equals minus 1, 0,
and 1 are given by
this table here.
So there are 1 0 0,
0 1 0, and 0 0 1.
We're asked to do
the following.
We're asked to express
this polynomial.
So y of x is minus x plus 5
in this basis, w1, w2, w3.
We're asked to find the change
of basis matrices between
these two bases, 1, x, x
squared, and w1, w2, w3.
And finally, we're asked to
find the matrix of taking
derivatives, which is a linear
map on this space, in both of
these basis.
And let me give you an extra
level of challenge, which is
to try to do as much of this as
possible without explicitly
finding w1, w2, and w3.
I'll let you think about the
problem and then you can come
back and compare your
solution with mine.
Hi.
Welcome back.
So to start with the problem
a, we need to find
coefficients alpha,
theta, and gamma.
So that y of x is expressed
through, with this
coefficient, in this new
basis, w1, w2, and w3.
now, one way to do that would
be to look at this table of
values, explicitly find w1,
w2, and w3, so a quadratic
polynomial is--
all the information we
need about it is in
values at three points.
So say w1 is a1 plus b times
x plus c times x squared.
Find a, b, and c.
Find w1, w2, w3 explicitly,
and then go back to this
system and try to find alpha,
beta and gamma.
However, there's a trick.
Let's try to see if we can do it
without finding w1, w2, and
w3 explicitly.
So let me try to see
what are the values
of y at these points.
So y is minus x plus 5.
So the values are 6, 5, and 4.
And let me, instead of
considering this equation, let
me evaluate it at x is minus
1, x is 0, and x is 1.
What I get through this is that
w is what is minus 1.
Actually, let me write this--
I get w with minus 1, which is
a number, equals alpha times
w1 is minus 1, which is a
number, plus beta times w2 is
minus 1, plus gamma times
w3 at minus 1.
And similarly at 0, and
similarly at 1.
And now let me think of this
as a linear system that has
unknowns alpha, beta, and gamma
coefficients, these
values here at minus
1, 0, and 1.
And the right-hand side, well
what's written here on the
left-hand side. y at minus
1, y at 0, and y at 1.
If you write this in a matrix
and read off coefficients from
there, you get the
following system.
So this is the matrix of the
system read off from here.
These are the unknowns.
And these are the values
of the right-hand side.
And I hope you'll agree
that this is a very
easy system to solve.
We just get alpha is 6, beta
is 5, and gamma is 4.
So the solution to the first
part is y equals 6w1
plus 5w2 plus 4w3.
And let's notice
another thing.
No matter what values we put
here, this matrix is always
going to stay the same.
It's only the right-hand side
that's going to change.
So if we're given any other
polynomial now to express in a
basis w1, w2, and w3, we don't
have to do any thinking.
We don't have to do
any computations.
What we do is go back to our
table at the beginning and
just read off, let's go back
to the table, and just read
these values.
So in this case, y is
6 times w1, 5 times
w2, and 3 times w3.
And that's already a hint to
solving the b part, which is
find the change of basis
matrices between 1, x, x
squared and w1, w2, w3.
Change of basis matrices means
expressing one basis in terms
of another.
So as a part of the problem, we
will have to express 1, x,
and x squared in terms
of w1, w2, w3.
So let's just find their values
at these three points.
One is a constant, it just
takes value 1 everywhere.
x takes value minus 1 at minus
1, 0 at 0, and 1 at 1.
And x squared takes values 1
0 and 1 at minus 1 0 and 1.
And from this we can already
conclude the part b here, we
can conclude that 1 equals
w1 plus w2 plus w3.
That x equals minus
w1 plus w3.
And that x squared equals
And from this, we can
immediately write one change
of basis matrix.
Namely, since we know how to
express 1, x, and x squared in
terms of w1, w2, and w3, we can
just copy this information
over to this matrix, getting 1
1 1, minus 1 0 1, and 1 0 1.
So which matrix is this?
This is a matrix, so we have 1,
x, and x squared expressed
in terms of w1, w2, and w3.
So if we feed this matrix
something expressed in the
basis 1, x, and x squared, say
a, b, and c, what is going to
throw out is the same polynomial
expressed in this
basis here, w1, w2, and w3.
So I'm going to just write that
this is a matrix of this
basis change.
How do we get the other one?
Well very easy.
We know it's just the inverse
of A. So this is going to be
the matrix that takes something
written in this
basis and transfers
it to this basis.
I'm not going to calculate
the inverse of a
matrix in front of you.
Instead I'm going to
consult my oracle.
Sorry about that.
And my oracle says that the
inverse should be 0 1 0, minus
1/2 0 1/2, and 1/2
minus 1 1/2.
And that solves the b part.
Let's go into the c part.
The c part required us to
find a matrix of taking
derivatives, which is a linear
map in the space of
polynomials, in both
of these basis.
So let's first do the 1, x, x
squared basis because that
one's easier.
I'm going to call it Dx.
So I'm going to work in
basis 1, x, x squared.
And what I want to express is
the transformation of taking
derivatives.
So here I'm going to write the
vector to which taking
derivatives maps the polynomial
1, which is 0.
And that this expressed in the
basis 1, x, x squared.
In the second column I'm going
to write x prime, the vector
to which Dx send to vector x,
and that's equal to 1, which
expressed in this
basis is 1 0 0.
And here I'm going to write x
squared prime, which is 2x,
which expressed in this
basis is just x.
That one was easy.
For the other one, well we could
calculate w1, w2, w3
explicitly, take the
derivatives, go back to the
table and repeat the procedure
that we did already.
So expressing these derivatives
in terms of w1,
w2, w3, and that's
a lot of work.
But we pretty much already
did most of this work.
So we know how to take
derivatives in this basis, and
we know how to go between
these two basis.
So if we want to take a
derivative of something
written in the basis w1, w2,
w3, well let's first write
this something in basis
1, x, x squared.
Then let's take a derivative
of it.
And then let's write it
back in the original
basis that we want.
So it's multiplication
of three matrices.
We have all three-- matrix
multiplication is easy.
And my oracle, again, says that
this should be minus 3
over 2, 2, minus 1 over 2, minus
1 over 2, 0, 1 over 2,
and 1 over 2, minus
2, 3 over 2.
And that solves the problem.
Now, one thing that I would want
to discuss in the end is
how did you do with respect to
my challenge, which was let's
try to do as much of it as
possible without finding w1,
w2, and w3 explicitly.
And it seems like we
did really well.
There's nowhere on the board
written w1 equals,
w2 equals, w3 equals.
But is it really so?
It's not.
We calculated the matrix
of A inverse here.
And what this really means is
that w1, w2, and w3 written in
the basis 1, x, and x squared
are as follows.
w1 is minus 1/2 x plus
1/2 x squared.
w2 is 1 minus x squared.
And w3 is 1/2 x plus
1/2 x squared.
So you can check your work with
the help of this matrix
in case you did find w1,
w2, and w3 explicitly.
And that's all I wanted
to say today.