Problem number one: problem
number one addresses the idea
of electric fields.
Suppose we have a uniform
electric field: E, and I think
the electric field is 10 to the
3 newtons per coulomb, and
we have an electron.
We're here at E minus--
the electron has a certain
velocity, a huge velocity.
It's about 2 1/2% of the speed
of light, and the force that
the electron will experience--
F, the magnitude of that force,
equals the charge of
the electron times
the magnitude of
the electric field.
It is in the direction of the
electric field, or in the
opposite direction of
the electric field--
in this case, it's in the
opposite direction, and so
here is that force.
The electron is being
decelerated as it moves into
this electric field.
You can calculate the magnitude
of the force right
away: the acceleration, or I
should say, deceleration of
the electron is, then, this
force divided by the mass of
the electron.
Oo-- this should be an E. You
can calculate what the
acceleration is, and then going
back to 801], v at time
t equals t equals v at
time 0 minus at.
This minus takes already into
account that it's a
decelleration.
You want this to be 0, if you
want to know when it stands
still, and where it stands
still, and so you have one
equation with one unknown,
because you know v 0--
it's given--
and you know a, because
you just calculated
that, so out pops t.
If you now want to know how far
it travels, again, 801]--
x at time t minus x at time 0
equals v 0 t minus 1/2 at
squared, and the minus sign
takes into account the
decelleration.
You know all these quantities,
and so you can calculate the
distance that it travels until
it comes to a halt--
of course, the force will
continue to be in this
direction, and so it will return
in exactly the same
time that it took to
come to a halt.
If the motion along the E field
is only 1 centimeter,
then of course, it hasn't
come to a halt--
it's small, of course, but it
turns out that it is still
moving, and you're being ask
what is the percentage loss of
kinetic energy?
The kinetic energy at any moment
in time t 1 equals the
kinetic energy at some time
t equals 0, minus--
if there is negative
work done--
the work that is done between
time 0 and t 1 done by the
work done on the electron,
in this case.
It's the electric field that is
doing work, and the work in
negative, because F is in this
direction, and ds is in this
direction as it moves out.
What is the work that is done
by the electric field?
If we take the magnitude only
for now, it is the force that
we calculated times
the distance--
that is the 1 centimeter,
and you have to
confer that to mks--
and out pops the amount of work
that has been taken out
of the kinetic energy of the
original kinetic energy, which
was the 1/2 m v 0 squared.
You can easily calculate now
which percentage is lost--
that should not be
too difficult.