That brings us, then,
to number seven--
dipoles.
Whenever I see dipoles, I
get a little nervous--
in general, that means
a lot of mass.
In this case, it turns out
that that's not so.
I have here an x-axis, and
here I have the y-axis.
Here at a distance 'a'--
'y=a' --
I have charge '-q', and a
'y=-a' , I have '+q'.
I want to know what the
potential is at a point 'P'
everywhere on the y-axis--
here, here, and everywhere.
We'll take V equals
0 at infinity.
Notice that V is also 0 here.
Think about Walter
Lewin with his +1
Coulomb coming from infinity--
he has to do positive work to
come to this one if he wants
to reach this point.
He has to do exactly the same
amount of negative work to
this one if he wants to
come to this point--
the two cancel each other out,
so it's clear that the
potential is 0 here if I
define the potential at
infinity 0.
What, now, is the potential
at that point 'P'?
It depends a little bit on
where P is located, and
whether the position of 'P' is
larger than 'a', or whether
the position of 'P' is
smaller than 'a'.
What I mean by that is--
is it somewhere here, or
is it outside there?
I will assume that it
is outside, and
you will do the inside.
If I assume that it is outside,
then the potential at
that point 'P'--
it's a scalar--
is the sum of the potential due
to this point, and the sum
of the potential due
to this point.
Let's first do this one: that
equals '-q' divided by '4 pi
epsilon 0'.
Now, I have to take the distance
between these two
points, which we called 'R'
earlier, and that is 'y' if
'y' is the position off
'P' minus 'a'--
so, 'y-a' plus, because this has
a plus charge, 'q' divided
by '4 pi epsilon 0' times the
distance from here to here.
The distance from here to
here equals 'a+y' , so
we get 'y+a' .
You can massage these a little
bit, and you can--
following the instructions
of your book--
calculate and can simplify
it for 'y'.
It's much, much larger than 'a',
and that will simplify
matters enormously.
I'm not going to do that,
because it's not all that
difficult, but I want you to
see that if that's the part
that you were going to do, that
if point 'P' lies below
'a', the situation changes.
When I now calculate the
potential at point 'P' to do
this charge '-q', the '-q'
remains here, the '4 pi
epsilon 0' remains here, but now
the distance between that
point 'P' and this position
is no longer 'y-a' --
that position has now
become 'a-y' .
That is now the distance,
and so this changes.
However, this part does not
change, because if I am here
at a distance 'a' below
the y-axis--
this is the y-axis and
this is the x-axis--
then this separation
remains 'y+a'.
It's only this term
that changes.