PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture you've been talking
about implicitly defined
functions and implicit
differentiation.
So one of the reasons that these
are important is, or
that implicit differentiation is
important, is it sometimes
you have a function to find
implicitly and you
can't solve for it.
You don't have any algebraic
method for computing the
function values as
a formula, say.
So, for example, this function
that I've written on the board
that I've called w of x is
defined implicitly by the
equation that w of x plus 1
quantity times e to the w of x
is equal to x for all x.
So this function, some of its
values you can guess.
Like at x equals 0, the function
value is going to be
negative 1.
And the reason is that this
can't ever be 0, so the only
way to get this side to be 0
is if w is negative 1 if
this term is 0.
So some of its values are easy
to compute, but some of its
values aren't.
So for example, if I asked
you what w of 3/2
is, it's very hard.
There's no algebraic way you can
manipulate this equation
that will let you
figure that out.
So in that situation you might
still care about what the
function value is.
So what can you do?
Well, you can try and find a
numerical approximation.
So in this problem I'd like you
to try and estimate the
value w of 3/2 by using a linear
approximation to the
function, to the curve--
yeah.
A linear approximation of the
function w of x in order to
compute this value.
So as a hint, I've given you,
so you're trying to
compute w of 3/2.
As a hint I'm pointing out
to you that w of 1 is 0.
Right?
If you put in x equals
0 and w of 0 equals--
sorry-- if you put in x equals
1 and w of 1 equals 0 on the
left hand side, you do indeed
get 1, as you should.
So, OK.
So, good.
So that'll give you a hint about
where you could base
your linear approximation.
So why don't you pause the
video, take a few minutes to
work this out, come back, and
we can work it out together.
All right.
Welcome back.
So hopefully you've had a
chance to work on this
question a little bit.
So in order to do this linear
approximation that we want,
what we need to know are we need
to know a base point and
we need to know the derivative
of the function
at that base point.
And those are the two pieces of
data you need in order to
construct a linear
approximation.
So we have a good candidate for
a base point here, which
is the point 1, 0.
So this curve, whatever it looks
like, it passes through
the point 1, 0.
And that's the point we're
going to use for our
approximation.
So we're going to use the linear
approximation w of x is
approximately equal to w prime
of 1 times x minus 1 plus w of
1 when x is approximately
equal to 1.
So this is the linear
approximation we're going to
use, and we have that
w of 1 here is 0.
So this is, this is equal
to w prime of one
times x minus one.
Just the w of 1 is 0.
It just goes away.
So in order to estimate w of x,
and in particular w of 3/2,
what we need to know is
we need to know the
derivative of w.
OK?
And to get the derivative
of w, we need to use--
well, we have only one piece
of information about w.
Which is we have that
it's defined by
this implicit equation.
So in order to get the
derivative of w we have to use
implicit differentiation.
OK?
So let's do that.
So if we implicitly
differentiate this equation--
so let's start with the, the
right hand side is going to be
really easy.
Right?
We're going to differentiate
with respect to x.
The right hand side
is going to be 1.
On the left hand side is going
to be a little more
complicated.
We have a product and then this
piece, we're going to
have a chain rule situation.
Right?
We have e to the w of x.
So, OK.
So we're going to
take an implicit
derivative and on the left--
so OK, so the product rule
first. We take the derivative
of the first part, so that's
just w prime of x times the
second part-- that's
e to the w of x--
plus the first part-- that's
w of x plus 1--
times the derivative
of the second part.
So the second part is
e to the w of x.
So that gives me an e to the
w of x times w prime of x.
That's the chain rule.
So that's what happens
when I differentiate
the left hand side.
And on the right hand side
I take the derivative
of x and I get 1.
OK, good.
So now I've got this equation
and I need to solve this
equation for w prime.
Because if you look up here,
that's what I want.
I want a particular
value of w prime.
And as always happens in
implicit differentiation, from
the point of view of this w
prime it's only involved in
the equation in a
very simple way.
So there's it multiplied by
functions of x and w of x, but
not, you know, it's just
multiplied by something that
doesn't involve w
prime at all.
And then here it's multiplied
by something that doesn't
involve w prime at all.
So you can just collect your w
prime's and divide through.
You know, it's just like solving
a linear equation.
So here if we collect our w
prime's, this is w prime of x
times-- looks like--
w of x plus 2 times
e to the w of x.
Did I get that right?
Looks good.
OK, so that's still
equal to 1.
So that means that w prime
of x is just--
well, just, you know--
it's equal to 1 over w of x plus
2 times e to the w of x.
OK, so this is true
for every x.
But I don't need this equation
I just need the particular
value of w prime at 1.
So that's, so I'm going to take
this equation, then, and
I'm just going to put
in x equals 1.
So I put in x equals 1--
well, let me do it over here--
so I get w prime of 1.
And I just everywhere I had
an x, I put in a 1.
So actually, in this equation
the only place x appears is in
the argument of w.
So this is w of 1 plus 2
times e to the w of 1.
OK.
So in order to get w prime
of 1 I need to
know what w of 1 is.
But I had that.
I had it, it was right
back here.
There was, that was
my hint to you.
Right, this is why we're using
this point as a base point,
which is we know the value
of w for this value of x.
So we take that value.
So w of 1 is 0.
So this is just 1 over--
well, 0 plus 2 is--
2, and e to the 0 is 1.
So it's just 1 over 2.
Sorry, that's written
a little oddly.
We can make it 2 times 1.
So 1 over 2.
OK.
So I take that back
upstairs to this
equation that I had here.
And I have that w of x is
approximately equal to w prime
of 1 times x minus 1.
So w of x is approximately
equal to w prime of 1--
we saw is--
1/2 times x minus 1.
And that approximation was
good near our base point.
So that's good when
x is near 1.
All right.
And then, so this is the
linear approximation.
And I asked for the linear
approximation, its value at
the particular point,
x equals 3/2.
So w of 3/2 is approximately
1/2 times--
well, 3/2 minus 1
is also 1/2--
so this is a quarter.
OK, so this is our estimate
for w of 3/2.
w of 3/2 is approximately 1/4.
If you wanted a better estimate
you could try
iterating this process.
Now you might have
a, you know--
or choosing some base point
even closer if you could
figure out the value of w and
x near that, near this point
that you're interested in--
3/2.
So just to sum up what we did
was we had this implicitly
defined function w.
We wanted to estimate its value
at a point where we
couldn't compute
it explicitly.
So what we did was we did
our normal linear
approximation method.
Right?
So we wrote down our normal
linear approximation formula.
The only thing that was slightly
unusual is that we
had to use implicit
differentiation.
In order to compute the
derivative that appears in the
linear approximation, we
implicitly differentiated.
OK?
So that happened just like
normal, and then at the end we
plugged in the values that
we were interested in, to
actually compute the particular
value of that
approximation.
So I'll end there.