I'm very proud of you.
You did very well on the last
exam.
Class average is a little bit
above seventy.
Congratulations.
There were twenty-two students
who scored a hundred.
Many of you are interested in
where the dividing line is
between C and D.
If I take only the three exams
into account,
forget the quizzes,
forget the homework,
forget the
motor, and you add up the three
grades of your three exams,
the dividing line between C and
D will be somewhere in the
region a hundred thirty-five to
a hundred thirty-eight.
So you can use that for your
calibration where you stand.
The controversy between Newton
and Huygens about the nature of
light was settled in eighteen oh
one when Young demonstrated
convincingly
that light shows all the
characteristic of waves.
Now in the early twentieth
century, the particle character
of light surfaced again and this
um mysterious and very
fascinating duality of being
waves and particles at the same
time is now beautifully merged
in quantum mechanics.
But today I will focus on the
wave
character only.
Very characteristic for waves
are interference patterns which
are produced by two sources,
which simultaneously produce
traveling waves at exactly the
same frequency.
Let this be source number one
and let this be source number
two.
And they each produce waves
with the same frequency,
therefore the same wavelength,
and they go out let's say in
all directions.
They could be spherical,
in the case of water surface,
going out like rings.
And suppose you were here at
position P in space at a
distance R one from source
number one and at a distance R
two from source number two.
Then it is possible that at the
point P the two waves that
arrive are in
phase with each other.
That means the mountain from
two arrives at the same time as
a mountain from one,
and the valley from two arrives
at the same time as the valley
from one.
So the mountains become higher
and the valleys become lower.
We call that constructive
interference.
It is also possible that the
waves as they arrive at point P
are exactly a hundred eighty
degrees out of phase,
so that means that the
mountain from two arrives at
the same time as the valley from
one.
In which case they can kill
each other, and that we call
destructive interference.
You can have this with water
waves, so it's on a
two-dimensional surface.
You can also have it with
sound, which would be
three-dimensional.
So the waves go out on a
sphere.
And you can have it with
electromagnetic radiation as we
will
also see today,
which is of course also three
dimensions.
If particles oscillate then
their energy is proportional to
the square of their amplitudes.
So therefore since energy must
be conserved,
the amplitude of sound
oscillations and also of the
electric vector in the case of
electromagnetic radiation,
the amplitude must fall off as
one over the distance,
one over R.
Because you're talking
about three-D waves.
You're talking about spherical
waves.
And the surface area of a
sphere grows with R squared.
And so the amplitude must fall
off as one over R.
Now if we look at the
superposition of two waves in
this case at point P and we make
the distance large so that R one
and R two are much much larger
than the separation between
these two points,
then this fact that the
amplitude of
the wave from two is slightly
smaller than the amplitude from
the wave from one can then be
pretty much ignored.
Imagine that the path from here
to here is one-half of a
wavelength longer than the path
from here to here.
That means that this wave from
here to here will have traveled
half a period of an oscillation
longer than this one.
And that means they are
exactly a hundred eighty
degrees out of phase and so the
two can kill each other.
And we call that destructive
interference.
And so we're going to have
destructive interference when R
two minus R one is for instance
plus or minus one-half lambda
but it could also be plus or
minus three-halves lambda,
five-halves lambda,
and so on.
And so in general you would
have destructive interference if
the difference between R two and
R one is two N plus one times
lambda divided by two whereby N
is an integer,
could be zero,
or plus or minus one,
or plus or minus two,
and so on.
That's when you would have
destructive interference.
We would have constructive
interference if R two minus R
one is simply N times lambda.
So then the waves at point P
are in phase and N is again
could be zero,
plus or minus one,
plus or minus two,
and so on.
If the sum of the distance to
two points is a constant you get
an ellipse in mathematics.
If the difference is a
constant, which is the case
here, the difference to two
points is a constant value,
for instance one-half lambda,
then the curve is a hyperbola.
It would be a hyperbola if we
deal with a two-dimensional
surface.
But if we think of this as
three-dimensional,
so you can rotate the whole
thing about this axis,
then you get hyperboloids,
you get bowl-shaped surfaces.
And so if I'm now trying to
tighten the nuts a little bit,
suppose I have here two of
these sources that produce waves
and the separation between them
is D, then it is obvious that
the line right through the
middle of them and perpendicular
to them is always a maximum if
the two sources
are oscillating in phase.
So this line is immediately
clear that R two minus R one is
zero here.
If the two are in phase.
And they always have to
generate the same frequency of
course.
So this line would be always a
maximum.
Constructive interference.
It's this zero substitute
there.
And in case that we're talking
about three-dimensional,
this is of course a plane.
Going perpendicular to the
blackboard right through the
middle.
The difference R two minus R
one equals lambda would again
give me constructive
interference.
That would be a hyperbola then,
R two minus R one equals
lambda, that would again be a
maximum, and you can draw the
same line on this side,
and then R two minus R one
being two lambda again would be
a maximum.
And again if this is
three-dimensional you can rotate
it about this line and you get
bowls.
And so in between you're
obviously going to get the
minima, the destructive
interference,
lambda divided by two,
and then here you would have R
two minus R one is three-halves
lambda.
We call these lines where
you kill each other destructive
interference,
we call them nodal lines or in
case you have a surface it's a
nodal surface.
And the maxima are sometimes
also called antinodes,
but I may also refer to them
simply as maxima.
And so this is what we call an
interference pattern.
If you look right here between
on the line between the two
points then
you should be able to convince
yourself that the linear
separation here between two
lines of maxima is one-half
lambda.
Figure that out at home.
That's very easy.
Also the distance between these
two yellow lines here right in
between is one-half lambda.
And so that tells you then that
the number of lines or surfaces
which are maxima is very roughly
two D
divided by one-half lambda.
So this is the number of
maxima, which is also the same
roughly as the number of minima,
is then approximately two D
divided by lambda.
And so if you want more maxima,
if you want more of these
surfaces, you have a choice,
you can make D larger or you
can make the wavelength shorter.
And if you make the wavelength
shorter you can do that by
increasing the frequency
if you had that control.
The first thing that I'm going
to do is to make you see these
nodal lines with a demonstration
of water.
We have here two sources that
we can tap on the water and the
distance between those two
tappers, D, is ten centimeters,
so we're
talking about water here.
Uh we will tap with a frequency
of about seven hertz and what
you're going to see are very
clear nodal lines,
this is a two-dimensional
surface, where the water doesn't
move at all.
The mountains and the valleys
arrive at the same time.
The water is never moving at
all.
So let me make sure that you
can see that well.
And so I have to change my --
my lights.
I'll first turn it on,
that may be the easiest.
Starts tapping already.
I can see the nodal lines very
well.
So here you see the two tappers
and here you see a line whereby
the water is not moving at all.
At all moments in time it's
standing still.
Here's one.
Here is one.
And you even with a little bit
of
imagination can see that they
are really not straight lines
but they are hyperbolas.
If you're very close to one
tapper, the zero can never be
exactly zero,
because the amplitude of the
wave from this one then will
always be larger than the
amplitude from that one,
because as you go away from the
source the amplitude must fall
off on a two-dimensional surface
as one over the square root of
R.
In a three-dimensional wave
must fall of as one over R.
But if you're far enough away
then the distance is
approximately the same and so
the amplitudes of the individual
waves are very closely the same
and you can then like you see
here the water is absolutely
standing still.
And here are then the areas
whereby you see traveling waves,
they are traveling waves,
they're not standing waves,
that here you see if you were
sitting here in space the water
would be up and down,
bobbing up and down,
and the amplitude that you
would have is twice the
amplitude that you get from one,
because the mountains add
to the mountains and the
valleys add to the valleys.
But if you were here in space
you would be sitting still.
You would not be bobbing up and
down at all.
And that is very characteristic
for waves.
If I were to tap them a hundred
eighty degrees out of phase,
which I didn't -- they were in
phase -- then all nodal lines
would become
maxima and all maximum lines
would become nodes,
that goes without saying of
course.
It is essential that you --
that the frequencies are the
same, that is an absolute must.
They don't have to be in phase,
the two tappers,
if they're not in phase then
the positions in space where you
have maxima and minima will
change but a must is that the
frequency is the same.
Now I was hiking last year in
Utah when I noticed a butterfly
in the
water of a pond which was
fighting for its life.
And you see that butterfly
here.
Tom, perhaps you can turn off
that uh overhead.
You see the butterfly here,
and you see here projected on
the bottom the beautiful rings
dark and bright,
because these rings on the
water act like lenses,
and what you see very
dramatically is indeed what I
said, that the amplitude of the
wave must go down with distance,
because energy must be
conserved of
course in the wave,
and since the circumference
grows linearly with R,
the amplitude must go down as
one over the square root of R
because the energy in the wave
is proportional to the amplitude
squared.
So when I saw this it occurred
to me that it would be a good
idea to catch another butterfly,
put it next to it,
and then photograph -- make a
fantastic photograph of an
interference pattern.
But I realized of course
immediately having taken eight
oh two that the
frequencies of the two
butterflies would have to be
exactly the same and so I gave
up the idea and I decided not to
be cruel.
So no other butterfly was
sacrificed.
If we look at the directions
where we expect the maxima as
seen from the location of the
sources, then I want to remind
you of what a
hyperbola looks like.
If here are these two sources
and here is the center I can
draw a line here,
then a hyperbola would look
like this.
Let me re- remove the part on
the left, doesn't look too good,
but it's the same on the left
of course.
And what you remember from your
high school math,
that it approaches that line.
And therefore you can define
angle theta as seen from the
center between these two which
are the directions where you
have maxima and where you have
minima.
And that's what I am going to
work out for you now on this
blackboard here.
So here are now the two sources
that oscillate,
there's one here and there's
one
here and here is the center in
between them,
and let this separation be D.
And I am looking very far away
so that I'm approaching this
line where the hyperbolas merge
so to speak with the straight
line.
And so I look very far away
without being -- committing
myself how far,
I'm looking in the direction
theta away.
This is theta.
And so this is theta.
And I want to know in which
directions of theta I expect to
see maxima, and in which
direction I expect to see
minima.
So this is what we called
earlier R one and we called this
earlier R two,
it is the distance to that
point very far away.
If I want to know what R two
minus
R one is that's very easy now.
I draw a line from here
perpendicular to this line and
you see immediately that this
distance here is R two minus R
one.
But that distance is also you
realize that this angle is theta
it's the same one as that one,
so that distance here is also D
sine theta.
And so now I'm in business,
I can
predict in what directions we
will see constructive
interference.
Because all we are demanding
now, requesting,
that R two minus R one is N
times lambda.
And so we need that D sine
theta and I'll give it a
subindex N, as in Nancy,
equals N times lambda.
In others words that the sine
of theta N is simply N lambda
divided by D.
And that uniquely defines all
those directions,
the whole zoo of directions N
equals zero, that is the center
line, N equals one,
N equals two,
N equals three,
and so on.
And then I have the whole
family of destructive
interference.
Which would require that lambda
R two minus R one which is D
sine theta must now be two N
plus one
times lambda divided by two.
Just as we had it on the
blackboard there.
We discussed that earlier.
And so that requires then that
the sine of theta N for the
destructive interference is
going to be two N plus one times
lambda divided by two D.
So this
indicates the directions where
we expect maxima and where we
expect minima as seen from the
center between the two sources.
But now I would like to know
what the linear distance is if I
project this onto a screen which
is very far away.
And so let us have a screen at
a distance capital L which has
to be very far away,
so here are now the two
sources.
It's a different scale.
And here is a screen.
And the distance b- from the
two sources to the screen is
capital L.
And here is one of those
direction theta.
And you see immediately that if
I call this the direction X,
X being zero here,
that the tangent of theta is X
divided by L.
If but only if I deal with
small angles,
the tangent of theta is the
same as the sine of theta.
And therefore I can now tell
you where the maxima will lie on
that screen away from the center
line, which I call zero,
that is now when X of N is L
times the sine of theta,
in small angle approximation.
So this is approximately L
times N lambda divided by D,
and for the same reason you
will get
here c- destructive
interference when X of N is
going to be L times two N plus
one times lambda divided by two
D.
That is simple geometry.
So now we have all the
ingredients here on the
blackboard and I'm going to
leave it there for the rest of
the lecture.
Whenever we're going to do an
experiment with two sources
which are in phase at the same
frequency, you can predict the
directions of
maxima and minima and you can
even predict the separation,
the linear separation,
if you know how far away you
are from these sources.
And the first demonstration
that I'm going to do is with
sound.
We have here two loudspeakers.
And the distance between those
two loudspeakers,
we're going to do it with
sound, D, is one point five
meters.
That's
a given.
And the frequency is three
thousand hertz.
The wavelength therefore,
lambda, equals V divided by the
frequency, the speed of sound is
about three hundred forty meters
per second, divided by three
thousand, is about oh point one
one three meters.
So the wavelength is about
eleven point three centimeters.
I can now calculate
everyone who is sitting here
fweet right in the middle
through this whole plane will
have a maximum of sound,
and then when we go away at
angle theta, some will again
have maxima, and we go further
away theta, again maxima,
and in between will be the
minima.
And I'm going to calculate
where they fall in the lecture
hall.
The first thing that I'm going
to do is I'm going to give you N
as in Nancy and calculate that
angle theta
of N and I will do it for the
maxima.
In other words,
I'm going to use constructive
interference and you see that
the sine of theta N is lambda
divided by D.
That's the equation I use.
When N is zero the angle is
zero.
That is zero angle.
Everyone here will hear a
maximum.
When N is one,
and you may want to check that
at home, I find an angle of four
point three degrees,
and when N is two,
the angle is about double that,
is about eight point seven
degrees, and when N is three,
it should be close to thirteen
degrees, thirteen point one.
In case you take N is ten,
so I skip a few,
you get about forty-nine
degrees.
This is where the maximum fall.
And so there's going to be a
maximum here and then four point
three degrees away is again a
maximum.
But surely we would like
to know how far you in the
audience will have to move in
order to go from a maximum to a
minimum.
And so the way you have to
think of this is that if I make
here a picture of the lecture
hall, if here are these two
sources, you are at a distance L
away from here.
Some of you are five meters
away.
Some are ten meters away.
Some are fifteen meters away,
all the way in the back of the
audience.
And you want to know where
you're going to hear the maxima.
I call this X one,
I call this X two,
and I call this X three,
and this is zero.
So this is the meaning of theta
one.
And this is the meaning of
theta three, and this angle here
would be theta two.
That's the meaning of these
angles.
And so I can calculate now how
far
you have to move depending upon
what capital L is to hear to go
from one maximum in sound to
another maximum.
And we raise the a little more.
And so I will show you now s-
some of the results for maxima.
So I only go now for
constructive interference.
And I have done this for three
different distances.
Those of you who are five
meters away from me,
ten meters away from me,
and fifteen meters away from
me.
And what you see on the left
side is going to be X,
that is the linear separation,
and these, so these were in
meters, forgive me but I will do
these in centimeters.
And this is X one,
if you are five meters away
from me, you will have -- I will
put X one a
little lower than I have it
now, you will see shortly why I
put it a little lower -- X one
this is about thirty-eight
centimeters.
So the linear separation from
one to the next is thirty-eight
centimeters.
And you're ten meters away,
it's double that,
that's no surprise,
seventy-six centimeters.
And if you're fifteen meters
away it is a hundred and
thirteen centimeters.
And then X two which is the
position where you have another
maximum would be at seventy-six
centimeters and it would be at a
hundred and fifty-two
centimeters and it would be at
two hundred and twenty-eight
centimeters if you're fifteen
meters away from me.
So the minima will fall almost
exactly in between and so the
minima where in an ideal case
there is no sound at all,
sound plus sound gives silence,
think about it,
sound plus sound will give
silence, will be when you are
roughly at nineteen centimeters,
half of this,
this will be thirty-eight
centimeters.
Half of this,
and here will be something like
fifty-seven centimeters.
And you can calculate what
these values are,
they are exactly in between.
And so the conclusion is that
if you're five meters away from
me and you're near the center
line,
but you can also be a little
bit in this direction,
that the separation between
bright sound,
loud sound, which is always at
zero of course in the middle,
to silence is nineteen
centimeters.
And then you move another
nineteen centimeters and then
you hear loud sound.
If you are however ten meters
away from me,
just past the cameras,
then you have to move
thirty-eight centimeters to go
from loud sound to silence.
And if you're all the way in
the audience,
in the back of the
audience, it's more like sixty
centimeters.
And this is what we're going to
do now together.
I want you all to stand up and
I'm going to make you listen to
three thousand hertz.
And what I want you to do when
I turn on the two loudspeakers,
I want you to move your head
very slowly and try to find
locations where you hear
silence.
The position of silence is
extremely well-defined,
so don't go too fast,
you miss it,
also keep in mind that there
are reflections of the sound
from the walls,
and from the blackboard,
and so the pattern that I have
calculated here is not perfect.
But you will see that there
will be locations where sound
plus sound will give you
silence.
[tone]
[tone] You are a couple of
lousy scientists.
If the separation between a lot
of sound and silence is nineteen
centimeters, that's about the
separation of your ears,
you dummies,
so one ear could be at a
maximum, the other ear could be
at a minimum,
so at least close one ear.
[laughter] [tone] Go very
slowly.
[tone]
Who has found clear location
where [tone] the sound is nearly
zero [tone] or practically zero?
[tone] Most of you.
And you certainly can hear if
you move that there's an
enormous difference [tone] in
sound intensity.
[tone] [tone] So again,
who has found locations [tone]
whereby you clearly say this is
practically silence?
[tone] Ah, you see them all the
way in the back,
[tone] [tone] and the
separation, how far you have to
move, depends on
how far you are away from me.
Sit down again.
[audience noise] Young was a
sound engineer and as a sound
engineer he was very familiar
with the interference of sound.
He knew that sound and sound
can make silence.
And so in eighteen oh one he
demonstrated in a convincing way
that light plus light can create
darkness.
That would be the nail in the
coffin
that would demonstrate uniquely
that light are indeed waves,
and there was still this
controversy between Huygens and
Newton as you perhaps remember.
Newton wanted light to be
particles but Huygens wanted
them to be waves.
And the way that Young did his
experiment is as follows.
He had a screen,
don't think of it as this big,
you're talking now about
extraordinarily small
dimensions, you will understand
shortly how
small, and in this screen are
two openings,
two pinholes,
and light is coming from the
left and think of light as being
plain waves.
They reach these two openings
and these two openings according
to Huygens will produce circular
waves, spherical waves of
course, three-dimensionally.
These openings become Huygens
sources and spherical waves will
propagate out in this direction.
And so now we have exactly the
situation that we had with our
sound.
Now if all works well there
should be directions theta away
from this line where you see
darkness and other directions
where you see bright light.
And we are going to do it in a
way, we have the luxury of laser
beams, so we have very strong
light sources,
which Young did not have.
The way we are going to do it,
we have a -- a slide,
which is completely black,
but with a razor blade two
lines have been drawn on it.
And so I will draw these lines
as white lines.
But they're really openings.
And there is another one here.
And the separation between
these lines D is oh point oh
eight eight millimeters,
less than a tenth of a
millimeter.
When you look at them you
cannot even see that they are
two lines.
Our laser beam has a diameter
of about three millimeters,
which is thirty times larger
than this distance,
thirty times larger.
So what I'm going to show you
now that this is our laser beam,
is not to scale,
the laser beam is much larger
than that.
And so the light will go
through some parts of these
slots, as far as our laser beam
reaches, and we are now capable
of predicting when we're going
to project it there,
here are the two slots which
are like so, and so you're going
to get
interference patterns in these
directions theta,
and we can calculate what the
position X is going to be there
between the maxima.
And so if that is the screen
and if this is X equals zero,
and if this is X one and this
is X two, and of course the
whole thing is symmetric,
you can always go in the
opposite direction,
you can now calculate,
and you have all the tools,
I did it for you in great
detail using sound,
but you have all the tools to
do it now, you know D,
I'm going to tell you what
lambda is, it's six thousand
three hundred and twenty-eight
Angstroms, and one Angstrom is
ten to the minus ten meters,
so you can calculate all the
direction theta for which there
are maxima and for which there
are minima.
Minima means light plus light
gives darkness,
an amazing concept.
And you can then
if you know the distance from
here to the screen,
which is capital L,
you can calculate what the
separation is as we see it on
the screen, and L is roughly ten
meters, maybe eleven,
but that's not so important.
And so I calculated,
and you can confirm that -- and
you should confirm that that the
angle theta one,
I will only calculate theta
one, which is the angle then to
this point, theta zero is of
course always zero,
right, that's the easiest,
I find that theta one is oh
point four one degrees,
that is for maximum,
and that means that X one given
the distance of ten meters then
becomes seven point two
centimeters.
So from here to here on the
screen, from maximum to maximum,
will be about seven point two
centimeters, and from here to
here will then of course also be
about seven two centimeters,
and in between you will see
darkness.
The light from the two sources,
a hundred eighty degrees out of
phase, and that will give you
darkness.
Let me turn on the laser.
And turn off the lights.
Make sure I have my -- OK.
And there you see it.
There you see a maximum,
darkness, a maximum,
darkness,
a maximum, darkness,
and so on.
And the separation if I didn't
make a mistake between the
maxima is indeed about seven
centimeters.
Imagine what an incredible
moment this is in your life,
that you actually see that
light plus light can make
darkness.
So the waves go simultaneously
through both openings,
and each opening acts like a
Huygens source,
and the net result is that
these two waves arrive there on
the screen a hundred eighty
degrees out of phase at the
locations of darkness.
The censor is of course that
they have exactly the same
frequency which is what they do,
because we have one laser gun
going in and so the wave goes
through both slots.
So we're guaranteed,
and that was the secret,
that Young understood you're
guaranteed that the waves are
not only the same frequency but
they're even in phase
because they both go through to
both slots.
Now if you look very carefully
here you will see of course that
these maxima don't have the same
strength.
We will understand next lecture
why that's the case.
They would have very closely
the same strength if the opening
where we scratched out the black
on the slide was much much
smaller than the separation
between the two slots,
so to speak.
And that separation is
point oh eight eight
millimeter.
If we make the openings much
narrower, indeed,
the light intensities would be
more uniform,
each maximum would be
approximately the same strength,
but then very little light will
go through.
And so it's a tradeoff.
And the moment you make these
two openings,
these two slots,
larger and larger,
you will understand Friday why
then the light intensities are
not the same,
why the light intensity is a
maximum at the center and then
falls off
near the edge.
As you see.
It's a maximum here,
and then the light intensities
become smaller.
I've shown you now the
interference pattern with sound
and for red laser light,
but imagine now that I did the
same with white light.
The situation would be very
different, and maybe even
disappointing for you.
Let this be the location on the
screen.
So we -- we have X here,
and here X is zero.
And I want to know where the
maxima are in the red,
well that's very easy,
there will be a maximum here
when this position is L times
lambda divided by D.
This is when Nancy is one.
And there will also be a
maximum here when we have two L
times lambda divided by D.
And of course there will be one
on this side same distance.
And there will be one here,
this is when N is zero.
N is one.
N is two.
The red light will have maxima.
How about the blue light?
The blue light will have maxima
here, where L lambda
divided by D,
but lambda is different,
lambda for blue light is
smaller.
Substantially smaller than red
light, so the maximum of the
blue will fall here,
the maximum of the blue will
always fall at N equals zero
together with red,
and then Nancy equals two the
blue will fall here,
so this is Nancy two,
Nancy one, Nancy zero.
And here Nancy zero,
Nancy one, Nancy two.
And so the red and the blue and
therefore all the other colors
live a life of their own.
They don't talk to each other.
They come in with their own
separation in terms of angles
and in terms of locations X.
That's the reason why I chose
one and only one frequency with
the sound.
Because if I had exposed you to
many different frequencies,
many different wavelengths,
then the location of silence
for one wavelength is not the
location of silence for the
other wavelength.
And so the experiment would not
have worked.
And that's why it worked so
well with the laser,
the red laser,
which is practically one
wavelength, and so the minima
and the maxima are extremely
well-defined.
If we had done the experiment
with white light,
it wouldn't have been so
impressive, and on the next
slide I show you what you w-
would have seen then.
This is what white light would
have
done, this is a two-slit
interference pattern.
This is what red light would
have done.
Red light is a narrow bandwidth
of wavelengths,
well-defined black lines,
light plus light give darkness,
well-defined maxima,
and the blue notice that the
separation between the dark
lines and therefore also the
separation between the bright
lines is substantially smaller.
Because blue light has a
wavelength of about forty-five
hundred
Angstroms and red light roughly
sixty-five hundred.
So there's a big difference.
And so white light would then
give you the superposition of
all these colors,
and so you don't really get a
very nice interference pattern
of dark areas and bright areas,
because all the colors begin to
overlap and each live a life of
their own.
What I can do with sound and
what I did with water and what I
have done with laser light
I can also do with radio
electromagnetic waves.
With radar we have a
ten-gigahertz transmitter here
that we have used earlier in
this course.
And so I will now show you that
with radar you can also show
interference patterns and the
calculation that you see there
are absolutely identical.
The only thing I want to remind
you of, that the approximation
when you
know capital L that the tangent
theta is roughly the same as the
sine of theta is only true for
small angles.
Five degrees is fine,
ten degrees is fine,
but by the time that you reach
fifty, sixty or seventy degrees
that approximation is not true.
So then you really have to take
the tangent of theta.
That's no problem because you
first calculate what theta is,
because that equation is
correct, and then you can
calculate always where X is,
but then you use the tangent
and not the sine.
So these are approximations
which hold for small angles.
And so if now we look at a
ten-gigahertz transmitter,
that means we have two
transmitters,
one here and one here.
And their separation D is
twenty-three centimeters.
You see them here.
This is where they are.
Here's one and here's the
other, twenty-three centimeters
apart.
At ten gigahertz the wavelength
is three centimeters.
You can confirm that.
The speed is speed of light.
Lambda is the speed of light
divided by frequency.
That gives you the wavelength.
And we have here at a distance
L which is a hundred and twenty
centimeters, we have here a
receiver and a track,
so this is X equals zero and
here we can move it along X and
so you can calculate now at what
angles seen from this point
there will be a maximum there.
Theta zero is obvious.
Right here there will be a
maximum.
The two waves,
the distance between them is
zero, R two minus R one is zero.
So they will constructively
interfere.
But there is another angle,
theta one, for which again
there
will be constructive
interference.
And you can confirm that I
found for these numbers that
theta one is about
seven-and-a-half degrees.
This is now for maxima.
And so roughly at an angle
which is half that value you
will find silence.
Silence means that the two
radio waves will kill each
other.
Essential for the maximum to be
here is of course that the two
transmitters are in phase.
We could have rigged it up so
that they were a hundred eighty
degrees out of phase in which
case there would be silence
here.
Silence in this case means that
the radar would kill the radar.
But I do use the word silence
for a good reason,
because the way we rigged this
up is the same way we did it
before.
We modulate this ten-gigahertz
signal with a thousand-hertz
audio signal.
We call that amplitude
modulation.
And the receiver
which is here receives the
ten-gigahertz radiation which is
modulated at a thousand hertz.
We feed it to an amplifier.
We demodulate it and you will
hear the thousand hertz.
And so we can also move it
along this track here and find
the location X one whereby we
have our first maximum apart
from the zero.
And I found that that is very
roughly at fifteen point five
centimeters.
And you should confirm that
using
those equations.
Equations are the same.
Whether you deal with sound or
with red laser light or with
gigahertz makes no difference.
And so let's turn now to this
demonstration.
I will turn on the -- the two
transmitters and here is the
receiver which is exactly at
angle theta zero.
So there's a maximum.
I'm now going to close one
transmitter,
[tone] put my hand in front.
[tone] And you think about what
will be the reduction of
intensity of the sound here.
[tone] If I close one,
it's substantially down.
You may think that it is down
by a factor of two.
Because we have only one
transmitter instead of two.
You're wrong.
If you think that,
you do not understand
interference.
It is four times lower when I
hold my hands over one.
Figure it out for yourself.
I'll test you on the final to
see
whether you really understood
that.
So now the sound is four times
larger than when I cover one up.
I'll cover the other one up.
It's down by a factor of four.
[tone] I can cover this one up
and then you hear nothing of
course.
[tone] Now I will move this one
[tone] to the location [tone]
where there is destructive
interference,
[tone] which should be about
half of fifteen point six
centimeters.
[tone] [cough]
Maybe you have good ears but I
hear nothing anymore.
Now I go through it and find
the maximum, which is about
fifteen point six centimeters.
[tone] Here it is.
[tone] And the other side,
[tone] here's the maximum at
center, so here should be a
minimum, there it is,
and I go to the other side,
there should be a maximum.
[tone] And there it is.
[tone] So what I have shown you
today is I've shown you the
interference pattern of sound,
of water, of red laser light,
of radar, and at the very least
I hope I've convinced you as
Young convinced the world in
eighteen oh one that light are
waves.
And that means that Huygens was
right and Newton was wrong.
Now that should perhaps not
surprise you because Huygens was
Dutch.