6.
27-16.
Oh, my goodness.
I have to draw a
large diagram.
Plus-minus 20 here.
1 ohm.
Here is a resistor.
6 ohms. Comes down.
Comes down the point 'a'.
Here is resistor, 4 ohms. Here
is a resistor, 1 ohm.
Then there is a battery of which
we do not know the EMF.
We call it 'E1'--
this is the plus side and
this is the minus side.
Goes to point 'b'.
But that's not all.
Here is a resistor, 1 ohm.
And then there is another
battery of which we do not
know the EMF, 'E2'.
Plus side, minus side.
And then there is here
a resistor, 2
ohms. And that is it.
And what you also are being
told, and I believe that's
all, that the current through
here is 1 ampere, and that the
current through here
is 2 amperes.
Now follow me very
closely now.
Charge cannot pile up.
Whatever charge flows in here
per second must flow out here
per second.
And that holds for this
point, for this
point, for this point--
it holds for any point
in the circuit.
If 1 ampere flows in and 2
amperes flow out, well, then
clearly there must have come
1 ampere from the sides.
Otherwise never 2 amperes
could come down here.
So also through here
there is 1 ampere.
But these 2 amperes keep
going down here--
2 amperes--
arrives here at this
point 'b'.
1 ampere goes to the left, so
it is a must that 1 ampere
goes this way.
Otherwise there would be a
pile up of charge here.
And so 1 ampere then goes
through this whole train here,
and indeed, ah.
You see that's exactly
what we have--
1 ampere.
And now what you're being asked
is what is the EMF of
battery one, EMF of battery two,
and what is the potential
difference from here to here?
I'm going to apply
Kirchhoff's Law.
I start at this point 'b', but
you can start at any point and
do close circles.
And I will go counter
clockwise.
And the first loop that I will
choose is the loop that goes
all the way around.
From here to here
to here to here.
So I ignore this inner part.
And remember, plus is uphill,
minus is downhill.
OK.
So here we are.
We're going this way, we're
going this way.
This point has a higher
potential than this-- the
current is in this direction--
so I go downhill.
So I get minus 6.
Now I go uphill.
I go to a higher potential.
Plus 20.
Now the current is in
this direction so I
go to a lower potential.
So it's minus 1.
Nothing here, nothing
here, nothing here.
Current is in this direction,
I go to a lower potential--
minus 2.
I reach this battery, I go from
a high potential to a low
potential, I go downhill--
minus E2'.
I go through this resistor, 2
ohms, 2 amperes, potential
difference is 4 volts, I go
to a lower potential,
minus 4 equals 0.
One equation with one unknown.
And I find that EMF of that
battery equals 7 volts.
Now I have a choice.
I can take this loop.
Or I can take this loop.
I can go clockwise, I can
go counter clockwise.
It should all make
no difference.
I have decided to take this loop
and go counter clockwise.
Where you start doesn't matter,
but I will start again
at the point b.
So I go up here.
Nothing happens.
I climb up the potential.
This is higher than that,
so I get plus 'E1'.
Here I have 1 ampere going
through 1 ohm.
I go downhill in potential,
minus 1.
Here I go 4 volts down in
potential, minus 4.
I come around here, I
go 2 volts down in
potential, minus 2.
Here I see 'E2'.
I go down in potential.
7 volts down in potential,
minus 7.
Here I go 4 volts down in
potential, minus 4.
And according to Kirchhoff's
Law that is 0.
And if I did not make a mistake,
I find that the EMF
of that battery is +18 volts.
So I've used Kirchhoff's
Law twice.
First this route to
get this one.
And then this route
to get this one.
But you could have chosen
other routes.
As long as you make close
loops and the direction
doesn't matter, but what does
matter that you are very
disciplinized in what
you call 'plus' and
what you call 'minus'.
If you want to call uphill
minus, be my guess.
That's OK.
I call uphill plus.
But you must do it in
a consistent way.
And now you're being asked
what is the potential
difference between
'Vb' minus 'Va'.
Well, I think you
can do that one.
I've no doubts.