Problem number 7,
which is 27-53.
A very interesting, very
interesting, problem.
Here is 6 ohm.
I call this point P.
Here is 3 ohm.
I will delete the word
ohm, the symbol ohm.
This is 3 ohm.
Switch 'S'.
Continues here.
3 ohm.
6 ohm.
This point connected
to a battery.
Plus minus 36 volts all the
way back to point 'P'.
And that's the circuit.
And as we start 'S' is open.
And you are being asked, what
is the potential difference
between this point 'a'
and this point 'b'?
If the switch is open, there's
no current flowing through
here, there is 36
volts over here,
there is 9 ohm in series.
So Ohm's Law immediately tells
me that the current through
here is 4 amperes.
Here is also 9 ohm.
So also the current for
both these two,
'i', is also 4 ampers.
And no current through here.
What is 'VP' minus 'Va'?
'VP' minus 'Va'?
'P' is a higher potential
than 'a'.
4 ampere 6 ohm.
So there is plus 24 volts.
What is 'VP' minus 'Vb'?
'VP' minus 'Vb'?
This has a higher potential than
this, 3 ohms, 4 amperes,
that is plus 12 volts.
So if you want to know the
potentials, this is 36, this
jump is 24, so that leaves
this with 12.
0 here.
This jump is 12, so that leaves
this with plus 24, and
this jump is 0.
So here you see the
full potentials
at these four positions.
And so it's immediately obvious
that 'Va' minus 'Vb'
equals 12 minus 24
equals -12 volts.
So therefore, if you throw the
switch, clearly there's going
to be a current going
through here.
That is inevitable.
And that's exactly what
we are going to do.
We're going to close the switch
and we want to know,
what is the current through
that horizontal section?
Now I will make a slightly
different drawing.
Not because there was anything
wrong with the previous one,
but I just feel like making
a difference drawing.
I don't want to get bored.
So when you don't want
to get bored you
do something different.
This is that point 'P'.
This is that point 'a'.
This is the point 'b'.
Circuit, no change.
3 ohms. Here, 6 ohms. This
points is going back, 36 volt
battery, to this point.
And you will convince yourself
that this circuit is
completely identical.
No.
Let current i going
through in here.
And let the current split here
between 'i1' and 'i2'.
So I always know that 'i'
equals 'i1' plus 'i2'.
I make now the assumption, which
could be wrong, that
there's also a current flowing
in this direction,
which I call 'i3'.
If I find 'i3' later to
be negative, no sweat.
It means that the current
is flowing in
the opposite direction.
So that's no problem.
When I come to this point here,
if 'i2' is coming in and
'i3' is going out-- excuse me.
Forgive me--
I call this 'i2' and
I call this 'i1'.
And I realize that it makes no
difference, but since that's
the way I have made my notations
I would like to
stick to that.
So I call this 'i1' and
I call this 'i2'.
So 'i2' comes in, 'i3' comes
out, so then there's only one
way that upwards must
go 'i1' minus 'i3'.
And if this number 'i1' minus
'i3' is positive, then indeed
there will be a current
in this direction.
If it is negative then there
will be a current going in
this direction.
Now we come to this point 'a'.
'i2' is coming in, 'i1' is
coming in, and 'i3'--
negative.
So therefore, I have
here minus i3.
So that's the current
for this resistor.
But now what's at this point?
'i1' plus 'i2' minus
'i3' plus 'i3'.
So what comes out here
is 'i1' plus 'i2',
which is exactly 'i'.
And so my symbols are internally
completely
consistent.
And so what I have to find now
is I have to find three
equations created with
three unknowns.
I want to know what 'i1'
is, what 'i2' is,
and what 'i3' is.
And then I, of course, also know
'i' because I know that
'i' is 'i1' plus
'i2' plus 'i3'.
And so I have to apply
Kirchhoff's Law three times in
an independent fashion so that
I can get, in a relatively
quick way, 'i1',
'i2', and 'i3'.
All right.
Where do we start?
And in what direction are
we going to march?
I suggest that we start here.
And I suggest that
we go in this
direction counter clockwise.
And I suggest that our
first journey--
you could, of course, choose
any other journey--
but I suggest that our first
journey is going to be all the
way through the top and back.
All the way through
the top and back.
Ready for that?
Uphill.
First, I'm going to make a
little easy table. 'E1', 'i1',
'i2', and 'i3'.
I go uphill 36 volts, so
I have here plus 36.
I go downhill '6 times 'i2'',
so I get a minus 6 here.
You must multiply
that by 'i2'.
I go downhill '3 'i1'.
Minus 3.
Downhill '3 'i2''.
Uphill '3 i3', therefore
plus 3.
Because remember, this
is a minus sign.
And I come out here
and I'm finished.
This is 0.
What now is my second
loop going to be?
Well, take your pick.
I've decided to take
the lower one.
I could have picked another
one, but I'm going to
pick the lower one.
You ready for the lower one?
36.
I go through here, I
go down '3 'i1''.
Minus 3.
I come here, I go down
in potential.
'6 'i3''.
Minus 6.
And there's a 0 here.
Ha.
There is no 'i2'.
And that equals 0.
Now I have to choose
a third loop.
And for my third loop--
watch me carefully--
I could pick this one, I could
pick this one, I could have
picked this one, but I'm
going to pick this one.
So here, through here, up
here, down here, this
way, I'm back here.
Why not?
I can choose any
one I want to.
Why not doing that one?
36--
that's this one--
minus '6 'i2''.
Now--
careful--
i1 is coming towards me.
That means I'm going up in
potential because of i1.
So there is plus 3.
But it's going to be
minus 3 for 'i3'.
So now I'm here.
I'm going down '6 'i3'', so I
have another minus 6 here.
And I come out here,
and this equals 0.
Well, three equations
with three unknowns.
You have to multiply
them, of course.
So this is 36 minus '3
'i1'' won't minus '9
'i2'' 3 i3 equals 0.
And you can solve these three
equations with three unknowns.
I have a little bit extra time
and I will help you a little,
although I'm not going to
solve them for you.
I'm going to divide them all by
3, so I will get 12 minus 1
minus 3 plus 1, 0.
12 minus 1, 0, minus 2, 0.
12 plus 1 minus 2 minus 3, 0.
I call this equation 1, equation
2, and equation 3.
And what is interesting, that
if you subtract 1 from 2--
so 2 minus 1--
if you subtract this one from
this one you find immediately
that 'i2' equals 'i3'.
And that's not so obvious.
And when I found that I said
to myself, maybe there is a
faster way to see that.
And so I went back to this
diagram and I looked.
Why?
Is there any obvious reasons why
this current here is the
same as this current here?
Well, there's a lot
of symmetry.
This is a 6, this is a 6, this
is a 3, this is a 3, but then
there is a 3 here.
I'll be very frank with you.
I could not find an obvious
reason why 'i2' is 'i3'.
If you do, I would be very
obliged and very grateful if
you give me a call and
you let me know.
In any case, you can massage
these three equations.
And I think I found
that 'i1' is
something like 5.14 amperes.
And I think I find 'i2' equals
'i3' equals 3.43 amperes.
Three equations with three
unknowns you have to solve.
Now you have to know what is
the current through 'iS'.
That, of course, is
'i1' minus 'i3'.
And if this turns to be
positive, turns out then the
current is indeed going up.
And it is indeed going up
because you find that it is
1.71 amperes.
And so the current through that
resistor three is indeed
in the upwards direction.