PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
We've been talking about
antidifferentiation or
integration by substitution
and also by a method that
Professor Jerison called,
advanced guessing.
So I have a few problems up
on the board behind me.
Three antiderivatives
for you to compute.
So the first one is e to the
2x times cosine of the
quantity 1 minus
e to the 2x dx.
The second one is 4x times the
quantity 5x squared minus 1
raised to the 1/3 power.
And the third one
is tan of x dx.
So why that you spend a few
minutes, try to compute those
antiderivatives yourself,
come back and we
can see how you did.
All right, so welcome back.
We have these three
antiderivative, so let's take
them in order.
So this first one that I wrote
is the antiderivative of e to
the 2x times cosine
of the quantity 1
minus e to the 2x dx.
So this problem seems to me like
a good candidate for a
substitution.
So we have this clear
sort of nested
function thing going on.
We have cosine of 1
minus e to the 2x.
And then out front we have
something that looks a lot
like the derivative of this
1 minus e to the 2x.
So I'm going to try this
with substitution then.
And I think there are, you
know, a few choices of
substitution but a natural one
is to sort of find the most
complicated inside piece.
So in this case, that's
this whole thing, 1
minus e to the 2x.
So I'm going to take for my
substitution, I'm going to
take u equals 1 minus
e to the 2x.
And so that means du is equal
to minus 2 e to the 2x dx.
OK, so that's my substitution.
And when I put my substitution
into this
integral, what do I get?
Well, so I have cosine of 1
minus e to the 2x just becomes
cosine of u.
Now e to the 2x dx,
that's very, very
close to this du here.
So what's different is that
here I have a minus 2.
So actually e to the 2x dx
is du divided by minus 2.
So this is cosine u times
du divided by minus 2.
Now another way to get to this
point is you could solve this
equation for dx and substitute
it in and also solve this
equation for e to the 2x and
substitute it in and things
should work out more or less the
same if you try that out.
So actually you won't even
need to make that second
substitution.
You'll just get some nice
cancellation there.
It's even simpler than
what I just said.
OK, so we do this
antiderivative, we've made
this substitution.
So now we have just the
antiderivative of a cosine function.
All right, well that's
not that bad.
Because we know that the
derivative of sine is cosine.
So the antiderivative
of cosine is sine.
So this is equal to-- so that
minus 2, that 1 over minus 2
is just going to stick around.
So it's 1 over minus 2 sine of
u plus a constant of course,
plus an arbitrary constant.
And OK, and so, but my original
function was in terms
of x, so I want to bring
everything back in terms of x.
And so I need to substitute
back in, get rid of u and
replace it with x.
So here that's a, I'll just go
back to what my substitution
was and I replace all
my u's with it.
So this is minus 1/2 sine the
quantity 1 minus e to the 2x
plus a constant.
All right, so this is the
antiderivative of this first
expression here.
OK, so now, how about
the second one?
So the second one, we could
also do it with a
substitution.
This is also sort of a prime
suspect for advanced guessing.
So we see here that we have
some, this polynomial raised
to some power.
So this is 5x squared
minus 1 to the 1/3.
So how can we get from a
derivative, something like 5x
squared minus 1 quantity
to the 1/3?
Well if you started off with 5x
squared minus 1 to the 4/3
thirds and took a derivative,
you would have this 5x squared
minus 1 to the 1/3 coming out.
And you would also have some
stuff coming out in front by
the chain rule.
Well what kind of stuff?
Well you know, it would be
some derivative of this
quadratic polynomial, which
would be some linear
polynomial.
And indeed, that
kind of matches
what we have out front.
So a good guess for advanced
guessing, is that we can look
at-- so d over dx of
5x squared minus 1
quantity to the 4/3.
So OK, so this derivative we can
compute by the chain rule.
So this is 4/3 times
5x squared minus
1 to the 1/3 times--
OK, so now I need to do the
chain rule, I need to take the
derivative of the inside.
Well that's--
OK, so the minus 1 gets killed
by the derivative, so 5x
squared, that becomes 10x.
So I can rewrite this as 40x
over 3 times 5x squared minus
1 to the 1/3.
So this looks very much like
the thing that we were
interested in.
Right?
We were-- where'd it go?
Oh, here it is.
And the thing we were trying
to antidifferentiate.
So the difference is just this
constant out front is a little
bit different.
So here I have 4, whereas
when I took this
derivative I had 40/3.
So I need to correct for that.
And the correction is just to
say, instead of starting with
this 5x squared minus 1 to the
4/3, I need to start with some
multiple of it to make
the constant work out
right in the end.
So in this case I was off by a
multiple of 10/3, so I need to
correct by multiplying
through by 3/10.
So we get that the
antiderivative that we want.
The antiderivative of 4x times
the quantity 5x squared minus
1 to the 1/3 dx is equal
to, well it's
equal to 3/10 of this.
5x squared minus 1 to the 4/3.
OK, so that's our second
antiderivative, which we got
by advanced guessing.
Now let's look at
the third one.
So the third one is tan x.
Now I sort of promised you by
asking this question in this
section on substitution that
there's, you know, some
substitution you can make.
But it's not sort of obvious
just from looking at tan x
what should be substituted
where.
At least it isn't
obvious to me.
But one thing that can help
often when you don't
immediately see a substitution,
is to try
rewriting things in
equivalent ways.
So sometimes you can do some
algebra or some other
manipulation.
In this case there's a very
simple sort of rewriting that
you can do.
Which is that tangent of x can
be expressed in terms of sine
and cosine of x.
So we can rewrite the
antiderivative of tan x dx as
integral sine x over
cosine x dx.
OK, so now what do we see?
So, I see in the denominator
a cosine of x.
And then up top I have
a sine x dx.
So sine x dx, that's really
close to the differential of
cosine of x.
So I'm going to try
this substitution.
And I'm going to try
the substitution u
equals cosine x.
So if I make the substitution
I get du is equal to
minus sine x dx.
Which is, OK, so now if I plug
these values in with this
substitution, this integral
becomes the integral, well
it's minus 1 or minus
du over u.
That's a nice simple
antiderivative to have. So
we've seen this before.
So this is just a logarithm.
So the minus sine
comes out front.
So this is minus ln
of the absolute
value of u plus a constant.
And now we had this, that
u was cosine of x.
So this is minus ln of the
absolute value of cosine of x
plus a constant.
Now this should look a
little bit familiar.
Because in one of Christine's
recitations earlier, she had
you compute the derivative
of ln of cosine x.
And in that case you saw that
that derivative was equal to
minus tangent of x.
Just like it should be.
So, all right, so there we go.
That was three examples of
antidifferentiation by
substitution and advanced
guessing.
So I'll leave you with that.