PROFESSOR: Problem number one.
Let's first look at Ampere's
law, which we are going to
need the closed loop integral of
B.dl, I'm not lucky with my
pens, am I?
This is a good one.
Equals mu zero times I thru
plus, and here comes the
famous term by Maxwell, d/dt
integral of E.da .
And this part, including the
epsilon zero is often called
the displacement current.
It's essential that you realize
that is a closed loop
and that's you must attach to
that closed loop an open
surface and you have to do the
calculation of this with that
open surface and take
the time derivative.
Now, the problem is
a very cute one.
I have a very small,
very small closed
loop and a huge balloon.
This is the balloon.
And there is an opening here.
So it's really a closed loop
and it's an open surface.
And I have such a closed loop
and an open surface here.
My Japanese balloon.
Let me first blow it up.
Here you see it.
You see the opening, I have a
pencil here, and you see you
can go in here, the opening.
So this is that closed loop
and in this problem we're
going to make this closed
loop go to zero.
I have in here a radioactive
source, alpha
particles coming out.
Alpha particles are two protons
and two neutrons.
There goes these alpha
particles.
So these is a positive current
flowing out, uniformly in all
directions.
Positive charge, positive
correct.
Q, enclosed here becomes
negative and therefore the dQ
/ dt becomes a negative value.
Because if we start with a
neutral radioactive source,
then the source becomes
increasingly more negative.
Now, if we're going to close
this gap, we can apply Gauss's
Law, which says that the closed
surface integral of
E.dA equals Q enclosed divided
by epsilon zero.
If I make this loop zero, then
this term becomes zero.
And so what I have now
is that zero equals--
if you get the mu zero, I
lose it on both sides--
equals I thru plus epsilon zero
times d / dt times the
integral of the electric flux
through that open surface.
Look now, that's this term
here, which is a closed
surface, and this term here,
which is an open surface,
become the same if you
make the loop zero.
And so I know find that zero
equals I thru plus, I take the
derivative and so this becomes
dQ / dt, I have an epsilon
zero here, and an epsilon zero
here, and so they cancel.
And this is a totally
trivial result.
It is immediately obvious.
What it's telling you is, that
I thru, this closed balloon,
equals minus dQ / dt.
Well, we did not Maxwell's
equations to tell us that.
The radioactive source is
becoming more and more and
more negative, so it's clear
that the current that is going
out through this surface,
by definition is the
charge per unit time.
And the minus sign is only
because the radioactive source
becomes more negative.
The beauty however is, that we
find is absolutely trivial
result, for which we did not
need Maxwell's equations at
all, but is entirely consistent
with Maxwell's equations.
And it's only consistent with
Maxwell's equations because we
allowed for this displacement
current term.
If we didn't have this
displacement current term, we
would've found the embarrassing
answer, clearly
the wrong answer, that
I thru would be zero.
Which is obviously not true.
And so, what I like about this
problem, that it derives in
what you may call a rather
complicated way using Ampere's
Law, including the displacement
term, and derives
in a very complicated way the
answer, which we already knew,
mainly that the current
is nothing but the
charge per unit time.
This we could have written
down without thinking.
We could only have found it from
Maxwell's equations, if
however we had incorporated
the displacement current.
And that's why I really like
this problem quite a bit.
It's really a marvel
in my opinion.