PROFESSOR: Historic moment:
we're going to discuss,
exclusively, Ampere's Law, as
it was amended by Maxwell.
He is a genius who recognized
that changing electric fields
can cause a magnetic field.
We will see some remarkable
examples why that was
necessary, and out of that, of
course, came this fabulous
victory of the theory.
You will see this later in the
course that it not only
predicts the existence of
electromagnetic radiation, but
it even predicts that the
speed of light of all
electromagnetic radiation is 1
over the square root of mu 0
times epsilon 0.
A remarkable victory, and
it turned out that
that's what it was.
Before I go into the specific
problems, I want to do with
you a classic, which covers
effectively all conceivable
problems, all conceivable
problems with this new concept
of displacement current, and
then we'll do the problems.
Let's first write down
the new equation.
Closed loop integral of B.dl
equals mu 0 times I thru plus
mu 0 times epsilon 0 times
d/dt the integral of E.dA
What does this mean?
It means that you must
choose a closed loop.
Any closed loop is fine.
Of course, if you don't choose
a clever loop, the equation
still holds, but it doesn't do
you any good, because you've
gone to introduce symmetry;
otherwise, you
can't solve a problem.
But any loop, in principle,
will do.
Then you attach to that
closed loop an open
surface; it's open.
Does it have to be flat?
No.
It can be a bag, like
a shopping bag.
So this could be the closed
loop, and you could have a
surface like a hat you can put
over your head, and we will do
that today.
I thru is the current that pokes
through that surface.
The whole concept of
a current going
through a loop is nonsense.
This is an electric flux, and
this is the time derivative of
that electric flux.
And this is the time derivative
of electric flux
going through that
open surface.
So now I come with my
classic problem.
Here is my classic problem.
Let's keep this equation
a little bit at hand.
I have a capacitor.
It is not a problem on your
assignment, although you have
similar ones.
Let's assume that the
plates are circular.
That makes it a little easy
to calculate things.
And let's assume that the radius
of the plates is R, so
the area of each plate
is pi R squared.
We are charging this capacitor
with a constant current, Ic.
So the inside here becomes
positively charged and is
growing the charge, and so you
get an electric field, which
is pointing in this direction,
and this electric field E is
growing in time, because more
and more charge accumulates.
We will make a simplified
assumption that the electric
field is constant between the
capacitor plates; it's not
true, but it will be our
assumption and that E outsides
the capacitor equals 0.
We will make that assumption.
Now, I'm asking you
three questions.
What is the magnetic field at
a point P1 at a distance r
from the wire, whereby for P1,
r equals larger than R. And I
want to know the same for a
point P2, which is inside the
capacitor, at least if I have
a plane perpendicular to the
wire, that plane would
completely go between the
capacitor plates.
So also for P2, r is larger than
R. And then I'm going to
ask you, what is the magnetic
field at point 3, which is at
a distance r from the center
line, whereby r is smaller or
equal than R. You can also
put equal signs here.
That is our goal.
Let's first take P1.
It's completely classic.
You don't even need Maxwell's
new equation; you simply take
Ampere's Law.
If this is your point P1, you
choose, as your closed loop, a
circle which is completely
symmetric
relative to the wire.
You choose a flat surface; there
is no reason why you
would not do that here.
There is a conduction current
Ic coming in here; and there
is a conduction current
Ic coming out there.
This is a surface, and
the current is
penetrating that surface.
If we look from the left, we
know that the magnetic field
will be going around
clockwise.
So if I look at the current
going away from me, by
convention, the magnetic field
will be going around in
circles, symmetric about
the central line.
And of course, if I choose a
circle, concentric circle, the
B field will be the same
everywhere, because it has the
same distance to the wire:
clockwise when the current
goes away from me,
counterclockwise when the
current comes to me.
It's a convention.
So I don't worry even about
the direction anymore.
I know the direction already,
so I don't even worry about
signs too much.
I am only interested, now,
in the magnitude.
So I apply Ampere's Law.
There is no changing electric
flux going through this
surface, which I have
here, so I'm only
dealing with this term.
This term is 0; this is the only
term I have. So I get B
times 2 pi r equals mu 0 times
the conduction current, and we
get a result that we have
seen before: mu 0 Ic
divided by 2 pi r.
Magnetic field falls off as 1
over r, and seen from the left
sides, it goes around
clockwise.
Now let's go to point P2.
With point P2, I'm going to make
exactly the same; I will
have, here, capacitor plates;
here are the current wires;
here is point P2.
Again, I'm going to make the
circle, concentric circle, and
the radius here is r;
this is point P2.
I now have a choice; well,
I have lots of choices.
But I have, now, two obvious
choices for the surface, open
surface attached to the loop.
One would be this; and another
one would be this.
It's like a shopping bag;
it's open here.
I can stick my hand in here,
and here is the surface.
This is that surface.
In the first case, I have no
contribution due to the
conduction current, because
there is no current going
through this, no conduction
current.
In the second case, here, this
term is 0; by the way, this
term has a name.
We call this term the
displacement current; it is a
misnomer, but that's
what it's called.
It has the same dimension
as I thru: Ampere's.
There is no displacement current
going through the
surface, but there is only going
a conduction current
going through that surface.
Whether I'd apply a flat surface
or this back surface,
I should get the same answer.
Well, be my guest. I don't care
which one we do first.
Let's first do the
back surface.
If we do the back surface; then
we get B times 2 pi r--
closed loop integral
along this line--
equals mu 0 times the conduction
current poking
through this surface, which is
Ic, and there is no changing
electric field anywhere going
through this surface, because
remember E will zero here; and
we have assumed that the E
will zero here, outside
the capacitor.
And this is open here.
There is no surface here.
So what do you find?
B equals mu 0 time Ic
divided by 2 pi r.
You find exactly the same
result that you
found for point P1.
So this is r larger than R or
equal to R, and you are in the
plane between the capacitors.
You are at point P2--
exactly the same result, and
that shouldn't surprise you.
Now we're going to use this
surface as our open surface
attached to this wire.
And we better get the same
results, but now the
calculation is a little
bit more complicated.
I have an electric field, and
the electric field is running
from left to right,
and it is growing.
And the reason why it is growing
is that the charge
that piles up here is, of
course, increasing.
If the current were constant,
then it is
increasing linearly in time.
What is that electric field?
Well, that electric field is
sigma, which is the surface
charge density divided by
epsilon 0, and it is
increasing in time, so surely
dE dt is not going to be 0.
In fact, dE dt is going
to be a constant.
Well, how do I calculate, now,
the changing electric flux
through this surface?
I'm going to make a slightly
different drawing.
This is a circle with radius
capital R, so that's the
capacitor plates, and this
is the circle through
which point P2 goes.
And outside the capacitor
plates, E equals 0, and inside
the capacitor plates, if I look
from right to left, I see
a constant but growing E field,
and this, now, is my
flat surface.
And there is no conduction
current going through here.
Now I have to do the closed
loop integral of B.dl --B
times 2 pi r equals
mu 0 epsilon 0,
d/dt integral E.dA--
And this is the surface, and
E and dA are in the same
direction, so I can immediately
drop the dot product.
What is E as a function of t,
between the capacitor plates.
That is sigma, which is changing
with t divided by
epsilon 0, which is the charge
divided by epsilon 0 times the
area between the plates,
which is pi R squared.
Q of t is growing linearly in
time; time t equals 0, it is
Q0 plus the conduction
current times t.
And therefore, dE dt equals dQ
dt divided by epsilon 0 pi r
squared; but dQ dt itself is
the conduction current.
So this is the conduction
current divided by epsilon 0
times pi r squared.
And it is constant here because
I of c, the conduction
current is not changing.
Later today we will see a
problem whereby the conduction
current is changing.
Here it's not; it's constant.
All right, so we are well
on our way, now.
We, now, have to integrate--
we have to calculate
this term.
If we take mu 0 epsilon 0, this
term, now, simply becomes
dE dt times the area, because
the dots disappear-- they are
the same direction--
times pi r squared.
But we know this; we
just calculated it.
And notice, you have downstairs,
here, epsilon zero
pi r squared, and you
have upstairs, here,
epsilon 0 pi r squared.
So what do you get?
This term becomes, simply,
mu 0 times I of c.
And therefore, your magnetic
field, B, at that location, P2
where r is larger than R,
between the capacitor plates
equals mu 0 Ic divided by 2 pi
r, and that is exactly what we
found before, and that should
not come as a surprise.
In other words, the induction
current, I of D is exactly the
same as the conduction
current--
actually the displacement
current.
This is the displacement
current; it is the total
displacement current.
Total, because I have chosen the
displacement current to go
through this entire
of the surface.
If, later, we are going to
calculate the displacement
current through a smaller flat
surface, then it will, of
course, be smaller.
But in this case, the total
displacement current going
through this surface, which
covers the entire surface of
the capacitor plates, that
displacement current is the
same as the conduction
current.
And that, of course, is a
requirement, because if not,
you would never see the same
answer for the magnetic field
at point P2, whether you take
the bag surface or whether you
take the flat surface.
So you had a choice: the bag
surface or the flat surface;
it's clear that the bag surface
goes a little faster.
But in any case, you see
we get the same answer.
So now what we have left: we
have left the magnetic field
between the capacitor plates for
a radius, which is smaller
than the radius of the plates.
So here, we have the plates;
now, we have a
radius little r.
Of course, our closed group
integral is, again, going to
be a concentric circle.
We have a conduction current
going in here, and we have a
conduction going in here, and
we have, here, in between a
growing electric field.
And now, you may think that
you have options about the
choice of the surface that you
attach to this closed loop.
It's true, you have an option.
If you think you're going to be
very clever, you may choose
a surface which runs parallel
here to E, then curves like a
shopping bag and, here, runs
parallel to E. So it's open;
it's an open surface, here.
You can stick your hand in.
And you may say that the
electric flux going through
this portion is 0 because
E is parallel to dA--
excuse me, is perpendicular to
dA, because dA would be in
this direction, E is in this
direction, so the dot product
would disappear.
So you will say, "Aha, all I
deal with is the current
coming out here." But
that's not true.
Because as a current charges up
this plate, there is also
current going up in this
direction, and there is
current going onto the
plate like this.
Therefore, there is current
going down here, and there is
current coming down from
the plate, here.
And that current is penetrating
this surface, and
you would have to take
that into account.
Now if you find an easier way to
calculate that current, be
my guest, and I'm sure you'll
get the right answer.
I prefer not to do
it this way.
Now you may be clever and say,
"Aha, now I'm going to choose
a surface, which is completely
bypassing the plates and which
goes like this." Wonderful.
I have here now, conduction
current penetrating through
the surface, here.
But, what do I have here?
Ah!
Through this part of the
surface, and through this part
of the surface, as long as I'm
inside the capacitor, there is
a changing electric flux, which,
now, I have to take
into account.
So not only is the second term
of Maxwell's equation not
zero, due to this conduction
current--
excuse me, not only is the
first term not 0, but the
second term is not 0 either.
And so I have to calculate both,
and I have to take the
dot product into account
of E dot dA (E.dA).
I have to take, therefore--
to calculate, again, the
displacement current, so why
do it that way.
I would suggest, here, that
we take a flat surface.
If we take a flat surface, we
have nothing to do with the
conduction current; we're
only stuck with the
displacement current.
And I suggest that that's the
way we're going to do it.
So now, I'm going to suggest
that we use this flat surface.
We have to calculate the
displacement current anyhow.
We have already calculated that,
and so that I'm going to
use to calculate the magnetic
field at that point briefly.
So what do I find?
I find B times 2 pi r; this
holds, now, for r or less than
R, inside the capacitor equals
epsilon 0 times mu 0 times dE
dt times pi little r squared.
Why little r squared?
Because the flat surface
here has a surface
area pi little r squared.
This distance here is little
r, which is smaller than
capital R, and so if I apply the
second term of Maxwell's
equations, it is that
area that I have
to take into account.
But we already calculated
dE dt.
We just did that.
That was, if I recall, Ic
divided by epsilon 0 times pi
capital R squared.
So what do I find?
I find epsilon 0 mu 0 Ic,
divided by epsilon 0 pi R
squared, times pi little
r squared, and that is
B times 2 pi r.
This r vanishes; I lose a
pi; I lose an epsilon 0.
And I find that, inside the
capacitor, B equals mu 0 times
the conduction current times
r divided by 2 pi capital R
squared, the surface area of the
plates of the capacitor,
and what you see here--
this by the way only holds when
r is smaller or equal
than R and it is inside
the capacitor.
Notice that it is proportional
to r.
It doesn't fall off as 1
over r, but is linearly
proportional with r.
When you substitute, in here,
r equals R, you better find
exactly the same result that you
would have found for P2.
If you bring P2 just to the
point where little r is
capital R; the two
must be the same.
If you stick in here capital
R, notice that you get B
equals mu 0 times I of c divided
by 2 pi times capital
R, and that is, indeed, exactly
the same that you
would have found if you look
at your solution for P2 and
you substitute r equals R.
The direction of the B fields
in all three cases is
clockwise when you look from
the left and you see the
current going away from
you, and here are
the capacitor plates.
So when you look at the
capacitor, these are the
capacitor plates, and you
are looking away--
the current going away from
you-- this E field is growing;
then you would see
magnetic fields
here circulating around.
It would reach a maximum
at a smaller circle.
This B field is smaller, and
right in the center the B
field equals 0, because
it grows linearly
with a little r.
So I suggest that I make a plot
of B versus r; this is b.
Let's first do that for
r outside the wire.
Let's give the wire an arbitrary
radius of little a;
if you make it 0, then the
magnetic field goes to
infinity; and this
is the radius of
the capacitor plates.
So you will get, here, then,
the magnetic field, which
falls off as 1 over r, and this
whole curve has the shape
mu 0 I conduction divided by 2
pi over r, and it stops here
at the surface.
When you're talking about in
between the capacitor plates,
then you can go to r equals 0.
B equals 0, as r equals 0.
It goes linearly, and then it
falls off in exactly the same
way as it did before, so this
part of the curve, here, is
exactly the same as that
part of the curve.
And right here, if you take
this curve, and you take r
equals capital R, or if you take
this curve, and you take
little r equals capital R, you
will find exactly the same
result as I just showed you.
You find this result with the
capital R downstairs.
Now, we have effectively dealt
with all conceivable problems
that you can encounter with
displacement current.
The only thing we haven't done,
which will not add at
all to the complication, is we
have not had a situation
whereby we charge or discharge
a capacitor
with a changing current.
You will see that it doesn't
make the situation any more
difficult, because you can
calculate at all moments in
time dE dt.
And therefore, you can calculate
the second term of
Maxwell's equations.
Now, the fact that there happens
to be also a second
derivative of E versus t--
namely, if you have a
d2 E dt squared--
will not make the calculations
any more difficult.