Problem 2 is 29-36.
I have a copper wire; I have
a known resistivity.
I have a certain area,
which I know.
I don't know what you want to
call that area, whether you
want to call it pi r squared.
It's an area; and it is 4.0
square millimeters.
Let's give it a radius r 0.
There is a current in the
beginning going through, which
is constant conduction current,
uniformly distributed
over the surface
of 30 amperes.
That's the situation in the
beginning; it's a copper wire.
And the first question you're
being asked: what is the
electric field inside
the wire itself?
Let us take a random section
of length l.
Then the resistance, R, of
length l equals rho times l
divided by the cross-sectional
area, which would then be, if
you accept my r 0, it would
be pi r 0 squared.
What is the voltage, the
potential difference, if I go
from here to here?
That is the integral of E.dl,
so that would be E times l,
because I have chosen a distance
l; E and l are in the
same direction.
E is constant, the dot
disappears, so I get El; but
according to Ohm's Law, it is
also the conduction current
times the resistance over
that distance l.
And so what do I find
when I combine that?
I find that the electric field
inside is the conduction
current times rho divided
by the area, which
is the pi r 0 squared.
And this, of course, is
independent of little l; it
better be independent of little
l, because clearly
Maxwell's equations doesn't
give a damn, so to speak,
about what you choose for l.
It has to be independent of l.
So, here, you see, that if I put
in the numbers-- but don't
take my numbers always too
seriously, because I can
easily make mistakes--
I found, sticking in the
numbers, 0.15 volts per meter.
Now you're being asked,
what is dE/dt.
Well, you will say there is no
dE/dt, because the current is
a constant.
Ah, but they are going to sneak
on you, that now they
are going to increase the
conduction current with a huge
amount: 6,000 amperes
per second.
So what is now dE/dt?
Well, that's the derivative
of this thing.
So that is rho divided by
the area times dIc/dt.
And you know that,
that is 6,000.
If I stick in the numbers--
I may well have made
a mistake--
I find 30 volts per meter per
second will be my answer.
That's right; that's dE/dt.
Now if we were charging, or
if we were discharging a
capacitor, there would also be
a second derivative of dE/dt
--of E versus time, I should
say, second derivative of the
electric flux through
the surface.
That, however, is not
the case now.
You may say, well, that's
strange because
the current is changing.
Well, but you're not charging
up a capacitor; you're not
building up a charge on
a plate, so you're not
increasing the electric field.
At least you are not, you are
increasing the electric
field-- that's what you're
doing-- but you don't have a
second derivative of
the electric field.
So if this were a capacitor,
and you were charging a
capacitor with a changing
conduction current; then as
you will see, you will get
a d2 E dt squared,
but here you won't.
So this one equals constant,
even though you have a
changing conduction current.
Having recognized that, you,
now, are being asked to
calculate the displacement
current.
Well, the displacement current,
again, they don't
specify the surface; it's pretty
sloppy of the authors,
but I would assume that they
mean the total one.
That means the displacement
current going through the
cross-section, the flat surface
of the copper wire.
So it's epsilon 0, it is
dE/dt times that area,
which, pi r 0 squared.
The dot product disappears,
because the area, the dA's and
dE's are in the same
direction.
And so, you will find now--
dE/dt you calculated, 30 volts
per minute per second.
So you find a number; if I
calculate the displacement
current density, then
I even lose my area.
I get epsilon 0 times dE/dt,
and if I did not make a
mistake, which I could easily
have done, I find 2.65 times
10 to the minus 10 amperes
per square meter.
Now look at this number; this is
an extremely small number,
and the reason why this second
term of Maxwell's equations is
often, but not always, is often
very small, is because
of this epsilon 0, right, which
is this 8.8 times 10 to
the minus 12.
But there are cases where
it is not negligible.
You are being, now, asked to
calculate the magnetic field,
B, at a distance r from the
wire, which is 5 centimeters
which is larger than r 0.
It doesn't have to be much
larger, it happens to be
larger than r 0, so it's
outside the surface.
Well, here is that cross-section
of the wire; my
r, which is 5 centimeters.
I choose, obviously, a circle,
a concentric circle, and I
have to attach, now,
an open surface.
Well, there is nothing to be
accomplished by being fancy
with hats and paper, you know,
shopping bag surfaces; I
would, now, simply go
for this surface.
That's all there is to it.
If I go for this surface,
remember that only through
this surface is there a changing
electric flux.
But keep in mind, if you go
through the integral of B.dr,
so you get B times to 2 pi
r, that the first term of
Maxwell's equation, the
conduction current
term, is not 0.
Neither is the displacement
current term.
I put a mu 0 outside, and I will
calculate the situation
when t equals 0, when the
current was 30 amperes.
A little later, of course, the
current is higher, but I will
calculate it at this moment,
so I get a 30, here.
That's a mu 0 times Ic,
a time t equals 0, so
that is t equals 0.
Now I have to add epsilon 0
times dE/dt times the area,
but it's this area, not this
area, because there is no
changing electric flux going
through this area.
So I have, now, times the area
which I will call pi r 0
squared, which was, I believe,
this 4 times 10 to the minus 6
square meters.
Well, earlier we calculated
this, which was ridiculously
small, and when you multiply
these two, you get an absurd
number, which is something like
10 to the, of the order
of 10 to the minus 15; and so
you see that in this case,
even though the current is
changing with an absurd amount
of 6,000 amperes per second,
the magnetic fields at this
location are 5 centimeters, is
exclusively dictated by the
conduction current.
And so to a high degree of
approximation, you still get
that it is Ic divided
by 2 pi r.
And if I calculated that
correctly, I found 1.20 times
10 to the minus 4 Tesla.
That's what I found; and this
is then a t equals 0.