That brings us, then, to
problem number four--
this is a semi-classic, 24-68.
I have an insulating arc, which
is half a circle, and I
put a charge here on the arc
at a uniform density.
I have a total charge of Q on
the arc, and the radius
of the arc is a--
it's only half an arc.
Lambda, if you want to express
it how many coulombs there are
per meter, lambda would be
Q divided by half the
circumference, so
that it's pi a.
Now you're being asked: what is
the potential at that point
P, right at the center
of that arc?
As I said earlier, the potential
is a scalar--
it's not a vector.
The advantage of scalars is that
you don't have to take
into account directions--
they have no direction, so all
you have to do is just add up
the individual potentials from
each one of those little
sections over the arc, and
that's exactly what
I'm going to do.
I'm going to carve out here
a little section, dx.
That little section dx contains
a charge dq, which is
lambda times dx, which is
therefore Q divided
by pi a times dx.
That is the little amount
of charge here.
The potential at the point P as
a result of this charge, if
I assume that infinity
is 0, that potential,
which I will call dVp--
it's only a teeny weeny little
bit due to this section dx.
It therefore equals Q divided
by pi a divided by 4
pi a epsilon 0.
Remember, it's 4 pi
epsilon 0 r--
r is the distance from the
charge to that point P, and
we've seen it in our
previous problems--
so that's why this a is
there times the x.
Now I have to add all these
elements of dx, so
that makes it easy--
I do an integral, and the
integral has to be
done along the arc.
That will give me that V p is
Q divided by pi a divided by
this times the integral
along the arc of dx.
The integral along the arc
of dx itself is pi a, so
I lose the pi a.
I get Q divided by 4 pi
epsilon 0 times a--
that would be the potential
at this point
P due to this half-arc.
Now you are being asked
what is the electric
field at point P?
That's harder, because the
electric field is a vector, so
now if you take this little
element, the positive charge
here would have a small e vector
is this direction.
But if you take the little
element here, that would have
e vector in this direction,
and if you take the small
element here, that would have an
e vector in this direction.
You will have to add up all
these e vectors to get the net
e vector, and I will help you
a little bit: the net e
vector, I claim, must be
in the direction e net.
That goes right through the
center of this arc.
The reason for that is that
it's clear that the y
components--
if I called these the
y components--
will cancel because of the
symmetry of the problem.
What I have here below this
horizontal line is exactly
what I have here, so you don't
even have to worry about the y
components--
all you have to do is
calculate all the x
components, due to all these
little elements.
Then you have to do an integral
over the whole arc,
forgetting the y components,
and out comes the net e
vector, which will
be, I guarantee
you, in this direction.