Problem number four is a very
interesting problem, and I
would say it is very important
problem, too.
I have a very long wire--
we think of it as infinitely
long-- with a charge per unit
length, which I call lambda
3 times 10 to the -
10 coulomb per meter.
Here is this long wire,
and here is x = 0.
I'm asking you a question which
is not asked by your
teachers, but I want to do that
first, and then you'll
see that the rest comes
out very easily.
That question is what is the
electric field at a location d
anywhere away from the wire?
The way we can do that is in two
ways: either we do it in a
nasty way, which is the way
that Chapter 22 is dealing
with it, or we do it in a
beautiful, easy way, which is
Chapter 23, which
is Gauss' Law.
I will do both.
I feel obligated to do the nasty
way, because after all,
the problem has a number 22.
The nasty way: here, I select as
location x a small element
dx, which therefore contains
a charge dq, and is
lambda times dx.
This little charge element,
alone, will produce at this
location an electric field
in this direction
which I will call dE--
it is a vector.
I can decompose that into
this direction--
the y direction--
so this will be dE y, and I can
decompose that into this
direction, which
would be dE x.
We have an angle theta
here, and we have
an angle theta there.
This distance from this
point to this charge--
I will call that little r--
equals the square root of
d squared + x squared.
First, the nasty way: I first
want you to appreciate that
easy calculating dE
is very easy.
The magnitude of dE--
only the magnitude--
equals 3 times 10 to the - 10
times 9 times 10 to the 9
times dx divided by that
distance r squared.
When you put in the numbers,
you'll find 2.7 divided by r
squared times dx.
That's the magnitude.
Now clearly, if you add up all
these elements here, there
cannot be any net vector
in the x direction--
they will all cancel out,
so the only one that
survives is this one.
I don't even bother about
the x direction--
I only calculate dE in
the y direction.
That is this value times the
sine of theta, and I find then
2.7 d divided by r
cubed times dx.
If I now wants to know what the
total value for E y is, I
have to execute the integral
from x all the way for -
infinity through plus infinity
of dx divided by r cubed, and
I will write down for r cubed
d squared plus x squared to
the power of 3/2.
To be frank with you, I'm not
very good at integrals, and I
find this a very
nasty integral.
I looked it up, and
I did even better.
I asked my graduate student
to confirm it.
If you do this integral
correctly, and I'm sure you
are better at it that
I am, then it is 2
divided by d squared.
So the net result is that E y
then becomes 5.4 divided by d,
and if E y has to be 0.5 newtons
per coulomb, that will
be the case if the
distance through
the wire is 2.8 meters.
So far, the nasty solution.
Now, the beautiful solution--
Gauss' Law, which you will
learn in Chapter 23.
Suppose I have here a closed
surface-- it is essential that
it is closed.
There cannot be an opening.
At the surface here, I have
small surface elements, and I
erect small vectors,
all perpendicular
to the local surface.
We have a ds here, and a ds
here, and by convention, they
are always pointing outwards
from inside the surface to
outside the surface.
There could be an electric field
vector here due to the
charge that is inside here,
there could be an electric
field here, and there could
be an electric field here.
What Gauss' Law now tells me
is that the closed surface
integral over this entire
surface of E dot ds--
it is a dot product--
equals the total charge
inside this volume
divided by epsilon 0.
I can only use Gauss' Law in a
meaningful way if I can create
geometry which is easy.
Easy geometries always require
symmetry, and you can only got
symmetry with spheres,
cylinders, and with planes.
We'll do one of each, and this
is going to be the cylinder.
Here is my infinitely long
wire, and I am going to
introduce what I call
a Gaussian surface.
It must be a closed surface,
and think of it as being a
coin, which could have any
width that you want to.
This would be a cross
section of the coin.
The thickness of the coin
is unimportant--
I'll call it l, and this now in
distance d from the wire.
If I try to make it look a
little bit three dimensional,
which is always a little
difficult, then it would look
like this--
so this is the coin.
It's actually a little
cylinder, but
it's completely closed.
I hope you realize that--
it's a closed surface.
The E field right here at the
ends must be pointing outwards
for reasons of symmetry.
There cannot be any components
like this or that-- nature
cannot decide between left and
right, and so the E field here
must also be pointing outwards,
radially outwards.
It's the same here, the same
here, but also on any surface
element here, it must be
pointing radially outwards.
In other words, if I looked at
this surface from this side--
and if this were that surface
which then had a radius d--
then everywhere at the surface,
the E fields must be
pointing radially outwards
for reasons of symmetry.
How about the values of ds?
Well, ds per definition is
pointing outwards, so ds here
is also pointing outwards, and
ds here is pointing outwards.
Everywhere where we have here
these E vectors, the ds and
the E's, are in the
same direction.
The dot product can be ignored,
because the cosine
between the angle between
E and ds is 1.
Let us calculate the electric
flux that goes out from this
curved surface.
That should be very easy: that
is the surface area itself,
which is 2 pi times d.
It has here a thickness l, so
this is now the total volume--
not volume, this is the
total surface area
of this curved surface.
I multiply that by E, according
to Gauss' Law.
I have to add now the flux that
escapes from the sides,
and that then equals 3 times
10 to the - 10--
that is the charge that is
located here at the wire,
which has a length l times
l divided by epsilon 0.
What is the flux that escapes
from the sides?
The flux that escapes from the
sides is 0, because ds is
always perpendicular to the
surface, and is therefore is
in this entire problem
for this side.
For this side of the coin, the
ds dot E is 0, because E and
ds are perpendicular
to each other--
so there is nothing
here, and it is 0.
You'll find immediately what the
E vector is, and you see
that l cancels, because nature
couldn't care less how wide
you take this cylinder.
If you work this out, you will
see that you find exactly the
same result as you had before.
But the beauty--
think of the beauty.
There's no nasty integrals, just
a choice, and that's very
important--
the choice of one nicely
symmetric geometric surface.
It must be symmetric, otherwise
you're nowhere.
You apply Gauss' Law-- you don't
even have to think, but
you have to be careful
that you take the dot
product into account.
It's very often that you can set
it up in such a way that
the dot product is
only non-zero
through certain surface--
in this case, through
the curved one--
and that it is zero through
other surfaces, which in this
case is the flat ones.
Then you execute the recipe, you
don't even think anymore,
and the E field pops out.
Gauss' Law is fantastic--
it cannot always be used
if there's no symmetry.
It's always correct, though,
but you can use it to your
advantage if you choose the
right surfaces and put in the
right symmetry.
The charge distributions also
have to be symmetric--
otherwise, it's pretty
hopeless.