JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been
learning about Stokes'
Theorem, and I have a nice
exercise on Stokes' Theorem
for you here.
So I'm going to let F be
this field that I've
written just above me.
So it's 2xz minus 2y comma 2yz
plus 2x comma x squared plus y
squared plus z squared.
And I've got C.
So C is this
complicated-looking curve here.
So it sort of dips up and
down and back around.
But the thing I'm really going
to tell you about it is it all
lies on this cylinder
of radius b.
So C is this curve in the
cylinder of radius b that
wraps around it once, but
behaves oddly while it's
wrapping around.
So what I'd like you to do is
I'd like you to use Stokes'
Theorem to compute the integral
around this curve of
F dot dr. Now, my hint to you
is that for Stokes' Theorem,
you can use-- just like you have
for Green's Theorem and
for divergence Theorem that
we've talked about before--
you have these extended versions
that let you consider
more than one boundary piece.
So the same thing works
for Stokes' Theorem.
So Stokes' Theorem works
perfectly well when you have a
piece of a surface with more
than one boundary curve,
provided you orient everything
correctly.
So you might think about how you
can use Stokes' Theorem to
replace this complicated curve
with a surface integral and an
easier to understand curve.
And if you can do that, then
computing the other two gives
you the third one.
All right.
So that's my hint to you for
computing this integral.
So why don't you pause the
video, have a go at that, come
back, and we can work
on it together.
Hopefully, you had some luck
working on this problem.
Let's talk about it.
So before I left, I gave you
this hint that maybe the thing
to do here isn't to try and
parametrize this curve
directly and compute the line
integral directly since it's a
complicated-looking curve, and
also since I haven't really
given you enough information
to do that, and instead to
think about applying
Stokes' Theorem.
So to think about applying
Stokes' Theorem, what we'd
like is a nice surface,
and with this curve
as part of its boundary.
Well, what is such a surface?
Well, this curve lies all on
the cylinder of radius b.
So a natural choice for a
surface is to use some piece
of this cylinder.
So maybe we could use the piece
of this cylinder with
this as its upper boundary.
So then what might be a natural
lower boundary to choose?
Well, we just want to choose
something nice and simple.
Right?
So, what's nice and simple?
Well, maybe we can choose this
bottom circle that's in the
plane y equals x.
All right.
So I'm going to call
that circle C1.
So that's the circle of radius
b in the xy plane.
Sorry, not the plane
y equals x.
The xy plane.
The plane z equals 0.
So we've got the top curve
C and we've got this
bottom curve C1.
Now, the way I've oriented them,
I've oriented them both
so that they're going
counterclockwise as you look
down from the z-axis.
So in that case, what does
Stokes' Theorem say?
Well, Stokes' Theorem says that
the integral over the
piece of the surface between
them-- let's call it S of curl
F dot n with respect
to surface area--
is equal to--
OK.
So let's say we can give it the
outward pointing normal.
In which case, C1 will be
positively oriented and C will
be negatively oriented.
So this is equal to the line
integral over C1 of F dot dr
minus the line integral
over C of F dot dr.
And so what's nice about this
formula is that it replaces
computing the integral
that we want.
Instead of computing that, we
can try and compute this other
line integral and this
surface integral.
And if these are easier to
compute, then computing the
two of them gives us what the
value of this is just by
subtracting, or by adding
and subtracting, or
by arithmetic, right?
So if these integrals are easy
to compute, then that makes
this one easy without actually
having to parametrize and
compute it.
So let's take a look at what
these integrals are.
Let's do the surface integral
first since it's on the left.
So in order to compute the
surface integral, we're going
to need to compute the
curl of F. So OK.
So F is this kind of messy
looking thing here.
So for curl of F, what
have we got?
So it's going to be big
thing times i hat.
So it's going to be i hat times
this determinant, right?
So let me write the
determinant.
So on top we've got i hat j hat
k hat, then we have the
partial x partial y partial
z, and then we have the
components.
So these are 2xz minus 2y, and
2yz plus 2x, and x squared
plus y squared plus z squared.
All right.
So that's i hat, j
hat, and k hat.
And then we've got partial over
partial x, partial over
partial y, and partial
over partial z.
So this is what the curl
is, and so now we have
to expand this out.
So for i, it's going to be
partial y of x squared plus y
squared plus z squared.
So that's 2y--
minus partial z of 2yz
plus 2x, so that's--
minus 2y, i hat.
Plus--
for j hat, it's going to
be partial z of 2xz
minus 2y, so that's--
2x--
minus partial x of x squared
plus y squared plus z squared,
so that's-- minus 2x, j hat.
Plus--
for k hat, we want partial x
of 2yz plus 2x, so that's--
2--
minus partial y of 2xz minus 2y,
so that's minus minus 2,
so that's-- plus 2, k hat.
Oh.
All right.
OK.
So the i-component is 0 and
the j-component is 0.
So this is a nice, simple one.
So the curl of here.
The k-component is just 4.
So this is equal to 4k.
OK.
So that's what the
curl of F is.
Now what do we need
to compute?
We need to compute curl of F
dot the normal vector with
respect to surface area.
Now let's look at what
our surface is.
Our surface is right here, and
it's this vertical cylinder.
Well, what is the normal vector
of a vertical cylinder?
Well, it's pointing straight
away from the axis.
Right?
It's perpendicular to the
surface of the cylinder, so
it's parallel to the xy plane.
It rotates as you go around the
cylinder, but it's always
in the xy plane.
So what does that mean?
Well, that means in particular,
it's perpendicular
to things in the z-direction.
Right?
So if we look, we see our curl
here is just straight upward
in the z-direction.
And our normal vector
has no z-component.
It's only in the xy plane.
So this k hat is orthogonal
to n, OK?
So the curl and n
are orthogonal.
So their dot product is 0.
So this surface integral is
a surface integral of 0.
So it just gives you 0.
OK.
So great.
So that's really nice.
That simplifies our
life very much.
Now, our line integral
that we want.
We just have it in terms of this
one other line integral.
Right?
So the surface integral is 0.
And let me see.
Where should I put this?
OK, the curl is 4k, so the
surface integral curl F dot n
ds is also equal to 0.
So having made that
simplification, now we just
need this line integral
over C1.
And that'll give us
what we need.
So let's have a go at that.
So C1 is the circle of radius
b centered at the origin and
the xy plane.
OK.
I'm not going to write
that down.
I'm just going to say it.
The circle of radius
b centered at the
origin and the xy plane.
So OK.
So it's not that hard
to parametrize.
So it's parametrized by x
equals b cosine theta, y
equals b sine theta.
We should check.
We should double-check that
we're doing the right
direction of parametrization.
Let's go have a look.
Let's see.
Yes.
OK.
So we parametrized
this circle going
counterclockwise in the xy plane.
So good.
So this parametrization is going
the right direction.
Otherwise, we'd have to change
the sine theta or something.
So it's x is b cosine theta,
y is b sine theta.
And we're going once around the
circle, so we want 0 less
than or equal to theta less
than or equal to 2 pi.
And so what do we have?
So now we want to compute the
integral over the circle of F
dot dr. So let's see what F
looks like in this situation.
So let's go back
and look at the
expression for F over here.
So in this plane, we have
z is equal to 0.
So F is minus 2y, plus 2x,
x squared plus y squared.
OK?
OK, so let's come back then.
So F is what I just said, so
this is equal to the integral
over C of minus 2y
dx, plus 2x dy--
plus x squared plus y squared
dz, but we're in the plane z
equals 0, so dz is always
0 in that plane--
so we don't have a
third term there.
Great.
So this is our integral, and now
we can substitute from our
parametrization here.
So this is equal to the integral
from 0 to 2 pi.
So minus 2y dx.
So that's minus 2b sine
theta, times--
dx is-- minus b sine theta
d theta, plus--
2x, so that's--
2b cosine theta, times--
dy, which is--
b cosine theta d theta.
Whew.
This is quite a long
expression.
So our line integral around C
of F dot dr is equal to the
integral from 0 to 2 pi of
minus 2b sine theta times
minus b sine theta d theta.
So this is 2b squared sine
squared theta d theta.
And this is 2b cosine squared
theta d theta.
So OK.
So that 2b squared
is a constant.
We can just factor it out.
And we're left with sine squared
theta plus cosine
squared theta d theta.
All right.
OK.
That's great.
I'm happy to have that.
Right?
Sine squared theta plus
cosine squared theta
is going to be 1.
OK.
So we can rewrite this.
I'm going to bring
it back up here.
So that's equal to the integral
from 0 to 2 pi, of 2b
squared d theta, which
is 4 pi b squared.
Great.
OK, so that's our line integral
around this bottom
curve
C. Oh, dear.
I've been writing C, but this
is not our original curve C,
this is our new curve C1,
like I wrote there.
Sorry.
So everywhere I wrote the line
integral over C-- both of
these places-- it was supposed
to be a line integral over C1.
Sorry about that.
So we've got this line integral
over C1, and it
worked out to 4 pi b squared,
just using our usual
parametrize-and-compute
technique for
computing line integrals.
So OK.
So now, let's see
where we're at.
Let's go back over here to when
we wrote down what the
extended Stokes' Theorem
says in our case.
So Stokes' Theorem told us
that the thing we were
interested in-- this
is the thing we're
trying to compute, right?
The problem asked us to compute
the line integral over
C of F dot dr. Well, extended
Stokes' Theorem said in order
to compute this line integral,
what you can do is you can
compute this surface integral
over S, and you can compute
this line integral over this
other curve C1, and then these
three things have to satisfy
this relationship.
That's what's Stokes'
Theorem says.
And now we've computed.
We've computed the surface
integral, and we found it was
equal to 0 by a simple geometric
argument that didn't
require us to actually compute
a surface integral.
And we computed this line
integral just now by
parametrizing and computing it.
So OK.
So this was 0 and this
was 4 pi b squared.
So if we just add our integral
in question to the other side,
what we find--
I'm going to go find
some empty board
space to write it down--
so our integral over C of F dot
dr is equal to this other
line integral minus the
surface integral.
So it's equal to 4 pi
b squared minus 0.
Just rearranging that equation
we were looking at a second
ago from Stokes' Theorem.
So it's just 4 pi b squared.
So that's the answer,
and I'll end there.