JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
We've been talking about Taylor
series and different
sorts of manipulations you can
do with them, and different
examples of Taylor series.
So I have an example here
that I don't think
you've seen in lecture.
So this is the Taylor series 1
plus 2x plus 3x squared plus
4x cubed plus 5x to the fourth,
and, and so on.
I'm going to tell you that this
is a Taylor series for a
fairly nice function.
And what I'd like you to do,
is try and figure out what
that function is.
Now, I'm kind of sending you
off onto this task without
giving you much guidance, so let
me give you a little bit
of a hint, which is that the
thing to do here, is you have
a bunch of different tools
that you know how to
manipulate Taylor series by.
So you know how to, you know, do
calculus on Taylor series,
you can take derivatives and
integrals, you know how to add
and multiply and perform these
sorts of manipulations.
So you might think of a
manipulation you could perform
on this Taylor series that'll
make it a simpler expression,
or something you're already
familiar with, or so on.
So let me give you some
time to work on that.
Think about it for a while.
Try and come up with
the expression
for this Taylor series.
And come back, and we can
work on it together.
So hopefully you had some luck
working on this problem, and
figured out what the right
manipulation to use is.
I didn't, I kind of tossed it at
you without a whole lot of
guidance, and I don't think
you've done a lot of examples
like this before.
So it's a little tricky.
So what I suggested was that
you think about things that
you, you know how to
do that could be
used to simplify this.
So looking at it, it's just
one Taylor series.
So it's not clear that sort of
Taylor series arithmetic is
going to help you very much.
It's not obviously a
substitution of some value
into some other Taylor series
that you're familiar with.
It's not obviously, say, a sum
of two Taylor series that you
already know very well.
So those things don't, aren't
immediately, it's not clear
where to go with them.
One thing that does pop
out-- well, OK.
So let's talk about
some of the other
tools that I mentioned.
We have calculus on
Taylor series.
So we have differentiation.
And if you take-- so we see here
that the coefficients are
sort of a linear polynomial.
If you take a derivative, what
happens is, well, this becomes
2 plus 6x plus 12x squared
plus 20x cubed.
And those coefficients, 2, 6,
12, 20, those are given by a
quadratic polynomial.
So that makes our life kind of
more complicated, somehow.
But if we look at this, we see
that integrating this power
series is really easy to do.
This power series has a really
nice antiderivative.
So what I'm going to do, is I'm
going to call this power
series by the name f of x.
And then what I'd like you
to notice, is that the
antiderivative of f of x dx--
well, we can integrate power
series termwise.
And so what we get is--
well, so all right.
So I'm going to do, I'm going
to put the constant of
integration first. So
the antiderivative
of this is c plus--
well, 1, you take its integral
and you get x.
And 2x, you take its
integral, and you
just get plus x squared.
And 3x squared, you take its
integral and you get plus x
cubed, and plus x to the fourth
from the next one, and
plus x to the fifth,
and so on.
So, OK.
So I put the c here, right?
So any power series of this form
is an antiderivative of
the power series that
we started with.
Any power series of this form
has a, has the derivative
equal to thing that we're
interested in.
And since we really care about
what f is, and not what its
antiderivative is, we
can choose c to be
any convenient value.
So I'm gonna, in particular,
look at the power series where
c is equal to 1.
And why am I going to
make that choice?
Well, because we've seen a power
series that looks very
much like this before,
with the 1 there.
So we know 1 plus x plus x
squared plus x cubed plus x to
the fourth and so on.
We know that this is equal
to 1 over 1 minus x.
OK?
So since we know that this is
the case, that means that our
power series, f of x, is just
the derivative of this.
That's what we just
showed here.
So, f of x is equal to d over
dx of 1 over-- whoops, that
should be--
over 1 minus x.
OK?
And notice that, you know if I'd
chosen a different choice
of constant here, it would
be killed off by this
differentiation.
So it really was irrelevant.
So d over dx of 1
over 1 minus x.
Yes, of d over dx of 1 minus x.
And, OK.
Well, this is an easy derivative
to compute.
This is 1 minus x to the minus
1, so you do a little chain
rule thing, and I think what you
get out is that this is 1
over 1 minus x squared.
So this gives me a nice
formula for this
function f of x.
If you wanted to check, one
thing you could do, is you
could set about computing a few
terms, the power series
for this function, for 1 over
1 minus x squared, 1 over 1
minus x quantity squared
I should say.
So you could do that either by
using your derivative formula,
which is easy enough to do.
Another thing you could do, is
you could realize that this is
1 over 1 minus x times 1 over
1 minus x, so you could try
multiplying that polynomial by
itself and that power series
by itself, and see if it's easy
to get back this formula
that we had.
But any of those ways is a good
way to double check that
this is really true, that this
function, that this power
series here, f of x, has
this functional form.
Now of course, I haven't said
anything about the radius of
convergence, but the thing to
remember when you're doing
calculus on power series,
is that when you take a
derivative or an antiderivative
of a power
series, you don't change the
radius of convergence.
Sometimes you can fiddle with
what happens at the endpoints,
but the radius of convergence
stays the same.
So this is going to be true
whenever x is between
negative 1 and 1.
And in fact, this series
diverges at this endpoint.
That's pretty easy to check.
So there we go.
So this is the functional form
for this power series.
It's valid whenever x is between
negative 1 and 1.
That's its range
of convergence.
And so here we have a cute
little trick for figuring out
some forms of power series.
And of course if you were
interested, so like I said,
now you had a, ypu could look
at the derivative of this,
which I mentioned had some
coefficients that were given
by some quadratic polynomial.
Now that you have a functional
form, you could figure out,
you know, "Oh what, you know,
what is the function whose
power series has that quadratic
polynomial as
coefficients?" And you can do
a whole bunch of other stuff
by similarly taking derivatives
of other power
series that you're familiar
with, or integrals.
So I'll stop there.