Welcome back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
do the following problem.
I want us to show that the
function, if I integrate x to
the n, e to the minus x from
1 to infinity, that that
actually converges for any value
of n, and I want us to
show this without using
integration by parts n times.
So I'd like you to figure out
a way to show that this
integral converges.
And again, what we mean by
converges, is for a fixed
value here, say, some b, if I
let, as the limit is b goes to
infinity, that that sequence
of values converges to a
finite number.
That's what we mean,
again, when we
say an integral converges.
Ultimately, we want to
show this is finite.
So show this is finite, without
using integration by
parts n times.
So I'll give you a little while
to work on it, and then
I'll be back, and I will
show you how I did it.
OK.
Welcome back.
Well, I want to show you how we
can show that this integral
actually convergences
for any n.
And I don't want to have to use
integration by parts and
kill off powers of x in
order to do that.
So again, the integral is from 1
to infinity of x to the n, e
to the minus x dx.
And if you recall, Professor
Jerison was showing, in the
lecture video, that if you can
show even from, not 1 to
infinity, but from very far
out to infinity, that that
integral converges, from 1 to
whatever the far out value is,
this integral is finite.
OK?
Doesn't blow up.
It's going to be potentially a
very big number, but it is
going to be a finite number.
There are no places
where we run into
trouble with this function.
It's a continuous function
from 1 to infinity.
So we can go very far out and
say, OK, from very far out to
infinity, the integral
converges.
And then that's going
to be enough.
So we did see that kind
of technique earlier.
But I just want to remind you,
that's what we're going to do.
Now, you might have thought
about this problem and said,
well, I know that x to the n is
much smaller than e to the
x for values of x very large.
So you might have said--
I think you used this notation
also in the lecture. x to the
n is much smaller than e
to the x for large x.
So what if we tried
to do a comparison
with those two functions?
We're going to see, that's
not quite enough.
But let's say x is very large,
and let's look at a
comparison.
If I say, the integral from,
say, some very large r to
infinity of x to the n, e to the
minus x dx, it's certainly
going to be much smaller than
the integral from big r to
infinity of e to the x times
e to the minus x dx.
And you think, well,
you know, that's a
pretty good first step.
I'm doing all right.
But what happens here?
What's e to the x times
e to the minus x?
It's e to the x plus negative
x, so it's e to
the 0, so it's 1.
So this is integrating
the constant 1.
Well, the constant 1 from r to
infinity, think of that.
It's the line y equals
1 from r to infinity.
It's an arbitrarily
long rectangle.
That's got a lot of area.
It's got infinite area.
So this integral diverges.
That doesn't mean this
one diverges, right?
Because this one is smaller
than that one.
So this one here could still
converge, even though this
integral diverged.
Again, let me remind you.
Why does this integral
diverge?
Because this is actually
equal to 1.
If I integrate 1 from
r to infinity, I
get something infinite.
So you might have started with
that, but that's not quite
good enough.
Right?
What is going to be good enough,
is if I pick any
constant in front of this n--
I can put any constant
in front of this n I
want, bigger than 1.
And that's going
to help us out.
So I'm going to pick the
constant 2, because it's going
to be easy, and it's a
nice fixed number.
If I--
so this is how you do it
correctly, or one strategy to
do it correctly.
If I take x to the 2n, instead
of just x to the n, for any n,
there's some r big enough so
that x to the 2n is much less
than e to the x for all x bigger
than sum, bigger than
or equal to sum r.
So if I go far enough out in
x-values, x to the 2n is much
smaller than e to the x.
So let's say that value
is capital R, and
then we're much smaller.
This is not very formal, but
it's getting closer to a
formal kind of thing.
Then that means x to the n
is much smaller than e
to the x over 2.
Right?
And that's going
to be the key.
Let's anticipate why that is.
The problem with the
substitution of e to the x was
that e to the x times e to
the minus x gave you 1.
But if I use e to the x over
2, I'm going to end up with
some function, e to the minus
something, and that's going to
be good, because that's
going to converge.
So if you tried e to the x
first, and you saw you didn't
get a good function, you didn't
have to stop there.
You could say, well,
I was close.
The problem is, I cancelled
off all the e to the minus
power, which is what I
want to keep around.
If I want to keep some of that
around, then I have to have a
little less power of
e to the x there.
I have to have, I can't
just have e to the x.
I should have something like
square root of e to the x.
So e to the x over 2.
That's going to help us out.
So this is, this is kind of, as
you're working on this type
of problem, this is some of the
thought process you want
to go through.
So what do we see here?
We have x to the n is much less
than e to the x over 2
for x bigger than
or equal to r.
So now let's do a comparison
with our
new comparative function.
So I'm going to come over, and
this will be our last line to
finish this off.
So now we're integrating from r
to infinity x to the n, e to
the minus x dx.
And we know that's going to be
much less than integral from r
to infinity, e to the x over
2, e to the minus x dx.
And now let's figure
out what this is.
e to the minus x plus x over 2
is e to the minus x over 2.
And the good news is, this is,
we know this converges.
I'll check, and I'll show you,
remind you that it converges.
But we know this converges.
And the reason is, because e to
the minus x is a function
that decays so fast
as it goes to 0.
That's really why you
get the convergence.
Actually, you could even compare
this to x to the minus
2 right away.
And you could get something
like, you know this decays
faster than x to the minus
2, and we know x
to the minus 2 converges.
So you could even compare
it to that.
You could do a second
comparison in here.
But I'll actually calculate
this, just to remind
us how we do this.
So e to the minus x over 2.
If I want to find an
antiderivative, I'm going to
guess and check.
I know I'm going to have an e
to the minus x over 2 again,
and then I need to be able to
kill off a negative 1/2.
So I should put a negative
2 in front.
Let's double check.
This is basically a substitution
problem.
An easy substitution.
So e to the minus x over 2.
Its derivative is negative 1/2
x, and then itself again.
The negative 1/2 times negative
2 gives me a 1.
So again, I'm just, it's an easy
substitution problem, but
I always want to check.
So I evaluate that from
r to infinity.
Well, the point is, e to
the minus infinity--
this is 0.
As x goes to infinity, this
quantity goes to 0.
So I get 0 minus a negative
2, so plus 2, e to the
minus r over 2.
For some fixed, big r.
Well, that's finite.
That's a finite number.
So we come back here.
This integral converges.
That integral was
this integral.
And this integral, then, is
bigger than this one.
So this one converges.
Now, this had a lot of pieces to
it, so I'm going to remind
us sort of what was happening.
So let's go back to the original
function, and I'll
just take us back through
one more time.
OK.
So the original problem was,
show that this integral from 1
to infinity of x to the n e to
the minus x dx converges.
And I reminded you that you knew
from lecture that if I
could show that it converged
for some very large number
down here to infinity, that was
sufficient, because this
function is continuous
from 1 to infinity.
I don't have to worry about
places where I might get
infinite area in a
finite interval.
I'm always going to
have finite area
and a finite interval.
So if I start at some big R to
infinity and that converges,
then I'm good.
Because from 1 to r,
that'll be finite.
So then the point is,
you want to compare.
And I mentioned, a comparison
that doesn't quite work, but
is a good first test. Because
you know x to the n is much
less than e to the x for
a sufficiently large x.
You might think to compare it to
that, but the problem again
was when we do that
substitution, we actually get
an integral that diverges.
But a divergent integral bigger
than something doesn't
mean this one diverges.
If the divergence was on, the
inequality was the other way,
then you could show
this one diverged.
But we actually show convergence
this way.
Or we're trying to show
convergence in this direction,
so we need to say, if
this one converges,
then that one converges.
This diverging doesn't tell
us anything about this.
So then we say, OK.
This one didn't work, but
it almost worked.
So what if I figure out a way
to compare x to the n to a
slightly smaller thing
than e to the x?
And that slightly smaller thing
is e to the x over 2.
It's not really slightly
smaller.
But the smaller function
is e to the x over 2.
OK?
And this is a way to think
about how that works.
Is that for any power of x to
the 2n, I can still get it
smaller than e to
the x for some
sufficiently large number.
OK?
And you don't even have to
think about these R's
as being the same.
I can change them, I can
make this bigger.
This doesn't compare to
this problem, also.
So don't be confused
by those two R's.
OK.
So then we found something
we wanted to
compare x to the n with.
Then we come back over here,
and we actually see that we
get a good comparison, because
we're able to see that the
integral on the right
hand side converges.
This integral is bigger
than this integral.
So this integral converges,
so we know
this integral converges.
And then, the integral from 1 to
r of this is finite, so the
integral from 1 to infinity
of this converges.
And that's sort of the strategy
for doing these types
of
problems. OK.
That's where I'll stop.