DAVID SHIROKOFF: Hi everyone.
I'm Dave.
Now today, I'd like to
tackle a problem
in orthogonal subspaces.
So the problem we'd like to
tackle, given a subspace S,
and suppose S is spanned by two
vectors, 1, 2, 2, 3, and
1, 3, 3, 2.
We have a question here
which is to find
a basis for S perp--
S perp is another subspace which
is orthogonal to S. And
then secondly, can every vector
in R4 be uniquely
written in terms of
S and S perp.
So I'll let you think about this
for now, and I'll come
back in a minute.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
OK, so why don't we tackle
this problem?
OK, so first off, what
does it mean for a
vector to be an S perp?
Well if I have a vector x, and
S perp, and x is in S perp,
what this means is x is going
to be orthogonal to every
vector in S. Now specifically,
S is spanned
by these two vectors.
So it's sufficient that x be
perpendicular to the two bases
vectors in S.
So specifically, I can take 1,
2, 2, 3, and dot it with x,
and it's going to be 0.
So I'm treating x as a
column vector here.
In addition, x must also be
orthogonal to 1, 3, 2, 2.
So any vector x that's an S
perp must be orthogonal to
both of these vectors.
So what we can do
is we can write
this as a matrix equation.
And we do this by combining
these two vectors as rows of
the matrix.
So if we step back and take a
look at this equation, we see
that what we're really asking
is to find all x that are in
the null space of this matrix.
So how do we find x in the
null space of a matrix?
Well what we can do is we can
row reduce this matrix and try
and find a basis for
the null space.
So I'm going to just row reduce
this matrix, and notice
that by row reduction, we don't
actually change the null
space of a matrix.
So if I'm only interested in the
null space, this system is
going to be equivalent to, I can
keep the top row the same.
And then just to simplify our
lives, we can take the second
row and subtract one copy
of the first row.
Now, if I do that, I
obtain 0, 1, 1, -1.
Now, to parameterize the null
space, what I'm going to do is
I'm going to write x
out as components.
So if I write x with components
x1, x2, x3 and x4,
we see here that this matrix
has a rank of 2.
Now, we're looking at vectors
which live in R4, so we know
that the null space is going
to have a dimension
which is 4 minus 2.
So that means there should be
two vectors in the null space
of this matrix.
To parameterize these two
dimensional vectors, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to let
x4 equals some constant,
and x3 equal another constant.
So specifically, I'm going
to let x4 equal b,
and x3 equal a.
Now what we do is we take a look
at these two equations,
and this bottom equation will
say that x2 is equal to
negative x3 plus x4, which is
going to equal -a, x4 plus b.
And then the top equation says
that x1 is equal to -2, x2
minus 2x3 minus 3x4, And
if I substitute in,
x2 is -a plus b.
x3 is a.
And x4 is b.
So when the dust settles,
the a's cancel and
I'm left with -5b.
So we can combine everything
together and we end up
obtaining x1, x2, x3,
x4 equals -5b.
x2 is -a plus b.
x3 is a, and x4 is b.
And now what we can do is we
can take this vector and we
can decompose it into pieces
which are a multiplied by a
vector, and b multiplied
by a vector.
So you'll note that this is
actually a times 0, -1, 1, 0
plus b times -5, 1, 0, 1.
OK?
So we have successfully achieved
a parameterization of
the null space of this matrix
as some constant a times a
vector 0, -1, 1, 0 plus b times
a vector -5, 1, 0, 1.
And now we claim that this is
the entire space, S perp.
So S perp is going to be spanned
by this vector and
this vector.
Now notice how if I were to
take either of these two
vectors in S and dot it with any
vector in the null space,
by construction it automatically
vanishes.
So this concludes part one.
Now for part two.
Can every vector v in R4 be
written uniquely in terms of S
and S perp?
The answer is yes.
So how do we see this?
Well if I have a vector v, what
I can do is I can try and
write it as some constant c1
times the vector 1, 2, 2, 3
plus c2 times the vector 1, 3,
3, 2 plus the vector c3, 0,
-1, 1, 0 plus c4, -5, 1, 0, 1.
OK?
So c1 and c2 are multiplying the
vectors in S, and c3 and
c4 are multiplying the
vectors in S perp.
So the question is, given any
v, can I find constants c1,
c2, c3, c4, such that
this equation holds?
And the answer is yes.
Just to see why it's yes, what
we can do is we can rewrite
this in matrix notation, and
there's kind of a handy trick.
What I can do is I can take
these columns and write them
as columns of the matrix.
And this whole expression is
actually equivalent to this
matrix multiplied by the
constant, c1, c2, c3, c4.
And on the right-hand side,
we have the vector v.
Now, by construction, these
vectors are linearly
independent.
And we know from linear algebra
that if we have a
matrix with linearly independent
columns, the
matrix is invertible.
What this means is for any v on
the right-hand side, we can
invert this matrix
and obtain unique
coefficients, c1, c2, c3, c4.
This then gives us a unique
decomposition for v in terms
of a piece which is in S, and
the piece which is in S perp.
And in general this can be done
for any vector space.
Well I'd like to conclude this
problem now and I hope you had
a good time.