We're going to talk about again
some new concepts.
And that's the concept of
electrostatic potential
electrostatic potential energy.
For which we will use the
symbol U and independently
electric potential.
Which is very different,
for which we will use the
symbol V.
Imagine that I have a charge Q
one here and that's plus,
plus charge,
and here I have a charge plus Q
two and they have a distant,
they're a distance R apart.
And that is point P.
It's very clear that in order
to bring these charges at this
distance from each other I had
to do work to
bring them there because they
repel each other.
It's like pushing in a spring.
If you release the spring you
get the energy back.
If they were -- they were
connected with a little string,
the string would be stretched,
take scissors,
cut the string fweet they fly
apart again.
So I have put work in there and
that's what we call the
electrostatic potential energy.
So let's work this out in some
detail how much work I have to
do.
Well,
we first put Q one here,
if space is empty,
this doesn't take any work to
place Q one here.
But now I come from very far
away, we always think of it as
infinitely far away,
of course that's a little bit
of exaggeration,
and we bring this charge Q two
from infinity to that point P.
And I, Walter Lewin,
have to do work,
I have to push and push and
push and the closer I get the
harder I have to push and
finally I reach that
point P.
Suppose I am here and this
separation is little R.
I've reached that point.
Then the force on me,
the electric force,
is outwards.
And so I have to overcome that
force and so my force F Walter
Lewin is in this direction.
And so you can see I do
positive work,
the force and the direction in
which I'm moving are in the same
direction, I do positive work.
Now, the work that I do could
be calculated.
The work that Walter Lewin is
doing in going all the way from
infinity to that location P is
the integral going from in-
infinity to radius R of the
force of Walter Lewin dot DR.
But of course that work is
exactly the same,
either one is fine,
to take the electric force in
going
from R to infinity.
Dot DR.
Because the force,
the electric force,
and Walter Lewin's force are
the same in magnitude but
opposite direction,
and so by flipping over,
going from infinity to R,
to R to infinity,
this is the same.
This is one and the same thing.
Let's calculate this integral
because that's a little easy.
We know what the electric force
is, Coulomb's law,
it's repelling,
so the force and DR are now in
the same direction,
so the angle theta between them
is zero, so the cosine of theta
is one, so we can forget about
all the vectors,
and so we would get then that
this equals Q one,
Q two, divided by four pi
epsilon zero.
And now I have downstairs here
an R squared.
And so I have the integral now
DR divided by R squared.
From capital R to infinity.
And this integral is minus one
over
R.
Which I have to evaluate
between R and infinity.
And when I do that that becomes
plus one over capital R.
Right, the integral of DR over
R squared I'm sure you can all
do that is minus one over R.
I evaluate it between R and
infinity and so you get plus one
over R.
And so U, which is the energy
that -- the work that I have to
do to bring this charge at that
position,
that U is now Q one.
Times Q two divided by four pi
epsilon zero.
Divided by that capital R.
And this of course this is
scalar, that is work,
it's a number of joules.
If Q one and Q two are both
positive or both ne- negative,
I do positive work,
you can see that,
minus times minus is plus.
Because then they repel each
other.
If one is positive and the
other is
negative, then I do negative
work, and you see that that
comes out as a sign sensitive,
minus times plus is minus,
so I can do negative work.
If the two don't have the same
polarity.
I want you to convince yourself
that if I didn't come along a
straight line from all the way
from infinity,
but I came in a very crooked
way, finally ended up at point
P, at that point,
that the amount of work that I
had to do is exactly the same.
You see the parallel with eight
oh one where we dealt with
gravity.
Gravity is a conservative force
and when you deal with
conservative forces,
the work that has to be done in
going from one point to the
other is independent of the
path.
That is the definition of
conservative force.
Electric forces are also
conservative.
And so it doesn't make any
difference whether I come along
a straight line to this point or
whether I do that in an
extremely crooked way and
finally end up here.
That's the same amount of work.
Now if we do have a collection
of charges, so we have pluses
and minus charges,
some pluses,
some minus, some pluses,
minus, pluses,
pluses, then you now can
calculate the amount of work
that I, Walter Lewin,
have to do in assembling that.
You bring one from infinity to
here, another one,
another one,
and you add up all that work,
some work may be positive,
some work may be negative.
Finally you h- arrive at the
total
amount of work that you have to
do to assemble these charges.
And that is the meaning of
capital U.
Now I turn to electric
potential.
And for that I start off here
with a charge which I now call
plus capital Q.
It's located here.
And at a position P at a
distance R away
I place a test charge plus Q.
Make it positive for now,
you can change it later to
become a negative.
And so the electrostatic
potential energy we -- we know
already, we just calculated it,
that would be Q times Q divided
by four pi epsilon zero R.
That's exactly the same that we
have.
So the electric potential,
electrostatic potential energy,
is the work that I have to do
to bring this charge here.
Now I'm going to introduce
electric potential.
Electric potential.
And that is the work per unit
charge that I have to do
to go from infinity to that
position.
So Q doesn't enter into it
anymore.
It is the work per unit charge
to go from infinity to that
location P.
And so if it is the work per
unit charge, that means little Q
fweet disappears.
And so now we write down that V
at that location P,
the potential,
electric potential at
that location P,
is now only Q divided four pi
epsilon zero R.
Little Q has disappeared.
It is also a scalar.
This has unit joules.
The units here is joules per
coulombs.
I have divided out one charge.
It's work per unit charge.
No one would ever call this
joules per coulombs,
we call this volts,
called after the great Volta,
who did a lot of research on
this.
So we call this volts.
But it's the same as joules per
coulombs.
If we have a very simple
situation like we have here,
that we only have one charge,
then this is the potential
anywhere, at any distance you
want, from this charge.
If R goes up,
if you're further away,
the potential will become
lower.
If this Q is positive,
the potential is everywhere in
space
positive for a single charge.
If this Q is negative,
everywhere in space the
potential is negative.
Electro- electric static
potential can be negative.
The work that I do per unit
charge coming from infinity
would be negative,
if that's a negative charge.
And the potential when I'm
infinitely far away,
when this R becomes infinitely
large, is zero.
So that's the way we
define our zero.
So you can have positive
potentials, near positive
charge, negative potentials,
near negative charge,
and if you're very very far
away, then potential is zero.
Let's now turn to our
Vandegraaff.
It's a hollow sphere,
has a radius R.
About thirty centimeters.
And I'm going to put on here
plus ten microcoulombs.
It will distribute itself
uniformly.
We will discuss that next time
in detail.
Because it's a conductor.
We already discussed last
lecture that the electric field
inside the sphere is zero.
And that the electric field
outside is not zero but that we
can think of all the charge
being at this point here,
the plus ten microcoulombs is
all here, as long as we want to
know what the electric field
outside is.
So you can forget the fact that
it is a -- a sphere.
And so now I want to know what
the electric potential is at any
point in space.
I want to know what it is here
and I want to know what it is
here at point P which is now a
distance R from the center.
And I want to know what it is
here.
At a distance little R from the
center.
So let's first do the potential
here.
The potential at point P is
an integral going from R to
infinity if I take the electric
force divided by my test charge
Q dot DR, but this is the
electric field,
see, this force times distance
is work, but it is work per unit
charge, so I take my test charge
out.
And so this is the integral in
R to infinity of E dot DL -- DR,
sorry.
And that's a very easy
integral.
Because we know what E is.
The electric field we have done
several times.
Follows immediately from
Coulomb's law and so when you
calculate this integral you get
Q divided by four pi epsilon
zero R which is no surprise
because we already had that for
a point
charge.
So this is the situation if R,
little R, is larger than
capital R.
Precisely what we had before.
We can put in some numbers.
If you put in R equals R,
which is uh oh point three
meters, and you put in here the
ten microcoulombs,
and here the -- the thirty
centimeters, then you'll find
three hundred
thousand volts.
So you get three times ten to
the fifth volts.
If you um take R equals sixty
centimeters, you double it,
if you double the distance,
the potential goes down by a
factor of two,
it's one over R,
so it would be a hundred and
fifty kilovolts.
And if you go to three meters,
then it is ten times smaller,
then it is thirty kilovolts.
And if you go to infinity which
for all practical purposes would
be
Lobby seven,
if you go to Lobby seven,
then the potential for all
practical purposes is about
zero.
Because R is so large that
there is no potential left.
So if I, if I,
Walter Lewin,
march from infinity to this
surface of the Vandegraaff,
and I put a charge Q in my
pocket,
and I march to the Vandegraaff,
by the time I reach that point,
I have done work,
I multiply the charge now back
to the potential,
that gives you the work again,
because potential was work per
unit charge, and so the work
that I have done then is the
charge that I have in my pocket
times the potential,
in this case the potential of
the Vandegraaff.
If I go all the way to this
surface,
which is three hundred thousand
volts.
If I were a strong man then I
would put one coulomb in my
pocket.
That's a lot of charge.
Then I would have done three
hundred thousand joules of work.
By just carrying the one
coulomb from Lobby seven to the
Vandegraaff.
That's about the same work I
have to do to climb up the
Empire State Building.
The famous MGH,
my mass times G times the
height that I have to climb.
So I know how the
electric potential goes with
distance.
It's a one over R relationship.
Now I have arrived at the
Vandegraaff, I am at the
surface, with my test charge,
and now I go inside.
And I slosh around inside,
I feel no force anymore.
There is no electric field
inside.
So as I move around inside,
I experience no force.
That means I do no work.
So that means that the
potential
must remain constant.
So the absence of an electric
field here implies that the
electric potential everywhere is
exactly the same inside is the
same as on the sphere.
Because no further work is
needed in marching around with a
test charge.
And so for this special case I
could make a graph of the
electric potential versus R and
this is then the radius of the
Vandegraaff and
that would be a constant all
the way up to this point and
then it would fall off as one
over R here.
And in for the numbers that we
have chosen, the potential at
the maximum here would be three
hundred thousand volts.
Just as when you look at maps
where you see contours of equal
height of
mountains, which we call equal
altitudes, here we have surfaces
of equipotential.
And if you had a point charge
or if you had the Vandegraaff,
these surfaces would be
concentric spheres.
The further out you go,
if the charge is positive,
the lower the potential would
be.
They would be nicely spherical
surfaces.
Suppose now we had more
than one charge,
we had a plus Q one charge,
and we had a minus Q two
charge, for instance.
And you're being asked now what
is the potential at point P.
Well, now the electric
potential at point P,
VP, is the potential that you
would have measured if Q one had
been there alone.
And you have to add the
potential that you would have
seen if Q two
had been there alone.
Just adding work per unit
charge for one with work per
unit charge of the other.
And if this is negative,
then this quantity is negative,
and this is positive.
So when you have configurations
of positive and negative charges
then of course depending upon
where you are in space,
if you're close to the plus
charge, the potential is almost
certainly positive,
because the one over R is huge.
If you're very close to the
negative charge again the one
over R of this little charge
will dominate and so you get a
negative potential.
And so you have surfaces of
positive potential and you have
equipotential surfaces of
negative potentials and so there
are surfaces which have zero
potential.
And they're not always very
easy to envision.
But what I want to show you is
some work that Maxwell himself
did in
figuring out these
equipotentials.
And so I have here a
transparency of publication by
Maxwell.
You see a charge,
let's assume it is plus four
and plus one,
it could be minus four and
minus one, but let's assume
they're plus.
And you see the green lines,
which we have seen before,
which are the field lines.
Don't pay any attention to the
green field lines now.
The red lines are
equipotentials.
And you have to rotate them
about
the vertical,
because they're of course
surfaces, this is
three-dimensional.
I have not drawn all the
equipotential surfaces in red
because they become too
cluttered here.
But I've tried to put most of
them in red.
Since this charge is positive
and that charge is positive,
everywhere in space,
no matter where you are,
the potential has to be
positive.
There is not a single point
where it could be negative.
If you are very far away from
the plus four and the plus one,
then you expect that the
equipotential surfaces are
spheres, because it's almost as
if you were looking at a plus
five charge.
So it doesn't surprise you that
when you go far out that you
ultimately get spherical shapes.
When you're very close to the
plus four they are perfect
spheres, when you're very close
to the plus one,
they are perfect spheres.
But then when you're sort of in
between, neither close to the
plus four nor to the plus one,
they have this very funny
shape.
It reminds me the shape of this
balloon a little bit.
Sort of like this.
You see.
And there is one surface which
is most unusual equipotential
surface which here has a point
where the electric field is
zero.
It's sort of like twisting the
neck of a goose,
you get something like this,
and so you have here a surface
which has a point here and it is
exactly at that point
where the electric field is
zero, that does not mean that
the potential is zero,
of course not,
the potential is positive here.
If you come with a positive
charge from the Lobby seven and
you have to march up to that
point, you have to do positive
work.
You have to overcome both the
repelling force from the plus
four and the repelling force
from the plus one.
But finally when you reach that
point you can rest because there
is no force on you at that
point.
That's what it means that the
electric field is zero.
It does not mean that you
haven't done any work.
So never confuse electric
fields with potentials.
I want to draw your attention
to the fact that the green
lines, the field lines,
are everywhere perpendicular to
the equipotentials.
I will get back to that during
my next lecture.
That is not an accident.
That is always the case.
Now, Maxwell shows you
something that is a little bit
more complicated.
Here, he calculated for us the
equipotential surfaces,
the red ones are the surfaces,
again you have to rotate them
about the vertical to make it
three-dimensional,
and now we have a minus one
charge and a plus four.
And so whenever it is red,
the surface,
the potential is positive,
and whenever I have drawn it
blue, the potential is negative.
First, if we were very far away
from both the plus four and the
minus one, you expect to be
looking at a charge which is
effectively plus three.
And so if you go very far away
for
sure the potential is
everywhere positive and you
expect them to be spherical
again.
If you look here you're very
far away from the plus four and
the minus one,
indeed this has already the
shape of a sphere.
So that's clear that the plus
four and the minus one far away
behave like a plus three.
If you're very close to the
plus four, you get nice spheres
around the plus four,
positive potential,
if you're very close to the
minus one, notice that the blue
surfaces are almost nice
spheres, but now they're all
negative because you're very
close to the minus one.
So a negative potential.
There is here one surface which
now has zero potential.
It has to be because if you're
negative potential close to the
minus one and you have positive
potential very far out,
you got to go through a surface
where it's zero.
And so there is here a surface,
I still have put it in blue,
which is actually everywhere on
this surface the potential is
zero.
Is the electric field zero
there?
Absolutely not.
Electric field should not be
confused with potential.
What it means is that if you
take a test charge in your
pocket and you come from
infinity and you walk to that
surface, that by the time you
have reached that surface,
you've done zero work.
That's what it means.
That the
potential is zero.
There is here one point which
we discussed earlier in my
lectures where the electric
field is zero.
The potential is not zero
there.
The potential is definitely
positive here.
Because here was the zero
surface.
Here is already positive
surface, and this is a positive
surface.
So the potential is positive.
However, if you reach that
point there's no force on your
charge.
So that means electric field is
zero.
And it's not so easy of course
to calculate these surfaces.
Maxwell was capable of doing
that a hundred ten years ago.
And nowadays we can do that
very easily with computers.
Equipotential surfaces which
have different values can never
intersect.
Plus five volt surface can
never intersect with a plus
three or a minus one.
And you think about why that
is.
Why that is,
that would be a total
violation of the conservation
of energy.
So equipotential surfaces,
different values,
can never intersect.
All right.
So you've seen that for the
various charge configurations,
the equipotential surfaces have
very complicated shapes and
cannot always be calculated in a
very easy way.
Now comes the question why do
we introduce electric
potentials,
who needs them?
And who needs equipotential
surfaces?
Isn't it true that if we know
the electric field vectors
everywhere in space that that
determines uniquely how charges
will move, what acceleration
they will obtain,
that means how their kinetic
energy will change,
and the answer is yeah,
if you know the electric field
everywhere in space sure.
Then you can predict everything
that happens with a charge in
that field.
But there are examples where
the electric fields are so
incredibly complicated that it
is easier to work with
equipotentials because the
change in kinetic energy as I
will discuss now really depends
only on the change in the
potential when you go from one
point to another.
So you will see very shortly
that sometimes if you're only
interested in change of kinetic
energy and not necessarily
interested in the details of the
trajectory, then equipotentials
come in very
handy.
Never confuse U which is
electrostatic potential energy
with V which is electric
potential.
This has unit joules.
And this has unit joules per
coulombs, which we call volts.
If I have a collection of
charges, pluses and minuses,
U has only one value.
It is the work that I have to
do to put all these crazy
charges exactly where they are.
But the electric potential is
different here from there from
there to there to there to
there.
If you're very close to a plus
charge, you can be sure that the
potential is positive.
If you're very close to a -- a
negative charge,
you can be sure that the
potential is negative.
But U has only one number.
It's only one value.
They're both scalars.
Don't confuse one with the
other.
In a gravitational field,
matter, like a piece of chalk,
wants to go from high potential
to low potential.
If I just release it with zero
speed, there it goes,
high potential to low
potential.
In analogy, positive charges
will also go from a high
electric potential to a low
electric potential.
And of course this is unique
for electricity,
negative charges will go from a
low potential to a high electric
potential.
Suppose I had a position A in
space
and I had another position B
and I specify the potentials.
So here we have A,
potential is VA,
and here we have point B where
the potential is VB.
By definition,
the potential
of VA as we discussed before is
the integral -- by the way if
these are separated by some
random distance R,
whatever you want.
So the potential of A is
defined as the integral going
from A to infinity of E dot DR.
That is the definition of the
potential of A.
There is an E here which is
force per unit charge.
So it is not work.
If there were force DR it would
be work but it is force per unit
charge that makes it E.
So the potential of B for
definition is the integral from
B to infinity of E dot DR.
And so therefore the potential
difference between point A and
B, VA minus VB,
equals the integral from A to B
of E dot DR, and for reasons
that I still don't understand
after having been in this
business for a long time,
books will always tell you they
reverse VA and B so they give
you VB, VB minus VA.
And then they say well we have
to put a minus sign in front of
the uh integral.
It's the same thing.
So books always give it to you
in this form.
But it is exactly the same.
Hope you realize that.
This is the two equations that
I have here are the same.
VA minus VB is the integral
from A to B of E dot DR.
If I flip this over then all I
have to do is put a minus sign
here and the two are identical.
Notice that if there is no
electric field between A and B
they have the same potential,
of course.
Because when you march from A
to B with a charge in your
pocket no work is done.
So the potential remains the
same.
I will change this DR to a
different symbol,
which I call DL.
DR would mean that we go from A
to
infinity along this straight
line and then we go from B to
infinity along the straight line
but it makes no difference how
you go.
If you go from A to B this
potential difference and you go
in this way then VA minus VB is
not going to change.
And so if now I introduce here
a element DL,
which is a small vector,
and if the local E vector here
is like so, at this point here,
then VA minus VB is then the
integral of E dot DL.
In other words I can replace
the R by an L and you may choose
any path that you prefer.
And that's the way that we will
show you this equation most of
the time.
So it makes no difference how
you
march because we are dealing
here with conservative fields.
So let's now make the
assumption that VA is a hundred
fifty volts.
And that VB for instance is
So it's a very specific
example.
What does it mean now?
It means that if I put plus Q
charge in my pocket and I come
all the way from Lobby seven and
I walk up to point B.
So Walter Lewin plus Q charge
in his pocket goes from Lobby
seven to point B,
I have to do work and the work
I have to do is the product of
my charge Q with the potential.
So that is Q the work I have to
do is Q times VB.
So in this case it's fifty
times Q, whatever that charge is
that I have in my pocket.
This
is in joules.
Now, I go from Lobby seven to
point A.
I have to do more work.
I have to do a hundred fifty Q
joules of work.
You can think of it I first
come to A to B,
I'm already exhausted,
I have to put in another work
to get all the way to point A.
So you can imagine if I have
this plus Q charge at point A,
where there it's it's a higher
potential, it wants to go back
all by itself to B.
It wants to go from a higher
potential to a lower potential.
Look, the E vector is in this
direction.
Positive charge will go to a
lower potential.
And as it moves from A to B
energy is released.
How much energy?
Well, this is the amount of
work I have done to get to A,
this is the amount of work I
did to get to B,
and so if now the charge goes
back from A to B,
it's the difference that
becomes available in terms of
kinetic energy.
It's a change in potential
energy.
And that change in potential
energy, so the change in
potential energy,
when the plus Q charge goes
from A to B, that change is Q
times VA minus VB.
QVB at point B and QVA
at point A.
So this is the potential energy
that is in principle available
if the charge moves from A to B.
And you remember from eight oh
one the work energy theorem.
If we deal with conservative
forces, then the sum of
potential energy and kinetic
energy of an object is the same.
That's also true for
gravitational forces.
In other words,
this difference in potential
energy that becomes available
like potential energy becomes
available when I drop my chalk
from a high
potential to a low potential,
that's converted to kinetic
energy.
So this difference now is also
converted into kinetic energy of
that moving charge.
And so that would be the
kinetic energy at point B minus
the kinetic energy at point A.
Which is really the work energy
theorem.
It's the conservation of
energy.
Now any piece of metal,
no matter how crumby or dented
it is, is an equipotential.
As long as there is no charge
moving inside the metal.
And that's obvious that it's an
equipotential.
Because these charges inside
the metal, these electrons,
when they experience an
electric field,
they begin to move immediately
in the electric field,
and they will move until there
is no force on them anymore,
and that means they have
effectively made the electric
field zero.
So charges inside the conductor
always move automatically in
such a way that they kill the
electric
field inside.
If the electric field hadn't
been zero yet,
they would still be moving.
And so each metal that you
have, no matter where you bring
it, as long as there are no
electric currents inside,
will always be an
equipotential.
So I can take a trash can and
bring it into an external field
and then very shortly after I've
brought it in when things have
calmed down, the trash can will
be an
equipotential and the electric
field inside the metal will
everywhere will everywhere be
zero.
So I could for instance attach
point A to a trash can,
metal trash can,
so the whole trash can would be
at a hundred fifty volts,
and I could put point B,
make it part of my -- of my
soda, which is also made of
metal.
And so the whole soda would be
at fifty
volts and the entire trash can
would be at a hundred fifty
volts.
I place the whole thing in
vacuum and now I release an
electron at point B.
An electron.
An electron wants to go to
higher potential.
A proton would go from A to B,
electron wants to go from B to
A.
And so now energy is available.
The electric potential energy
is available and the electron
will
start to pick up speed and
finally end up at A.
Now how it will travel I don't
know.
The electric field
configuration is enormously
complicated.
Between the can and this trash
can.
Amazingly complicated.
If you were to see the field
lines it would be weird.
But if we all we want to know
is what the kinetic energy is,
what the speed is,
with which this electron
reaches the can,
so what?
Then we can use the work
energy theorem and find out
immediately what that kinetic
energy is.
Because the available potential
energy is the charge of the
electron times the potential
difference between these two
objects.
Well the charge of the electron
is one point six times ten to
the minus nineteen coulombs.
The potential difference is a
hundred volts.
And that is the difference in
kinetic energy.
If I assume that I release the
electron at zero speed,
then I have immediately the
kinetic energy that it has at
point A which is one-half M of
the electron times the speed at
A squared.
So now you see that accepting
the fact that we know the
equipotentials,
we can very quickly calculate
the kinetic energy and therefore
the speed of the electron,
as they arrive at A,
without any knowledge of the
complicated electric field.
If you put in the numbers for
the mass of the electron,
then, which is nine times ten
to the minus thirty-one
kilograms, then you'll find that
this speed is about two percent
of the speed of light.
A substantial speed.
All our potentials,
electric potentials,
are defined relative to
infinity.
That means at infinity they are
zero.
That is because of the one over
R relationship.
That's very nice and dandy and
it works.
However, there are situations
whereby it really doesn't matter
where you think of your zero.
Remember with gravity we had a
similar situation.
With gravity we always worried
about difference in potential
energy but sometimes we call
this zero and this plus.
Sometimes you call this plus
and this minus.
It doesn't really matter
because the change in kinetic
energy is dictated only by the
difference
in potentials.
So it is very nice and dandy to
call that a hundred fifty and to
call that fifty but you wouldn't
have found any different answer
for the electron if you called
this potential one hundred volts
and you called this one zero or
you called this one zero and
this one minus one hundred or
you called this one fifty and
this one minus fifty.
So the behavior of the
electrons of the charges would
of course not change.
And of course electrical
engineers would always per
definition call the potential of
the earth zero when they built
their circuits.
So now I would like to
demonstrate to you with the
Vandegraaff that if you get a
strong electric field from the
radially outwards from the
Vandegraaff that you get a huge
potential difference between
this point here and this point
there.
Uh if I have my numbers still
there,
I hope I do,
there they are,
at the surface of the
Vandegraaff which takes about
ten microcoulombs,
it will be three hundred
thousand volts right here,
here it would be a hundred
fifty thousand volts,
and here three meters from the
center, it's about thirty
kilovolts.
So that means that if I place
this fluorescent tube into that
electric field that there would
be a gigantic potential
difference between here and
there provided that I hold it
radially.
If I hold it like this
then the potential difference
between here and there would be
zero of course,
if I hold it tangentially,
they would be both at the same
electric potential.
But when I hold them radially
you will see perhaps that this
fluorescent tube will show a
little bit of light.
Once you see light it means
that electrons are moving
through that gas.
It means charge is moving.
We haven't discussed current
yet,
but that's what it means.
A current is flowing.
And this current has to be
delivered by the Vandegraaff and
the Vandegraaff is only capable
of providing very modest
currents.
So you're not going to see a
lot of light.
But I want to show you that you
will see some light.
No wires attached.
Just here.
And then I will rotate it
tangentially and you will see no
light at all.
So if we can make it a little
darker as a start and I'll start
the
Vandegraaff and then if Marcos
comes to make it completely dark
when necessary,
because the light is so little
that we really have to make it
completely dark.
I will put on a glove for
safety reasons although I don't
think it will do me much good.
Notice I have here a piece of
glass to well,
to be well-insulated from the
glass so that I don't mess up
the
demonstration by if I hold my
fingers here it will be very
different than holding my hands
here.
So let's go first close without
-- with the lights still on and
then OK why don't you turn the
lights off now all the way off.
OK I -- I think you can see a
glow.
It's radially outwards now.
And Marcos can you give a
little light?
OK I will now go tangential,
can you turn uh the lights off?
And now you see nothing,
very little.
And now I go radial again.
And there you go.
Now if I -- if I'm crazy,
if I were crazy,
then I would touch the end of
this tube with my finger thereby
allowing this current to go
straight through my body to the
earth which may increase the
light.
Let me try that.
So -- so I'm
going to touch the -- the --
the -- this -- this fluorescent
tube on your right side.
Ah.
Every time I -- I touch it ah.
But that's not ah.
But you see every time I touch
it I make it easier for the
current to flow and you see very
clearly that it lights up.
Now I want to do the same
demonstration with a neon flash
tube and the neon flash
tube I will place at the end of
a fishing rod.
This neon flash tube we used
during the first lecture when I
was beating up students but I've
learned not to do that anymore.
Um this takes um several
kilovolts to get a little bit of
light out of it from one side to
the other, oh,
that's duck soup for the
Vandegraaff, you know you're
talking about hundreds and
thousands of volts,
and so here I will actually
start spinning it and then when
it is radially inwards maybe
you will see light and when it
is tangential you won't see much
light and then if I feel very
good I will do that again.
OK uh so Marcos if you make it
uh dark I'll give it a twist.
OK, radial, radial,
radial,
radial, radial,
OK.
Now I ah OK I touched it now I
touch it again.
And I touch it again.
And again.
Ah.
You see every time I touch it
it lights me.
And it gives a nice flash of
light.
So you see here in front of
your
eyes without any wires attached
that the potential difference
created by the electric field
that those potential differences
make these lights work.
All right, see you Friday.