CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this segment, we're going to
talk about the product rule
for three functions and then
we're going to do an example.
And what I want to do first is
remind you the product rule
for two functions, because we're
going to use that to
figure out the product rule
for three functions.
So throughout this segment, we
are going to assume that U and
V and W are all functions
of x.
So I'm going to drop the
of x just so it's a
little easier to write.
This notation should be familiar
with things you saw
in the lecture.
So, for two functions,
let me remind you.
If UV, the product, and you take
its derivative, so prime
will denote d dx.
Then we can take the derivative
of the first times
the second function left alone,
plus the derivative of
the second function times
the first left alone.
So this should again be
familiar from class.
And now what we want to do is
expand that to the product of
three functions, U times V times
W. And we're going to
explicitly use this rule.
So, U V W prime is what
we want to look at.
So we're just going to take
advantage of what we know to
figure out what this
expression will be.
What this product of three
functions when I take its
derivative will be.
So in order to do this easily,
what we're going to do is
treat V times W as a
single function.
OK?
So V times W will be our
second function that
essentially takes the place
of the V up here.
So using the product rule for
two functions, what I get when
I take this derivative, is I get
U prime times VW plus, I
take the derivative
of this second
thing, which is VW prime.
And then I leave U alone.
OK?
We're quite done, but you can
see now, again if we compare
to what's above, you take the
derivative of the first
function, you leave the
second function alone.
You take the derivative of the
second function, you leave the
first function alone.
But now again, what
do we do here?
Well we have a product rule
for two functions,
so let's use it.
So, I'll leave the first thing
alone, U prime-- oops, that
does not look like a UV--
VW plus, now let's
expand this.
Take the derivative of the
first function there.
That's V prime.
I leave the W alone.
Plus the derivative of
the second function.
That's w prime.
I leave the V alone.
And I keep the U there.
OK?
I'm going to just expand and
write it in a nice order, so
we can see sort of exactly
what happens.
So, U prime VW plus V prime UW
plus W prime UV. So what you
can see here is, what happens?
You take the derivative of the
first function, you leave the
second and third alone.
Then you take the derivative
of the second function, you
leave the first and
third alone.
Then you take the derivative
of the third function, you
leave the first and
second alone.
And you add up those
three terms.
I would imagine that
at this point you
anticipate a pattern.
So if I had a fourth function.
If I did U times V times
W times Z, let's say.
And I took that derivative
with respect to x.
You could probably anticipate,
you would have four terms when
you added them up.
And that fourth term would have
to include a derivative
of the fourth function.
So from here, actually you can
probably tell me what the
derivative of the product
of n functions is.
And you can check it using
the same kind of rule.
But what we're going to do at
this point, is we're going to
just make sure we
understand this.
We're going to compute
an example.
So since we know products,
or we know derivatives
of powers of x.
And we know derivatives of the
basic trig functions, we'll do
a product rule using
those functions.
So, let me take an example.
So we'll say, f of x equals
x squared sine x cosine x.
OK?
And I want you to find
f prime of x.
Ok, I'm going to give you
a moment to do it.
You should probably pause the
video here, make sure you can
do it, and then you can, you can
restart the video when you
want to check your answer.
OK, so we have a product role
for three functions, we have
an example that I asked you to
determine and gave you a
moment to do it.
So now I will actually
work out the example
over here to the right.
So I will determine
f prime of x.
Now what are our three
functions?
Well we have x squared is the
first, sin x is the second,
cosine x is the third.
So we'll have three terms. The
first term has to have the
derivative of the x squared.
That's going to give me a 2x.
And I leave the other
two terms alone.
So I have 2x sine x
cosine x plus--
I may want to just write
these below.
OK.
Now in the next term,
I should take the
derivative of the sine x.
And leave the x squared and
the cosine x alone.
The derivative of sine
x is cosine x.
So I'm actually going to
write this underneath.
So we'll have--
I'm going to put the plus
underneath also so we remember
it's a sum.
Plus, so the derivative
of sine x is cosine x.
And then we have a times x
squared times-- oops--
another cosine x of the
third function.
OK?
And then the third term, I take
the derivative of the
third function and I leave the
first and second alone.
The derivative of cosine
x is negative sine x.
So I actually have a negative
sine x times x squared times
the sine x here.
I can do some simplifying
if I want.
But maybe, if I were trying to
write this nicely for someone
who was reading mathematics,
I would put all of the
polynomials in front and all of
the coefficients in front.
So to be very kind to someone,
I might write it like this.
And notice cosine x, cosine
x is cosine squared x.
And then minus x squared
sine squared x.
And there are other ways, I
could rewrite this and using
trig identities.
But this is a sufficient
answer at this point.
So this is actually a good way
to write the derivative of
that function f if x.
And this is where we'll stop.