PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
Last time in lecture you
started learning about
implicit differentiation.
And you saw some examples of how
implicit differentiation
can be used to compute
derivatives of functions
defined implicitly.
So let's do another
example today.
So here I have a curve that's
defined by the implicit
equation y cubed plus
x cubed equals 3xy.
And I'd like to know what the
slope of the tangent line to
that curve is at the
point 4/3, 2/3.
So before we start doing
anything, let me just make a
couple of observations.
If you don't believe me, that
the point 4/3, 2/3 is on this
curve, you can always check by
plugging the values in and
confirm that really, yes, 4/3
cubed plus 2/3 cubed is equal
to 3 times 2/3 times 4/3.
So it's how I found this point
is maybe a little magical.
Because as you can see, this
equation is really a tough one
to solve for y.
What you sort of, a natural
thing to want to do when asked
this question is to solve for y
and get an equation for y in
terms of x and then take the
derivative using the various
differentiation rules
that you've learned.
But here, this is, I'll
let you in a secret.
There is a way to do this.
But it's really hard.
It's really ugly and
it's beyond the
scope of this course.
So really we're much better
off treating this as an
implicit differentiation problem
than as an explicit
differentiation problem.
So having said that, why don't
you take a minute or two.
Try and have a go at
this yourself.
And then we'll come back and
work through it together.
All right, so welcome back.
We were in the middle--
we were just
about to start, actually--
solving this problem, computing
the slope of the
tangent line to the curve y
cubed plus x cubed equals 3xy
at this point, 4/3, 2/3.
So the slope of the tangent line
is the value y prime of x
at that point.
So we need to answer
this question.
What we need to do is we need
to find the derivative of y.
But as I said earlier, this is
tough to do explicitly, to
find y in terms of x, so we're
going to use implicit
differentiation.
So, so we start with this
equation, y cubed plus x cubed
equals 3xy and we can take a
derivative with respect to x.
So some parts, all right, so
let's start with it in the
order its given.
So you have y cubed.
If you take a derivative of y
cubed with respect to x, what
you need to use the chain rule
because y is implicitly a
function of x and so y cubed
is the chain rule.
It's the cubed function applied
to the y function.
And this is true of implicit
differentiation in general.
That the reason that we can do
this, the really fundamental
reason this works is that we
have the chain rule and that
it lets us evaluate derivatives
of compositions.
So in our case we have, so we
take a derivative of the whole
thing, of this whole--
I'm going to write, this is a
little sloppy notation, but I
hope you know what I mean.
We have this identity and
so we're going to take a
derivative of the whole thing.
And so the first part on
the left, we get the
derivative of y cubed.
So by the chain rule, so we
first take the derivative of
the cube function at y and
then multiply by the
derivative of y.
So this is the derivative
of y cubed.
It just gives us 3y squared.
So that's what happens
when you just deal
with the cubed part.
But then we need to
multiply by--
in the chain rule-- by the
derivative if the inside.
Which in this context
is dy by dx.
OK.
Plus the derivative
of x cubed.
That's more straightforward.
Nothing really complicated
going on here.
We've seen this for a
little while now.
It's just 3x squared equal.
OK.
So on the right now, we don't
actually have a chain rule, we
have a product rule
situation here.
We have 3 times x times y.
So 3 is just a constant.
And so we could just pull
it out in front.
So we take the derivative
of xy.
So we take the derivative of
the first times the second
plus the derivative of the
second times the first. So the
derivative of the first is
just-- ah sorry, x is the
first, so its derivative is 1.
So we got 3 times
the second is y.
Plus--
OK, so we take the first times
the derivative of the second,
which is dy by dx.
So because this is an identity
it holds for all
values of x and y.
This equality follows
just by taking the
derivative of both sides.
Good.
So now the thing we want is that
we want the slope of the
tangent line at a particular
point.
So we want to isolate dy dx.
That's the thing we're
trying to find.
So here, if you're only
interested in dy dx, this is
actually a linear equation
in some sense.
Right?
We have dy dx, a constant,
something-- or it's not a
constant-- something times dy
dx plus something equals
something plus something
times dy dx.
There are no squares of dy
dx is what I really mean.
So OK.
So that that's nice.
It makes it relatively easier
to solve so we can just
combine all the terms
with dy dx in them.
Let's say we'll combine maybe,
put them over here and put
everything else over there.
So over here we get, so
dy dx, so we have a 3y
squared minus a 3x.
And on the other side we have
a 3y minus a 3x squared.
And so this is times,
multiplication there.
And so we want dy by
dx just by itself.
So we can just divide through
by 3y squared minus 3x.
So then we have dy
dx is equal to--
well, all right, so there
are a lot of 3s here.
There's a constant multiple of
3 on this side, a constant
multiple of 3 on this side.
Those are going to cancel.
So this is y minus x squared
over y squared minus x.
OK, so at any point, xy on this
curve, the slope of the
tangent line is given by
this expression here.
And we're interested
in a particular
point in this problem.
We're interested in the
point 4/3 comma 2/3.
So at-- let me take that back up
here-- so at the point 4/3
comma 2/3 we have dy by dx.
So OK, we just we just plug that
value of y and that value
of x into this formula
that we've got.
So that's 2/3 minus 4/3
squared is 16/9 over--
well, let's see, 2/3 squared
is 4/9 minus 4/3.
All right, so we have a little
bit of irrational number
arithmetic here.
Maybe I'll multiply top and
bottom through by 9 to get 6
minus 16 over 4 minus 12.
So this is negative 10 over
negative 8, which is 5 over 4.
And if we go back to the
picture that I drew, it
actually looks pretty reasonable
over here, right?
This slope of this tangent line
is actually a little bit
bigger than 1.
Great.
So that's that.