It's in the same direction as
column one.
It's not independent.
I'll expect to discover that in
the process.
Actually, with rows,
I notice that that row plus
this row gives the third row.
So the third row is not
independent.
So, all that should come out of
elimination.
So now what I --
my algorithm is elimination,
but extended now to the
rectangular case,
where we have to continue even
if there's zeros in the pivot
position, we go on.
OK, so let me execute
elimination for that matrix.
My goal is always,
while I'm doing elimination --
I'm not changing the null
space.
That's very important,
right?
I'm solving A x equals zero by
elimination, and when I do these
operations that you already
know, when I subtract a multiple
of one equation from another
equation, I'm not changing the
solutions.
So I'm not changing the null
space.
Actually, I changing the column
space, as you'll see.
So you have to pay attention.
What does elimination leave
unchanged?
And the answer is the solutions
to the system are not changed
because I'm doing the same thing
to -- I'm doing a legitimate
operations on the equations.
Of course, on the right hand
side it's always zero,
and I don't plan to write zero
all the time.
OK, so I'm really just working
on the left side,
but the right side is,
is keeping up always zeros.
OK, so what's elimination?
Well, you know where the first
pivot is and you know what to do
with it.
So can I just take the first
step below here?
So that pivot row is fine.
I take two times that row away
from this one and I get zero
zero.
That's signaling a difficulty.
Two, two twos away from the six
leaves me with a two.
Two twos away from the eight
leaves me with a four.
And now three of those away
from here is zero,
again another zero,
three twos away from that eight
is the two, three twos away from
that ten is a four.
OK.
That's the first stage of
elimination.
I've got the first column
straight.
So of course I move on to the
second column.
I look in that position,
I see a zero.
I look below it,
hoping for a non-zero that I
can do a row exchange.
But it's zero below.
So that's telling me that that
column is -- well,
what it's really going to be
telling me is that that column
is a combination of the earlier
columns.
It's that second column is
dependent on the earlier
columns.
But I don't stop to think here.
In that column there's nothing
to do.
I go on to the next.
So here's the next pivot.
So there's the first pivot and
there's the second pivot,
and I just keep this
elimination going downwards.
So, so the next step keeps the
first row, keeps the second row
with its pivot,
so I've got my two pivots,
and does elimination to clear
out the column below that pivot.
So actually you see the
multiplier is one.
It subtracts row two from row
three and produces a row of
zeros.
OK.
That I would call that matrix
U, right?
That's our upper -- well,
I can't quite say upper
triangular.
Maybe upper -- I don't know --
upper something.
It's in this so-called echelon
form.
The word echelon means,
like, staircase form.
It's the, the non-zeros come in
that staircase form.
If there was another pivot
here, then the staircase would
include that.
But here's a case where we have
two pivots only.
OK, so actually we've already
discovered the most important
number about this matrix.
The number of pivots is two.
That number we will call the
rank of the matrix.
So let me put immediately.
The rank of A -- so I'm telling
you what this word rank means in
the algorithm.
It's equal to the number of
pivots.
And in this case,
two.
OK, for me that number two is
the crucial number.
OK, now I go to -- you remember
I'm always solving A x equals
zero, but now I can solve U x
equals zero, right?
Same solution,
same null space.
OK.
So I could stop here -- why
don't I stop here and do the
back substitution.
So now I have to ask you,
how do I describe the
solutions?
There are solutions,
right, to A x equals zero.
I knew there would be.
I had three equations in four
unknowns.
I certainly expected some
solutions.
Now I want to see what are
they.
OK, here's the critical step.
I refer to it up here as
separating out the pivot
variables, the pivot columns,
which are these two.
Here I have two pivot columns.
Those, obviously,
they're the columns with the
pivots.
So I have two pivot columns.
And I have the other columns,
I'll call free.
These are free columns,
OK.
Why do I use those words?
Why do I use that word free?
Because now I want to write,
I want to find the solutions to
U x equals zero.
Here is the way I do it.
These free columns I can assign
any number freely to those --
to the variables x2 and x4,
the ones that multiply columns
two and four.
So I can assign anything I like
to x2 and x4.
And then I can solve the
equations for x1 and x3.
Let me say that again.
If I give -- let me,
let me assign.
So, so one particular x is to
assign, say, the value one to
the, to x2, and zero to x4.
Those are -- that was a free
choice, but it's a convenient
choice.
OK.
Now I want to solve U x equals
zero and find numbers one and
three, complete the solution.
OK.
Can I write down -- let's see.
Shall we just remember what U x
equals zero represents?
What are my equations?
That first equation is x1 plus
just -- I'm just saying what are
these matrices meaning.
That's the first equation.
And the second equation was 2x3
+ 4x4=0.
Those are my two equations.
OK.
Now the point is I can find x1
and x3 by back substitution.
So we're building on what we
already know.
The new thing is that there
were some free variables that I
could give any numbers to.
And I'm systematically going to
make a choice like this,
1 and 0.
Now what is x3?
Let's, let's go backwards,
back up.
I look at the last equation.
x3 is zero, from the last
equation, because,
because x4 we've set x4 to
zero, and then we get x3 as
zero.
OK.
Now we set x2 to be one,
so what is x1?
Negative two,
right?
So then I have negative two
plus two, zero and zero,
correctly giving zero.
There is a vector in the null
space.
There is a solution to A x
equals zero.
In fact, what solution is that?
That simply says that minus two
times the first column plus one
times the second column is the
zero column.
Of course that's right.
Minus two of that column plus
one of that, or minus two of
that plus one of that.
That solution is --
that, that's just what we saw
immediately, that the second
column is twice as big as the
first column.
OK, tell me some more vectors
in the null space.
I found one.
Tell me, how to get a bunch
more immediately out of that
one.
Just take multiples of it.
Any multiple of -- I could
multiply this by anything.
I might as well call it,
I could say,
C, some multiple of this.
So let me -- so X could be any
multiple of this one.
OK, that, that describes now a
line, an infinitely long line in
four dimensional space.
But -- which is in the null
space.
Is that the whole null space?
No.
I've got two free variables
here.
I made this choice,
one and zero,
for the free variables,
but I could have made another
choice.
Let me make the other choice
zero and one.
You see my system.
So let me repeat the system.
This is the algorithm that you,
you just learned to do.
Do elimination.
Decide which are the pivot
columns and which are the free
columns.
That tells you that,
that variables one and three
are pivot variables,
two and four are free
variables.
Then those free variables,
you assign them -- you give one
of them the value one and the
others the value zero -- in this
case, we had a one and a zero --
and complete the solution.
And you do --
you give the other one the
value one and zero.
And now complete the solution.
So let's complete that
solution.
I'm looking for a vector in the
null space, and it's absolutely
going to be different from this
guy, because,
because any multiple of that
zero is never going to give the
one.
So I have somebody new in the
null space, and let me finish it
out.
What's x3 here?
So we're going by back
substitution,
looking at this equation.
Now x4 we've changed,
we're doing the other
possibility, where x2 is zero
and x4 is one.
So x3 will happen to be minus
two.
And now what do I get for that
first equation?
x1 -- let's see.
Two x3s is minus four plus two
-- do I get a two there?
Perhaps, yeah.
Two for x1, minus four,
and two.
OK.
That's in the null space.
What does that say about the
columns?
That says that two of this
column minus two of this column
plus this column gives zero,
which it does.
Two of that minus two of that
and one of that gives the zero
column.
OK, now, now I've found another
vector in the null space.
Now we're ready to tell me the
whole null space.
What are all the solutions to
Ax=0?
I've got this guy and when I
have him, what else is,
goes into the null space along
with that?
These are my two special
solutions.
I call them special -- I just
invented that name.
Special solutions.
What's special about them is
the special numbers I gave to
the free variables,
the values zero and one for the
free variables.
I could have given the free
variables any values and got
vectors in the null space.
But this was a good way to be
sure I got t- got everybody.
OK, so once I have him,
I also have any multiple,
right?
So I could take any multiple of
that and it's in the null space.
And now what else -- I left a
little space for what?
What -- a plus sign.
I can take any combination.
Here is a line of vectors in
the null space.
A bunch of solutions.
Would you rather I say in the
null space or would you rather I
say, OK, I'm solving Ax=0?
Well, really I'm solving Ux=0.
Well, OK, let me put in that
crucial plus sign.
I'm taking all the combinations
of my two special solutions.
That's my conclusion there.
The null space contains,
contains exactly all the
combinations of the special
solutions.
And how many special solutions
are there?
There's one for every free
variable.
And how many free variables are
there?
Oh, I mean, we can see all the
whole picture now.
If the rank R was two,
this is the,
this is the number of pivot
variables, right,
because it counted the pivots.
So how many free variables?
Well, you know it's two,
right?
What is it in -- for a matrix
that's m rows,
n columns, n variables that
means, with rank r?
How many free variables have we
got left?
If r of the variables are pivot
variables, we have n-r -- in
this case four minus two -- free
variables.
Do you see that first of all we
get clean answers here?
We get r pivot variables -- so
there really were r equations
here.
There looked like three
equations, but there were really
only two independent equations.
And there were n-r variables
that we could choose freely,
and we gave them those special
zero one values,
and we got the special
solutions.
OK.
For me -- we could stop at that
point.
That gives you a complete
algorithm for finding all the
solutions to A x equals zero.
OK.
Again, you do elimination --
going onward when a column,
when there's nothing to be done
on one column,
you just continue.
There's this number r,
the number of pivots,
is crucial, and it leaves n-r
free variables,
which you give values zero and
one to.
I would like to take one more
step.
I would like to clean up this
matrix even more.
So now I'm going to go to --
this is in its,
this is in echelon form,
upper triangular if you like.
I want to go one more step to
make it as good as it can be.
OK, so now I'm going to speak
about the reduced row echelon
form.
OK, so now I'm going to speak
about the matrix R,
which is the reduced row
echelon form.
So what does that mean?
That means I just -- I can,
I can work harder on U.
So let me start,
let me suppose I got as far as
U, which was good.
Notice how that row of zeros
appeared.
I didn't comment on that,
but I should have.
That row of zeros up here is
because row three was a
combination of rows one and two,
and elimination discovered that
fact.
When we get a row of zeros,
that's telling us that the --
original row that was there was
a combination of other rows,
and elimination knocked it out.
OK, so we got this far.
Now how can I clean that up
further?
I can do, elimination upwards.
I can get zero above the
pivots.
So this reduced row echelon
form has zeros above and below
the pivots.
So let me do that.
So now I'll subtract one of
this from the row above.
That will leave a zero and a
minus two in there.
And that's good.
OK, and I can clean it up even
one more step.
I can make the pivots -- the
pivots I'm going to make equal
to one, because I can divide
equation two by the pivot.
That won't change the
solutions.
So let me do that.
And then I really -- I'm ready
to stop.
One, two, zero,
minus two, zero,
zero, one, two.
I divided the second equation
by two, because now I have a one
in the pivot and zeros below.
OK.
This is my matrix R.
I guess I'm hoping that you
could now execute the whole
algorithm.
Matlab will do it immediately
with the command -- reduced row
echelon form of A.
So if I input that original
matrix A and then I write,
then I type that command,
press return,
that matrix will appear.
That's the reduced row echelon
form, and it's got all the
information as clear as can be.
What, what information has it
got?
Well, of course it immediately
tells me the pivot rows,
pivot rows, one and two,
pivot columns,
one and three.
And in fact it's got the
identity matrix in there,
right?
It's, it's got zeros above and
below the pivots,
and the pivots are one,
so it's, so it's got a -- so
notice the two by two identity
matrix that's sitting in the
pivot rows and pivot columns.
it's I in the pivot rows and
columns.
It's got zero rows below.
Those are always indicating
that original rows were,
were combinations of other
rows.
So we really only had two rows
there.
And now it also -- so there's
the identity.
Now it's also got its free
columns.
And, they're cleaned up as much
as possible.
Actually, actually it's now so
cleaned up that the special
solutions, I can read off -- you
remember I went through the
steps of computing this -- doing
back substitution?
Let me, let me,
instead of that system,
let me take this improved
system.
So I'm going to use these
numbers, right.
In these equations,
what did I do?
I divided this equation by two
and, oh yeah and I had
subtracted two of this,
which knocked out this guy and
made that a minus sign.
Is that what -- I've now
written Rx equals zero.
Now I guess I'm hoping
everybody in this room
understands the solutions to the
original A x equals zero,
the midway, halfway,
U x equals zero,
and the final R x equals zero
are all the same.
Because going from one of those
to another one I didn't mess up.
I just multiplied equations and
subtracted from other equations,
which I'm allowed to do.
OK.
But my point is that now if I
do this free variables and back
substitution,
it's just, the numbers are
there.
When I let x -- so in this guy,
I let x2 be one and x4 be zero.
I, I guess, what I seeing here?
Let me, let me sort of separate
this out here.
I'm seeing in the pivot,
in the pivot columns,
if I, if I put the pivot
columns here,
I'm seeing those.
And I'm -- in the free columns
I'm seeing -- what I seeing in
the free columns?
A two, zero in that first free
column, the x2 column,
and a minus two,
two in the fourth column,
the other free column.
And the row of zeros below,
which of course have no -- that
equation is zero equals zero.
That's satisfied.
Here's my point.
That when I do back
substitution,
these numbers are exactly what
shows up -- oh,
their signs get switched.
I was going to say those
numbers, two,
minus two, zero,
two, can I just circle the --
this is the free part of the
matrix.
This is the identity part.
This is the free part,
maybe I'll call it F.
This, of course,
I call I, because it's the
identity.
The free part is a,
I mean, I'm just doing back
substitution.
And those free numbers will
show up, with a minus sign,
because they pop onto the other
side of the equation --
so I see minus two,
zero, and I see two,
minus two.
So that wasn't magic.
It had to happen.
Let me, show you clearly why it
happened.
OK, so that's -- this is what
I'm interested in here.
And now let me,
let me just,
like, do it,
do it for -- let's suppose
we've, we've got to -- let's
suppose we've got this system
already in, in rref form.
So my matrix R is -- what does
it look like?
OK, and I'll -- let me pretend
that the pivot columns come
first and then whatever's in the
free columns.
And there might be some zero
rows below.
There's a typical -- a pretty
typical reduced row echelon
form.
You see what's typical.
It's got -- this is r by r.
This is r pivot rows.
This is r pivot columns.
And here are n-r free columns.
OK.
Tell me what are the special
solutions?
What are the -- what's x?
If I want to solve R x equals
zero -- in fact,
let me -- I'm really going to,
do the whole --
since these -- this is now
block matrices,
I might as well do all of the
special solutions at once.
So I want to solve R x equals
zero, and I'll have some special
solutions.
Let me, actually -- can I do
them all at once?
I'm going to create a null
space matrix,
OK.
A matrix.
Its, its, its columns are the
special -- the columns are the
special solutions.
This is, I'm making it sound
harder, it's going to be totally
easy.
N will be this null space
matrix.
I want R N to be the zero
These columns of N are supposed
to multipl- to get multiplied by
R and give zero columns.
So what N will do the job?
Let me put -- I'm going to put
the identity in the free
variable part and then minus F
will show up in the pivot
variables, just the way it did
in that example.
There we had the identity and
F.
Here -- in the special
solution.
So these columns are -- there's
the matrix of special solutions.
And actually,
there -- so there's a Matlab
command or a teaching code
command, NULL -- N equal,
so this is the -- produces the
null basis, the null space
matrix, NULL of A,
and there it is.
And how does that command
actually work?
It uses Matlab to compute R,
then it picks out the pivot
variables, the free variables,
puts, puts ones and zeros in
for the free variables,
and copies out the pivot
variables.
It, it does back substitution,
but back substitution for this
system is totally simple.
What is this system?
R x equals zero.
So this is R is I F,
and x is the pivot variables
and the free variables,
and it's supposed to give zero.
So what does that mean?
That means that the pivot
variables plus F times the free
variables give zero.
So let me put F times the free
variables on the other side.
I get minus F times the free
variables.
There's my, equation,
as simple as it can be.
That's what back substitution
comes to when I've reduced and
reduced and reduced this system
to the, to the best form,
OK.
And, then if the free
variables, I make this special
choice of the identity,
then the pivot variables are
minus F.
OK, can I do,
another example?
Could you do another example?
Can I -- let me just take
another matrix and,
and let's go through this
algorithm once more,
OK.
Here we go.
Here's a blackboard for another
matrix, OK.
So I'll call the matrix A
again, but let me make it --
yeah, how big shall we make it
this time?
Why don't I do this?
Just for the heck of it.
Let me take the transpose of
this A and see what happens to
that.
Two four six eight and three
six eight ten.
Before we do the calculations,
tell me what's coming?
How many pivot variables do you
expect here?
How many columns are going to
have pivots?
How many -- we have three
columns in that matrix,
but are we going to,
are we going to have three
pivots?
No, because this third columns
is the sum of the first two
columns.
I'm totally expecting,
totally expecting that these
will be pivot columns --
because they're independent,
but that this third guy,
the third column,
which is dependent on the first
two, is going to be a free
column.
Elimination better discover
that.
And elimination will also
straighten out the rows,
dependent rows and some
independent rows.
What's the, what's the row
reduced echelon form for this?
Let's just do it,
OK.
So, so that's the first pivot.
Two times that away from that
gives me a row of zeros.
gives me a zero two two.
And two times that away from
that gives me a zero four four.
OK, first column is straight.
First variable is a pivot
variable.
No problem.
On to the second column.
I look at the second pivot,
it's a zero.
I look below it.
There's a two.
OK, I do a row exchange.
So this zero is now there.
I now have a perfectly good
pivot, and I use it.
OK, and I subtract two of that
row away from this row.
All right if I do it like that?
I've got to the form U now.
This was my A.
Now there's my U.
I can see now -- I have to
stop, right?
I would go on to the third
column.
I should have tried.
I quit, but without trying.
I shouldn't have done that.
On to the third column,
look at the pivot position.
It's got a zero in it.
Look below, all zeros.
Now I'm entitled to stop,
OK.
So the rank is two again.
What about the null space?
How many special solutions are
there this time?
How many special solutions for
this matrix?
I've got -- and which are the
free variables and which are the
pivot variables and so on?
Pivot columns,
I've got two pivot columns,
and that's no accident.
The number of pivot columns for
a matrix A, that's a great fact,
that the number of pivot
columns for A and A transpose
are the same.
And then I have a free column.
There's a free column.
One free column,
because the count is three
minus two.
Three minus two gives me one
free column.
OK, so now let me solve,
what's in the null space.
OK, so how do I -- let's see.
These vectors have length
three.
They only have three
components.
I'm making too much space for
the, to write x.
x has just got three
components, and what are they?
I'm looking for the null space.
OK, so how do I start?
I give the free variable some
convenient value.
And what's that?
I set it to one.
I set the free variable to one.
If I set the free variable to
zero and solve for the pivot
variables, I'll get all zeros:
no progress.
But by setting the free
variable to one -- you see w- my
two equations now are --
my equations are x1+ 2x2+ 3 x3
is zero, that's my first
equation.
And my second equation is now
2x2+2x3 equals zero.
And, OK.
So if x3 is one,
then x2 is minus one.
And if x3 is one and x2 is
minus one, then maybe x1 is
minus one.
And actually I go back to check
now.
I don't, like -- I did a quick
calculation mentally.
Can I mentally do a quick
check?
That matrix,
that solution x says that minus
this column minus this column
plus this one is the zero
column.
And it is.
Minus that minus that plus that
is zero.
So that's in the null space.
And now you can tell me what
else is in the null space.
What's, what's the whole null
space now?
I multiply by C,
right.
The whole null space is a line.
So that's the description.
You know, if I ask you on a
homework or a quiz or the final
what --
give me, describe,
tell me the null space,
find the null space of this
matrix, you can take those
steps.
And that's the answer I'm
looking for.
And I'm looking for that C too,
because that's telling me that
you're remembering that it's a
whole space and not just one
vector.
Later I will ask you for a
basis for the null space.
Then I just want this vector.
But if I ask for the whole null
space, then there's the whole
line through that vector.
OK, now one more natural thing
to do with this example,
right, is keep going to the
reduced matrix,
R.
So can I push onwards to R?
That should be quick,
but let's just practice.
Let me keep going to R.
OK, so what do I do here?
I subtract -- I clear out above
the pivot, so I subtract that
from that, that's one zero one
is left, right?
When I subtracted this row from
this it produced a zero above
this pivot.
And now I want that pivot to be
a one.
So for the R matrix,
I'll divide this equation by
two, and of course these zero,
zeros are great,
they don't change.
There's R.
That's R.
You see what R is?
You see the identity matrix
sitting up here?
You see the free part F,
the F part here?
And you see the zeros below.
This is I F zero zero.
And what's the x?
The x has the identity --
well, it's only a single number
one, but it's the identity
matrix in the free,
in the free part.
And what does it have in the
pivot variables?
What did back substitution
give?
It gave minus these guys.
You see that what this is is
any multiple of -- this is the
identity there,
and this is minus F here.
This is our null space matrix N
for this.
Our, our null space matrix is
the guy whose columns are the
special solutions.
So their free variables have
the special values one and,
pivot variables have minus F.
So do you see,
though, how the minus F just
automatically shows up in the
special solutions.
That's it really.
I don't think there's anything
more I can say about A x equals
zero.
There's more I can say about A
x equal b, but that'll be on
Friday.
OK, so that's,
that's the null space.
Thanks.