MARTINA BALAGOVIC: Hi.
Welcome back.
Today's problem is about solving
homogeneous linear
systems, ax equals 0, but it's
also an introduction to the
next lecture and next recitation
section, which are
going to be about solving
non-homogeneous linear
systems, ax equals b.
The problem is fill
the blanks type.
And it says the set S of all
points with coordinates xy and
z, such that x minus 5y plus 2z
equals 9 is a blank in R3.
It is in a certain relation to
the other blank S0 of all the
points with coordinates x,
y, and z that satisfy the
following linear equation, x
minus 5y plus 2z equals 0.
After we solve this, we have
the second part of the
problem, which says all points
of x have a specific form, x y
z equals blank 0 0 plus some
parameter times blank 1 0 plus
some other parameter
times blank 0 1.
And we need to fill out
all six blanks.
Now you should pause the video,
fill in the blanks, and
then come back and see some
pretty pictures that I
prepared for you.
And we're back.
So you probably picked this
up in lectures already.
If you have a three dimensional
space with three
degrees of freedom, and put in
one constraint, so put in one
equation, you get something
that has two degrees of
freedom, something that's
two dimensional.
If this equation is linear,
rather than quadratic or cubic
or exponential, this something
is something two
dimensional and flat.
Something two dimensional and
flat in R3 is also called a
plane, or a two plane.
Similarly, S0 is also a plane.
Now, what's the relation between
S and S0 if they're
given by these two equations?
Well first let's look at the
general positions in which two
planes in R3 can be.
First one is that they're
intersecting along a line.
What's going to happen here is
that all points on this plane
are points whose coordinates
satisfy the
equation of this plane.
The points in this plane are
points whose coordinates
satisfy the equation
of this plane.
And the points on the line are
points whose coordinates
satisfy the system of this
equation and this equation.
The other position in which
two planes can be is that
they're not intersecting at all,
that they're parallel.
So let's start by trying
to find this line here.
The equation of one plane is
x minus 5y plus 2z equal 9.
The equation of the other
one is x minus 5y
plus 2z equals 0.
Now you can just look at it
and see how many solutions
it's supposed to have, or you
can try doing elimination, and
after one step of elimination
get 0 equals
9, which never happens.
There cannot exist numbers x,
y, and z such that this
combination of them produces 0,
and the same combination of
them produces 9 at
the same time.
So this red line here doesn't
exist, and the situation of
these two planes S and S0 is
this one, they're parallel.
So let's add the word
parallel in here.
And let's move on to the other
half of the problem.
The other half said all points
of S have this specific form.
Now let me call this
point here P0.
If all points of S have this
form, we can plug in any
parameter c1 and c2 here and
we're going to get a
point of the plane.
So in particular, we can plug
in c1 and c2 equal to 0.
What we get then is that the
point x y z equals P0 is a
point of the plane
S. So P0 is in S.
What do we know about
the point P0?
Well the fact that it's in S
means the its coordinates, x
minus 5y plus 2z equal 9.
That's the equation of S. But we
also know that y and z are
equal to 0 and 0.
Solving this system we get that
the x-coordinate of this
point P0 is 9, and we
can just add 9 here.
So we just have two blanks
left to fill.
Before we'll fill them,
let me show you a
picture that I drew here.
So we have these two planes, S0
and S, which are parallel.
They're given by these
equations.
And the plane S0 has a point 0
in it, because the equation is
x minus 5y plus 2z equals 0,
so it satisfied by 0 0 0.
The plane S has this point P0
in it, which is 9 0 0-- we
just figured this out.
And there's this vector
connecting one
plane to the other.
Now, since those two planes are
parallel and there's this
vector going between them, what
we can see is that a good
way to get any point in S is to
go to any point in S0 and
go up by this vector.
Now let me write this down.
What I just said is that any
point in S is of the form--
use this vector to go up--
plus any point in S0.
And if we compare this to this
expression here, we also get
P0 plus this linear
combination.
So this here has to
be a point in S0.
Now we're left with a question
of how to parameterize all
points in S0.
What are all the points in S0,
and what does this problem
have to do with solving
homogeneous linear equations?
Well let me write this equation
of S0 in a slightly
different way.
Let me write it as 1, minus
5, 2, x y z, equals 0.
And let me think of this as
a matrix of the system.
It's a very tiny matrix,
but it's a matrix.
And think of it as a matrix
dot a vector equals 0, and
trying to find all solutions
of the system.
Well let's do row
reductions here.
It's already as upper triangular
as these tiny
matrices get.
This is a pivot.
So we have a pivot variable x.
These are free variables,
y and z.
And if you remember how to solve
these systems, for each
free variable we get one
particular solution.
So we get one particular
solution when we plug in y is
1 and all the other free
variables are 0.
Plugging it in here, we just
get that in that case, x--
so we get x minus 5 times 1
plus 2 times 0 equals 0.
So x is equal to 5.
And the other solution is for
setting all free variables
equal to 0, except z which
we set equal to 1.
And then we get x minus
5 times 0 plus 2
times 1 equals 0.
So we get that in this case,
x equals minus 2.
And any solution of this system
is going to be of the
form some constant times
this plus some other
constant times this.
And if we walk back to our
original problem here, we see
that these parameters, these
numbers here, have been set up
exactly so that we can just take
these numbers and just
copy them over, 5 and minus 2.
And this is the general form of
any point of the plane S.
It's go up this vector, and then
add a point in S0, in the
parallel plane that passes
through the origin.
This finishes our problem.
But what I would encourage you
to do now is to go on to the
next lecture, watch the next
recitation video, and then
come back here and think about
what is it that we really did
here on this half
of the board.
Thank you.