CHRISTINE BREINER: Welcome
back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
work on the following problem.
We're going to let F be the
vector field that's defined by
r to the n, times the
quantity xi plus yj.
And r in this case is x squared
plus y squared to the
1/2 as it usually is.
The square root of x squared
plus y squared.
And then I'd like us to
do the following.
Use extended Green's theorem to
show that F is conservative
for all integers n.
And then find a potential
function.
So there are two parts.
The first part is that you
want to show that F is
conservative.
And then once you know it's
conservative, you can find a
potential function.
So why don't you take a little
while to work on that.
And then when you're feeling
good about your answer, bring
the video back up, and I'll
show you what I did.
OK, welcome back.
So again, what was the
point of this video?
We want to do two things.
We want to work on
two problems.
The first is to show that this
vector field F I've given you
is conservative.
And then we want to find
a potential function.
And we want to be able to show
it's conservative for all
integers n.
And what I want to point out
is that for certain integer
values of n, we're going to run
into some problems with
differentiability
at the origin.
OK?
So we're going to try and deal
with all of it at once, and
simultaneously deal with all
of the integers by allowing
ourselves to show that F is
conservative even if we don't
include the origin
in our region.
OK.
So I want to point out a few
things first. And the first
thing I want to point out is if
we denote F as we usually
do in two dimensions as (M,N),
then the curl of F is going to
be N sub x minus M sub y.
OK.
I actually calculated these
earlier, but I want to point
out that M sub y is actually
equal to n times r to the n
minus 2, times xy.
Let me make sure I wrote
that correctly.
Yes.
But that is also exactly
equal to N sub x.
And so what does that give us?
Since N sub x minus M sub y is
the curl of F when we have
this vector (M,N), we know that
the curl of F is equal to
0 by this work.
OK, now if our vector field
was defined on a
simply-connected region, then
that's enough to show that F
is conservative.
OK?
We just use Green's theorem
right away.
Right?
But the problem is that we
are not necessarily on a
simply-connected region because
we could have problems
at the origin.
And so I'm going to deal
with this in a
slightly different way.
To show that F is conservative,
what
do I want to show?
I want to show that when I take
the line integral F dot
dr over any closed loop
that I get 0.
That's ultimately what
I'm trying to show.
So there are fundamentally two
types of curves that I'm
concerned with.
Two closed curves in r2 that
I'm concerned with, and I'm
going to draw a picture of those
two types of curves.
So in r2 I'm going to have
curves that miss the origin.
Some curve like this,
which I'll call C1.
And then I'm going to have
curves that go around the
origin, and I'll call this C2.
OK?
Fundamentally, there's a
difference between this curve
and this curve, because this
curve contains the region
where F is defined and
differentiable, right?
Every point on the interior of
this curve, F is defined and
differentiable and therefore,
I can apply regular old
Green's theorem here.
OK?
So I know by Green's theorem,
the integral over the closed
curve C1 of F dot dr is equal
to 0, and that's simply
because the curl of
F is equal to 0.
Right?
We can immediately use Green's
theorem because we know that
the integral over this loop C1
is equal to the integral over
this region of the curl of F.
That's just Green's theorem.
So I can apply Green's
theorem here.
Now the problem here is I can't
apply Green's theorem
because this origin
is a trouble spot.
Right?
I'm not necessarily
differentiable there, so I
have to be a little
more careful.
OK, and so what I do is I'm
going to explain why
immediately I can get the
integral over C2 is
actually also 0.
And what I'm going to do is I'm
actually going to draw,
hopefully, a circle
that contains C2.
So I'm going to draw a circle.
It's a lot of curves,
but this is supposed
to look like a circle.
Sorry about that.
It's a little big on the low
side, but it's a circle.
OK.
This is a circle.
And I'm going to call this C3.
Now, I can tell you right away
that the integral over the
curve C3 of F dot dr is equal to
0, and let me explain why.
OK?
F is a normal vector field
relative to a circle.
Let's look at this again.
It's radial, and that's
why we know this.
F is a radial vector field.
It's really the vector field
(x,y) times a scalar,
depending on the radius.
So if I look at this
picture right here,
then F is going to--
let me draw it in color--
F is going to, at any
given point, be
in the radial direction.
But that is exactly normal
to the tangent
direction of this curve.
So this is the direction F
points, and this is the
direction the tangent vector
points to the curve.
But remember, F dot dr is the
same as F dotted with the
tangent vector ds.
OK?
And so that is why for this
circle, it's immediately
obvious that F dot
dr is equal to 0.
Because at any given point on
this circle, I'm taking a
vector field, I'm dotting it
with a vector field that's
orthogonal to it, so
I get 0, and when I
integrate 0 I get 0.
OK?
So that's why this is 0.
And now where the extended
version of Green's theorem
comes in, is the fact that, if
I look in this region, F is
defined and differentiable.
Right?
F is defined and differentiable
in this entire
region that I've just shaded.
Which is the region between
my circle and my curve C2.
And what that tells me is that
because this one is 0--
when I integrate along this
curve it's 0-- the integral
along this curve also
has to be 0, right?
That's what you actually have
seen already when you talked
about the extended version
of Green's theorem.
You can compare the integral
along this curve to the
integral along this curve
because in the region between
them, F is everywhere defined
and differentiable.
So you can apply Green's
theorem there.
It just now has two boundary
components, instead of in this
case where it just has one
boundary component.
And so since the integral on
this curve is 0, and the curl
of F is 0, and F is defined and
differentiable everywhere
in this region, that tells you
that the integral on the curve
C2 is also 0.
Let me say that one
more time, OK?
I'm going to label it in
blue so you can see it.
I'm going to call this region
that's shaded R. So Green's
theorem says that the double
integral in R of the curl of F
is equal to the integral
around this curve.
And then I come in and I go
around this direction and I
come back out, and that gives me
the entire integral of the
curl of F on this region.
Right?
The curl of F is 0 everywhere
in this region, so that
integral is 0.
And so the sum of the integral
on C3 minus the integral on C2
has to be 0.
Since this one is 0,
that one is 0.
So you've seen this before.
I just want to remind
you about where
that's coming from.
All right.
So now we have to do one other
thing, and that's we have to
find a potential function.
OK, so let's talk about how to
I'm going to do this by one of
the methods we saw in lecture.
I'm in R2, and I'm going to
start at a certain point and
I'm going to integrate
up to (x1,y1) from
this certain point.
And then I'm going to
figure out what the
function is that way.
So what I'm going
to do again--
I'll write it this way--
I'm going to figure out f of
(x1,y1) by integrating along a
certain curve, F dot dr.
Now I can't do exactly what I
did previously, because for
certain values of n, I run into
trouble with integrating
F from the origin.
So what I'm going to do is
instead of integrating from
the origin, I'm going
to integrate from
the point (1, 1).
OK?
So I'm going to start at the
point (1,1), and I'm going to
integrate in the y-direction,
and then I'm going to
integrate in the x-direction.
So this will be my first
curve and this will
be my second curve.
And I will land at (x1,y1).
So again, this is one of the
strategies we've seen
previously.
This is the idea that I'm going
to integrate in the
y-direction, from y equals
1 to y equals y1.
So this will be the point
(1,y1), so x is fixed there.
And I'm going to integrate in
the x-direction, from x equals
1 to x equals x1, when
y is equal to y1.
So let's break this down.
And let me remind you, also, the
integral along this curve
C of F dot dr should
be P dx plus Q dy.
Right?
And so I'm going to look at what
P dx is and what Q dy is
on C1 and on C2.
All right.
So let's do that.
OK, so I have to remind myself
what P and Q actually are in
order to do this.
So let me write that down,
because this will be
helpful: (P, Q).
P is r to the n, x, and
Q is r to the n, y.
All right?
So that's what we're
dealing with here.
I'm going to come back to this
picture, and then I'm going to
come back and forth a little
bit at this point.
So if I want to integrate P dx
plus Q dy on the curve C1,
what I need to observe
first is that x is
fixed, so dx is 0.
So I'm actually just going
to integrate Qdy.
All right.
So the first integral
along C1 is just a
parameterization in y.
So it's the integral from 0 to
y1 of Q evaluated at x equal
1, and y going from 1 to y1.
SPEAKER 1: 1 to y1.
CHRISTINE BREINER: y
going from 1 to y1.
OK?
Sorry.
Yes. y going from 1 to y1.
Sorry about that.
Right?
I was avoiding the origin, so
I'd better not put a 0 down
there, because that's where I
was running into problems. OK.
So Q is r to the n, y.
So I have to remember what r
is. r is x squared plus y
squared to the 1/2.
So in this case, Q is: x is 1,
and then I square it and I get
1, and then I have y squared,
and then to the n over 2--
so this is my r to the n part
along the curve C1--
and then I multiply by y,
and then I take dy.
So there are a lot of pieces
here, so let me just make sure
we understand what's
happening.
I am interested in this entire
thing, P dx plus Q dy along
the curve C1.
dx is 0 along that
curve. x is 1.
And y is going from 1 to y1.
So if I come back over
here, I see I'm only
interested in the Qdy part.
y is going from 1 to y1.
And then this is r to the n,
when x is 1 and y is y.
And this is the y part.
So this is exactly Qdy
on the curve C1.
Now let's look at what happens
on the curve C2.
So if I come back over here
again, I want to have P dx
plus Q dy on the curve C2.
Notice y is fixed at y1
there, so dy is 0.
And so I'm only interested
in the P dx part.
Everything is going to
be in terms of x.
And let's see if we can do
the same kind of thing.
I'm going to be integrating
from 1 to x1.
Now r is going to be of the
form x plus y1 squared,
to the n over 2.
And then--
P has an x here and not
a y-- times x dx.
So again, P is r to the n times
x, so this is r to the n
times x exactly on
the curve C2.
Because on C2, y is fixed at y1,
so that's why I actually
substituted in a y1 here.
It's the same reason I
substituted in a 1 here for x,
because x was fixed at
1 on the curve C1.
So now I have to integrate
these two things.
I'm going to just write down
what you get in both cases,
because it's really
single-variable calculus at
this point in both cases.
The easiest way to do this,
probably, in my mind, is to do
a u-substitution.
Oops, I made a mistake.
This should be an x squared.
I apologize.
This should be an x squared,
because this is supposed to be
a radius, right?
It's x squared plus whatever y
is squared, to the n over 2.
So if you didn't see the squared
here, and you got
nervous, you were correct.
There should be a
squared here.
So anyway, I'm going to go
back to what I was saying
previously.
To integrate these things, the
easiest thing to do is to take
what is inside the parentheses
and set it equal to u, and
then do a u-substitution
from there.
So again, I'm not going to
actually do that for you, but
I'm going to tell you
what you get.
Now, there are two different
situations.
And the situations follow when
n is any integer except
negative 2, and then when
n is negative 2.
And the reason is because when n
is negative 2, this exponent
is a minus 1.
So when you integrate, you end
up with a natural log.
So let me just point out the
two things that you get in
each case, and then we'll
evaluate and see what the
solutions are in each case.
So I'm just going to at this
point write down what I got,
because this is your
single-variable calculus.
OK, so what I got when n was not
equal to minus 2, you get
the following thing.
You get 1 plus y squared,
evaluated at n plus 2, over 2,
over n plus 2.
And this is evaluated
from 1 to y1.
And then this one you get a
similar thing there, but now
the y1 is fixed here.
So you get an x squared plus y1
squared, to the n plus 2,
over 2, over n plus 2, evaluated
from 1 to x1.
So here, the y1 is fixed and
it's the x-values that are
changing, and here the y-values
are changing.
So when n is not equal to 2, I
get exactly this quantity when
I integrate these two
terms. And so now,
let's see what happens.
OK?
Exactly what happens
is the following.
Notice that when I put in y1
here, I get a 1 plus y1
squared, to the n plus 2
over 2, over n plus 2.
Right?
I'm not going to write it down,
because I'm going to
show you it gets killed
off immediately.
Where does it get killed off?
It gets killed off when I
evaluate this one at 1.
OK?
So the upper bound here is the
same as the lower bound here.
When I put in a 1 here, I get
1 plus y1 squared to the n
plus 2 over 2 over n plus 2.
It's a lot of n's and 2's.
But the point is that when I
evaluate this one at y1 and I
evaluate this one at 1, I get
exactly the same thing, but
the signs are opposite and
so they subtract off.
In the final answer, I'm not
going to see this upper bound
and I'm not going to see this
lower bound, because they're
going to subtract off.
And what I'm actually left with
is just two terms. And
those two terms I'm going
to write up here.
Those two terms are going to be
x1 squared plus y1 squared
to the n plus 2, over
2, over n plus 2.
Minus, 1 plus 1--
which is just--
2 to the n plus 2, over
2, over n plus 2.
What it this really?
This is just r to the
n plus 2, over n
plus 2, plus a constant.
Because this is just a
constant for any n.
And notice n is not
equal to minus 2--
negative 2.
That was the place we
were going to run
into trouble otherwise.
And so when n is not equal to
negative 2-- when you do all
the integration--
you should arrive at this as
your potential function.
OK?
And again, what I did was I
evaluated to make it simpler
on ourselves so we didn't have
to write everything out.
I noticed that if I evaluate
this at the two bounds, and
evaluate this at the two
bounds, and I add them
together, that the evaluation
here plus the evaluation here
are the same numerically but
opposite in sign, and so they
subtract off.
And then I just have
to evaluate at this
one and this one.
So that's n not equal
to negative 2.
Now let's do the n equal
to negative 2 case.
OK, so now I'm integrating this
exact same thing in the n
equal to negative 2 case.
And I'll just write down
again what I get by the
substitution.
And what I get is natural log of
one plus y squared, over 2,
evaluated from 1 to y1.
Plus, natural log of x squared
plus y1 squared, over 2,
evaluated from 1 to x1.
Let me make sure I
have that right.
Yes.
And the same kind of thing is
going to happen that happened
before, in terms of when I put
y1 in here, and I put 1 in
here, I get the same thing but
with an opposite sign.
Here it's a positive.
It's natural log 1 plus
y1 squared over 2.
And here it's natural log 1 plus
y1 squared over 2, but
because it's the lower bound,
it's a negative sign.
So whatever I get here and what
I get here subtract off.
And then in the end, I wind up
getting just the following two
terms. I get x1 squared plus
y1 squared over 2, minus
natural log of 2 over 2.
So this term comes from
evaluating this at x1.
And this term comes from
evaluating this one at y
equaling 1.
And if you notice,
what is this?
This is exactly natural log
of r plus a constant.
So let me step to the other side
so we can see it clearly.
So this is natural log of r
squared, but by log rules,
that's really 2 times natural
log of r, so it divides by 2
and I'm just left with
natural log of r, and
this is just a constant.
And so my potential function
in that case is exactly
natural log of r plus
a constant.
All right, this was a long
problem, so I'm just going to
remind us where we came from
and what we were doing.
So let's go back to
the beginning.
So what we did initially, was we
had this vector field F. It
was a radial vector field. r
to the n times xi plus yj.
And we wanted to first show that
it was conservative for
any integer value of
n, and then to find
its potential function.
And obviously we do it in that
order, because if it's not
conservative, we're not going to
find a potential function.
In this case, what I observed
first was that the
curl of F was 0.
And so in places where I had
a closed curve that didn't
contain the origin, I knew that
the integral all around
that closed curve was 0 just
by Green's theorem.
But if I had a closed curve
that contained the origin,
because F is not differentiable
for all the n
values there, I have to
be a little careful.
It's actually even 0, right?
When x is 0 and y is
0, I'm going to
get something 0 there.
So I need to figure out
a way to determine the
line integral on C2.
Right?
And that was my goal.
For any C2 that contains the
origin, how do I figure out F
dot dr.
And so I just compared it to
what I get when I take F dot
dr around a circle.
Because I know that I can always
find a circle bigger,
and then I can say I've
got this region here--
in between-- on which F is
defined everywhere, so I can
apply Green's theorem to
that inside region.
And I know that the curl of F on
the inside region is 0, and
so the integral on C2 and C3
is going to agree, right?
Because the integral on
C3 I showed was 0 just
geometrically.
And then the integral on
C2 then has to be 0.
All right?
And so that was just when you
were using the extended
version of Green's theorem.
And then to find a potential
function, we came over here.
And we had to avoid the
origin because of the
differentiability problem
at the origin.
So we started--
instead of where we usually
start, which is from (0, 0)--
we started from the
point (1, 1).
And we just determined the
potential function going from
the point (1, 1) to the point
(x1, y1) along a curve that
went straight up so x was fixed,
and then along the
curve that went straight
over so y was fixed.
And so then we were able to
break up this thing where I'm
integrating over C--
P dx plus Q dy--
into two separate pieces, and
each of them was fairly simple
to write down.
So let's look at
what they were.
This first one was where
we were moving up.
And there was no dx. x
was just fixed at 1.
And y was going from 1 to y1.
Right?
And so x is fixed at 1,
so I put a 1 there.
And y is going from 1 to y1.
So I evaluate Q dy
on that curve.
And then the next one was P dx
on the curve where I'm moving
straight across.
Right? dy is 0 there, so I
just pick up the P dx.
And my y value was fixed
at y1, and x was
varying from 1 to x1.
And so then I just had to
be a little bit careful.
I didn't show you exactly how
you integrate, but using a
substitution trick--
single-variable calculus--
shouldn't be too bad for
you at this point.
We distinguished between when n
was not equal to negative 2
and when n was equal
to negative 2.
In the case n not equal to
negative 2, we determined the
integral, we simplified, and
we got to a place where the
potential function was exactly
equal to r to the n plus 2
over n plus 2, plus
some constant.
Then in the case where n was
equal to negative 2, when you
do the substitution, you get
a different integral.
And in that case, you get
into natural log.
And so again, we just
had the natural log.
We have these different
functions.
We're evaluating the
natural log of
these different functions.
We have the bounds.
We simplify everything, and we
get exactly to the place where
you have natural log of
r plus a constant.
And so we found our potential
function in the case n is
equal to negative 2, and
then any other n value.
So, a very long problem.
I hope you got something
out of it.
And this is where I will stop.