33, 13.
We have monochromatic
light, 75 watts.
We have a wavelength which I
believe has nothing to do with
the problem.
500 nanometers.
And it radiates uniformly
in all directions.
And the question now is, what is
the associated e 0 and b 0,
the amplitudes of the e vector
and the b vector, if I am at a
distance r from the
source, light
source, of about 3 meters?
Now, in what follows, I'm going
to pretend that I can
represent this radiating source,
which radiates--
I hate to use that word, but
it radiates photons in all
directions.
I pretend that it can be
represented by a plain
electromagnetic wave, described
in the way we just
did, with a uniquely defined
e vector and b vector.
Except that now it doesn't go in
one direction, but it goes
out spherically.
And when I do that, I have here
this source, which has a
certain energy per second.
75 watts.
I call that luminosity, because
I'm an astronomer, and
astronomers call that
luminosity.
And let me put around this
source, at radius r, a sphere.
And let me put here
a little surface
element on the spehere.
Then there will be an energy
flux flowing through this
little surface element, which
is perpendicular to this
direction of r.
This elements a, little elements
da, whatever you want
to call it, is perpendicular
to this flux.
It's in the same direction that
the radiation is going.
So l is luminosity, which is
always in joules per second.
That means in watts.
f is energy flux, which
is joules per
second per square meter.
And so therefore, if there is
no absorption between the
source and this sphere--
this sphere could be huge.
It could be 10 meters, it
could be 10 light years.
But all the energy must come out
of that sphere, if there's
no absorption between the source
of electromagnetic
radiation and the sphere
with radius r.
So it follows immediately, if
there's no absorption, that 4
pi r squared times f equals l.
But f, as you will see, is
exactly what we have called in
the past the mean
pointing factor.
I say mean, because if we take
plane wave solutions to
Maxwell's equations, then of
course we have cosine terms,
and if we have cosine
terms, we have to
take the mean values.
And so the mean value of the
pointing vector, which equals
the mean value of e cross b
divided by miu 0, then also
equals l divided by 4 pi
r squared, and you see
immediately, which is no
surprise, of course, that the
pointing vector falls off
as 1 over 4 squared.
The further you are way, the
smaller the flux, and it goes
as 1 over 4 squared.
The luminosity, the amount of
energy that comes out here, of
course, is independent of r.
So let us pursue this
a little bit.
Notice, by the way, that the
pointing vector is completely
independent of the wavelength
lambda.
So if now you are being asked,
what is the e 0 and what is
the b 0, you effectively have
to use this equation.
We know that the pointing
vector, the mean pointing
vector s, is the mean value
of this quantity.
Well, the mean value of that
quantity equals 1/2 e 0
squared divided by
miu 0 times c.
Remember, the 1/2 comes from the
fact that you're going to
get a cosine squared
term in here.
Because this has a cosine
dependence of time, and this
has a cosine dependence
of time.
They're perpendicular to
the each other, so I
can forget the cross.
But b 0 is also e 0 divided
by c, so that's why
I get this c here.
And that now equals l divided
by 4 pi r squared.
And you see, you
know everything
that has to be known.
You know l, you know
r, miu zero, and c.
So out pops 0, and if you have
to e 0, out pops b 0.
And so the e 0 and the b 0
only depend on l and r.
They only depend on the
pointing vector.
And they are independent
of the wavelength.
And since the pointing vector
falls off as 1 over r squared,
you see that e 0 falls of as
1/r, and b 0 also falls
off as 1 over r.
Let us take the sun.
The sun is a very
powerful source.
It has a luminosity of
4 times 10 to [? 2 ?]
[? 6 ?] watts.
And the distance, d, from the
sun to the earth is 150
kilometers.
Being an astrophysicist, I just
happen to remember that.
When you apply the above, you
will find that e 0 is about
1000 volts per meter at the
distance of the earth, and
that b 0 seems significantly
small, 3.4 times 10 to the
minus 6 tesla.
The reason being that you have
to divide this by c.
And the mean value of the
pointing vector, which is the
luminosity of the sun, divided
by 4 pi r squared, is the same
as number 1.4 times 10 to the
3 watts per square meter.
And this number I will come
back to is very important.
It's a little bit more than 1
kilowatt per square meter.
And what does that mean?
It means that the amount of
energy from the sun that
reaches the earth for every
square meter in the direction
perpendicular to the radiation
is a little more than 1
kilowatt per square meter.
1000 joules per second.
If you ever want to harvest
solar energy, this is the
maximum you can ever get.
And I will get back to that,
and you'll see the
consequences of that.
The consequences of that are,
as I will show you, that to
harvest solar energy is by no
means a trivial matter.