PROFESSOR: So far, so good.
And we're now going on
to problem 33-39.
I return to the sun.
This is my symbol for the sun,
which has a luminosity of 4
times 10 to the twenty
sixth watts.
The radius of the sun itself
is about 7 times 10 to the
eighth meters, which is about
100 times larger than the
radius of the earth.
This is my symbol
for the earth.
And if you calculate the mean
Poynting vector at the surface
of the sun itself, you'll have
to take L divided by 4 pi R of
the sun squared and that gives
you a number 6.5 times 10 to
the seventh watts every square
meter coming out of the
surface of the sun.
6.5 times 10 to the seventh
joules per second.
Now if I were to hold a surface
there at the surface
of the sun, no pun implied, and
I were to absorb all the
radiation from the sun, full
absorption, no reflection,
then the radiation pressure--
I'll put the radiation here
--would be S divided by C. But
of course you might as well take
this quantity divided by
C, whatever you prefer,
it's the same.
And that is about 0.22 newtons
per square meter, a very,
very, very, small pressure.
And if you take the radius, 1/2
the radius of the sun, so
you go inside the sun, then of
course the Poynting vector
will be 4 times higher because
if R is twice as small than
this one, it will be up by
a factor of 4 and so the
radiation pressure will be up by
a factor of 4, and so this
number will be up by
a factor of 4.
But in both cases, the
radiation pressure is
insignificant compared to the
gas pressure, as is given by
Professor [? Burschinger ?]
in this particular problem.
Now this is not necessarily true
for all stellar objects.
It is true that radiation
pressure in the sun plays a
very minor role in terms of the
size so to speak of the
sun, in terms of
how big it is.
However there are stars which
have a luminosity which is a
million times larger than
that of the sun.
And now the radiation pressure
begins to play an enormously
important role.
In fact there are stars which,
as I said, are a million times
more luminous, whereby at the
top of the star, near the
atmosphere of the star, the
gravitational attraction
balances just the radiation
pressure and so the atmosphere
of the star is literally
floating on top of the
radiation pressure.
A nice balance between, on the
one hand, gravitational pull
inwards and radiation
pressure outwards.
So this is not important
for our sun.
It is important for many
very luminous stars.