Let's now talk about
radiation pressure.
This is an extremely
interesting subject in physics.
There are several ways
that you can
derive radiation pressure.
It can be derived purely from
the concept of electromagnetic
plane wave solutions to
Maxwell's Equations.
It's a long road, but
it can be derived.
I've seen Professor
[? Yewits ?]
when she lectured to 803 do
it in a beautiful way.
I would like to shortcut my
way to success and do it a
little faster, but perhaps not
so transparent for you.
Perhaps you remember one of
the famous relations from
Einstein, in that if I have
individual photons--
if I have an individual
photon--
and an individual photon is a
very different thing from this
continuous stream of
electromagnetic radiation,
which has no beginning in
time, no end in time, no
beginning in space, and
no end in space.
That is our mathematical
representation of plane wave
solutions to Maxwell's
Equations--
a photon is a very
different thing.
It's only generated during a
very certain amount of time--
it's more like a wave package,
and it propagates with the
speed of light.
It's a very different thing.
In physics, we deal with both,
and if you deal with both in
the correct way, you always
get consistent answers.
In a way, you have a choice:
I now choose the photon
representation.
I write down for the photon
energy E of n--
E n--
because I don't want to write
a E, because that might
confuse you with energy.
That, according to Einstein,
is the momentum that the
photon carries times
the speed of light.
Assume now that we have here a
source of photons going off in
many directions.
We're dealing with many photons,
but the luminosity L,
which is in joules per seconds,
is a given value--
it's a light bulb, and it could
be a 100 watt light
bulb, or it could be the Sun--
and at a distance R, which is
a sphere, there is here a
little element d A. When these
individual photons hit this
little element d A, they are,
in what follows, fully
absorbed by that element d A.
That means the momentum is
destroyed, and that means if
the momentum is destroyed, the
whole photon is destroyed.
This little element d A must
feel a pressure, and it must
feel a force.
It's like throwing rotten
tomatoes at someone's face--
every time you feel a rotten
tomato, the momentum is
completely taken out, because it
goes whoosh and it slushes
to the ground.
There's no momentum left--
it doesn't bounce off--
and every time you feel a rotten
tomato on your face,
you feel a little push
backwards, you feel pressure,
and you feel a force.
In that same way, this little
element here, d A, will feel a
pressure, and it will
feel a force.
The energy per second, which
is absorbed by d A, is very
simply d A times L divided
by 4 pi R squared.
That's immediately obvious,
because d A invited by 4 pi R
squared is the fraction of all
the radiation that goes out in
this direction, and L is the
number of joules per second,
so this is the energy that
flows out of here.
That, of course, energy per unit
time is the derivative of
this quantity, so you can also
write down that it is d E n
dt, but that, according to
Einstein's equation, equals dp
dt times c.
These are now not individual
photons anymore, because L
represents many, many photons,
so this is the
results of many photons.
These many photons
on this surface
element d A cause a force.
You see right here that dp dt
represents a force, and if you
go back to 801, you'll remember
that dp dt is a force.
If I take that force and I
divide that by the area d A,
then I get the pressure.
So you see here for the first
time that the radiation
pressure is simply this quantity
divided by d A, and I
have to bring the c here,
because it is 1 over
d A times dp dt--
the radiation pressure equals
L divided by 4 pi R squared
divided by c.
This is the radiation pressure
only in case the radiation is
fully absorbed.
This quantity here we earlier
called the pointing vector, so
the radiation pressure is also
the pointing vector divided by
c, but now I have to take the
mean pointing vector, because
we have to take into account
the oscillation of the
electromagnetic radiation.
You should convince yourself
that both this and this are in
units of newtons per
square meter.
Whichever one of the two you
want to apply, it's fine--
either one will do.
The radiation pressure, when we
have full absorption, full
absorption is given
by this quantity.
If this radiation pressure
x on a surface
which has area A--
and if I called that radiation
pressure T--
then the radiation force, the
force due to radiation
pressure, would be the radiation
pressure times the
area A. If, however, the
radiation is not fully
absorbed, but is reflected
400%, which can happen.
You can have a mirror, and you
can reflect almost 100% light.
You can have metal surfaces
which can reflect radar, and
also radio emission for 100%
then you gain a factor of 2.
If you were dealing with
100% reflection--
I hope you can read colors--
then you would get a factor of
2 here, you would get factor
of 2 here, and you would
get a factor of 2 here.
This is now no longer throwing
rotten tomatoes at your face
that go boom, boom, boom, but
this is now throwing tennis
balls at your face, which bounce
back exactly with the
same speed at which
they came in.
There is a reversal of the
velocity, and so the momentum
transfer is twice, that's
exactly what you have here
also with radiation
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].