This brings us to problem
number five, and problem
number five is 33-50.
Now we're going to do some
science fiction--
we're going to do
solar sailling.
We use an 100% reflecting
sail--
100%, because we want twice
the momentum that we would
have with full absorption.
Here is the Sun: this is the
luminosity of the Sun, this is
the mass of the Sun, and at
a distance R, here is our
wonderful science fiction
sailboat with area A, and here
is the boat.
Let the mass of the boat plus
the sail be m, and we want a
net force in this direction
which is larger then 0.
In other words, we want the
radiation pressure to be
larger than the gravitational
pull.
What do we want?
The radiation pressure, which is
the luminosity of the Sun,
times the area of this--
I want the radiation
force, by the way.
I'm going from pressure
immediately to force, so I'm
going to multiply the pressure
by this area A. Then I have
this factor 2, because we
have 100% reflection--
it's not fully absorbed, but
it's 100% reflected--
divided by 4 pi R squared c.
You should recognize this now,
because this has become a
force because of A, and the
2 is because of the 100%
reflection.
We want this radiation force
larger than the gravitational
attraction, which is m mass
of the Sun times G
divided by R squared.
What you find out, which may not
be so intuitive, is that
this is independent of R--
the reason being is that the
pointing vector falls off as 1
over R squared, but the
gravitational attraction also
falls off was 1 over
R squared.
If there's no absorption of the
radiation between you and
the sailboat, so to speak, it
remains to be seen whether
that is through.
If those distances become very,
very large, you may well
lose some of that radiation due
to dust particles, very
fine particles that are between
the Sun and you.
If we ignore any possible
assumption, then it doesn't
matter where you are, if you
have a net force outward due
to radiation force, you will
always have that net force
outwards because it's
independent of the distance R
to the Sun.
I know what m is, I know what
L is, and so I can now
calculate what A is,
and I want you to
calculate what A is.
A is huge; I found A to be about
3 times 10 to the sixth
square meters, which is
something like 1.7 by 1.7
square kilometers.
Indeed, you see that it is an
unbelievably, completely
impractical area that you would
need in order to get a
free ride, so to speak, or
an acceleration which is
non-zero, because once you have
a force, you always have
an acceleration.
I want to expand on this a
little bit by showing you
something cute.
If you look at the very fine
grains in our solar system,
you can show that if they're
small enough, that they're all
blown out of our solar system
because of radiation pressure.
Let these fine grains have
radius r, and let them have a
density rho, for which you may
take 2 1/2 grams per cubic
centimeter--
that is sort of like
what sand has.
I just made this number a little
bit arbitrary, but it's
not a ridiculous number.
The mass of the grain would be
4/3 pi r cubed times rho, and
the cross-sectional area of a
grain would be pi r squared.
If I use this equation, and I
want these grains to be blown
out of our solar system,
then I have to
replace A by pi r squared.
I would have full absorption,
and I would have no
reflection, so I don't have this
factor of 2, and I would
have to substitute for
this little m 4/3 pi
r cubed times rho.
I would get that the luminosity
of the Sun times
the cross-sectional area of the
grains divided by 4 pi r
squared c, must be larger than
4/3 pi r cubed times rho times
the mass of the Sun times
G divided by r squared.
That would be the condition for
these grains, if this were
the only thing that mattered
in the solar system to be
blown out of the solar system.
I lose a pi here, I lose r
squared here, I lose r squared
here again with this r, and if
you work this out, you know
all these numbers.
You will see that with r smaller
than a certain number,
these grains will not
be able to survive
in our solar system.
That is quite remarkable.