I'm gonna begin with two by
two.
All matrices are symmetric,
right?
That's understood;
the matrix is symmetric,
now my question is,
is it positive definite?
Now, here are some -- each one
of these is a complete test for
positive definiteness.
If I know the eigenvalues,
my test is are they positive?
Are they all positive?
If I know these -- so,
A is really -- I look at that
number A, here,
as the, as the one by one
determinant, and here's the two
by two determinant.
So this is the determinant
test.
This is the eigenvalue test,
this is the determinant test.
Are the determinants growing in
s- of all, of all end,
sort of, can I call them
leading submatrices,
they're the first ones the
northwest,
Seattle submatrices coming down
from from there,
they all, all those
determinants have to be
positive, and then another test
is the pivots.
The pivots of a two by two
matrix are the number A for
sure, and, since the product is
the determinant,
the second pivot must be the
determinant divided by A.
And then in here is gonna come
my favorite and my new idea,
the, the, the the one to catch,
about x transpose Ax being
positive.
But we'll have to look at this
guy.
This gets, like a star,
because for most,
presentations,
the definition of positive
definiteness would be this
number four and these numbers
one two three would be test
four.
OK.
Maybe I'll tuck this,
where, you know,
OK.
So I'll have to look at this x
transpose Ax.
Can you, can we just be sure,
how do we know that the
eigenvalue
test and the determinant test,
pick out the same matrices,
and let me, let's just do a few
examples.
Some examples.
Let me pick the matrix two,
six, six, tell me,
what number do I have to put
there for the matrix to be
positive definite?
Tell me a sufficiently large
number that would make it
positive definite?
Let's just practice with these
conditions in the two by two
case.
Now, when I ask you that,
you don't wanna find the
eigenvalues, you would use the
determinant test for that,
so,
the first or the pivot test,
that, that guy is certainly
positive, that had to happen,
and it's OK.
How large a number here -- the
number had better be more than
what?
More than eighteen,
right, because if it's eight --
no.
More than what?
Nineteen, is it?
If I have a nineteen here,
is that positive definite?
I get thirty eight minus thirty
six, that's OK.
If I had an eighteen,
let me play it really close.
If I have an eighteen there,
then I positive definite?
Not quite.
I would call this guy positive,
so it's useful just to see that
this the borderline.
That matrix is on the
borderline, I would call that
matrix positive semi-definite.
And what are the eigenvalues of
that matrix, just since we're
given eigenvalues of two by
twos, when it's semi-definite,
but not definite,
then the -- I'm squeezing this
eigenvalue test down,
-- what's the eigenvalue that I
know this matrix has?
What kind of a matrix have I
got here?
It's a singular matrix,
one of its eigenvalues is zero.
That has an eigenvalue zero,
and the other eigenvalue is --
from the trace,
twenty.
OK.
So that, that matrix has
eigenvalues greater than or
equal to zero,
and it's that "equal to" that
brought this word
"semi-definite" in.
And, the what are the pivots of
that matrix?
So the pivots,
so the eigenvalues are zero and
twenty, the pivots are,
well, the pivot is two,
and what's the next pivot?
There isn't one.
We got a singular matrix here,
it'll only have one pivot.
You see that that's a rank one
matrix, two six is a -- six
eighteen is a multiple of two
six, the matrix is singular it
only has one pivot,
so the pivot test doesn't quite
pass.
The -- let me do the x
transpose Ax.
Now this is -- the novelty now.
OK.
What I looking at when I
look at this new combination,
x transpose Ax.
x is any vector now,
so lemme compute,
so any vector,
lemme call its components x1
and x2, so that's x.
And I put in here A.
Let's, let's use this example
two six, six eighteen,
and here's x transposed,
so x1 x2.
We're back to real matrices,
after that last lecture that-
that said what to do in the
complex case,
let's come back to real
matrices.
So here's x transpose Ax,
and what I'm interested in is,
what do I get if I multiply
those together?
I get some function of x1 and
x2, and what is it?
Let's see, if I do this
multiplication,
so I do it, lemme,
just, I'll just do it slowly,
x1, x2, if I multiply that
matrix, this is 2x1,
and 6x2s, and the next row is
6x1s and 18x2s,
and now I do this final step
and what do I have?
I've got 2x1 squareds,
got 2X1 squareds is coming from
this two, I've got this one
gives me eighteen,
well, shall I do the ones in
the middle?
How many x1 x2s do I have?
Let's see,
x1 times that 6x2 would be six
of 'em, and then x2 times this
one will be six more,
I get twelve.
So, in here is going,
this is the number a,
this is the number 2b,
and in here is -- x2 times
eighteen x2 will be eighteen x2
squareds and this
is the number c.
So it's ax1 -- it's like ax
squared.
2bxy and cy squared.
For my first point that I
wanted to make by just doing out
a multiplication is,
that is as soon as you give me
the matrix, as soon as you give
me the matrix,
I can --
those are the numbers that
appear in -- I'll call this
thing a quadratic,
you see, it's not linear
anymore.
Ax is linear,
but now I've got an x transpose
coming in, I'm up to degree two,
up to degree two,
maybe quadratic is the -- use
the word.
A quadratic form.
It's purely degree two,
there's no linear part,
there's no constant part,
there certainly no cubes or
fourth powers,
it's all second degree.
And my question is -- is that
quantity positive or not?
That's -- for every x1 and x2,
that is my new definition --
that's my definition of a
positive definite matrix.
If this quantity is positive,
if, if, if, it's positive for
all x's and y's,
all x1 x2s, then I call them --
then that's the matrix is
positive definite.
Now, is this guy passing our
test?
Well we have,
we anticipated the answer here
by, by asking first about
eigenvalues and pivots,
and what happened?
It failed.
It barely failed.
If I had made this eighteen
down to a seven,
it would've totally failed.
I do that with the eraser,
and then I'll put back
eighteen, because,
seven is such a total disaster,
but if -- I'll keep seven for a
second.
Is that thing in any way
positive definite?
No, absolutely not.
I don't know its eigenvalues,
but I know for sure one of them
is negative.
Its pivots are two and then the
next pivot would be the
determinant over two,
and the determinant is -- what,
what's the determinant of this
thing?
Fourteen minus thirty six,
I've got a determinant minus
twenty two.
The next pivot will be -- the
pivots
now, of this thing are two and
minus eleven or something.
Their product being minus
twenty two the determinant.
This thing is not positive
definite.
What would be -- let me look at
the x transpose Ax for this guy.
What's -- if I do out this
multiplication,
this eighteen is temporarily
changing to a seven.
This eighteen is temporarily
changing to a seven,
and I know that there's some
numbers x1 and x2 for which that
thing, that function,
is negative.
And I'm desperately trying to
think what they are.
Maybe you can see.
Can you tell me a value of x1
and x2 that makes this quantity
negative?
Oh, maybe one and minus one?
Yes, that's -- in this case,
that, will work,
right, if I took x1 to be one,
and x2 to be minus one,
then I always get something
positive, the two,
and the seven minus one
squared, but this would be
minus twelve and the whole thing
would be negative;
I would have two minus twelve
plus seven, a negative.
If I drew the graph,
can I get the little picture in
here?
If I draw the graph of this
thing?
So, graphs, of the function
f(x,y),
or f(x), so I say here f(x,y)
equal this -- x transpose Ax,
this, this this ax squared,
2bxy, and cy squared.
And, let's take the example,
with these numbers.
OK, so here's the x axis,
here's the y axis,
and here's -- up is the
function.
z, if you like,
or f.
I apologize,
and let me, just once in my
life here, put an arrow over
these, these,
axes so you see them.
That's the vector and I just,
see, instead of x1 and x2,
I made them x- the components x
and y.
OK.
So, so, what's a graph of 2x
squared,
twelve xy, and seven y squared?
I'd like to see -- I not the
greatest artist,
but let's -- tell me something
about this graph of this
function.
Whoa, tell me one point that it
goes through.
The origin.
Right?
Even this artist can get this
thing
to go through the origin,
when these are zero,
I, I certainly get zero.
OK.
Some more points.
If x is one and y is zero,
then I'm going upwards,
so I'm going up this way,
and I'm, I'm going up,
like, two x squared in that
direction.
So -- that's meant to be a
parabola.
And, suppose x stays zero and y
increases.
Well, y could be positive or
negative; it's seven y squared.
Is this function going upward?
In the x direction it's going
upward, and in the y direction
it's going upwards,
and if x equals y then the
forty-five degree direction is
certainly going upwards;
because then we'd have what,
about, everything would be
positive, but what?
This function -- what's the
graph of this function?
Look like?
Tell me the word that
describes the graph of this
function.
This is the non-positive
definite here,
everybody's with me here,
for some reason got started in
a negative direction,
your case that isn't positive
definite.
And what's the graph look like
that goes up,
but does it -- do we have a
minimum here,
does it go from,
from the origin?
Completely?
No, because we just checked
that this thing failed.
It failed along the direction
when x was minus y -- we have a
saddle point,
let me put myself,
let me, to the least,
tell you the word.
This thing, goes up in some
directions, but down in other
directions, and if we actually
knew what a saddle looked like
or thinks saddles do that -- the
way your legs go is,
like, down, up,
the way,
you, looking like,
forward, and,
the, and drawing the thing is
even worse than describing --
I'm just going to say in some
directions we go up and in other
directions, there is,
a saddle -- Now I'm sorry I put
that on the front board,
you have no way to cover it,
but it's a saddle.
OK.
And, and this is a saddle
point, it's the,
it's the point that's at the
maximum in some directions and
at the minimum in other
directions.
And actually,
the perfect directions to look
are the eigenvector directions.
We'll see that.
So this is,
not a positive definite matrix.
OK.
Now I'm coming back to this
example, getting rid of this
seven, let's move it up to
twenty.
Let's, let's let's make the
thing really positive definite.
OK.
So this is, this number's now
twenty.
c is now twenty.
OK.
Now that passes the test,
which I haven't proved,
of course, it passes the test
for positive pivots.
It passes the test for positive
eigenvalues.
How can you tell that the
eigenvalues of that matrix are
positive without actually
finding them?
Of course,
two by two I could find them,
but can you see -- how do I
know they're positive?
I know that their product is --
I know that lambda one times
lambda two is positive,
why?
Because that's the determinant,
right, lambda one times lambda
two is the determinant,
which is forty minus thirty-six
is
four.
So the determinant is four.
And the trace,
the sum down the diagonal,
is twenty-two.
So, they multiply to give four.
So that leaves the possibility
they're either both positive or
both negative.
But if they're both negative,
the trace couldn't be
twenty-two.
So they're both positive.
So both of the eigenvalues that
are positive,
both of the pivots are positive
-- the determinants are
positive, and I believe that
this function is positive
everywhere except at zero,
zero, of course.
When I write down this
condition,
So I believe that x transposed,
let me copy,
x transpose Ax is positive,
except, of course,
at the minimum point,
at zero, of course,
I don't expect miracles.
So what does its graph look
like, and how do I check,
and how do I check that this
really is positive?
So we take it's graph for a
minute.
What would be the graph of that
function -- it does not have a
saddle point.
Let me -- I'll raise the board,
here, and stay with this
example for a while.
So I want to do the graph of --
here's my function,
two x squared,
twelve xy-s,
that could be positive or
negative, and twenty y squared.
But my point is,
so you're seeing the underlying
point is, that,
the things are positive
definite when in some way,
these, these pure squares,
squares we know to be positive,
and when those kind of
overwhelm this guy,
who could be m- positive or
negative,
because some like or have same
or have same or different signs,
when these are big enough they
overwhelm this guy and make the
total thing positive,
and what would the graph now
look like?
Let me draw the x - well,
let me draw the x direction,
the y direction,
and the origin,
at zero, zero,
I'm there, where do I go as I
move away from the origin?
Where do I go as I move away
from the origin?
I'm sure that I go up.
The origin, the center point
here, is a minim because this
thing I believe,
and we better see why,
it's, the graph is like a bowl,
the
graph is like a bowl shape,
it's -- here's the minimum.
And because we've got a pure
quadratic, we know it sits at
the origin, we know it's tangent
plane, the first derivatives are
zero, so, we know,
first derivatives,
First derivatives are all zero,
but that's not enough for a
minimum.
It's first derivatives were
zero here.
So, the partial derivatives,
the first derivatives,
are zero.
Again, because first
derivatives are gonna have an x
or an a y, or a y in them,
they'll be zero at the origin.
It's the second derivatives
that
control everything.
It's the second derivatives
that this matrix is telling us,
and somehow -- here's my point.
You remember in Calculus,
how did you decide on a
minimum?
First requirement was,
that the derivative had to be
zero.
But then you didn't know if you
had
a minimum or a maximum.
To know that you had a minimum,
you had to look at the second
derivative.
The second derivative had to be
positive, the slope had to be
increasing as you went through
the minimum point.
The curvature had to go
upwards, and that's what we're
doing now in
two dimensions,
and in n dimensions.
So we're doing what we did in
Calculus.
Second derivative positive,
m- will now become that the
matrix of second derivatives is
positive definite.
Can I just -- like a
translation of -- this is how
minimum are coming in,
ithe beginning of Calculus --
we had a minimum was associated
with second derivative,
being positive.
And first derivative zero,
of course.
Derivative, first derivative,
but it was the second
derivative that told us we had a
minimum.
And now, in 18.06,
in linear algebra,
we'll have a minim for our
function now,
our function will have,
for your function be a function
not of just x but several
variables, the way functions
really are in real life,
the minimum will be when the
matrix of second derivatives,
the matrix here was one by one,
there was just one second
derivative, now we've got lots.
Is positive definite.
So positive for a number
translates into positive
definite for a matrix.
And it this brings everything
you check pivots,
you check determinants,
you check all your values,
or you check this minimum
stuff.
OK.
Let me come back to this graph.
That graph goes upwards.
And I'll have to see why.
How do I know that this,
that this function is always
positive?
Can you look at that and tell
that it's always positive?
Maybe two by two,
you could feel pretty sure,
but what's the good way to show
that this thing is always
positive?
If we can express it,
as, in terms of squares,
because that's what we know for
any x and y, whatever,
if we're squaring something we
certainly are not negative.
So I believe that this
expression, this function,
could be written as a sum of
squares.
Can you tell me -- see,
because all the problems,
the headaches are coming from
this xy term.
If we can get expressions -- if
we can get that inside a square,
so actually,
what we're doing is something
called, that you've seen called
completing the square.
Let me start the
square and you complete it.
OK, I think we have two of x
plus, now I don't remember how
many y-s we need,
but you'll figure it out,
squared.
How many y-s should I put in
here, to make -- what do I want
to do, the two x squared-s will
be correct, right?
What I want to do is put in the
right number of y-s to get
the twelve xy correct.
And what is that number of y-s?
Let's see, I've got two times,
and so I really want six xy-s
to come out of here,
I think maybe if I put three
there, does that look right to
you?
I have two- this is,
we can mentally,
multiply out,
that's X squared,
that's right,
that's six X Y,
times the two gives from,
right, and how many Y squareds
have I now got?
How many Y squareds have I now
got from this term?
Eighteen.
Eighteen was the key number,
remember?
Now if I want to make it
twenty,
then I've got two left.
Two y squared-s.
That's completing the square,
and it's, now I can see that
that function is positive,
because it's all squares.
I've got two squares,
added together,
I couldn't go negative.
What if I went back to that
seven?
If instead of twenty that
number was a seven,
then what would happen?
This would still be correct,
I'd still have this square,
to get the two x squared and
the twelve xy,
and I'd have eighteen y squared
and then what would I do here?
I'd have to remove eleven y
squared-s, right,
if I only had a seven here,
then instead of -- when I had a
twenty
I had two more to put in,
when I had an eighteen,
which was the marginal case,
I had no more to put in.
When I had a seven,
which was the case below zero,
the indefinite case,
I had minus eleven.
OK.
Now, so, you can see now,
that this thing is a bowl.
It's going upwards,
if I cut it at a plane,
z equal to one,
say, I would get,
I would get a curve,
what would be the equation for
that curve?
If I cut it at height one,
the equation would be this
thing equal to one.
And that curve would be an
ellipse.
So actually,
already, I've blocked into the
lecture, the different pieces
that we're aiming for.
We're aiming for the tests,
which this passed;
we're aiming for the connection
to a minimum,
which this -- which we see in
the graph,
and if we chop it up,
if we set this thing equal to
one, if I set that thing equal
to one, that -- what that gives
me is, the cross-section.
It gives me this,
this curve, and its equation is
this thing equals one,
and that's an ellipse.
Whereas if I cut through a
saddle
point, I get a hyperbola.
OK.
But this minimum stuff is
really what I'm most interested
in.
OK.
By -- I just have to ask,
do you recognize,
I mean, these numbers here,
the two that appeared outside,
the three that appeared inside,
the two that appeared there --
actually, those numbers come
from elimination.
Completing the square is our
good old method of Gaussian
elimination, in expressed in
terms of these squares.
The -- let me show you what I
mean.
I just think those numbers are
no accident,
If I take my matrix two,
six, six, and twenty,
and I do elimination,
then the pivot is two and I
take three, what's the
multiplier?
How much of row one do I take
away from row two?
Three.
So what you're seeing in this,
completing the square,
is the pivots outside and the
multiplier inside.
Just do that again?
The pivot is two,
three -- three of those away
from that gives me two,
six, zero, and what's the
second pivot?
Three of this away from this,
three sixes'll be eighteen,
and the second pivot will also
be a
two.
So that's the U,
this is the A,
and of course the L was one,
zero, one, and the multiplier
was three.
So, completing the square is
elimination.
Why I happy to see,
happy to see that coming
together?
Because I know about
elimination
for m by m matrices.
I just started talking about
completing the square,
here, for two by twos.
But now I see what's going on.
Completing the square really
amounts to splitting this thing
into a sum of squares,
so what's the critical thing --
I have a lot of squares,
and inside those squares are
multipliers but they're squares,
and the question is,
what's outside these squares?
When I complete the square,
what are the numbers that go
outside?
They're the pivots.
They're the pivots,
and that's why positive pivots
give me sum of squares.
Positive pivots,
those pivots are the numbers
that go outside the squares,
so positive pivots,
sum of squares,
everything positive,
graph goes up,
a minimum at the origin,
it's all connected together;
all connected together.
And in the two by two case,
you can see those connections,
but linear algebra now can go
up to
three by three,
m by m.
Let's do that next.
Can I just, before I leave two
by two, I've written this
expression "matrix of second
derivatives." What's the matrix
of second derivatives?
That's one second derivative
now, but if I'm in two
dimensions,
I have a two by two matrix,
it's the second x derivative,
the second x derivative goes
there -- shall I write it --
fxx, if you like,
fxx, that means the second
derivative of f in the x
direction.
fyy, second derivative in the y
Those are the pure derivatives,
second derivatives.
They have to be positive.
For a minimum.
This number has to be positive
for a minimum.
That number has to be positive
But, that's not enough.
Those numbers have to somehow
be big enough to overcome this
cross-derivative,
Why is the matrix symmetric?
Because the second derivative f
with respect to x and y is equal
to -- I can, that's the
beautiful fact about second
derivatives, is I can do those
in either order and I get the
same thing.
So this is the same as that,
and so, that's the matrix of
second derivatives.
And the test is,
it has to be positive definite.
You might remember,
from, tucked in somewhere near
the end of eighteen o' two or at
least in the book,
was the condition for a
minimum, For a function of two
variables.
Let's -- when do you have a
minimum?
For a function of two
variables, believe me,
that's what Calculus is for.
The condition is first
derivatives have to be zero.
And the matrix of second
derivatives has to be positive
definite.
So you maybe remember there was
an fxx times an fyy
that had to be bigger than an
an fxy squared,
that's just our determinant,
two by two.
But now, we now know the answer
for three by three,
m by m, because we can do
elimination by m by m matrices,
we can connect eigenvalues of m
by m matrices,
we can do sum of squares,
sum of m squares instead of
only two squares;
and so let's take a,
let me go over here to do a
three by three example.
So, three by three example.
OK.
Oh, let me -- shall I use my
favorite matrix?
You've seen this matrix before.
Yes, let's use the good matrix,
four by one,
oops, open.
Is that matrix positive
definite?
What's -- so I'm going to ask
questions about this matrix,
is it positive definite,
first of all?
What's the function associated
with that matrix,
what's the x transpose Ax?
Is -- do we have a minimum for
that function,
at zero?
And then even what's the
geometry?
OK.
First of all,
is the matrix positive
definite, now I've given you the
numbers there so you can take
the determinants,
maybe that's the quickest,
is that what you would do
mentally,
if I give you all a matrix on a
quiz and say is it positive
definite or not?
I would take that determinant
and I'd give the answer two.
and I would give the answer for
that two by two determinant,
I'd give the answer three,
and anybody remember the answer
for
the three by three determinant?
It was four,
you remember for these special
matrices, when we do
determinants,
they went up two,
three, four,
five, six, they just went up
linearly.
So that matrix has -- the
determinants are two,
three, and four.
Pivots.
What are the pivots for that
matrix?
I'll tell you,
they're -- the first pivot is
two, the next pivot is three
over two, the next pivot is four
over three.
Because, the product of the
pivots has to give me those
determinants.
The product of these two pivots
gives me that determinant;
the
product of all the pivots gives
me that determinant.
What are the eigenvalues?
Oh, I don't know.
The eigenvalues I've got,
what do I have a cubic equation
-- a degree three equation?
There are three eigenvalues to
find.
If I believe what I've said
today, what do I know about
these
eigenvalues,
even though I don't know the
exact numbers.
I -- I remember the numbers.
Because these matrices are so
important that people figure
them.
But -- what do you believe to
be true about these three
eigenvalues -- you believe that
they are all positive.
They're all positive.
I think that they are two minus
square root of two,
two, and two plus the square
root of two.
I think.
Let me just -- I can't write
those numbers down without
checking the simple checks,
what the first simple check is
the trace, so if I add those
numbers I
get six and if I add those
numbers I get six.
The other simple test is the
determinant, if I -- can you do
this, can you multiply those
numbers together?
I guess we can multiply by two
out there.
What's two minus square root of
two times two plus square root
of
two, that'll be four minus two,
that'll be two,
yeah, two times two,
that's got the determinant,
right, so it's got,
it's got a chance of being
correct and I think it is.
Now, what's the x transpose Ax?
I better give myself enough
room
for that.
x transpose Ax for this guy.
It's two x1 squareds,
and two x2 squareds,
and two x3 squareds.
Those come from the diagonal,
those were easy.
Now off the diagonal there's a
minus and a minus,
they come together there'll be
a minus two
minus two whats?
Are coming from this one two
and two one position,
is the x1 x2.
I'm doing mentally a
multiplication of this matrix
times a row vector on the left
times a column vector on the
right, and I know that these
numbers show up in the answer.
The diagonal is the perfect
square, this off diagonal is a
minus two x1 x2,
and there are no x1 x3-s,
and there're minus two x2 x3-s.
And I believe that that
expression is always positive.
I believe that that curve,
that graph, really,
of that function,
this is my function f,
and I'm in more dimensions now
than I can draw,
it -- but the graph of that
function goes upwards.
It's a bowl.
Or maybe the right word is --
just forgot, what's a long word
for bowl?
Hm, maybe paraboloid,
I think, paraboloid comes in.
I'll edit the tape and get that
word in.
Bowl, let's say,
is, that, so that,
and if I can -- I could
complete the squares,
I could write that as the sum
of three squares,
and those three squares would
get multiplied by the three
pivots.
And the pivots are all
positive.
So I would have positive pivots
times squares,
the net result would be a
positive function and a bowl
which goes upwards.
And then, finally,
if I cut -- if I slice through
this bowl, if I -- now I'm
asking you to stretch your
visualization here,
because I'm in four dimensions,
I've
got x1 x2 x3 in the base,
and this function is z,
or f, or something.
And its graph is going up.
But I'm in four dimensions,
because I've got three in the
base and then the upward
direction, but now if I cut
through this four-dimensional
picture, at level one,
so, suppose I cut
through this thing at height
one.
So I take all the points that
are at height one.
That gives me -- it gave me an
ellipse over there,
in that two by two case,
in this case,
this will be the equation of an
ellipsoid, a football in other
words.
Well, not quite a football.
A lopsided football.
What would be,
can I try to describe to you
what the ellipsoid will look
like, this ellipsoid,
I'm sorry that the,
that I've ended the matrix
right -- at the point,
let's -- let me be sure you've
seen the equation.
Two x1 squared,
two x2 squared,
two x3
squared, minus two of the cross
parts, equal what?
That is the equation of a
football, so what do I mean by a
football or an ellipsoid?
I mean that,
well, I'll draw a few.
It's like that,
it's got a center,
and it's got it's got three
principal directions.
This ellipsoid.
So -- you see what I'm saying,
if we have a sphere then all
directions would be the same.
If we had a true football,
or it's closer to a rugby ball,
really, because it's more
curved than a football,
it would have one long
direction and the other two
would be equal.
That would be like having a
matrix that had one eigenvalue
repeated.
And then one other different.
So this sphere comes from,
like, the identity matrix,
all eigenvalues the same.
Our rugby ball comes from a
case where --
three, the three,
two of the three eigenvalues
are the same.
But we know how the case where
-- the typical case,
where the three eigenvalues
were all different.
So this will have -- How do I
say it, if I look at this
ellipsoid correctly,
it'll have a major axis,
it'll have a middle axis,
and it'll have a minor axis.
And those three axes will be in
the direction of the
eigenvectors.
And the lengths of those axes
will be determined by the
eigenvalues.
I can get -- turn this all into
linear algebra,
because we have -- the right
thing we know about
eigenvectors and eigenvalues,
for that matrix is what?
Of -- let me just tell you
that, repeat the main linear
algebra point.
How could we turn what I said
into algebra;
we would write this A as Q,
the eigenvector matrix,
times lambda,
the eigenvalue matrix
times Q transposed.
The principal axis theorem,
we'll call it,
now.
The eigenvectors tell us the
directions of the principal
axes.
The eigenvalues tell us the
lengths of those axes,
actually the lengths,
or the half-lengths,
or one over the eigenvalues,
it turns out.
And that is the matrix
factorization which is the most
important matrix factorization
in our eigenvalue material so
far.
That's diagonalization for a
symmetric matrix,
so instead of the inverse I can
write the transposed.
OK.
I've -- so what I've tried
today is to tell you the --
what's going on with positive
definite matrices.
Ah, you see all how all these
pieces are there and linear
algebra connects them.
OK.
See you on Friday.