MARTINA BALAGOVIC: Hi.
Welcome to recitation.
Today's problem is about
positive definite matrices.
And it's asking us, for which
values of the parameter c,
which is sitting here in the
matrix, is the matrix B, 2,
minus 1, minus 1, minus 1, 2,
minus 1, minus 1, minus 1, 2
plus c, positive definite, and
for which values of c is it
positive semidefinite?
I'm going to leave you alone
with the problem.
You should pause the video and
then come back and compare
your solution.
And we're back.
As you remember from the
lectures, there are several
tests that you can do on
matrices to find out if
they're positive definite
and if they're positive
semidefinite.
And I'm going to demonstrate
three to you.
First, I'm going to do the one
that you should do in case you
have very little time and you're
asked to do a problem
like this on the test, which is
of course the determinant
test. The determinant test
asks us to compute
determinants of the matrices
in the upper left
corner of all sizes.
And it says that it's going
to be positive definite if
they're all greater than 0 and
positive semidefinite if some
0's sneak into into
that sequence.
So let's calculate
the determinants.
The first determinant is the
determinant of this tiny
matrix here.
So it's just 2.
The next one is the determinant
of this two by two
submatrix, 2, minus 1, minus
1, 2, which is equal to 4
minus 1, which is 3.
And finally, we have the
determinant of B, which I'm
going to calculate for you.
I'm going to calculate it, I'm
going to decompose it along
the first line, first row.
So it's 2 times the determinant
of this submatrix,
2, minus 1, minus 1, 2 plus c,
minus minus 1, this one here,
times this determinant, which
is minus 1, minus 1,
minus 1, 2 plus c.
And then plus minus 1, this
one here, times this
determinant, which is minus
1, 2, minus 1, minus 1.
And in total, that's 2 times 4
plus 2c minus 1 plus minus 2
minus c minus 1 and
minus 1 plus 2.
And in total, this should give
us 6 plus 4c minus 3 minus c
minus 3, which is 3c.
So let's look at the
determinants.
2 is positive.
3 is positive.
3c is positive.
So the answer is the matrix is
positive definite if c is
bigger than 0, and it's positive
semidefinite if it's
either strictly bigger
than 0 or equal to 0.
And that's all.
If you're on the test, this is
everything that you should do.
Now let me show you two more
tests to demonstrate that
first, they take longer, and
second, to see these numbers
and their quotients show up in
other tests and to try to
convince you that these tests
really are equivalent.
Let me do the pivots
test for you.
So we take our matrix B, 2,
minus 1, minus 1, minus 1, 2,
minus 1, minus 1, minus
1, 2 plus c.
And let's pretend we're solving
a system that has this
as a matrix.
So we multiply the first row by
1/2, and we add it to the
second and to the third row.
We get 2, minus 1, minus 1, 0,
3/2, minus 3/2, 0, minus 3/2,
3/2 plus c.
So the first column is good.
And then we just replace the
third column with the third
column plus the second column.
And we get 2, minus 1, minus
1, 0, 3/2, minus
3/2, 0, 0, and c.
And so the pivots are
2, 3/2, and c.
And again, the answer
is as before.
It's positive definite if c is
strictly bigger than 0, and
it's positive semidefinite if
c is greater or equal to 0.
But I want you to notice
something else here.
So before, we had
2, 3, and 3c.
And now for determinants, as
these pivots, we have 2, 3/2,
which is the second determinant
over the first
determinant, and c, which can be
thought of as 3c/3, so the
third determinant over the
second determinant.
And something like this is
always going to happen.
And finally, let me do
the energy test, or
completing the square.
So one of the definitions of
positive definite, one could
say the definition because of
which we are really interested
in such matrices, is
the following.
It's positive definite if when
we consider this quadratic
form, so a form that maps x,
y, and z to this expression
here that's going to be
quadratic in x, y, and z, it's
positive semidefinite if
this is always greater
or equal than 0.
And it's positive definite if,
when we have an expression
like this and try to solve
this equals 0, the only
solution is that x, y, and
z all have to be 0.
So let's try calculating this
form, completing the squares
on it, and seeing these
numbers show up again.
So when I multiply this like
this, put in a B, do the
multiplication, we get
something like this.
2x squared plus 2y squared plus
2 plus c z squared minus
2xy minus 2xz minus 2yz.
And now let's try completing the
squares using the formulas
that I prepared for you up here
in this pop-up window in
the corner.
So let's try completing, we have
a formula for the square
of a plus b plus c and the
square of a plus b.
So first, we try to get
something squared so that this
something has all the x's that
appear here, so that we get
something squared plus some
expression that only
takes y's and z's.
I'm not going to do the
calculation in front of you,
further embarrass
myself with it.
But let me tell you that what
you get is 2 times x minus 1/2
y minus 1/2 z squared.
And this ate all the x's
that showed up here.
The remainder only
has y's and z's.
When you use the second of those
formulas in a pop-up
window to complete the square
of y's and z's, you get 3/2
times y minus z squared.
So this took up all the y's, and
we're left just with a z
that comes as c times
z squared.
And now, let's look
at the following.
This is a square of
some real number.
So that's positive.
This is a square of some real
number, so that's positive.
And this is a square
of some real
number, so that's positive.
They're all multiplied by
positive numbers, 2, 3/2, and
c, which we've already
seen here.
And so if c is bigger or equal
than 0, this is certainly
always bigger or equal than 0.
Now to the question of if this
can be equal to 0 without x,
y, and z all being 0, well,
let's look at two cases.
If c is strictly bigger than
0, then let me write this
matrix here as 2, 3/2 and c
times 1, minus 1/2, minus 1/2,
0, 1, minus 1, and 0, 0, 1.
Let's imagine c is strictly
bigger than 0.
And let's see when can this
expression be equal to 0.
Well, as we said, it's a
sum of certain squares.
They're all greater or equal to
0, so they all have to be
equal to 0 for this expression
to be 0.
In other words, z needs
to be equal to 0.
y minus z needs to
be equal to 0.
And x minus 1/2 y minus 1/2 z
also needs to be equal to 0.
And since this matrix has all
the pivots, this can only
happen if x, y, and z
are all equal to 0.
On the other hand, if c is equal
to 0, then let me write
this matrix here again.
Take 2 out here.
Take 3/2 out here.
And write again 1, minus 1/2,
minus 1/2, 0, 1, minus
1, and 0, 0, 0.
And so imagining that c is 0,
when can this whole expression
be equal to 0?
Well, the last bit
is already 0.
We need to have y minus
z equal to 0.
And we need to have 1 times x
minus 1/2 times y minus 1/2
times z also equal to 0.
So we need to have x, y, z in
the kernel of this matrix.
But this matrix only
has two pivots.
It has one free variable.
So we can find a solution to
this times x, y, z equals 0
that's not 0 itself.
Namely, if you remember how to
solve systems like this, we
set z equal to 1.
From this, we calculate
that y has to be 1.
And then from this, we calculate
that x has to be 1.
And you can check that for in
case c is 0, this thing here,
when you plug it in here,
you really get 0.
In fact, this thing here is in
the kernel of the matrix B. In
fact, in case c is 0, the
columns of matrix B sum up to
0 because of this here.
And that's all I wanted
to say for today.