The Fourier coefficients applet
lets us explore the
approximation of periodic
functions by Fourier series.
This is the opening screen
of the applet.
On the right, you see a series
of sliders controlling
coefficients.
And they're the coefficients of
the sine terms in a Fourier
series, as you can see by
clicking this formula box.
So at this point, what we're
studying is an odd function, a
sine series, and the sliders
let us control the
coefficients of sine of kt.
If I click the cosine box,
I'd see coefficients
of the cosine functions.
Let's go back to sine and start
to play with the tool a
little bit.
What will happen if I
move the b2 slider?
I should get multiples of the
sine of 2t showing up on my
graphing window.
If I push b2 to the right, I get
positive multiples of the
sine of 2t.
The sine of 2t goes through two
full periods when t ranges
from 0 to 2pi.
And if b2 is negative, I
get negative multiples
of the sine of 2t.
What happens if I change
b1 in this tool?
This will add a multiple of the
sine of t to the function
that I already have.
If I push this to the right,
I'm going to get positive
multiples of the sine of 2t, and
you can see the alteration
in the yellow graph
when I do that.
When I push b1 to the left, I'm
adding negative multiples
of the sine of t.
You get quite a variety of
interesting functions by
playing with these
various sliders.
But it's even more fun to try
to match a target periodic
function by means of sine
or cosine series.
And the tool has built into it
a whole family of target
functions to try for.
Right now, the target
function is 0.
But we can select target A
instead, and what we have now
is a square wave.
Actually, this isn't the
standard square wave that we
deal with in the
course, quite.
It is periodic, of period 2pi,
and alternates between
positive and negative values,
but those values are pi over 4
and minus pi over 4, instead of
plus 1 and minus 1, as they
are for the standard
square wave.
That's chosen so that the
Fourier coefficients come out
more neatly, as we'll see.
So let's try to approximate
this function by a finite
trigonometric sum.
I'm going to push the Reset
key here to reset all the
coefficients to zero, and start
trying to match the
function that I have at hand
with multiples of sine of kt.
Let's begin with the sine
function itself, sine of t.
Well, I don't know what to do.
Let's just set it so the
maxima coincide.
Why not?
Maybe that will be an
appropriate amount of the sine
of t function to put into the
pot when I'm trying to mix up
the square wave.
Let's go on to b2 now.
I'm going to push the B2
slider to the right.
When I do that, you see a hump
forming on the left-hand side
of the positive part
of the square wave.
If push b2 to the left, the same
kind of hump forms on the
right-hand side of that
positive part
of the square wave.
Neither one of them seems to
be doing us very much good.
And in fact, it's creating an
asymmetry in the Fourier
series that's not present
in our target function.
It's not respecting the symmetry
that you see around
pi over 2 in the square
wave itself.
So I suspect that b2 is not
going to be useful to us, that
the sine of 2t is not going
to be a constituent in the
Fourier series for
square wave.
In fact, I think that none
of the even sines will be
of any use to us.
And I can get rid of them and
look only at the odd terms by
clicking this Odd Terms box.
This leaves the sine function
that we had in place.
It eliminates all the odd
terms in the series.
It eliminates all the even
coefficients and leaves us
only with the odd ones.
But there are more of them, so
we should be able to do a
better job of approximating
the square wave.
So let's continue.
Let's try changing b3 to get
a good approximation.
Well, I can push b3 to the
left, and I get a sharper
spike in the middle.
That doesn't look too good.
It looks better to push
b3 to the right and
flatten out the top.
But when I do that, the
top becomes too low.
And so maybe I made a mistake
in changing b1 so that the
maxima agreed.
Maybe I should have made
b1 a little bit bigger.
Now you can see the white curve
there-- that's giving me
the multiple of the sine wave
itself, the one that I'm
controlling by this slider.
And I guess I should push it up
so that my flat part comes
closer to the top of
the square wave.
Maybe that's a better
approximation.
Well, I can continue playing
this game, trying out various
multiples of higher sine
functions, and going back to
try to fix up what
I had before.
In fact, what we should be
trying to do is create a least
squares fit.
You should try to look at the
root mean squared distance
between the Fourier series and
the target function, and
minimize that distance.
That distance can be read out
in this tool by clicking the
Distance button down here.
And so the root mean squared
distance between the green
curve and the yellow one is 0.24
and so on, in this case.
Let me come down here and
kill the formula.
We know the formula well now,
and it makes the screen a
little less cluttered
if we get rid of it.
And let me reset the values of
the coefficients to zero, and
start to try to approximate
this square wave again by
watching the root mean squared
distance between the Fourier
series that I'm creating and
the target function.
So I'll start with b1 in this
case, If I move it down, the
distance increases.
If I move it up, the
distance decreases
more and more slowly.
But now when b1 becomes
greater than one,
it starts to increase.
So let me push it down again.
I can use these little arrow
keys to step the value of b1.
That's very convenient.
I'm just watching the root mean
squared distance, this
number up here.
I'm trying to make that
as small as possible.
It's a measure of the
closeness of fit.
Ah, it just started
to increase again.
Let me step up.
And I found the value of one.
I didn't set it to one.
I set it to the value that
minimized this number.
And that's the right quantity of
the sine wave to put in, if
you want to mix up the square
wave, or rather pi over 4
times the square wave.
Let's look at b3.
Again, if I decrease b3,
things get worse.
The root mean squared
distance increases.
But if I increase b3 above the
value of zero, that number is
getting smaller.
Now it's growing again.
I think I'll stop there and
use these arrow keys.
That's better, that's better,
that's better, that's worse.
Let me go back.
And I find the value
0.33 for b3.
That's the optimal amount of
the sine of 3t to put in if
you want to mix up the formula
for this square wave.
I'll do one more.
Any guesses for what the optimal
value of b5 should be?
It's not going to be negative.
That will increase the root
mean squared distance.
Let's push it up in the
positive direction.
That's about right.
That's worse, that's better,
that's better,
better, better, worse.
I come down here.
That's optimal.
We've discovered by
experimentation with this
applet that the optimal
value of b5 is 0.200.
Each one of these coefficients
seems to have optimal value
equal to the reciprocal
of the index.
1/3 in this case, 1 in this
case, 1/5 in this case.
And I predict that the optimal
value of b7 is going to be
1/7, which is about 0.14.
There you go.
it's right in there.
So this applet lets you
understand the true meaning of
the Fourier coefficients.
They're the multiples of the
sine waves or the cosine waves
which give you the optimal
fit, in terms of a finite
Fourier series, to the
target function.