PROFESSOR: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So today I'd like to look at
a problem on a manipulating
Fourier series.
Specifically, we're asked to
find the Fourier series of
cosine 2t minus pi/4.
And then the second problem is
given a square wave function,
which takes on the value
of minus 1 and 1,
and it's 2pi periodic.
We're also told that the square
wave function has the
Fourier series 4/pi,
1/n, sine nt.
And the question is to find the
Fourier series of three
related functions.
So the first function takes on
the value of 0 and 4 on the
intervals minus pi
to 0 and 0 to pi.
Note that this function
is also 2pi periodic.
The second problem it is to find
the Fourier series of a
function which is minus
1 from minus 1 to 0,
and 1 from 0 to 1.
So this is the square
wave function, but
now has period two.
And then lastly we're asked to
find the Fourier series of a
function f of t, which
is absolute t.
And it's defined as absolute
t on the interval
from minus pi to pi.
However this function f is going
to be extended on the
entire domain with period 2pi.
So I'll let you think about this
problem and I'll be back
in a moment.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So let's take a look at the
first problem, finding the
Fourier series of cosine
2t minus pi/4.
So in this class when we say
find the Fourier series, what
we're really looking for are
coefficients a0 an and bn,
such that, for example, we can
write our function out as a
sum of sine and cosines with
these values an and bn.
Now, what we could do is we
could take this function, plug
it into the integral formulas,
and compute using integrals,
the value a0, an, and bn.
However, there's a
bit of a trick.
And that's to realize that this
function, cosine 2t minus
pi/4 is really just a sinusoidal
function with a
single frequency.
And it's currently in an
amplitude phase form.
And we can always convert an
amplitude phase form of a
sinusoidal function into some
amplitude times a sine and
some amplitude times a cosine
and add the two up.
So specifically, this can be
done by recalling the cosine
identity, cosine A minus B, is
cosine A times cosine B plus
sine of A, sine of B.
And if we identify A with 2t
and B with pi/4, we obtain
that f of t is cosine
2t cosine pi/4 plus
sine 2t sine of pi/4.
And now sine pi/4 and cosine
pi/4 are both 1 over root 2.
So f of t becomes 1 over
root 2 cosine 2t plus 1
over root 2 sine 2t.
And that's it.
So when we take a look at this
expression for f of t, we see
that this is actually in exactly
the same form that we
were seeking in the beginning,
the Fourier series
representation for f.
So this is the end
of the problem.
We don't have to actually
compute any integrals.
So now let's take a
look at part two.
So for part two, we're asked to
find the Fourier series of
several different functions.
And I'll just take a
look at part one.
So in this case, f of t takes
on the value of 0 from minus
pi to zero, and the value
of 4 from 0 to pi.
And if I were to quickly sketch
this function, it would
look like a square wave,
0, pi, minus pi.
This is f of t.
And we see that it's
actually related--
I can draw in dashes
just to be clear--
what the original square wave
function might look like.
So this is square wave of t.
We see that if we were to take
the square wave function and
shift it up, the square wave
takes on values of
plus 1 and minus 1.
But if we take the square wave
function and shift it up 1
unit, and then rescale it, we'll
then get the function
we're looking for, f of t.
So specifically, we can write f
of t in terms of the square
wave as well.
We have to shift the square wave
function up 1, and then
we have to amplify it
by a factor of 2.
So then when we seek the Fourier
series for f, all we
have to do is substitute the
Fourier series for the square
wave function n.
So let's do this.
So we have 1 plus 4/pi.
So I'm writing here this Fourier
series for the square
wave function, n odd
1/n sine nt.
So by manipulating the Fourier
series for the square wave
function, we can arrive at a
Fourier series for f of t, n
odd 1/n sine nt.
So this is the first function.
The second function f of t--
I'll just rewrite it again--
f of t takes on the value of
negative 1 from negative 1 to
0, and takes on the value
of plus 1 from 0 to 1.
So it's somewhat useful to draw,
just to quickly sketch
this function.
And I'll draw in my axes here.
So this is f of t.
This is t.
And it transitions.
It makes its jumps
at the integers.
So for example, it jumps from
plus 1 to minus 1 at 1, and
from plus 1 to minus 1
at minus 1 as well.
And if I were to just quickly
sketch the square wave
function underneath of it, the
square wave function makes its
transitions at minus
pi and pi.
So this is the square
wave function.
This is t.
So we see that we can take the
square wave function and
squeeze it to obtain this
function f of t.
And the question now is, what
factor do we have to squeeze
the square wave function
by to get f of t.
Well, usually what I like to do
is take one characteristic
point in the sketch
for in this case
the square wave function.
So a nice characteristic point
is when the square wave
function has a 0, so when it
goes through the origin, and
compare it to the same point
on this function f of t.
So we see that the point
pi has to get stretched
to the point 1.
So we basically need to take
the time axis in the square
wave function and squeeze
it by a factor of pi.
So what this means is that f of
t is going to be the square
wave. And when we do what
mathematicians sometimes
called a dilatation, a
stretch or a squeeze.
If we're squeezing by some
factor, that factor always
appears in the argument of the
function we're squeezing.
If it's a stretch, then
it would be t
over the stretch factor.
And we can quickly check here
that if t equals 1, so as t
goes from 0 to 1, so when t is
1, the square wave function is
being evaluated at pi.
And I'll now write out
the Fourier series.
So this is going to be
4/pi sum of n odd 1/n
sine of n pi t.
And there's another quick
check we can do.
And that's this function
f we were told is
periodic with period 2.
And if we just take a look at
this function here, the
Fourier series representation of
it, we see that each sine n
pi t is in fact periodic
with period 2.
So that's just another quick,
back of the envelope check
that we've done our calculation
correctly.
So this concludes part two.
And then lastly than for part
three, f of t is the absolute
value of t from minus
pi to pi.
And it's extended beyond
minus pi to pi
to make it 2pi periodic.
And at first it might look like
this function f of t is
not related to the square
wave function.
But if we look at it a little
more carefully, and analyze
the derivative of f of t, we see
that this function takes
on the value plus 1 on the
interval of 0 to pi and takes
on the value of minus 1 on the
interval of minus pi to 0.
And this is exactly the square
wave. So what we can do is we
can write f of t.
It's going to be an integral of
the square wave function.
So specifically, we have the
integral of square wave, which
is going to be the integral
of 4/pi 1/n sine
nt summation n odd.
And I'm going to leave this
as an indefinite integral.
So when we integrate, we have
a constant of integration c
plus 4/pi sum of 1
over n squared.
And we have negative
cosine nt.
And this is n odd again.
And now we have one last
question to answer.
What is the constant
of integration?
Well, notice how the constant
of integration can be
identified with the a0 term
of a Fourier series.
So if we want the constant of
integration, we can just
calculate it directly by the
integral formula for the a0 of
this function.
So what this means is c
is going to be 1/2pi.
Essentially it's just the
average of the function, but
it's pi to pi, the absolute
value of t, which is 1/pi, pi
squared over 2.
So we get pi/2.
So just to quickly recap, in
this problem we were given
several functions which
were related to
the square wave function.
And we started off knowing what
the Fourier series for
the square wave function was.
And by manipulating or rewriting
these functions in
terms of the square wave
function, we were able to
compute their Fourier series.
And we were able to do this
essentially without having to
evaluate any integrals.
OK.
So I hope you enjoyed this
problem, and I'll
see you next time.