Problem number 7.
29-52.
And here we have to deal
with Biot and Savart.
Two Frenchmen.
Biot and Savart said, if I have
a small element of a wire
that draws a current, 'dl' is
always in the direction of
that current.
If I want to know, at a
particular position here, what
the magnetic field is due to
this small element alone, then
they argued--
they call this the vector 'r'.
From the current element to that
point 'P', where you want
to know the magnetic field.
This is the unit vector 'r'.
They argued that the 'dB' right
here, 'dB' equals 'mu 0'
divided by '4 pi' times 'i'
times 'dl cross r' divided by
'r squared'.
It was interesting that they
have an 'r squared'.
They like the idea, of course of
Coulomb's law, whereby the
electric field force is
'1 over r squared'.
And they intuitively sensed,
well, the 'B' field due to
such a small line element would
also fall off as '1 over
r squared'.
That's certainly
not incorrect.
But you cannot have a short
section of wire in isolation.
You must always have a closed
loop, otherwise
you can't run a current.
And when you take that into
account, you will never see '1
over r squared' magnetic
field.
It's always a '1/r'.
Or, in some special cases, you
can have '1/r cubed' field.
When you have magnetic dipole
fields, but we will get back
to that later.
But never a '1 over
r squared'.
So that is Biot and Savart.
And you have to use Biot and
Savart when you deal with
short sections of wire.
When you use infinite wires,
then you can always Ampere's
law, but that's not
the case here.
The direction of the 'dB' must
be perpendicular a 'dl' and
must be perpendicular to 'r'
it's a cross product.
So perpendicular to 'dl,
perpendicular to 'r' to must
be perpendicular to the paper.
'dl' cross 'r', you can
do that yourself.
'dl' is always in the
direction 'i'.
That I think, is pointing in the
paper, in this direction.
Now we have the following
configuration.
There's a current
flowing here.
'i in' and 'i out'.
Goes up here, goes here,
goes down here, here,
and comes back bere.
I will call this little section
1, this little section
2, I will call this [? coil ?]
3 and this wire I continued as
a continuous wire, I consider
that a continuous wire,
I call that 4.
You are being asked what the
magnetic field is right at the
center here, at point 'P'.
You should be able to convince
yourself that all these wires,
1, 2, 3, and 4 in all cases
contribute to a magnetic field
that is pointing in
the blackboard.
In all four cases.
So they support each other.
Convince yourself of that, it's
the logical consequence
of this cross product.
Now 1 and 3 will have obviously
exactly the same
effect, so it's enough
that you only
calculate 1 double it.
2 and 4 also have the
same effect in
magnitude, and in direction.
So it's enough that you
calculate 2 and double that,
if you so desire.
I will set up the situation,
in general terms, and then
I'll leave you alone
with the details.
My script falls on the floor,
I have to go and get it.
You won't me for a minute, but
it's a small price to pay.
That was my script.
I also lost something else
which fell on the floor.
I will get that in
the meantime.
I need that for a
demonstration.
I'm back in business.
The table is a bit small and
yeah occasionally things fall
on the floor.
It does happen.
I'm going to set
it up for you.
In general terms, and then you
work out the details with the
particular geometry.
If I have here a wire which
has a finite length 'l', I
call this the x- direction, here
is 0, here is 1/2'l' .
1/2 and here is '-1/2 l'.
There's a current flowing in
this direction I'i', and I
consider here a small
element 'dx'.
Think of that that as being
'dl' in our Biot Savart
calculation.
And I would like to know what
here at the point 'P', at a
distance 'd' the from the wire,
the magnetic fields is.
The magnetic field contribution
will be
perpendicular to the paper
and in the paper.
That you should be able to
figure out for yourself now.
And there is a contribution
'dB'.
So I draw this line, this is
that vector 'r', and the units
vector 'r' is in
this direction.
Now what is 'dB'?
I take the magnitude, because I
already know the direction,
it's down, so I'm not interested
in that anymore.
Equals 'mu 0' times 'i', divided
by '4 pi' times the
sine of theta because, remember,
it's a cross product
and if this angle is theta I
have to take the cross product
into account between
'dx' and 'r'.
And then I got 'dx', which is my
'dl' and I divide the whole
thing by 'r squared'.
I also know that the sine of
theta equals 'd' divided by
'r', and I also know that 'r'
equals the square root of 'd
squared' plus 'x squared'.
If I call the distance from here
to my element that I have
chosen, if I call that 'x'.
So that means that I will find
that 'B' equals twice, because
I'm going to integrate only from
here to there, but I must
take this part into account,
so double it because it's
completely symmetric, so
I can put a 2 here.
Integral from 0 to '1/2 l', 'mu
0' divided by '4 pi' times
'i' times 'd' and now I get
here 'dx' divided by 'x
squared' plus 'd squared'
to the power 3/2.
Perhaps you remember that we
have seen this one before and
perhaps you remember my honesty
when I said, I looked
it up, what it was.
And I even asked my graduate
student to check it, and I'm
not going to do that now.
We've done it before, you've
done it before, you were much
better at it than I am.
You can solve that integral
without any doubt.
When you have solved this
integral I think it's
interesting that you should at
least convince yourself that
if l goes up, if you make 'l'
longer, then you better must
find that 'B' increases.
That's completely intuitive
for a given value of 'd'.
You would also want to find that
if you make 'd' larger
that 'B' goes down.
Because if you're farther
away you got a
smaller magnetic field.
And so that's at least the
minimum you can check when you
get your final answer.
Other than that, I have
no wisdom on this.
You can do this problem now.
For this particular geometry,
and the particular geometry is
not just one line, but you
have various lines with a
little section 1, what I
have called 'l', you
would call that 'a'.
And what I have called 'd'
you would call '1/2 b'.
And you can do that for
the other sections
2, 3, and 4 as well.