PROFESSOR: Problem number 8.
And problem number 8 is 29-54.
Now we deal with
circular wires.
Half circle.
And another half circle.
Here's is a point, let's call
this point 'P', exactly at the
center of these circles.
And there's a current flowing,
there's a current flowing in
this direction, i; i; i; i; i.
This has a radius 'a', and
this has a radius 'b'.
If we, again, give these lines
numbers, 1, 2, 3, 4, then it
is immediately obvious that 2
and 4 do not contribute to the
magnetic field at 'B', because
the sine of theta equals 0 in
this cross product.
So we only deal with
3 and with 1.
Now 1 is going to give me a
magnetic field which is
pointing perpendicular to
the paper, in the paper.
This is 1.
But 3 will give me one that is
in the opposite direction,
coming out of the paper.
So this one is due to 3.
And this one will be stronger
than this one because the
radius is smaller.
The current is the same, the
radius is smaller, it is
therefore closer to the
wire, so the magnetic
field will be stronger.
This will be the winner, so
finally the magnetic field
will be pointing upwards.
What I propose to do is to
simply calculate for you the
magnetic field of one arc, and
then I'm sure that you can do
the superposition
for both arcs.
Here's one arc.
I call this point 'A' and I call
this 'D', and this is the
center, it is 'P'.
I have a current 'i' in this
direction, and I have here a
little element 'dl'.
I have here this vector 'r', and
the unit vector 'r' is in
this direction.
Let the radius of this circle
be capital 'R'.
What is interesting that every
element 'dl', for every
element 'dl', 'r' is
perpendicular to 'dl'.
Therefore, in all cases, is the
sine of that angle theta
is the same.
1.
Whether it is plus or minus 1,
it is a matter of taste.
The dot product is 'dl' cross
'r', sine of theta, 90
degrees, is 1.
If you want to call it
-1, I don't care.
I really don't care.
Because I do know that the
magnetic field is in this
direction, and that's ultimately
all I want to know.
So I can delete the cross and I
can write down now what the
magnitude of dB is which is 'mu
0' times 'i', divided by
'4 pi' and I do know a very
dirty integral from 'A' to
'D', along this arc, of 'dl'
divided by 'R squared'.
But the integral of 'dl' is
simply '2 pi R', so what comes
out of this is that the--
oh this should be the
integral of 'dB', so
this is really 'B'.
It's the integral of all these
elements, so what comes out at
'B', at that point 'P'
equals 'mu 0' times
'i' divided by '4R'.
Notice that it's inversely
proportion to '1/R'.
And that is very
characteristic.
You will never find an
inverse 'R squared'.
Now you have to do another
current which goes in the
opposite direction, and so you
have to add to the two
factorially, and I will
leave you with that.
I don't think that's going
to be a problem at all.