JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture, you've been learning
about computing
double integrals and about
changing the order of
integration.
And how you can look at a
given region and you can
integrate over it by integrating
dx dy or by
integrating dy dx.
So here I have some examples.
I have two regions.
So one region is the triangle
whose vertices are the origin,
the point 0, 2, and the
point minus 1, 2.
And the other one is a
sector of a circle.
So the circle has a radius 2 and
is centered at the origin.
And I want the part of that
circle that's above the x-axis
and below the line y equals x.
So what I'd like you to do is
I'd like you to write down
what a double integral over
these regions looks like, but
I'd like you to do it
two different ways.
I'd like you to do it as
an iterated integral in
the order dx dy.
And I'd also like you to do it
as an iterated integral in the
order dy dx.
So I'd like you to express the
integrals over these regions
in terms of iterated integrals
in both possible orders.
So why don't you pause the
video, have a go at that, come
back, and we can work
on it together.
So the first thing to do
whenever you're given a
problem like this--
and in fact, almost
anytime you have
to do a double integral--
is to try and understand
the region in question.
It's always a good idea
to understand
the region in question.
And by understand the region in
question, really the first
thing that I mean is
draw a picture.
All right.
So let's do part a first.
So in part a, you have a
triangle, it has vertices at the
origin, at the point 0, 2,
and at the point minus 1, 2.
So this triangle is our
region in question.
So now that we've got a picture
of it, we can talk and
we can say, what are
the boundaries of
this region, right?
And we want to know what
its boundaries are.
So the top boundary is the line
y equals 2, the right
boundary is the line x equals 0,
and this sort of lower left
boundary-- the slanted line--
is the line y equals minus 2x.
OK.
So those are the boundary
edges of this triangle.
And so now what we want to
figure out is we want to
figure out is, OK, if you're
integrating this with respect
to x and then y, or if you're
to y and then x, what does that
integral look like when
you set it up as a
double integral.
So let's start on one of them.
It doesn't matter which one.
So let's try and write the
double integral over this
region R in the order dx dy.
OK, so we have inside
bounds dx dy.
So OK.
So we need to find the bounds
on x first, and those bounds
are going to be in terms of y.
So the bounds on x.
So that means when we look at
this region, what we want to
figure out is we want to figure
out for a given value
y, what is the leftmost
point and what is
the rightmost point?
What are the bounds on x?
So for given value y, the
largest value x is going to
take is along this
line x equals 0.
When you fix some value of y,
the rightmost point that x can
reach in this region is at
this line x equals 0.
So x is going to go up to 0.
That's going to be
its upper bound.
The lower bound is going to be
the left edge of our region.
For a given value of
y, what is that
leftmost boundary value?
So what we want to do is we want
to take that equation for
that boundary and we want to
solve it for x in terms of y.
So that's not hard to
do in this case.
The line y equals minus
2x is also the line x
equals minus 1/2 y.
So that's that left boundary:
minus 1/2 y.
OK?
So then our outer
bounds are dy.
So we want to find the
absolute bounds on y.
What's the smallest value that
y takes, and what's the
largest value that y takes?
So that means what's the lowest
point of this region
and what's the highest?
And so the lowest point
here is the origin.
So that's when y takes
the value of 0.
And the highest point-- the
very top of this region--
is when y equals 2.
OK.
So this is what that double
integral is going to become
when we evaluate it in
the order dx dy.
So now let's talk about
evaluating it in
the opposite order.
So let's switch our
bounds for dy dx.
So we want the double integral
over R, dy dx.
OK, so this is going to be
an iterated integral.
And this time the inner bounds
are going to be for y in terms
of x, and the outer bounds
are going to be
absolute bounds on x.
So for y in terms of x, that
means we look at this region--
we want to know for a
fixed value of x--
what's the bottom boundary of
this region, and what's the
top boundary?
So here, it's easy to see that
the bottom boundary is this
line y equals minus 2x, and the
top boundary is this line
y equals 2.
So y is going from
minus 2x to 2.
Yeah?
So for a fixed value of x, the
values of y that give you a
point in this region are the
values that y is at least
minus 2x and at most 2.
So OK.
And now we need the
outer bounds.
So the outer bounds have to be
some real numbers, Those are
the absolute bounds on x.
So we need to know what the
absolute leftmost point and
the absolute rightmost point
in this region are.
And so the absolute leftmost
point is this
point minus 1, 2.
So that has an x-value
of minus 1.
And the absolute rightmost point
is along this right edge
at x equals 0.
OK.
So here are the two integrals.
The double integral with respect
to x then y, and the
double integral with respect
to y and then x.
OK.
So that's the answer
to part a.
Let's go on to part b.
So for part b, our region is we
take a circle of radius 2,
and we take the line y equals x,
and we take the line that's
the x-axis.
And so we want a circle, and
we want this sector of the
circle in here.
So this region inside the
circle, below the line y equal
x, and above the x-axis.
So this wedge of this circle.
Let's see.
This value is at x equals 2,
this is the origin, and this
is the point square root of
2 comma square root of 2.
A common point of the line y
equals x in the circle x
squared plus y squared
equals 4.
That's what this boundary curve
is: x squared plus y
squared equals 4.
And of course, this boundary
curve is the line y equals x.
And this boundary line is the
x-axis, which has the equation
y equals 0.
So those are our boundary
curves for our region.
We've got this nice picture,
so now we can talk about
expressing it as an iterated
integral in
two different orders.
So let's again start off with
this with respect to x first,
and then with respect to y.
So we want the double integral
over R, dx dy.
So this should be an
iterated integral,
something dx and then dy.
OK, so we need bounds on x,
which means for a fixed value
of y, we need to know what is
the leftmost boundary and
what's the rightmost bound.
So for a fixed value of y, we
want to know what the left
edge is and the right edge is.
And it's easy to see
because we've drawn
this picture, right?
Drawing the picture makes this
a much easier process.
The left edge is this line y
equals x and the right edge is
our actual circle.
Yeah?
So those are the left and right
boundaries, so what we
put here are just the equations
of that left edge
and the equation of
that right edge.
But we want their equations in
the form x equals something.
And that's the something
that we put there.
So for this left edge, it's
the line x equals y.
So the left bound is y there.
In this region, x
is at least y.
And the upper bound here,
which is going to be the
rightmost bound-- the largest
value that x takes--
is when x squared plus
y squared equals 4.
So when x is equal to
the square root
of 4 minus y squared.
Now you might say to me, why
do I know that it's the
positive square root here and
not the negative square root?
And if you said that
to yourself,
that's a great question.
And the answer is that this part
of the circle is the top
half of the circle
and it's also the
right half of the circle.
So here we have positive
values of x.
So it's the right half
of the circle.
We want the positive values of
x, so we want the positive
square root.
OK.
Good.
And so those are the
bounds on x.
Now we need the bounds on y.
So the bounds on y, well,
what are they?
Well, we want the absolute
bounds on y. y is the
outermost variable that we're
integrating with respect to,
so we want the absolute bounds--
the absolute lowest
value that y takes in this
region, and the absolute
largest value that y takes.
So the smallest value that y
takes in this region-- that's
the lowest point--
that's along this line, and
that's when y equals 0.
And the largest value that y
takes-- that's when y is as
large as possible as it can
get in this region--
is up at this point of
intersection there, so that's
when y is equal to the
square root of 2.
OK, three quarters done.
Yeah?
This is that iterated
integral.
So now, we want to do
the same thing.
R--
the integral over
this region R--
dy dx.
OK.
So we're going to look at this
region and we want to say--
dy is going to be
on the inside--
so we're going to say, OK, so
we need to know for a fixed
value of x, what's the smallest
value that y can take
and what's the largest value
that y can take?
So what's the bottom boundary
and what's the top boundary?
But if you look at
this region--
right?-- life is a little
complicated here.
Because if you're in the left
half of this region--
what do I mean by left half--
I mean if you're to the
left of this point of
intersection-- if you're at the
left of this line x equals
square root of 2--
when you're over there, y
is going from 0 to x.
But if you're over in the right
part of this region,
there's a different
upper boundary.
Right?
It's a different curve
that it came from.
It has a different equation.
So over here, y is going from
the x-axis up to the circle.
So this is complicated,
and what does this
complication mean?
Well, it means that it's not
easy to write this as a single
iterated integral.
If you want to do this in this
way, you have to break the
region into two pieces, and
write this double integral as
a sum of two iterated
integrals.
OK?
So one iterated integral will
take care of the left part and
one will take care of
the right part.
So let's do the left part first.
So here we're going to
have a iterated integral
integrating with respect to y
first. So to fix the value of
x, we want to know what the
bounds on y are.
And well, we can see from
this picture-- when
you're in this triangle--
that y is going from the
x-axis up to the
line y equals x.
So that means the smallest value
that y can take is 0,
and the largest value that
y can take is x.
So here it's from 0 to x.
And when you're in this
triangle, we need to know what
the bounds on x are, then.
We need to know the
outer bounds.
So we need to know the absolute
largest and smallest
values that x can take.
Well, what does that mean?
We need to know the absolute
leftmost and absolute
rightmost points.
So the absolute leftmost
point is the origin.
The absolute rightmost is this
vertical line x equals
square root of 2.
So over here, the
value of x is 0.
And at the rightmost boundary of
this triangle, the value of
x is the square root of 2.
OK.
So that's going to give us the
double integral just over this
triangular part of the region.
Yeah?
So now, we need to
add to this--
but I'm going to put it down on
this next line-- we need to
add to this the part of the
integral over this little
segment of the circle here.
The remainder of the region
that's not in that triangle.
So for that, again, we're
going to write down two
integrals, and it's
going to be dy dx.
Whew.
We're nearly done, right?
So y is inside, so we need to
know what the bounds on y are
for a given value of x.
So we need to know for a given
value of x, what are the
bottom and the topmost points
of this region?
So for a given value of x, that
means that y is going
here between the x-axis and
between this circle.
So the x-axis is y equals 0,
so that's the lower bound.
So for the upper bound, we
need to know this circle.
What is y on this circle?
Well, the equation of this
circle is x squared plus y
squared equals 4, so y is equal
to the square root of
the quantity 4 minus
x squared.
Where again here, we take the
positive square root, because
this is a part of the circle
where y is positive.
Yeah.
If we were somehow on the bottom
part of the circle,
then we would have to take a
negative square root there,
but because we're on the top
part of the circle where y is
positive, we take a positive
square root.
OK, good.
So those are the bounds on y,
and now we need to know the
absolute bounds on x.
Yeah?
So those are the bounds
on y in terms of x.
And now because x is the outer
thing we're integrating with
respect to, we need the
absolute bounds on x.
And you can see in
this circular--
I don't really know what the
name for a shape like that
is-- but whatever that thing is,
we need to know what its
leftmost and rightmost
points are.
We need to know the smallest
and largest
values that x can take.
And so its leftmost edge
is this line x equals
square root of 2.
And its rightmost edge is that
rightmost point on the circle
there-- where the circle
hit the x-axis--
and that's the value
when x equals 2.
OK, so there you go.
There's this last integral
written in the dy dx order,
but we can't write it as a
single iterated integral.
We need to write it as a sum
of two iterated integrals
because of the shape
of this region.
All right.
Let me just make one quick,
summary comment.
Which is that if you're doing
this, one thing that should
always be true, is that these
integrals, when you evaluate
them- so here, I haven't been
writing an integrand.
I guess the integrand has always
been 1, or something.
But for any integrand, the
nature of this process is that
it shouldn't matter which
order you integrate.
You should get the same
answer if you
integrate dx dy or dy dx.
So one very low-level check that
you can make-- that you
haven't done anything horribly,
egregiously wrong
when changing the bounds
of integration--
is that you can check that
actually these things
evaluate the same.
Yeah?
Where you can choose any
function that you happen to
want to put in there--
function of x and y-- and
evaluate this integral, and
choose any function that you
happen to want to put in
there, and evaluate
those integrals.
And see that you actually get
the same thing on both sides.
Now one simple example is that
you could just evaluate the
integral as written with
a 1 written in there.
And so in both cases, what you
should get is the area of the
region when you evaluate
an integral like that.
But you can also check
with any other
function if you wanted.
It won't show that what you've
done is right, but it will
show if you've done
something wrong.
That method will sometimes
pick it out, right?
Because you'll actually be
integrating over two different
regions, and there's no
reason you should
get the same answer.
So if you were to compute
these integrals and get
different numbers, then you
would know that something had
gone wrong at some point for
sure, and you'd have to go and
figure out where it was.
I think I'll end there.