Today I would like to talk to
you about some of the research
that I did during my early days
at MIT.
It's a long time ago.
I got my Ph.
in the Netherlands on nuclear
work and so the tension during
physics and I came over to MIT
in nineteen sixty-six.
I was supposed to be here only
for one year.
I had a one-year postdoc
position.
But I loved it so much I never
left.
I changed fields.
I joined the research group of
Professor Bruno Rossi.
Here at MIT I changed from
nuclear physics to x-ray
astronomy.
X-ray astronomy speaks for
itself.
You're trying to do astronomy
in x-rays.
You cannot see any x-rays from
the ground because the earth
atmosphere absorbs them
completely.
So you have to go outside the
atmosphere unlike optical
astronomy and radio astronomy
which you can do from the
ground.
When I use the word x-rays I'm
thinking of the kind of x-rays
that your dentist would be
using, medical purposes,
about one to fifty kilo
electron-volts.
And since all of you took eight
oh two you should know by now
what a kilo electron-volts.
Uh optical light is two
electron volts,
where x-rays,
way more energetic than optical
light.
Uh during the Second World War
Werner von Braun in Peenemunde
developed under Hitler Germany
destructive rockets.
They were used to destroy the
Allies.
To destroy you and me.
And after the war,
around nineteen forty-eight,
the Americans used these
rockets to do science.
They also got Werner von Braun
over to this country and for
reasons unknown to me he became
a hero.
They tried to observe x-rays
from the solar system.
And they found indeed that the
sun
emits x-rays.
The sun is very close.
So you may say well that's not
a surprise.
But it's really very unusual
because to create x-rays you
need extremely high
temperatures,
which we didn't think existed
on the sun.
And if you take the power that
the sun puts out in x-rays,
this is joules per second now,
and you divide that by the
power in the optical and the
infrared light of the sun,
this symbol stands for sun,
that ratio is about ten to the
minus
seven.
So you must conclude that the
sun emits largely optical light
and infrared and that the amount
of x-rays is a modest byproduct.
Interesting as it is all by
itself.
In nineteen sixty-two several
scientists here in Cambridge,
Massachusetts,
among them Bruno Rossi and
Riccardo Giacconi and Herb
Gursky, made an attempt to
observe x-rays from stars
outside our solar system.
The odds were strongly against
them.
The detectors were not
sensitive enough.
If you take the sun and you
bring the sun to the nearest
stars, which is a distance say
of ten light-years,
then there would be no hope
that you would be able to detect
x-rays from an object like the
sun.
In fact the detectors were too
insensitive by about a factor of
one billion.
They tried anyhow and they were
successful.
They did indeed find to
everyone's surprise and joy,
they found x-rays
from at least one object
outside the solar system.
This object was later called
SCO X one.
SCO stands for the
constellation Scorpio in the sky
and X for x-rays and one for the
first source observed in that
constellation.
We now know that this object is
a faint blue star.
And what is extremely special
about the object SCO X one is
that if you take the ratio x-ray
power over optical power then
that ratio is
about ten to the third.
Compare that with the sun.
This object,
we had no clue what it was in
those days, primarily emit
x-rays, and the optical emission
is a byproduct.
Whereas with the sun it is
reversed.
And so the burning question was
in those days what kind of
animal is this?
It must be a totally different
beast.
Something very different from
our sun.
And when I came to MIT in
nineteen sixty-six,
there were six sources known
outside our solar system.
And they were all discovered
with rockets.
The rockets in those days could
spend about five minutes above
the earth atmosphere and they
would quickly make a scan over
the sky, five minutes,
that's all they had.
And I joined the group of uh
George Clark,
who is still at MIT,
uh he was doing x-ray astronomy
from very high-flying balloons,
very close to the top of the
atmosphere, and the advantage of
balloons was that you could
observe the sky for
many many hours,
if you're lucky sometimes even
a day or more.
But on the other hand,
since there is always a little
bit of atmosphere left above
you, even though there's very
little, there is still some
left, the x-rays are absorbed,
almost all x-rays below twenty
kilo electron-volts would be
absorbed, and we would not be
able to see them.
But of course the compensation
was that we could look at the
sky for many many many hours.
Nowadays no one is doing these
balloon observations anymore.
No more rocket observations.
Everything is done of course
from satellites.
So when I came to MIT,
together with George Clark,
I developed new x-ray detectors
for these balloon observations.
Many graduate students were
involved.
Many undergraduates.
It would take about two years
to build a telescope.
To give you a rough idea it
would take a million dollars in
terms of nineteen sixty-six
dollars, and the weight of such
a telescope
would be roughly a thousand
kilograms.
The balloons in those days
would cost about a hundred
thousand dollars to get us up to
these high altitudes,
and we would need about eighty
thousand dollars of helium,
and you will see some slides of
that.
We have to go to altitudes of
about a hundred forty thousand
feet.
We had huge balloons for that.
You will see one.
They have diameters of about
six hundred feet.
And the material was
polyethylene.
Extremely thin to make them
light-weight so that they can go
high.
The thickness of that
polyethylene was about half of
one-thousandth of an inch.
Which is thinner than the saran
wrap that you have in the
kitchen.
It is thinner than cigarette
paper.
A very risky business to fly
these balloons.
No guarantee of course that
they would work.
You pay your money.
If they work that's great.
If they don't work that's just
tough luck.
There is a good chance that you
have a failure when you launch
the balloon.
They're very fragile.
There could be damage right at
the launch.
But even if they make it up in
the atmosphere they have to go
through
the tropopause,
near about a hundred thousand
feet where it's very very cold,
the balloons get brittle,
and then they can burst.
And that of course would be the
end then of that balloon flight.
And that could also be the end
of a Ph.D.
thesis.
Because that all these flights
of course were connected with
research and therefore with Ph.
in the Netherlands on nuclear
work and so the tension during
these early phases of the launch
were always extremely high.
Sometimes even unbearable.
So now I would like to show you
some slides.
Which will give you a good idea
of what these expeditions were
like.
Oh, yeah, a classic problem.
This is nice that these -- ah,
now they work.
All right, so if I can have the
first slide,
you see here Jim and Pat who at
the time were undergraduates,
they are now both Ph.D.s,
and they are working there,
very tedious work,
trying to put the electronics
together.
You may think that science is
not very romantic.
But I can assure you it is.
They fell in love.
They married.
They have kids.
And that's the way it sometimes
goes in life.
And so here you see the plant
in Texas where these huge
balloons were made.
Uh balloons are put together
sort of like the -- the way that
the tangerine is put together.
At the surface you see these
gores of the balloon.
And the sealing of these gores
to make up the balloon were --
was only done by women.
Only women were allowed to work
there.
Has nothing to do with sex
discrimination of any kind.
It just turned out that women
were
more patient.
They did the work better.
They make way fewer mistakes
than men did.
That's the way it goes
sometimes in life.
Here you see balloon coming out
of the box.
Nicely protected.
Plastic cover.
And we also have here cloth on
the -- on the grass because the
balloon is so thin that it would
certainly get damaged if it
touches the grass,
it's enormously thin.
This was not my balloon.
Uh we were worried that there
was something wrong with it.
You can see here the concern.
They thought it was a -- there
was a hole in the balloon.
And that if there is a hole in
the balloon there's just nothing
you can do about it anymore.
You can't patch it because the
hole is almost always through
many many layers.
What you're looking at here is
hundreds of layers of balloon
that are folded together.
But as I said,
since it wasn't my balloon I
wasn't too worried,
but of course it's never nice
if you see a failure of your
colleagues.
Now I bring you to the desert
town Alice Springs in uh
Australia.
Right at the heart of
And now you get a pretty good
idea of what it's like.
Here you see the launch truck.
The telescope is there.
And then you see this
enormously big balloon.
All of it is empty now and most
of this will stay empty.
This is the roller arm which
holds this part down.
This is the only part that will
be inflated.
And here you see the helium
truck.
And here you see the inflation
tubes.
And we will let helium in from
both sides which will then
gradually begin to fill this top
part of the balloon.
And you see here the roller arm
in detail.
The roller arm is very
important because when this part
of the balloon is being filled
it wants to lift,
it wants to go up,
and of course you have to keep
it down, you have to keep it
under control.
And so this roller arm and this
-- this car is loaded down with
concrete.
It's very heavy.
And then just before the launch
this roller arm by command is
fweet flipped over and then as
you will see later then the
balloon will make it up.
And here you see the early part
of the inflation.
Helium comes in from both
sides.
And so we -- we fly these
balloons almost always early
morning because then the winds
are very calm.
You need extremely reliable
winds.
You need to know the direction
very well.
And the winds should be uh no
more than something like three
or four miles per hour.
If they are stronger you would
lose
the balloon.
You see here these gores that I
mentioned to you earlier.
Where the sun is behind the
balloon.
Here the bubble is nearly fully
inflated now.
Here it's still going on.
Still going on,
the inflation.
But we are very close to the
end of the inflation.
Here is the roller arm and then
in this direction here five
hundred feet or so down is the
payload with the truck.
We're now very close to a
launch.
We're still in Alice Springs.
This is -- was my graduate
student Jeff McClintock at the
time.
He's now Doctor McClintock.
Here you see radar reflectors
which allows us to follow the
balloon -- radar.
Here you see the telescope
hanging on the launch truck.
Here is the roller arm.
All this is empty.
And here you see the parachute.
We have here a connection
between the parachute and the
bottom of the balloon.
And we can control that on
radio command.
We can separate that so that
the telescope safely comes back
to earth.
At least that's the idea on
paper.
And so now you see the release
of the bubble.
So the roller arm is up and
this bubble now takes off.
This is an incredibly fantastic
moment.
This is really butterflies in
your stomach and ants in your
pants.
This is the moment that balloon
can easily fail.
Very thin material,
the helium goes up,
reflects against the top,
is pushed back again,
you get this peculiar mushroom
shape, it makes an enormous
sound like a storm.
The idea now is that this
balloon will go higher and
higher in the sky.
Will pick up all this empty
part.
This is not inflated.
As the balloon goes up in the
atmosphere the atmospheric
pressure will go down.
And the helium will expand and
will fill the balloon.
And the -- the trick now is for
this truck to manipulate,
to maneuver itself under what
we
call the bubble.
And therefore the wind has to
be in this direction so that the
balloon comes to the truck.
And then the truck tries to get
straight under the balloon.
And then the payload will be
released here.
Here you see a close-up of this
mushroom.
You can actually see this
reflection of the helium going
up and coming back.
You can also see these gores
very clearly.
It's tedious work.
By these women who have to seal
these balloons.
Enormous amount of labor goes
into it.
Amount of helium as I said
earlier is about eighty thousand
dollars.
About the same price of the
balloon.
And here it goes higher.
We're in Alice Springs.
The cover is falling off.
Balloon is going up.
See the engine is already
running.
The truck cannot move yet
because if it started to move
this part of the balloon would
slide over the cloth.
There would be friction and
there would be holes in the
balloon.
So this truck has to wait until
all of this is off the ground.
Going higher.
And I'm now so close to the
balloon that I couldn't continue
my picture-taking from Alice
Springs.
So I will jump back to an
earlier flight in the United
States.
We flew these balloons in the
United States from a town called
Palestine, Texas.
And so you will see then the
remaining part of the flight
from Palestine,
Texas.
So the balloon is now
completely off the ground.
See a little bit of gas,
well it's not so little,
but it looks very little
compared to the size of this
balloon.
You see the parachute here and
here then is the connection
which on radio command we can
separate.
So now this is a very crucial
moment.
The person in charge on this
launch truck has probably driven
the truck to get straight under
the balloon.
And when it's straight under
there
they will allow the payload to
go free.
The payload is attached to this
truck.
If the balloon is too far ahead
and the payload is released it
will pendulum into the ground.
And if you release it too early
then of course the payload will
pendulum back into the launch
truck.
Both would be a disaster.
If the pull of the balloon is
not enough, for instance if a
hole developed during the
launch, so if the tension is not
strong enough,
you would release the payload,
it would go bang,
back to the ground.
So all these factors have to be
taken into account,
and then finally the person in
charge commits to a launch.
And then there it goes.
All the way empty.
Here you see the helium.
The parachute.
And you see the -- the payload.
And here you see the balloon at
a hundred fifty thousand feet,
forty-five kilometers high in
the sky.
The helium has now expanded.
The balloon is fully inflated.
And you can look straight
through it.
It's only half of
one-thousandth of an inch of
polyethylene.
And these are huge ducts which
have openings of about ten
meters each.
And they are there because the
balloon cannot stand any
over-pressure.
If there is any over-pressure
the balloon would pop and so
when the balloon keeps rising
and rising and rising when it
reaches -- reaches its maximum
volume the helium would escape
at the bottom.
That's the idea of these ducts.
Here you see George Ricker who
was graduate student,
my graduate student at the
time.
This is in Australia.
He is now Doctor Ricker.
He's still at MIT.
He's a staff member.
And this is the kind of
equipment that we built,
at least partially.
And he is checking the early
results during the ascent of the
balloon.
The balloon will go up with
about a thousand feet a minute.
If all goes well,
there's no leak,
it will take about
two-and-a-half,
three hours to make it to
altitude.
You see me here sitting on the
plane that we used to follow the
balloon.
We fly of course at much lower
altitudes.
Five thousand,
ten thousand feet.
We stay as close to the balloon
as we possibly can.
It's not always so -- not
always easy, certainly not in
Australia.
And so we keep an eye on things
and if necessary we can
terminate the balloon flight by
giving a radio command so that
the parachute comes down.
Certainly when we get close to
the ocean of course that is
necessary if
you don't want to lose the
payload.
The data -- data come back via
radio, so we wouldn't lose the
-- the data.
You get very sick,
by the way in these planes.
If you're sitting for eight or
ten or twelve hours or longer in
these planes as I have,
I learned actually a little bit
of flying which is quite easy
with a plane like this.
Here you see a map of
Australia.
Here's Alice Springs.
Uh we fly pro-balloons weather
balloons at a hundred forty
thousand feet every
day to find out in what
direction the balloon would be
drifting.
And we had all reason to
believe that the balloon would
drift somewhere in this
direction.
And we alerted these radar
stations.
These circles here are radar
Because there are no airfields
here in Australia.
And so we knew we couldn't
follow the balloon.
We would probably lose it.
And therefore we alerted these
radar stations.
They could tell us then when
the balloon was in sight.
And that would allow us then to
cut the balloon,
cut the payload loose and --
and make the recovery.
Instead, the balloon went
straight south.
So the predictions by the
weather balloons were not too
accurate.
The balloon went straight
south.
And here there was sunset and
then we don't know too precisely
where the balloon was.
Remember this was in the
nineteen seventies.
And so we were uncertain.
But here about twenty-six hours
later when we were getting close
to Melbourne which we were not
allowed to enter the air space
here between Sydney and
Melbourne we cut the balloon
loose.
That means we separate the
payload from the balloon.
The balloon is very brittle.
It's extremely cold up there.
The balloon then fractures and
comes down in many pieces and if
everything worked well then
parachute opens and brings the
payload safely back to earth.
And then comes the big problem
how are you going to recover the
payload.
You're in the middle of
nowhere.
This balloon came down,
this payload came down in the
desert.
And there are no airports.
At
least the chances are that you
are a few hundred miles away
from the nearest airport with
your payload.
So what you do then is the
following.
You try to find a house close
to where the payload is located.
We locate the payload.
We see the stuff come down.
Radio beacons on the payload.
And then you fly over that
house many many times in a very
obnoxious way.
You make a -- a lot of noise.
You fly over very low.
And so the people who -- whose
next neigh- neighbor is probably
se- seventy miles away from
them know what you're trying to
tell them.
You're trying to draw their
attention.
And they know what that means
is that they want you -- they
want you to meet them at the
airport.
Whatever airport means.
It's sometimes just a strip in
the desert.
You can't land there at night
but you can land there during
the day.
And so that's exactly what we
did.
We drew attention to the house
of this guy Jack.
He was -- he was a complete
nut, he was always drunk,
was a crazy guy.
And so we went to the airstrip
and we waited and indeed after
fifteen
hours he showed up with this
truck.
Uh there is no windshield here
in the -- in the truck.
And he used to shoot kangaroos
there.
He would go sixty miles per
hour on the desert floor and he
would -- he would shoot
kangaroos.
And he gave me a demonstration.
Uh he put his dog on the roof.
He would go sixty miles an
hour.
And he would slam the brakes.
And then the dog would catapult
through the air,
the poor dog.
And then all he would say is
oh, you can't teach an old dog
any new tricks.
And he seemed to enjoy that.
When we go after the payload
the plane, the recovery plane,
is in the air.
Takes off from that airstrip
and we have contact with the
recovery plane.
They and only they can see and
know where the payload is.
From the ground of course you
can't tell.
And so they maneuver you to the
payload.
And so of course Jack's help
was invaluable.
We needed him.
That was independent from the
fact that the man was a little
strange.
On these recoveries you
encounter many animals.
You see a koala bear here.
In a l- eucalyptus tree.
Very lazy animal.
Unlike most of you.
And then when we came close to
the payload there was this
animal, a goanna,
six-feet tall goanna.
I'll tell you,
it scared the hell out of me.
And uh I didn't want to show
that to my graduate student who
was with me and I said to him
look you know these a- these
animals are completely harmless,
why don't you go first.
This animal was no farther than
four feet from the payload.
And so my graduate student went
first and the amazing thing is
during the ten hours that it
took us to recover the payload
and put it back on Jack's truck
this animal never moved.
It was just sitting there
completely still.
This is their way of trying not
to be noticed.
And so here you see the
payload.
This was Alice,
was Jack's wife,
this is Tom Brooks,
he came from the United States,
he was an electronic expert.
And you see here the payload.
It looks heavily damaged but it
really isn't.
This is crash pad which
protects the payload when it
impacts.
And an impact crash pad worked
very well, very little damage to
this payload.
And then you come back after
several days to Alice Springs.
Alice Springs is a hole in the
ground.
Nothing ever happens there.
And so obviously you make it to
the front page of the Centralian
Advocate.
Perfect balloon launch,
thousand watch start of space
probe.
They think of this as a space
probe which is fine.
Balloon professor is back in
Alice.
They called me there the
balloon professor.
I gave -- I gave several talks
there for high schools and for
uh the Rotary Club.
So I was a sort of a local
celebrity.
I talked to the uh news
reporter for
several hours.
And when you read this story
you won't believe the nonsense
but that's all a detail of
course.
OK, that's enough for the
slides for now.
I had si- about twenty
successful s- flights.
Between nineteen sixty-six and
nineteen eighty.
Many from the United States.
From Canada and also from
Australia.
Where that's a s- southern
hemisphere which covers part of
the sky that we cannot see from
the United States.
I had two free falls.
Two of my balloon burst on the
way up in the tropopause.
We were unable to separate
payload fast enough and then the
whole thing, parachute gets
entangled.
You get a free fall.
Big hole in the ground and
that's the end of the telescope.
And it was.
Twice did I lose the telescope
completely.
But I was lucky and I made
several interesting discoveries
during those successful flights.
We discovered very early on
five new x-ray sources.
None of them had ever been seen
with the rockets.
And several of these sources,
that was the really new thing,
were highly variable.
They changed their x-ray
intensity on a very short time
scale.
We noticed even one source went
up by a factor of three in about
ten
minutes.
And that of course could not
have been discovered with
rockets.
Because the rockets were only
above the atmosphere for five
minutes.
They would quickly scan the sky
and so there's no way they could
discover variability on a time
scale of tens of minutes.
But with balloons you can do
that.
So it did pay off that we were
watching the sky sometimes for
ten, twenty hours.
Our -- my longest balloon
flight was actually twenty-six
hours.
We also observed x-rays from
one source
which we named GX one plus
four.
Which stands the one plus four
stands for the position in the
sky.
And um this showed a periodic
signal in x-rays.
About two point three minutes
periodicity.
At the time we had no clue what
that meant but later of course
we understood the significance
of that.
And you will understand that
also very shortly.
How significant that was.
So what kind of objects are
they?
They are very very different
from the sun.
And we now know what they
are.
These objects are binaries.
Binary stars.
One star is not unlike the sun,
it's a normal nuclear burning
star.
And it is in orbit with a
neutron star or in some cases a
black hole.
They go around each other.
And if they are close enough
together it is possible that the
matter of this star is attracted
by this neutron star with a
larger force than it is
attracted
by the star itself.
And if that's the case this
matter doesn't want to stay
here.
But wants to go to the neutron
star.
Now of course the matter has
angular momentum because they
goes around.
So it cannot free fall to the
neutron star.
But it would spiral in and
slowly make its way to the
neutron star.
And we call this an accretion
disk.
And we call this the donor,
provides the fuel for the
transfer of mass onto the
neutron star.
And let's assume that the
neutron star has a mass capital
M and has a radius R.
And let's assume that we dump
some matter, little M,
onto the neutron star.
Well all of you should remember
from eight oh one that you can
calculate very easily the speed
with which this matter reaches
the neutron star.
The kinetic energy,
one-half MV
squared, must be equal to MMG
over R.
We had this equation on the
blackboard last lecture when we
discussed cosmology.
It was the same equation.
This is the speed with which
the matter will fall onto the
neutron star.
If this is the mass of the
neutron star and this is the
radius of the neutron star.
You lose the -- the mass as you
always do.
And so you can calculate this
speed.
This speed is horrendous
because the radius of a neutron
star
is so ridiculously small.
The mass of a neutron star is
very comparable to the mass of
the sun.
A little larger.
But not much larger.
But the radius is a hundred
thousand times smaller than that
of the sun.
It's only ten kilometers.
And as a result of that the
speed with which the matter hits
the neutron star is about
one-third of the speed of light.
When it hits the neutron star
this kinetic energy is converted
to heat.
It will heat up the surface
layers of the neutron star and
increases
the temperature to about um ten
million, a hundred million
degrees, and at such high
temperatures,
the star would emit almost all
its radiation in x-rays and not
in the optical.
Our sun is relatively cold.
It's only six hundred six
thousand degrees.
And so the sun has most of its
radiation in the optical but
when the temperature becomes ten
million, a hundred million
degrees, the maximum of the
emission is in x-rays.
To give you a little bit
respect, a little bit of
insight, for this incredible
power,
for this incredible
gravitational pull of the
neutron star,
because R is so small,
if you took a marshmallow and
you threw a marshmallow from a
large distance onto the surface
of a neutron star,
at impact the energy that is
going to be released is
comparable to the energy of an
atomic bomb as was thrown on
Hiroshima and Nagasaki near the
end of the Second World War.
Neutron stars have very strong
magnetic fields.
And the matter that flows from
the donor onto the neutron star
is ionized.
It's plasma.
It's charged.
And as you remember from eight
oh two when you have a charged
particle in a magnetic field
there is the V cross B term.
The V cross B force.
And the V cross B force will
then spiral these charged
particles around the magnetic
field lines and they would end
up near the magnetic poles,
not unlike the solar wind when
it reaches the earth,
these charged particles enter
the earth atmosphere near the
magnetic poles,
giving rise to aurora as we
discussed earlier.
And so you end up on the
neutron star with two hot spots
where this matter slams into the
neutron star.
At the magnetic poles.
And if the axis of rotation of
the neutron star is not the same
as the -- [Audience noise] Q:
Tall male physicist.
[noise] Hi, Miss Peltier.
[laughter] I remember your
name.
[laughter] You were in my eight
oh one class.
Q: [unintelligible] Q:
[noise] And [unintelligible]
physics, is this a physics
lecture?
Ask the students.
I don't know.
[laughter] Q:
Very handsome and charming.
OK.
[laughter] So are you.
[laughter] Q:
[unintelligible]
I think you know the answer to
that one.
Q: OK, I think we have the
right person.
[background noise] Q:
We have a song to sing to you.
Q: [unintelligible] [tone]
Singing: When I
wisdom, times have changed.
Singing: Maxwell's equations
are too hard for me,
so please just help me,
help me.
Singing: Help.
I need somebody.
Help.
Not just anybody.
You know I need someone.
Walter.
Singing: When I was younger,
so much younger than today.
I never needed anybody's help
in any way.
But now these days are gone,
I'm not so self-assured,
now I've found my homework's
hard, no nothing anymore.
Singing: Help me if you can I'm
failing now.
Walter Lewin,
can't do physics,
I don't know how.
I am on pass-fail,
don't let me down.
Singing: Won't you please
please pass me.
When I was dumber,
so much dumber than today,
I didn't know about Lentz,
Maxwell
or Faraday.
Singing: But now those days are
gone, I'm not so dumb no more.
Thanks to eight oh two and our
daring professor.
Help me if you can I'm failing
now.
Singing: Walter Lewin,
can't do physics,
I don't know how.
I am on pass-fail don't let me
down.
Singing: Won't you please
please pass me.
Walter Lewin thanks for
teaching eight oh two.
Now it's summer and we will all
miss you.
Singing: You've been crazy and
we've all had a good time.
So in your praise the Muses'
voices chime.
Singing: Eight days a week.
I love you.
Eight days a week.
Is not enough to show I care.
Singing: Thanks for all you've
done, I'll pass somehow.
E and M can't get
me down, I know this now.
I'll miss pass-fail next year,
this I vow.
Singing: Won't you please
please pass me,
pass me, pass me,
ooh.
I have tears in my eyes.
[applause] So that was very
nice.
So now you won't have any time
to fill out your evaluation
form.
So I was going to um talk to
you about the um show you some
evidence for these binary
systems.
So we have these hot spots on
the neutron star and as the
neutron star rotates then and
the axis of rotation doesn't
coincide with the dipole,
magnetic dipole axis,
you're going to see hot spot,
hot spot, hot spot,
hot spot, and that explains
then the x-ray
pulsations.
Uh you can also see in some
cases x-ray eclipses.
If the neutron star as seen
from the earth hides behind the
donor star which is much bigger
then all the x-rays are absorbed
and so the x-rays stop
completely.
You go into an x-ray eclipse
and a few hours later you come
out of the x-ray eclipse again.
And that's what I would like to
show you the evidence for,
which came in the early
seventies.
With the satellite Uhuru,
the first slide is the basic
idea.
No, that was right,
uh John, John,
go back to that picture,
yeah, so you see here this is
of course a sketch,
this is not the real thing.
Here you see a star.
Not unlike the sun.
And then here you see the
neutron star.
In some cases a black hole.
And then the matter is being
sucked off this star because the
gravitational force in this
direction is larger.
Forms the accretion disk and
ends up on the neutron star.
And the next slide is then the
discovery of the early --
convincing discovery of a
pulsating system.
The rotation of the neutron
star.
This time scale here is about
one-and-a-quarter second.
And the data are here,
this is the data,
unfortunately in this
publication this -- this very
bold line dominates almost the
data, but the idea being very
clear that the x-ray signal,
this is the strength of the
x-ray signal,
this is time,
one-and-a-quarter seconds,
is oscillating
one-and-a-quarter second
periods.
And that's the rotation of the
neutron star.
And the next slide shows you of
the
same object,
it's called Hercules X one.
You see on a very different
time scale this is days.
You see that the x-ray
eclipses, that the x-rays
disappear completely when the
neutron star goes behind the
donor.
And the orbital period is one
point seven days.
The x-rays disappear
completely.
And so this picture is
well-established.
It's beyond a shadow of a doubt
we do know what these objects
are.
With no one is flying balloons
anymore I make all my reserv- o-
observations nowadays from
satellites using European
satellites, Japanese satellites
and American observatories.
Lately we have the Rossi timing
explorer in orbit and also
Chandra which is the biggest
thing in town.
Now between nineteen
seventy-five and nineteen
seventy-nine we were so
fortunate here at MIT that we
had our own private x-ray
observatory.
It was called Sas three.
It was an all-MIT operation.
We uh maneuvered it from my
building, Center for Space
Research,
Building thirty-seven,
twenty-four hours a day,
three hundred sixty-five days
per year.
It was at that time that Josh
Grindlay and John Heise had
discovered using a Dutch
satellite believe it or not --
they had discovered that some of
these x-ray sources showed
sudden x-ray bursts.
The x-ray intensity would rise
in about a few seconds,
would become ten,
twenty, thirty times stronger,
and then over a time scale of
maybe a few minutes,
the x-ray intensity would peter
out
again.
And we had this Sas three
observatory which ideally suited
to do research in these x-ray
bursts.
And we discovered within two
years eight new burst sources.
And I think it's fair to say
that it's largely due to our
observational work and also to
the theoretical work by
Professor Joss who was at MIT
and still is at MIT that we now
understand what these x-ray
bursts are.
They are huge nuclear bomb
explosions on the surface of a
neutron star.
The matter that falls onto the
neutron star is largely hydrogen
and helium.
Because that's the matter of
this star.
And the density and the
temperature on the surface of
the neutron star is so high that
you get nuclear reactions.
And three helium four nuclei
can fuse to carbon twelve.
And then energy is released.
And this nuclear reaction is
very unstable,
is extremely sensitive to the
temperature.
If the temperature goes up the
reaction rate is higher,
more energy is released.
Temperature goes up.
When the temperature goes up
the reaction rate goes up and so
on, more energy is released.
And the whole thing gets out of
hand.
You get a thermonuclear runaway
as we call it.
You see a thermonuclear flash.
A gigantic bomb explosion on
the surface of the neutron star.
These bomb explosions are about
eighteen orders of magnitude
more powerful than the most
powerful
hydrogen bombs that we can
build on earth.
So this -- this layer,
this fresh accreted layer,
goes up in one huge bomb
explosion and then new material
is accreted and a few hours
later you will see another bomb
explosion.
So you can see several of these
x-rays bursts per day.
The optical counterparts of
these stars, these binary
systems, uh are very faint,
but you can see them from the
--
the ground with uh optical
observatories from the ground.
And we had reasons to believe
at the time that simultaneously
with an x-ray burst you might
actually observe an optical
burst.
And I'll give you the reasons
why we believed that.
You see here the neutron star
and you see the accretion disk.
And let us assume that there is
an x-ray burst going on now.
These red wiggles is uh x-rays
from the x-ray burst.
The earth is in this direction.
So these x-rays reach the earth
first.
But there are x-rays which go
in this direction.
They are absorbed by the disk.
And then the disk heats up.
To thirty, forty thousand
degrees.
And starts to emit optical
light.
Some of that optical light will
go in the direction of the
earth.
And so what this means now is
that there is a delay between
these x-rays,
these -- this optical light and
these x-rays.
Because look.
This path length is longer to
us than this path length.
And therefore we were hoping
not only to be able to see an
optical flash,
which would mean the x-ray
heating of the disk with the
optical light from the disk,
but we were al- also hoping to
see the delay.
If you can measure the delay,
if you see a one-second delay,
it would mean that this
geometry was
roughly one light-second from
here to here.
And so we were very ambitious.
We organized a worldwide
campaign in the summer of
nineteen seventy-seven.
With Sas three we were going to
observe one particular x-ray
burst source in the sky for two
weeks on.
And we were asking observers
from the ground,
optical, radio,
infrared observers,
to keep an eye on that object
and also observe that,
all the time,
as long as they could.
Seventeen countries
contributed.
Forty-four observatories
Participated.
And during these two weeks we
saw one hundred and ten x-rays
bursts from this object with Sas
three, none was -- were observed
in the optical,
none were observed in the
radio.
In nineteen seventy-eight we
tried it again and we were
successful.
This was a collaboration with
Joss Grindlay who was at the
time at Harvard and my graduate
student Jeff McClintock who was
at that time already Doctor
McClintock.
He also was at Harvard and he
still is there.
It was a smashing success.
We made it to the cover of
Nature, which is a rather
prestigious uh scientific
journal.
It was covered by the New York
Times and by many newspapers in
the world.
So we were the first to be able
to detect simultaneously an
x-ray burst and an optical burst
from this binary system.
Uh the data that I want to show
you are not the nineteen
seventy-eight data.
But they are data from a year
later because they have better
quality.
We learned how to do it of
course.
These are the x-ray data not
from Sas three.
Because Sas three was no longer
in orbit in nineteen
seventy-nine.
This was a Japanese satellite
Hakucho.
And so here you see the times
in seconds, and here you see the
x-ray intensity and you see here
the x-ray burst as we observed
it with the Japanese observatory
Hakucho.
And here you see the optical
data which were taken by my
friend and colleague Holger
Pedersen.
He used a European southern
observatory in -- in Chile.
And he observed clearly an
optical flash.
This is the intensity of the
light before the x-ray burst and
then you see an incredible
increase and then you see a
decay.
I have plotted these so that
they both have the same height.
That of course is artificial.
But it makes it easier to
compare the two.
And so now comes the acid test.
If now I put one on top of
another then you see very
clearly that as we expected all
along that the optical signal is
indeed delayed relative to the
x-ray signal.
And you can now do the
measurement
that we hoped we could do.
You shift one curve on top of
another and if you shift it by
about two seconds then they're
almost carbon copies of each
other.
And so we succeeded then for
the first time to measure the
geometry of the accretion disk
around these neutron stars.
They have radii of very roughly
two light-seconds.
Light had to travel two seconds
more, first x-rays,
x-ray heating and then the
optical.
Two light-seconds is about
twice the distance from the
earth to the
moon.
So these systems are amazingly
compact, very small indeed.
Needless to say that during the
past term I haven't been able to
do any research,
no science at all,
eight oh two has swallowed up
everything that I had to offer
and more.
And I think you should feel
sorry for my graduate students.
And I think you have all the
right to feel guilty as well.
Uh you were on my mind all the
time and not only at MIT but
also at home,
in my living room,
my kitchen, when I took
showers, and even very often
appeared in my dreams.
Believe me, it was hell for my
-- for my significant other,
who is in the audience,
Susan, it wasn't very nice for
her.
Frankly, my life will change
after today.
I make myself no illusion
however.
Most of you will quickly forget
all four Maxwell's equations and
you will forget all about
induction and about
nonconservative fields.
I hope for you though that it
will not be before next week.
But surely when you will see a
rainbow you won't be able to
resist to check that the red is
on the outside and the blue is
on the inside.
It is a disease for which there
is no cure.
And if you carry your personal
polarizers with you,
then you will want to verify
that indeed the bows are
strongly polarized,
and if you do that I'll be very
proud of you.
And I hope those will be happy
memories.
Thank you for
attending my lecture. [applause]