JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture you discussed
the sum of the inverse
trigonometric functions as part
of your discussion of
inverse functions in general,
and implicit differentiation.
And I just wanted to talk about
one, briefly, that you
didn't mention in lecture, as
far as I recall, which is the
inverse cosine.
So what I'm going to call
the arc cosine function.
So I just wanted to go briefly
through its graph and its
derivative.
So here I have the graph of the
curve, y equals cosine x.
So this is a, you know--
you should have seen this
before, I hope.
So it has at x equals 0 it
has its maximum value 1.
And then to the right
it goes down.
Its first 0 is at pi over 2.
And then it has its trough
at x equals pie.
And then it goes
back up again.
And, OK, and it's an even
function that looks the same
to the right and the
left of the y-axis.
And it's periodic with
period 2 pi.
And it's also, you know, what
you get by shifting the sine
function, the graph of the
sine function to the
left by pi over 2.
So, OK, so this is y
equals cosine x.
So in order to graph y equals
arc cosine of x, we do what we
do for every inverse function,
which is we just take the
graph and we reflect it across
the line, y equals x.
So I've done that over here.
So this is what we get when
we reflect this curve--
the y equals cosine x curve--
when we reflect it through
that diagonal line,
y equals x.
So one thing you'll notice
about this is
that it's not a function.
Right?
This curve is not the graph of
a function because every, all
these humps on cosine x--
there are more humps
out here--
those horizontal lines cut
the humps in many points.
And when you reflect you get
vertical lines that cut this
curve in many points.
So it doesn't pass the
vertical line test.
So in order to get a function
out of this, what we have to
do is we just have to take a
chunk of this curve that does
pass the vertical line test.
And so there are many, many
ways we could do this.
And we choose one basically
arbitrarily, meaning we could
make a different choice, and
we could do all of our
trigonometry around some other
choice, but it's convenient to
just choose one and if everyone
agrees that that's
what that one is then we can
use it and it's nice.
We have a function and we can,
the other ones are all closely
related to this one choice
that we can make.
So in particular here, I think
there's an easiest choice,
which is we take the curve, y
equals arc cosine x to be just
this one piece of
the arc here.
So this has maximum--
so it goes from x equals
minus 1 to x equals 1.
And when x is minus 1 we have
y is pi, and then when x
equals 1 y is 0.
So this is the, this curve is
the graph of the function, y
equals arc cosine of x.
And if you want-- so there's a
notation that mathematicians
use sometimes to show that
we're talking about the
particular arc cosine function
that has this as its domain
and this as its range.
So we sometimes write
arc cosine and
it takes this domain--
the values between 1 and 1--
and it spits out values
between 0 and pi.
So this is a sort of fancy
notation that mathematicians
use to say the arc cosine
function takes values in the
interval minus 1, 1-- so
it takes values between
negative 1 and 1--
and it spits out values in
the intervals 0, pi.
So every value that it spits
out is between 0 and pi.
OK, so if you graph the
function, so now this is a
proper function.
Right?
It's single-valued, it
passes the vertical
line test. So, OK.
And so that's the graph of
y equals arc cosine of x.
So the other thing that we did
in lecture, I think we talked
about arc sine and
we graphed it.
And we talked about arc
tan and we graphed it.
And we also computed
their derivatives.
So let's do that for the
arc cosine, as well.
So what have we got?
Well so, in order to compute
the derivative--
this function is defined as
an universe function--
so we do the same thing that we
did in lecture, which is we
use this trick from implicit
differentiation.
So in particular, we have that
if y is equal to arc cosine of
x then we can take the
cosine of both sides.
And cosine of arc cosine, since
we've chosen it as an
inverse function, that
just gives us back x.
So we get cosine of
y is equal to x.
And now we can differentiate.
So what we're after is the
derivative of arc cosine of x,
so we're after dy dx.
So we differentiate this through
with respect to x.
So on the right hand
side we just get 1.
And on the left hand side, well,
we have a chain rule
here, right?
Because we have cosine of y,
and y is a function of x.
So this is, so the derivative of
cosine is minus sine y, and
then we have to multiply
by the derivative of
y, which is dy dx.
Now, dy dx is the thing we're
after, so we solve this
equation for dy dx and we get
dy dx is equal to minus 1
divided by sine y.
OK, which is fine.
This is a nice formula, but
what we'd really like,
ideally, is to express this
back in terms of x.
And so we can, well we can
substitute, right?
We have an expression
for y in terms of x.
So that's y is equal
to arc cosine of x.
So this is equal to minus
1 divided by sine of
arc cosine of x.
Now, this looks really ugly.
And here this is another place
where we could stop, but
actually it turns out that
because trigonometric
functions are nicely behaved
we can make this nicer.
So I'm going to appeal here
to the case where x is
between 0 and 1.
So then x, so then
we have a right
triangle that we can draw.
And the other case you can do a
similar argument with a unit
circle, but I'll just
do this one case.
So if, OK so arc cosine of x.
What does that mean?
That is the angle whose
cosine is x.
Right?
So if you draw a right triangle
and you make this
angle arc--
two c's--
arc cosine of x.
Well, that angle has cosine
equal to x so--
and this is a right triangle--
so it's adjacent side over the
hypotenuse is equal to x, and
one easy way to get that
arrangement of things is
say this side is x
and the side is 1.
So OK.
So what?
Why do I care?
Because I need sine
of that angle.
So this is the angle arc cosine
of x, so sine of that
angle is the opposite side
over the hypotenuse.
And what's the opposite side?
Well I can use the Pythagorean
theorem here, and the opposite
side is square root of
1 minus x squared.
That's the length of
the opposite side.
So the sine of arc cosine of x
is square root of 1 minus x
squared divided by 1.
So sine of arc cosine of
x is just square root
of 1 minus x squared.
So we can write this in the
somewhat nicer form, minus 1
over the square root of
one minus x squared.
So if you remember what the
derivative of arc sine of x
was, you'll notice that
this is a very
similar looking function.
And this is just because cosine
and sine are very
similar looking functions.
So in fact, the graph of arc
cosine is just a reflection of
the graph of arc sine, and
that's why the derivatives are
so closely related
to each other.
So OK, so there you go.
You've got the graph of arc
cosine up there and you've got
the formula for its derivative,
so that sort of
completes the tour of the
most important inverse
trigonometric functions.
So I think I'll end there.