Welcome back to recitation.
In this video I'd like
us to consider
the following problem.
So the question is for what
simple closed curve C, which
is oriented positively around
the region it encloses, does
the integral over C of minus the
quantity x squared y plus
3x minus 2y dx plus 4y squared
x minus 2x dy achieve its
minimum value?
So again, the thing we want to
find here, the point we want
to make, is that we have this
integral and we're allowed to
vary C. So we're allowed to
change the curve, the simple
closed curve.
And we want to know for what
curve C does this integral
achieve its minimum value?
So why don't you work on that,
think about it, pause the
video, and when you're feeling
like you're ready to see how I
do it, bring the
video back up.
Welcome back.
So again, what we would like to
do for this problem is we
want to take this quantity which
is varying in C and we
want to figure out a
way to minimize it.
To find its minimum value.
And actually what's interesting
to think about,
before we proceed any further,
is you might think you want to
take the smallest possible
simple closed curve you can.
In other words, you might want
to shrink it down to nothing.
But then this integral would be
0 and the question is, can
we do better?
Because we could have a minimum
value, of course,
that's negative.
And so we could do better by
having a larger curve put in
the right place.
So I just want to point that
out, if you were thinking why
just make C not actually a
curve, I just shrink it down
to nothing.
That won't be the
best we can do.
We can actually find a curve
that has an integral that is
not 0, but is in
fact negative.
And then we want to make it
the most negative we can.
So that's the idea.
So what we're going to do here
is we're going to use Green's
theorem to help us.
And so what we want to remember
is that if we have
the integral over C of M dx
plus N dy we want to write
that as the integral over R of
N sub x minus M sub y dx dy.
So what I want to point out, I'm
just going to write down
what these are.
I'm not going to take the
derivatives for you.
I'm just going to show
you what they are.
So in this case, with the M
and N that we have, we get
exactly this value
for the integral.
We get N sub x minus M sub y is
equal to x squared plus 4y
squared minus 4 dx dy.
You can obviously compute
that yourself.
Just take the derivative of N
with respect to x, subtract
the derivative of M with respect
to y, you get a little
cancellation and you
end up with this.
And so now, instead of thinking
about trying to
minimize this quantity over here
in terms of a curve, now
we can think about trying to
minimize the quantity here in
terms of a region.
And the goal here is to make
the sum of all of this over
the whole region--
we want to make it as negative
as we can possibly make it.
So essentially what we want to
do is we want on the boundary
of this region, we would like
the value here to be 0 and on
the inside of the region we'd
like it to be negative.
So let me point that out again
and just make sure we
understand this.
To make this quantity as small
as possible, what we would
like-- let me actually just
draw a little region.
So say this is the region.
To make this integral as small
as possible, what we want is
that x squared plus 4y
squared minus 4 is
negative inside the region.
So if this whole quantity is
less than 0 inside the region,
and we want it to, on
the boundary of the
region, equal 0.
And why do we want it to equal
0 on the boundary?
Well, that's because then we've
gotten all the negative
we could get and we haven't
added in any positive and
brought the value up.
So that's really why we want the
boundary of the region to
be exactly where this
quantity equals 0.
And so let's think about
geometrically
what describes R--
oops, that should have an s.
What describes R where x squared
plus 4y squared minus
4 is less than 0 inside R, and
that's the same thing as in
what we're interested in x
squared plus 4y squared minus
4 equals 0 on the
boundary of R.
And if you look at this, this is
really the expression that
will probably help you.
This expression, if you rewrite
it, you rewrite it as
x squared plus 4y squared
is equal to 4.
And you see that this is
actually the equation that
describes an ellipse.
Maybe you see it more often if
you divide everything by 4,
and so on the right hand side
you have a 1, and your
coefficients are fractional
potentially there.
But this is exactly the equation
for an ellipse.
And so the boundary of R is an
ellipse described by this
equation, but the boundary
of R is actually just C.
So C we now know is exactly the
curve that is carved out
by this equation on the plane,
on the xy plane.
That's an ellipse.
So just to remind you what
we were trying to do.
If you come back here, we were
trying to figure out a way to
minimize the certain integral
over a path.
And what we did was instead of
trying to look at a bunch of
paths and figure out what would
minimize that, we tried
to see if Green's theorem
would help us.
So Green's theorem allowed us to
take something that was an
integral over a path
and change it to an
integral over a region.
And then when we look at what
we ended up with, we realize
that we could make this as small
as the most minimum if
we let this be on the region
where it was negative
everywhere.
So we were looking for a region
where this quantity was
everywhere negative on the
inside and 0 on the boundary.
And that's exactly
what we did.
And then we see that we get to a
point where the boundary has
this equation, x squared plus
4y squared equals 4.
We see then the boundary's an
ellipse, and C is indeed the
boundary of the region.
So we see that C is the ellipse
described by this equation.
So that's where I'll stop.