This is number 3, 25-24.
Again, a classic, because we're
dealing with plane geometry.
We have a capacitor, two
capacitor plates, each area
'A', and they have a distance
between the plates,
which is 'd1' .
The thing that is given is 'U1'
, the total energy in the
system at this situation--
the 1 refers to this one.
Let me just write down again 'C'
equals 'Q' divided by 'V',
'U' equals '1/2 C 'V squared'',
and you've seen
this just right now--
it's also '1/2 Q V' and '1/2
'Q squared' divided by C'.
The question now is, what
happens when we decrease 'd1'
, when 'd1' becomes smaller?
We go from 'd1' to 'd2' , and
'd2' is smaller than 'd1' .
What happened with 'U'?
It is essential that you realize
as we squeeze this
together, there is no battery.
If there's no battery, there's
only one thing that cannot
change, and that is the charge
on the capacitor.
There is no way that charge is
kept or captured, so to speak,
on the plates, so no
matter how you move
it, that cannot change.
But if the charge cannot change,
then the electric
field cannot change-- but the
electric field, remember, is
'sigma' divided by
'epsilon 0'.
In the absence of a battery, we
can already say that 'Q' on
each plate is a constant,
and 'E' between
the plates is a constant.
Since the potential difference
between the plates is the
electric field times
the distance 'd'--
it's the integral
of E dot 'dl'--
it's immediately obvious that
if 'd' goes down, and if 'd'
remains the same, that
the potential
difference goes down.
You can easily calculate
how much that is.
'U2' , which is '1/2 Q V2' is
clearly lower than 'U1' ,
which is '1/2 Q V1' , because
'V2' is smaller than 'V1' ,
and the 'Q's are the same--
the 2 is smaller than that.
Now since 'U2' is smaller
than 'U1' --
the plates pull on each other,
because a system always wants
to go from high potential energy
to a lower potential
energy, and I can prove
that to you.
Here is a pen: I let it
go, and it falls.
This potential energy is higher
than a lower one, and
that's exactly the
same electricity.
If with a smaller distance the
total electric energy is
smaller, it means that the
system wants to become
smaller-- it means that 'd'
wants to become smaller.
It's immediately obvious why
'd' wants to be smaller,
because if you have the
capacitor, and if this side
were negative, and if this side
were positive, clearly
they attract each other--
they do want to go together,
and it makes all the
sense in the world.
If I, Walter Lewin,
increase 'd'--
so I now increase it--
then I have to do
positive work.
That's immediately obvious that
they want to go together,
and I want to pull them apart.
If they want to go together, and
I want to pull them apart,
I have to do positive work: that
means when I move them
apart, it's clear since I have
to do positive work, that's
the total potential energy,
electric energy in this case,
will increase.
I hope that you get
the connection--
smaller distance, slower
electric potential energy,
larger distance larger potential
energy, assuming
that there's no battery
connected.
If I increase 'd', then 'U' will
go up, 'V' will go up--
potential difference--
and the capacitance will go
down, because the capacitance
is inversely proportional to
'd', so if 'd' goes up, 'C'
will go down.
Now the situation changes
dramatically, because I'm
going to attach a battery--
when I attach the battery,
'Q' is not fixed anymore.
The only thing that is now
fixed is the potential
difference, so it's a very
different situation: 'Q' is
not fixed with the battery,
but now 'V' is fixed.
The potential difference
between the
plate cannot change.
Since 'U' equals '1/2 C 'V
squared'', and 'C' is
proportional to '1 over d', it
is immediately obvious that if
'd' goes down, 'C' goes up
therefore and 'V' remains
constant, that now since 'C'
goes up, 'U' goes up.
With the smaller distance, 'U2'
is now larger than 'U2' ,
so the situation is
exactly reversed.
'U' is also '1/2 Q V'--
'U' goes up, and 'V'
remains the same.
We also learn that 'Q'
goes up: that means a
current must flow.
The battery, which is connected
as we bring them
closer together, and more charge
appears on the plate--
that charge must be
provided by a
current from the batteries.