Now we go to problem number
two, which is 25-22.
It's a classic, and the reason
why it's a classic is because
Gauss' Law can be applied--
this is here inside
the sphere.
The inner sphere is metallic--
'R1' that is vacuum--
and the outer sphere is
also metallic, and has
the radius 'R2' .
This is probably
a solid sphere.
Remember, 'C' is 'Q'
divided by 'V'.
I will also write the total
energy of the system, which
equals '1/2 C V squared', also
'1/2 Q V', and it is also '1/2
Q squared over C'.
This is all the same: you can
apply any one of these three
as it suits you.
The question now is what is
the potential difference
between here and here if the
charge on this is '+Q' and the
charge on here is '-Q'?
The charge on here will be on
the inside of the sphere--
I leave you with the exercise
to prove that--
and the charge on the inner
sphere will be on the outside
of the sphere.
Whenever we have a problem like
that, you always go in
two steps: first, you calculate
the 'E' fields in
this gap, and then, two, you do
the integral of 'E dot dl'.
You go from, in this case, 'R1'
to 'R2' , and that's the
potential difference.
The question now is: what
is the 'E' field
here in this gap?
You apply a Gaussian sphere,
which has the
radius little 'r'--
you have done that several
times, and I will leave you
with that exercise.
You can prove very easily that
factorially 'E' equals capital
'Q' divided by ''4 pi epsilon
0' 'r squared'' times 'r
roof', pointing radially outward
because the inner
sphere is positive.
This holds only as long as 'r'
is smaller than 'R2 and larger
than 'R1' .
Now we want to do the potential
difference--
let me call this point 'a' and
let me call this point 'b'.
It doesn't matter how I go from
the inner sphere to the
outer sphere, so I call
it just 'Va - Vb'.
That is now 'Q' divided by '4
pi epsilon 0' times the
integral from 'R1' to 'R2' dr
dot 'r root'-- there's a dot
product there--
divided by 'r squared'.
As we discussed last time, the
dot product between two
vectors is a scalar--
this scalar is nothing but 'dr',
and this integral, then,
becomes a very easy one--
it is '1 over R1' minus
'1 over 'R2' .
This is larger than 0, for the
simple reason that 'R1' is
smaller than R2 , and so 'Va'
is larger than 'Vb' .
What is the total energy
of the system?
You can pick any one of
these equations--
any one of these three, I don't
care which-- you just
pick the one that is the
most convenient.
I would pick '1/2 Q V', because
'Q' was given, 'V' we
just calculated, and so
you're in business.
If you were interested in what
the capacitance is, then you
take 'Q' divided by 'V'.
We know 'Q', we just calculated
'V', and so you can
calculate the capacitance.
I want to stress that the
capacitance is independent of
'Q', and it is independent
of 'V'--
it only depends on geometry.