This is number 8 and
this is 25-2.
I have a huge plate.
There's an area 'A'
and there's a
charge '+Q' on the plate.
And I have at a separation
little 'd', same area 'A', and
I have '-Q' charge
on this one.
Well the electric field outside
these huge plates is
going to be 0, and I want
you to prove that
using Gauss' law.
'E' is 0 here and
'E' is 0 there.
And it's not because I am lazy,
but I also want you to
prove that the electric field
inside is constant--
I already anticipated that
earlier --and that the
electric field inside 'E' equals
the surface charge
density, 'sigma', divided
by 'epsilon 0'.
And the surface charge density
'sigma' is defined as 'Q' of
one of the plates divided by the
area of one of the plates.
So it is 'Q' divided by 'A'
divided by 'epsilon 0'.
That is the electric fields
and if the plates are very
large compared to 'd', it
is constant throughout.
There are some fringe
fields here.
We will ignore them and to a
very good approximation will
the 'E' field outside
the plates be 0.
The potential difference between
the plates, 'Delta V',
is the integral 'E dot dl'.
Well when you go from here to
here, 'E' and 'dl' will be in
the same directions.
So you've got a plus sign there
for the cosine of the
angle 'theta'.
The integral of 'dl' is simply
the separation 'd', so you get
that the potential difference
is that value 'E' that you
already calculated
here times 'd'.
And so that becomes 'Q'
divided by 'A',
'epsilon 0' times 'd'.
We define the capacitance of
two metal surfaces, spheres
and spheres or cylinders and
cylinders or planes parallel,
whatever, we define capacitance
as the charge of
one of them, assuming that the
charge on the other one is the
same, divided by the potential
difference between the two.
It is the ability to carry a
certain amount of charge for a
given potential difference.
If this number is large, it can
carry a lot of charge for
the same potential difference.
And after what we have just
done, you should be able to
show very easily that for
a plane capacitor, the
capacitance is 'A' times
'epsilon 0' divided by 'd'.
And the unit is in farads
in SI units.
It's linearly proportional
to the area.
The larger the area, the more
charge it can contain.
That is intuitive.
It's not so intuitive that is
inversely proportional to 'd'.