Let's start with problem
number one.
And I have a little introduction
to problem number
one that I want to start with.
If I have here what we call a
set of parallel capacitors,
point 'a', point 'b', and 'Va
- Vb', that's called a 'V'.
Higher here than there.
And this capacitance is 'C1',
and this capacitance is 'C2'.
They both see the
same voltage.
Well, it always holds that 'C
of i', which is capacitor i,
always has a charge 'Q of i'
on it, if the voltage over
that capacitor is 'V of i'.
This you can always use.
It's always true.
Now both capacitors see the
same voltage over them.
So therefore, the 'Q of 1'
equals 'C of 1' times 'V' and
'Q of 2' equals 'C
of 2' times 'V'.
And in this particular case,
where the two are parallel,
they have this in common.
And the 'Q's are clearly
different, because the 'C's
are different.
That's called parallel.
If now we go to series,
here we have two
capacitors in series.
'C1', C2'.
Point 'a', positive potential,
point 'b', let's call it 0,
negative potential.
And again, 'Va - Vb' is V.
Now there's something very
important I want you to
appreciate.
This part here has
no net charge.
Because as you connect this to
a battery, no electrons are
supposed to jump through
this vacuum.
It is true that this side
becomes positive of the
capacitor, therefore, this side
becomes negative by induction.
It is true that this side
becomes negative, and
therefore, that this side
of the capacitor
'C2' becomes positive.
But the net results here must
be that the net charge
negative here must exactly
cancel the
positive charge there.
That is very characteristic
for series.
Therefore, 'Q1' equals 'Q2' .
The charge on here is the same
as the charge on there.
Because charge left is charge
right, and charge left is
charge right.
So now we have 'Q' equals 'C1'
times 'V1' and we have 'Q'
equals 'C2' times 'V2'.
And now these two
are the same.
And so now, as you can see,
since 'C1' is not the same as
'C2', the potential difference
over 'C1', which is 'V1', will
be different from the potential
difference over 'V2'.
So here, the essential is that
the 'Q' is the same in each
case, but not the potential
difference.
If you work this out, then you
could easily show that 'V'
equals that 'Q' times '1 over
C1' plus '1 over 'C2'.
And this is often called
'1 over C equivalent'.
The 'C equivalent' is, so to
speak, replacing these two.
If you had a parallel set of
capacitors, then that 'C
equivalent' would become
'C1 + C2'.
And I'm sure you will have
no problems proving it.
So let's now go to problem
number one, and apply some of
what I've just told you.
To really have point 'a
positive', 'C1', 'C2', rather
complicated.
'C3'.
This point is called 'd'.
'C4'.
And here is 'b',
which is minus.
And the potential difference
'Va - Vb' equals 'V'.
And now one of the questions is,
what is the charge on each
of these capacitors?
The first thing I'm going to do,
I'm going to replace these
two by an equivalent
capacitor.
'1 over C1 prime'--
equivalent capacitor would
be 'C1 prime'--
equals '1 over C1'
plus '1 over C2'.
And then I'm going to replace
all 3 by an equivalent
capacitor, which I will
call 'C prime'.
And so we now have that 'C
prime' equals 'C3' plus 'C1
prime', which we just
calculated.
And so I have now reduced this
circuit to an entirely
different circuit.
I have now here 'C prime', and I
know how large 'C prime' is.
Then I have 'C4'.
This point is 'd', this
is 'a', and this is b.
Check for yourself, this
is exactly what
the circuit is now.
And if you go back to my
introduction, then the 'Q' on
'C prime' must be the 'Q' on
'C4', two capacitors in
series, and therefore,
I will call this 'Q'.
And so it's very easy to
calculate for you now what 'Vc
prime' is, the potential
difference over here, because
'C of i' equals 'Q of i' divided
by 'V of i', and it is
also very easy for you to
calculate what the potential
difference is over number 4.
Now let's go back to the
original scheme.
We have here 'a', and we have
here 'C1', and we have here
'C2', and we have here 'C3'.
This is point 'd'.
OK.
Let's leave it as it is now.
This is between 'a' and 'd'.
And I just leave
4 out for now.
There is a 4 here,
I realize that.
I want you now to concentrate
on this part.
And that part is exactly what I
covered in my introduction.
Therefore, 'Q1' must be 'Q2'.
The charge on here must be
the charge on this one.
And I would like you to--
I leave you with the problem.
Because you do know
what 'Va - Vd' is.
You know that because we
just did that only
thirty seconds ago.
So you can calculate now the
charge on here, and you can
calculate the charge on there.
'Q3' equals 'C3' times the
potential difference between
'a' and 'd', which we
just calculated.
I want to remind you that the
potential difference between
'a' and 'd' is nothing but
the potential difference
over that 'C prime'.
So you know 'Va - Vd' .
And so you can calculate now
charge here, charge there, and
you can calculate charge
there, and I will
leave you with that.
I don't think there's too much
more to this problem.
Rather straightforward, but
it can be a little nasty.