PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So today we're going to take a
look at solving differential
equations using the Laplace
transforms, and the problem
we're going to take a look at is
a simple ODE, x-dot plus 2x
equals 3 delta t plus
5 is a forcing on
the right hand side.
We're going to look at having
rest initial conditions, x of
0 minus is equal to 0, and we're
asked to use Laplace
transforms to solve this
initial value problem.
For part B, we're asked to have
the initial value problem
without any delta function
forcing on the right-hand side
to give it an equivalent initial
value problem without
it delta function forcing on
the right-hand side, but
yields the same solution
as in part A.
And then in question two,
we're asked to solve the
second order differential
equation, x-dot-dot plus 9x
equals u of t with rest initial
conditions, so x of 0
minus is 0, x-dot of
0 minus is also 0.
So I'll let you work on
this problem, and I'll
be back in a moment.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
OK, so for part A, the first
step is to Laplace transform
both sides of the equation.
So we take the Laplace transform
of x-dot plus 2x,
and that's going to be equal to
the Laplace transform of 3
delta of t equals 5.
And we can use the distribution
properties of the
Laplace transform, so this is
going to be Laplace transform
of x-dot plus 2 times the
Laplace transform of x.
On the right-hand side, we have
three times the Laplace
transform of the delta function
plus 5 times the
Laplace transform of 1.
Now, we can replace the Laplace
transform of x-dot if
we use the identity with s times
the Laplace transform of
x minus x 0 minus.
And we're told that x of 0 minus
in this case is just 0,
so this term's going
to vanish.
And just for brevity, I'm going
to write x of s as the
Laplace transform of x.
So we now have s times x of s
plus 2x of s equals, and on
the right-hand side, we have
three times the Laplace
transform of the
delta function.
Laplace transform of the delta
function is just one, so we
have 3 plus 5, and the Laplace
transform of 1
is just 1 over s.
So I can now factor the
left-hand side, and I get x of
s times s plus 2 equals
3 plus 5 over s.
And note how, when we have
x of s multiplied by some
polynomial in s, this is
always going to be the
characteristic polynomial.
So if we look back, s plus
2 is the characteristic
polynomial of x-dot plus 2x.
So this yields 3 divided by s
plus 2, on the right-hand
side, plus 5 divided by
s times s plus 2.
And for the second piece, we can
use partial fractions to
decompose it into a term times
s and a term times s plus 2.
And when we do that, we end up
getting 5/2 1 over s minus 1
over s plus 2.
So I can combine the 3 divided
by s plus 2 with the minus 5/2
divided by s plus
2 into one term.
So this gives you 1/2 1 over
s plus 2, and we also
have 5/2 1 over s.
And now we just take the inverse
Laplace transform of
both sides.
So on the left-hand side, we
recover x of t, so we get 1/2
e to the minus 2t plus 5/2.
The inverse Laplace transform
of 1/s is just 1.
So we end up with x of t is 1/2
e to minus 2t plus 5/2,
and this solution is valid
for t bigger than 0.
Sometimes, people write it as
this quantity multiplied by
step function.
And x of t is also 0 for t
less than 0, for example.
And it's just useful to quickly
sketch what x of t
looks like, so it's an
exponential decay for t bigger
than 0, and it's flat
for t less than 0.
So here's our x of t.
So for part B, now, we're asked
to find a differential
equation and new initial
conditions that reproduce the
solution offered t
bigger than 0.
So note how we'd be looking for
a new solution, x of t,
which would be an exponential
decay.
And essentially, we just grow,
so we're looking at initial
conditions, which start at 0.
If I were to write the original
differential equation--
So this is the original
differential equation from
part A. Looks like this.
And just quickly to note that
x-dot near the origin is going
to be approximately three times
the delta function,
which means in the original
differential equation, x is
going to have a jump of three
about the origin.
So the new initial
value problem--
Well, we don't want the delta
function on the right-hand
side, so we're going to solve
x-dot plus 2x is equal to 5.
But what initial conditions
do we need?
Well, we need x of 0
minus to now be 3.
So when we eliminate the 3 delta
on the right-hand side,
we have to introduce new initial
conditions so that the
solution agrees for
t bigger than 0.
OK, so this concludes
part one.
For part two, we're asked to
solve a new differential
equation, x-dot-dot plus 9x
equals u of t, and we're just
going to follow the same
procedure where we Laplace
transform both sides.
So Laplace transforming the
left-hand side gives me
x-dot-dot plus 9x equals the
Laplace transform of u of t.
And again, I can use the
formula, which relates
derivatives of x back to the
Laplace transform of x, and so
in this case, the Laplace
transform of x-dot-dot is
going to be s squared times the
Laplace transform of x.
And then I'm going to have plus
a term which involves x
of 0 minus and a term which
involves x-dot of 0 minus.
And if your initial conditions
were not 0, you would have to
keep these terms in.
However in our case, these terms
are both 0 because we
deal with rest initial
conditions, I'm just not going
to write them.
Plus 9x of s equals the Laplace
transform of u oft is 1/s.
So again, we have x
of s s2 plus 9--
so note again how this is the
same characteristic polynomial
as in our differential
equation--
Is equal to 1/s.
So x of s is 1/s s squared
plus 9, which we can use
partial fractions, now, to
decompose it into a/s plus bs
plus c divided by s
squared plus 9.
And if I were to take a look at
my notes, I have, in this
case, a is 1/9th, b is -1/9th,
and c is equal to 0, if you
were to work out these
coefficients.
So what this means is x of
s is 1/s minus 1/9th 1/s
squared plus 9.
And when we invert the Laplace
transform, the inverse of 1/s
it's just 1, so x of
t becomes 1/9.
Sorry, this should
be s up here.
The inverse Laplace transform of
s divided by s squared plus
9 is cosine 3, so we end up with
-1/9th cosine of 3t, and
again, this is a solution
for t bigger than 0.
So as soon as we turn on the
input, the function x of t
starts growing continuously from
1, and then achieves an
oscillation with period 3.
So just to quickly recap, in
this problem, we solved
several ODEs, several initial
value problem ODEs using
Laplace transforms. Laplace
transforms are particularly
nice because they convert
an ODE into an algebraic
equation, which we can
solve fairly easily.
The drawback is we sometimes
have to manipulate, using
partial fractions, the
right-hand side into functions
that we know how to
invert using the
Laplace transform inverse.
So I'll just conclude here, and
I'll see you next time.