DAVID SHIROKOFF: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
So today I'd like to take a look
at gain and phase lag.
And we're going to consider
this simple problem.
So first off, find a periodic
solution to x dot dot plus 8x
dot plus 7x equals F0 times
cosine omega t.
So basically, it's just
forcing a differential
equation with some frequency
cosine omega t.
And the problem we're interested
in today is to give
the gain and phase lag to
this periodic solution.
So I'll let you take a look at
this problem and I'll be back
in a minute.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
OK, so we're interested in
finding this periodic solution
to the differential equation.
And we see here that we're
forcing it with right-hand
side of cosine omega t.
So the standard procedure
is to first complexify.
So we're going to consider the
differential equation x dot
dot plus 8x dot plus 7x equals
F0 e to the i omega t.
And then at the end, we're going
to take the real part of
our solution to this
differential equation.
And we do this because cosine
omega t is the real part of e
to the i omega t.
Now, for this equation, we see
that we're forcing it with an
exponential.
So we can just use the
exponential response formula.
And this gives us a particular
solution.
So the exponential response
formula is 1 over p of i omega
times the right-hand
side, which is F0 e
to the i omega t.
And in this case, the
characteristic polynomial, p
of s, is s squared
plus 8s plus 7.
So that p of i omega is going
to be 7 minus omega squared.
So the omega squared comes from
s squared plus 8i omega.
Now, I'd just like to
take a moment and
step back for a second.
If we take a look at the
differential equation, the
input on the right-hand side
is F0 e to the i omega t.
Now notice how this
characteristic--
sorry, the exponential response
formula gives us a
particular solution, which is
1 over p of i omega F0 e to
the i omega t, which is
a periodic solution.
But moreover, the output of this
formula shows that it's
actually the input forcing
multiplied by this factor 1
over p of i omega.
So this factor right here, 1
over p of i omega relates the
input forcing to the
output forcing.
Or sorry, to the output
response.
And this factor is sometimes
called the complex gain.
And the reason it's the complex
gain is because if we
take a look at p of i omega,
it has a real part and an
imaginary part.
So specifically, p of i omega
contains two pieces of
information.
Because it's a complex number,
we can think of it as being an
amplitude in a phase.
So the amplitude of p
of i omega is It's
sometimes called the gain.
And the phase of p of i omega
is the phase lag.
So p of i omega contains two
pieces of information, which
relate the input forcing signal
to the output response
of the differential equation.
Now, I'd like to go ahead and
write x of t, decomplexify.
So we're going to take the real
part of 1 over p of i
omega times F0 e to
the i omega t.
So we have 7 minus omega
squared plus 8 i omega.
Upstairs is F0 e to
the i omega t.
And I'm going to just put this
in amplitude phase form.
And when I take the real part,
I'll do it in two steps first.
8 omega squared.
Square rooted.
F0 e to i omega t divided
by e to the i phi.
Where here phi is the phase lag
and tangent phi is going
to be the imaginary part
over the real part.
And just quickly note that as
omega goes from 0 to infinity,
tangent phi will go
from 0 to pi.
So this is the range of phi
that we're interested in.
And now, when we take the real
part, we end up with F0 1 over
7 minus omega squared quantity
squared plus 8 omega squared,
all squared rooted.
Cosine omega t minus phi.
And now we'd like to look at
what the amplitude and phase
are as a function of omega.
So for each fixed omega, the
output is going to be a
sinusoid which oscillates
at the same
frequency as the input.
However, the only difference is
that it's going to have a
rescaled amplitude.
And it will have a shifted
phase as well.
So for the amplitude response,
we're interested in plotting 1
over the amplitude
of p of i omega.
So here's the amplitude.
And this function is just
going to decrease and
asymptotically approach
infinity.
So this is the amplitude
response.
This is 1 over 7 minus omega
squared square rooted equals 8
omega squared, quantity
square rooted.
This is omega.
And then in addition to the
amplitude response, we also
have the phase.
And the phase, if I go back up
here for a second, we can
write it explicitly as phi is
equal to tan inverse 8 omega
divided by 7 minus
omega squared.
So I'm going to plot
omega on this axis
and phi on this axis.
And, OK, so to plot this curve,
we note that when omega
is 0, tan inverse of 0 is 0.
So we're going to start at 0.
Typically, what I usually like
to do in this case is look at
the denominator in
the arctangent.
We see that when omega is equal
to the square root of 7,
this argument blows up.
It goes to infinity.
And the arctangent of infinity
is pi over 2.
So I can draw a curve in here,
which is pi over 2.
So we know that phi is pi
over 2 when omega is
equal to root 7.
And note how this is the natural
frequency if there was
no damping in the system.
And then lastly, there's another
curve here at pi.
We see that as omega approaches
infinity, again,
this argument approaches 0.
And if you were to take the
derivative of this whole
quantity, we would
see that it's--
of tan inverse of this argument,
we would see that
the function's increasing
for all omega.
So it actually looks something
like this.
It looks like an s-shaped curve
that asymptotically
approaches pi as omega
goes to infinity.
So just to quickly recap.
When we look at the differential
equation, or a
particular solution to a
differential equation which is
being forced by a periodic
sinusoidal function, the
output is always going to be
rescaled and phase shifted,
but still oscillating at
the same frequency.
And specifically, depending
on which frequency the
differential equation's forced
at, the amplitude will take on
different values.
The amplitude response will
take on different values.
And the phase shift will also
have different values
depending on the frequency
of forcing.
So I'd just like to conclude
here, and I'll
see you next time.