JOEL LEWIS: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
You've been doing some work
on trig integration.
I have a nice example here of
a problem that requires trig
integration in order to solve.
So what I'd like you to do is
to compute the volume of the
solid that you get when you take
one hump of the curve, y
equals sine ax, and you revolve
it around the x-axis.
So you take the curve between
two consecutive roots, and
then you, you know, revolve
that around the x-axis and
that gives you some, I
don't know, vaguely
football-shaped thing.
And so then the question
is, what's the
volume of that solid?
So why don't you pause the
video, take a little while to
work that out, come back, and
we can work it out together.
Welcome back.
In order to solve this problem,
we just are going to
apply our usual methods for
computing a volume of a solid
of rotation.
So in order to do that, remember
that one of the
things you need is you need to
know the region over which
you're integrating, and you
need to choose a method of
integration.
So in this case, looking at
this region, here, I'm
rotating it around the x-axis.
i looks to me, so we
have two choices.
We could do shells with
horizontal rectangles, or we
could do disks with vertical
rectangles.
Looks to me like vertical
rectangles are going to be the
way to go for this function.
Nice, simple, have their
base on the x-axis.
You know, this is a nice
setup for disks.
So we're going to take vertical
disks here, like this.
Vertical rectangles that
are going to spin
into vertical disks.
And so we're going to integrate
all these disks,
we're going to add them up
starting at x equals 0, and
going until the end
of this region.
So we need to figure out what
the end of that region is, so
we need sine ax to
be 0, again.
Well, the first 0, the first
time sine is 0 after 0 is at
pi, so we need ax to be pi.
So this value is at pi over a.
OK.
So that's the setup
for the problem.
And now we just need to remembe,
you know, how to do a
problem like this.
So we have each of
these disks.
Well, it's height here is the
height of the function, which
is y, in this case.
So the area of a little disk--
sorry.
The area of a disk, the
little-- oh, dear.
The element of volume, the
little bit of volume that we
get is equal to--
well, the area of the disk is pi
y squared, which is pi sine
squared of ax.
And then the thickness of
the disk is a little dx.
So this is our little element
dV of volume.
And now to get the whole volume,
we just integrate this
over the appropriate range.
So this means V is equal to the
integral from 0 to, as we
said, to pi over a of pi times
sine squared of ax dx.
So this is just like the
sorts of integrals you
were doing in class.
It's a definite integral.
I guess most of the ones
you did were just
anti-derivatives, but of
course, that's an easy
translation to make by via
the fundamental theorem.
So, OK, so we have
this ax here.
You know, it's up to you.
I think my life will be simpler
if I just make a
little u-substitution, get rid
of the ax, and then I don't
have to think about it
very much anymore.
So I can take u equals ax,
so du equals a dx, or dx
equals 1 over a du.
So I, OK, so I make this
quick substitution.
When x is 0, u is also 0.
When x is pi over
a, u is just pi.
So this becomes the integral
from 0 to pi.
I can pull this pi out front.
And I can pull, so I'm going to
get pi times sine squared u
times dx is 1 over a du.
So I'm going to pull the 1 over
a out front, as well.
So it's pi over a times the
integral from 0 to pi of sine
squared u du.
OK.
So now we've just simplified
it to the situation where
we've just got a trig
integral, no other
complications at all.
How do we do this one?
Well, OK, so this is not one
of those nice ones where we
have an odd power for either
sine or cosine.
We have sine is appearing to the
even power, 2, and cosine,
well, it doesn't appear.
It appears to the
even power, 0.
If you like, you could
say it that way.
So when we have a situation
where sine and cosine both
appear in even powers, what we
need to do is we need to use
one of our trig identities.
We need to use a half
angle identity.
So the identity in particular
that we want to use is we want
to replace sine squared u
with something like a
cosine of 2u somehow.
So in order to do that, we
need to remember the
appropriate identity.
So one of the double angle
identities is cosine of 2t
equals 1 minus 2 sine squared t,
which we can rewrite as the
half angle identity, sine
squared t equals 1 minus
cosine 2t over 2.
So this is true for
any value, t.
In particular, it's true
when t is equal to u.
Back over here.
So we can rewrite this by
replacing sine squared u with
1 minus cosine of
2u divided by 2.
So this integral becomes, so
our integral is equal to--
well, we've still got the
pi over a in the front--
integral from 0 to pi of 1 minus
cosine of 2u over 2 du.
OK, and so now we
integrate it.
So 1 over 2, that's easy.
That's just so, OK, so the pi
over a is still out in front.
1 over 2 integrates, just
gives us u over 2.
How about cosine of 2u?
Well, so minus cosine of
2u, so that should
give us a minus sine.
Right?
Derivative of sine is cosine,
derivative of minus sine is
minus cosine.
So its minus sine of 2u, and
then because it's 2u, we're
going to have to divide
by 2 again.
So over 4.
All right.
If you don't believe me, of
course, you could always check
by differentiating this
expression and making sure
that it matches that
expression,
the integrand, here.
And OK, and so we need to take
that between u equals 0
and u equals pi.
So luckily we changed our bounds
of integration and we
don't have to go all the
way back to x again.
OK, so this is pi
over a times--
OK, so u over 2 minus sine, 2u
over 4 when u is pi over 2
minus sine of 2 pi.
That's just 0, right?
Yes, that's just 0.
Good.
So this term is just 0.
pi over 2 minus--
OK, now when we put in 0, here,
well, we get 0 minus
sine of 0, so that's just
0-- so just pi over 2.
OK.
So the answer, then, is
pi squared over 2a.
So that's the volume we
were looking for.
So just to quickly recap, we
have our solid of revolution
here that we get by spinning
this region around the x-axis.
We use our typical methods for
computing volumes of solids of
revolution.
We've go a, when we do that, the
integral that we set up is
a trig integral with a
sine squared in it.
So both sine and cosine appear
to an even power
in this trig integral.
When you're in that situation,
you're going to have to use
your half angle formulas,
like so.
Once you do that,
you'll simplify.
Sometimes life is hard, you'll
have to do it more than once.
In this case, we only had to do
that once, so we got, then
we, that reduces the integral
to something that's easy to
compute, where you have one
of sine or cosine always
appearing to an odd power.
In this case, very simple.
You just had a cosine.
And then you integrate it, and
this was our final answer.
I'll end there.