JOEL LEWIS: Hi, welcome
back to recitation.
In lecture, Professor Miller
did a bunch of examples of
integrals involving
trigonometric functions.
So I thought I would give you
a couple more, well I guess
three more examples, some of
them are a little different
flavor than the ones he did, but
some nice examples of some
integrals you can compute now.
One thing you might need for
them is you're going to have
to remember some of your
trig identities.
Just like you had to remember
some of them last time.
So in particular, one identity
that you might need today that
you didn't need in lecture,
was the angle sum
identity for cosine.
So let me just remind you what
that is, it says the cosine of
a plus b is equal to cosine a
cosine b minus sine a sine b.
So you're going to need that
formula to compute one of
these three integrals.
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time
to work these out.
Come back you can check your
answers against my work.
Hopefully you had some
fun and some luck
working on these integrals.
Let's have a go at them.
The first integral is sine
cubed x secant squared x.
So I don't think that Professor
Miller did any
integrals that involved the
secant function, but one thing
to remember is that the secant
function is very closely
related to the cosine
function.
It's just cosine
to the minus 1.
Sorry, by that I mean 1 over
cosine, not the arc cosine.
So in order to, so we can view
this first integral here as an
integral of a power of sine
times a power of cosine, just
like the ones you
had in lecture.
So we can write this as sine
cubed of x times--
I'm going to write--
cosine x to the minus 2 dx.
And here we see this is a nice
example where the sine occurs
with an odd power.
So when the sine occurs with an
odd power, or when one of
them at least occurs with
an odd power, life
is relatively simple.
And what we do is just what we
did in lecture, which is we
break it up so that we just have
one instance of the one
that occurs to an odd power and
then a bunch of powers of
the other one.
So in this case, we have
sine to an odd power.
So we want to pull out all the
even, you know, all the extra
multiples, so in this case we
have sine times sine squared.
So we take all those sine
squared's and we convert them
into 1 minus cosine squared's.
This is going to be equal to the
integral of sine x times,
well, times sine squared x,
which is 1 minus cosine
squared x times cosine x to
the minus second power dx.
And now you take all these
cosines and you multiply them
together and you see
what you've got.
So in this case that's equal
to the integral--
OK, so 1 times cosine to the
minus 2, is just cosine
to the minus 2.
So this first term is cosine x
to the minus 2 sine x and then
minus, OK we have cosine squared
times cosine to the
minus 2, so that one's even
simpler, that's just
minus sine x dx.
So at this point, if you like,
you could do a substitution of
a trigonometric function.
You could set u equal
to cosine x.
All right?
What's going to happen if you
set u equal to cosine x, well
du is going to be
minus sine x dx.
Each of these have exactly one
appearance of sine x in them,
so this would become--
so if we set u equal cosine x.
So, as I said du equals
minus sine x dx.
Because each of these have a
sine x dx in them, that's
going to get clumped into the
du and the cosines will just
get replaced with
u everywhere.
So I'm going to take this
over here so I have
a little more space.
So this becomes the integral of
u to the minus 2, I guess
it's minus u to the
minus 2 plus 1 du.
That minus sine x is just
exactly equal to du.
OK.
And now this is easy to
finish from here.
This is equal to, well OK, so
minus 2, so we have to go up
one to minus 1, so that's just
u to the minus 1 plus 1 gives
us a u plus a constant, and
then of course we have to
substitute back in.
So this is u is cosine x, so u
to the minus 1 is secant x
plus cosine x plus a constant.
So that's the first one.
For the second one, sine
x cosine of 2x.
We actually have
a slightly more
complicated situation here.
Because the cosine 2x is no
longer, it's not just a
trigonometric function of x
alone, it's a trigonometric
function of 2x.
So in order to do the sort of
the things we did in lecture,
what you're going to have to do
is, you're going to have to
expand this out in terms of
just sine x and cosine x,
rather than cosine of 2x.
So in order to do that you just
need to remember your
double angle formula.
Now if you don't remember your
double angle formulas, one way
you can remember them is
remember the angle sum formula
and apply it with a and
b both equal to x.
If you like.
But, or you could just
remember your
double angle formulas.
So let's go over here.
And so in this case, we have the
integral of sine x times,
well cosine 2x-- so there are
actually, right, there are
several different ways you
can write cosine 2x.
So one way you can write it is
cosine squared x minus sine
squared x, but we want
everything-- again we have an
odd power of sine, so it would
be nice if everything else
could be written in terms
of just cosine.
So an equivalent form for cosine
2x is to write, is that
it's equal to 2 cosine
squared x minus 1 dx.
And here, this is very, very
similar to the last question.
Again, you can make the
substitution u equals cosine,
if you like.
And so I'm not going to do out
the whole substitution for
you, but this is going to work
out to 2 cosine squared x sine
x, the integral of that is minus
2/3 cosine cubed x and
then the integral of minus
sine x is cosine x plus a
constant of integration.
So that's the second one.
The third one now is of a
similar flavor, except you
have here, you have sine
2x and cosine 3x.
So again, when you
want to integrate
something where you have--
so here we have both
trigonometric functions occur
in multiples.
No if it was the same multiple,
if it were 2x and
2x, say, that would be fine.
You know, you could just make
a substitution like u equals
2x or something and then
proceed as usual.
But because they're different
multiples, we need, when we do
these trig integrals, we need
to apply the methods that we
used in lecture.
You want the arguments
to agree.
So you want it all to be sine of
something and cosine of the
same thing.
So here the thing to do, I
think, is to try and put
everything in terms of just
sine x and cosine x.
So sine 2x is one you
should remember,
double angle formula.
Cosine 3x, well in order to
figure out what cosine 3x is,
you could just know it,
maybe you learned
it once upon a time.
The other thing you can do for
cosine 3x, is you can use this
angle sum formula.
So let me just work that
out for you quickly.
So cosine of 3x, well how do you
use the angle sum formula?
You can write 3x as 2x plus x.
So this is equal to cosine
of 2x plus x.
And now this is a sum, so you
can use the cosine sum
formula, so you get this is
equal to cosine 2x cosine x
minus sine 2x sine x.
OK and now you can use
the double angle
formulas here and here.
so in the end, if you do this
all out, what you get is
you're going to get 4 cosine
cubed x minus 3 cosine x.
You might say, oh what happened
to the sine x's?
We're going to get a sign
squared x and I want to write
everything in terms of cosine.
So I've replaced the, I've done
an extra step here that
I'm not showing, where I
replaced the sine squared x
with a 1 minus cosine
squared x.
So you make this substitution,
and you also make the
substitution for sign x--
sorry-- for sine 2x that you
have. OK, sine 2x is equal
to-- you know,
double angle formula--
2 sine x cosine x.
And so when you multiply sine 2x
by cosine 3x you again have
an expression that's got powers
of cosine with a single
power of sine.
So doing these simplifications,
you again get
this nice form.
One of them's odd, the other
one, so, one of the trig
functions, sine or cosine
appears to just the power of
1, so, OK, so you can do this
nice simple substitution.
You don't need to do any of
the double angle, or half
angle complication.
I'm not going to finish this
one out for you, but I did
write down the answer so you
can check your answer.
When you, the third integral
that we had, which is integral
sine 2x cosine 3x dx, when you
work it all out you should
get, let's see what I got, OK,
you should get minus 8/5
cosine to the fifth x plus 2
cosine cubed x plus a constant
of integration.
So if you work out all the
details, this is what you
should get.
I'll stop there.