PROFESSOR: Welcome back
to recitation.
In this segment I'm going to
actually show, well, you're
actually going to show, the
derivative of tangent x using
the quotient rule.
So what I'd like you to do, I
wanted to remind you of what
the quotient rule is.
So u and v are functions of x.
We want to take the derivative
of u divided by v. I've
written the formula that you
were given in class for this.
And I'm asking for you to take
d dx of tangent x using the
quotient rule.
And the hint I will give you is
the reason we can obviously
use the quotient rule is because
tangent x is equal to
a quotient of two
functions of x.
It's sine x divided
by cosine of x.
So I'm going to give you a
minute to work this out for
yourself, and then when
we come back I
will do it for you.
OK.
So we want to find the
derivative of tangent x.
So let me, let me work on
this side of the board.
So I'm actually going to take
d dx of sine x divided by
cosine of x.
OK.
So in this case, sign x is u.
Cosine x is v. So using my
quotient rule I know that
first I have to take the
derivative of sine x--
that's cosine x-- and then
I multiply it by the
denominator, the v,
which is cosine x.
So my first term in the
numerator is cosine squared x.
Again, one cosine x comes from
the derivative of sine x, one
cosine x is the v. It's the
cosine x in the denominator.
Then I have to subtract
v prime u.
The derivative of cosine
x is negative sine x.
I'll actually just write
that one down.
And then I bring the u
along for the ride.
So I multiply by sine x here.
And then I take v
squared in the
denominator from the formala.
v, again, is cosine x, so I take
cosine squared x in the
denominator.
Now this at this point is a
little bit messy, but the nice
thing is that we can use some
trigonometric identities to
simplify this.
So let me first write out what
it is a little more clearly.
Minus a negative gives
you a positive.
And then here I get sine x times
sine x, so I get the
sine squared x.
And then I keep divided
by cosine squared x.
Now at this point some of you
might have divided by cosine
squared x here and gotten 1, and
divided by cosine squared
x here and gotten tangent
squared x.
And then from there you could
simplify to another
trigonometric function.
I'm going to go straight a
different way to show you what
that actually also equals.
So there, at this point I want
to stress there are sort of
two ways you can get
to the same place.
But I'm going to use the fact
that the numerator is a very
nice trigonometric identity
that we know.
We know cosine squared
x plus sine squared x
always equals 1.
So this is quite lovely, the
numerator simplifies to 1, the
denominator stays cosine
squared x.
What is this function?
1 over cosine x is actually
secant x.
So if you need at this point
to rewrite the whole thing
like this, right?--
1 squared is 1 and in the
denominator we still get
cosine squared x--
this tells you that 1 over
cosine squared x is actually
just equal to secant
squared x.
So again, what I want to point
out is we've now taken the
derivative of tangent x
and we got that that's
secant squared x.
Now using this quotient rule,
you can do the same kind of
thing with cotangent x, with
cosecant x, with secant x.
You can find all these
derivatives of these
trigonometric functions using
the quotient rule.
So if you want to know what the
derivative of secant x is,
you should take dd x of 1
divided by cosine x and use
the quotient rule.
Or, in fact, the chain rule
would work well there also, to
find that derivative.
So we are building up the number
of derivatives we can
find using these different
rules.
So we'll stop there.