MARTINA BALAGOVIC: Hi.
Welcome.
Today's problem is about finding
solutions of this
non-homogeneous linear system, x
minus 2y minus 2z equals b1,
2x minus 5y minus 4z equals
b2, and 4x minus 9y
minus 8z equals b3.
And as you can see, the system
doesn't only have numbers and
unknowns, it also has
parameters, b1, b2, and b3,
and the solution will depend on
this parameters, but also
the existence of the solution
will depend on these
parameters.
And we're asked to find a
solution and find when it
exists, depending on the values
of b1, b2, and b3.
So now you should pause the
video, solve the problem, and
come back and compare your
solution with mine.
And we're back.
Let's try it.
Let's start by solving this
system as though b1, b2, and
b3 were numbers.
So we write the matrix of the
system, which is 1 minus 2
minus 2, b1, and then 2 minus
5 minus 4, b2, and 4 minus 9
minus 8, b3.
And we do elimination.
So we multiply the first row by
minus 2 and add it to the
second row.
And we multiply it by minus 4
and add it to the third row.
And we get 1 minus 2 minus 2 b1,
0, 4 minus 5 is minus 1, 4
minus 4 is 0, and minus
2 times b1 plus b2.
And here we get 0, 8 minus
9 is minus 1, and
8 minus 8 is 0.
Finally on the right-hand
side, minus 4b1 plus b3.
And you can already see
that something's
going to happen here.
But let's do one more step.
So eliminating further we get 1
minus 2 minus 2 b1, 0 minus
1 0 minus 2b1 plus b2.
And in the last row we replace
it with the last row minus the
second row, and we get 0
0 0 minus 4b1 plus 2--
so minus minus 2b2 is minus
2b1 minus b2 and plus b2.
I hope I did this right.
So now let's think of it
as a system again.
The last equation says 0 equals
this expression in b1,
b2, and b3.
So this is something
to note down.
If minus 2b1 minus b2 plus b3
is some number that's not 0,
then the last equation is going
to say 0 equals non-0.
It's never going to be
satisfied, and the entire
system is never going
to have a solution.
So in this case, we
have no solutions.
If this is equal to 0, so minus
2b1 minus b2 plus b3 is
equal to 0, then let's do one
more step on this matrix here.
Let's turn this number into 1
by multiplying this row by
negative 1.
And let's use it to eliminate
this number here as well.
So in this case, we get--
let me write it from the last
row, which now becomes 0 0 0
equals 0, which is fine.
The second row becomes
0 1 0 2b1 minus b2.
And the first one to get rid of
this minus 2, we multiply
this row by negative 2 and
add it to the first one.
We get 1 0 negative 2, and here
we get b1 plus 4b1, which
is 5b1 minus 2 b2.
The reason why we did
it was to get the
identity matrix here.
And now let's solve this.
These two columns corresponding
to variables x
and y have pivots in them.
So these are the pivot
variables.
This column here has
no pivot in it,
so it's a free variable.
And now we're going to calculate
the solutions, but
by picking particular values
for z, and then calculating
the values for x and y, which we
have two kinds of solution.
One kind is the particular
solution.
So this one solves
Ax equals b.
There's only one of them.
And we get it by setting the
free variable equal to 0.
Setting the free variable equal
to 0, we get, well this
is equal to 0.
The second equation says y
equals this thing here,
so 2b1 minus b2.
And the first equation says x
minus 2 times 0 equals this
expression here.
So 5b1 minus 2b2.
That's our particular
solution.
The next kind is the
special solution.
So remember, those solve
Ax equals 0.
There's as many of them as
there are free variables.
In our case, there's only one.
And we get it by setting all
free variables equal to 0,
except one equal to 1.
And do it for every
free variable.
So in our case there's only one
free variable and we set z
equal to 1.
The solution that we get in this
case, and remember we're
solving Ax equals 0-- we
don't care about the
right-hand side anymore--
so z is 1.
This second equation says y
equals 0, and the first
equation says x minus
2 times 1 equals 0.
In other words, x equals 2.
So the special solution
is 2 0 1.
And now all solutions are of the
form x equals a particular
solution plus any multiple
of the special solution.
Let me recap.
In case this particular
combination of parameters is
not 0, there's no solutions.
In case this particular
combination of parameters is
equal to 0, there are solutions,
there are as many
of them as there are real
numbers c, and they're all of
this form for these
two vectors.
And that's all I wanted
to say today.