PROFESSOR: Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So today, we're going to take
a look at some forced
oscillators and the exponential
response formula.
And the problem we're going to
take a look at is first, for
part one, to consider the
equation x dot dot plus 8x
equals, and then a forcing term
on the right-hand side,
cosine omega t.
And we're going to consider the
case when omega squared is
not equal to 8.
So in the language
of resonance,
we're not on resonance.
And we're also asked why is this
called an undamped forced
oscillator.
And then for part two, to
use the ERF to solve the
differential equation x dot
dot plus 2x plus 4x
equals cosine 3t.
And then, what is the natural
angular frequency of this
differential equation?
So I'll let you take a look at
these problems and try them
out for yourself.
And I'll be back in a moment.
Hi everyone.
Welcome back.
So we're asked to find the
general solution to the
differential equation, x
dot, dot plus 8x equals
cosine omega t.
And notice how this is a
differential equation with
constant coefficients.
But it's being forced by a
periodic function on the
right-hand side.
So the first thing to
do is to write down
the homogeneous solution.
So the homogeneous solution,
which I'll denote with a
subscript h, solves the
differential equation with the
right-hand side of 0.
This gives us a characteristic
polynomial of s squared plus 8
equals 0, which then gives
us roots of plus
or minus root 8i.
So the homogeneous solution
is some constant C1.
And when we have purely
imaginary roots, we have
cosine of the imaginary term
times t plus some constant C2
times sine of the imaginary
term, which in this
case is root 8t.
So the homogeneous solution is
always contains two constants.
And it's solves the differential
equation with a
zero right-hand side.
The general solution, however,
is the homogeneous solution
plus one particular solution
that solves the differential
equation, 8 dot, dot plus 8x
equals cosine omega t.
So we just need to find
one solution to this
differential equation.
And in this case, I'll use the
exponential response formula.
But first note that when we use
the exponential response
formula, we need a forcing to be
of the form e to st on the
right-hand side.
And cosine omega t is
not in that form.
However, what we can do is
there's a trick to complexify
the right-hand side.
So we know that the cosine omega
t is actually the real
part of i omega t.
So what this means is if we have
a complex solution, zed,
which solves zed dot, dot plus
8 zed equals e to the i omega
t, then we can take x equals
the real part of zed, then
solves the differential equation
8 dot, dot plus 8x
equals the real part of
the right-hand side,
cosine omega t.
And now we're in business
because this equation has the
form where we can use the
exponential response formula.
So solving this differential
equation for zed, we have a
particular solution for zed,
is going to be e to the i
omega t divided by the
characteristic polynomial
evaluated at the exponential.
So in this case, the exponential
is i omega.
So we must evaluate the
polynomial at i omega.
And this is the solution
provided that the polynomial
evaluated at i omega
doesn't vanish.
And in our case, the
characteristic polynomial, p
of s, we worked out already
to be s squared plus 8.
So this gives us a particular
solution for zed, which is 1
divided by I omega squared plus
8 on the denominator.
We have e to i omega
on the numerator.
And of course, 1 over i omega
squared plus 8 becomes 1 over
8 minus omega squared.
And we know we don't have a
problem because omega, we were
told in the problem, is not
equal to the square root of 8.
So in this case, we know
that the denominator is
not going to vanish.
And now what we need to do is
just take x for the particular
solution to be the real part of
zed, which is going to be
the real part.
I'll write it out.
8 minus omega squared cosine
omega t plus i sine omega t,
which gives us 1 over 8 minus
omega squared cosine omega t.
So the total solution, the
general solution, is going to
be the sum of the homogeneous
solution plus
the particular solution.
And in our case, that's going
to be C1 cosine omega t plus
C2 sine omega t plus 1 over
8 minus omega squared
cosine omega t.
Sorry.
These should be root 8's.
So this is the homogeneous
part.
And this is the particular
solution.
And this is the general
So we were asked, also, why this
is sometimes called an
undamped forced oscillator.
Well, it's undamped, because in
the differential equation,
there is no damping term.
There's no term proportional
to x dot.
And then, secondly, it's forced
because we have a
forcing on the right-hand
side.
We have an input function, f,
which in this case is cosine
omega t which doesn't
depend on x.
And that forces the differential
equation.
Also note that the forcing term
gives rise to part of the
solution which is directly
proportional to the forcing.
In fact, it has the
same frequency
but a different amplitude.
So this concludes part A.
Now for part B, we're asked to
use the ERF to solve the
differential equation x dot,
dot plus 2x dot plus 4x
equals cosine 3t.
And again, we can use
the same trick.
The right-hand side isn't of
the form e to the i3t.
But what we can do is we can
write cosine 3t as the real
part of e to the i3t, and then
solve the differential
equation, zed dot, dot plus 2
zed dot plus 4 zed equals e to
the i3t, and then take x equals
the real part of zed.
And in this case, we're only
looking for a particular
solution, which we can compute
using the ERF.
So it's 1 over the
characteristic polynomial
evaluated at 3i times
e to the i3t.
And what's a characteristic
polynomial of this
differential equation?
Well, p of s is going to be s
squared plus 2s plus 4, which
means that p of 3i is going to
be 3i squared plus 2 times 3i
plus 4, which gives us
negative 9 plus 4 is
negative 5 plus 6i.
And putting the pieces together,
we end up getting
that x is equal to the real part
of 1 over negative 5 plus
6i e to the i3t.
And we can expand out the
numerator using Euler's
formula to get cosine
3t plus i sine 3t.
And when the dust settles,
I got 1 over 61--
let me check my notes--
minus 5 cosine 3t
plus 6 sine 3t.
So I'll let you work at this
last step for yourself.
And then, lastly, what is the
natural angular frequency of
the differential equation?
Well, this is just
some notation.
We sometimes call the natural
angular frequency to be the
square root of the term
proportional to x.
So in this case, the term
two here comes in
as a damping term.
The natural frequency, which is
sometimes written as omega
naught squared, is always
equal to this
term, which is 4.
So the natural frequency, the
natural angular frequency,
omega naught, would be
the square root of 4,
which would be 2.
So I just like to
quickly recap.
We've taken a look at
forced oscillators.
And we computed their solutions
using the ERF.
And one common trend,
particularly when we have an
oscillating input, a forcing
term, is to first change the
oscillating term into a complex
exponential, then
compute a particular solution
using the ERF formula, and
then take the real part of the
ERF solution to recover a real
solution to the ODE.
That gives us the particular
solution.
And then, in some cases,
we also have to add the
homogeneous solution to it to
get the full general solution
to the ODE.
So I like to conclude here.
And I'll see you next time.