DAVID JORDAN: Hello, and welcome
back to recitation.
The problem I'd like to work
with you right now is we have
a line which goes through two
points that are given to us
explicitly, and we have a plane
which is given to us by
an equation.
And what we want to know is
where does this line intersect
this plane?
And so one thing I would suggest
to get started is we
need to give a parametrization
of our line to get started.
OK, so why don't you work on
that, pause the tape, and
we'll come back in a moment
and work it out together.
OK, welcome back.
Let's get started.
So let's start off by
drawing a cartoon of
what's going on here.
So we have this plane
sitting in space.
And we have some line kind
of going through space.
So maybe it's like this.
And there's this single
point of intersection.
So even from the cartoon, we can
kind of, sort of see two
things which are going on.
Which is that we would expect a
point of intersection, or we
would expect exactly one, if
we choose kind of a generic
line and generic plane.
In order for there to be no
points of intersection, we
would have to have a line which
was parallel to the
plane, which is very unlikely.
And then otherwise, we expect
exactly just one point of
intersection.
So I want to break this sort
of into two components.
So we have an equation
for the plane.
And when I see an equation
describing a plane, I think of
that as a sort of test
for membership.
We can plug in a point--
x, y, z--
to the equation, and we can ask,
does this point make the
equation true, or doesn't it?
And if it does, then that point
x, y, z is in the plane,
and otherwise it's
not in the plane.
For the line, what we're going
to need to do in a second is
we're going to need to come
up with a parametrization.
And a parametrization is a
different kind of thing than
an equation describing a line.
A parametrization, rather than
being a test for membership,
is really a way of listing all
the points on the line.
So when we give a
parametrization--
in a second-- then we're going
to be able to list all the
points in the line.
And then we're going to be able
to plug our list into the
equation for the plane, and find
out which point on our
list is actually in the plane.
Which one satisfies the
membership equation.
So why don't we get
started first with
parametrizing the line.
So the general kind of picture
here is we have a point P1 in
space, and we have another point
P2 in space, and we want
to parametrize the line which
goes between them.
And there's actually a very
simple way to do this.
What we do is we want to take
our original point P1, and we
want to add a variable t times
the vector P2 minus P1, which
connects them.
So that's this one here.
OK.
So this is a reasonable thing to
do, because if we plug in t
equals 0, then we just get P1.
And if we plug in t equals
1, then we get P1
plus P2 minus P1.
We just get P2.
So this line definitely goes
through those two points, and
that's all that we
really need.
So in our specific problem
here, we have P1--
we can take to be the
first point--
0, minus 1, 1.
And then we have t times--
so we have 2 minus 0 is--
2--
3 minus a negative 1 is--
4--
and 3 minus 1 is--
2.
And this is the vector
connecting those.
And so we can write, we can just
combine these two and we
get 2t, 4t minus 1,
and 2t plus 1.
OK?
So this here is a
parametrization of the line.
So as we vary t-- now, walking
back over to our picture-- as
we vary t, we're going to
just be listing all the
points on the line.
And we're going to ask, for
which point are we actually
contained in the plane?
So let's go over to the board
over here and solve that.
So what we want to know is does
this point satisfy the
equation for the plane?
And our plane was given to us
by the equation 2x plus y
minus z equals 1.
So x on our line is 2t.
So we have 2 times 2t, plus--
y is--
4t minus 1, minus--
z is--
2t plus 1.
And all this is meant
to equal 1.
OK.
So if we expand this out, we get
4t plus another 4t minus
2t and we get--
minus 1 minus another 1--
so we get minus 2 equals 1.
So altogether we get 6t equals
3, so that tells
us that t is 1/2.
OK?
And finally, to get our answer,
we need to go back
over to our parametrization
of the line and
plug in t equals 1/2.
So coming back over here,
plugging in t
equals 1/2, we get 1--
2 minus 1 is--
1--
and 1 plus 1 is--
2.
OK, so we get the point of
intersection 1, 1, 2.
So that was quite a few steps,
so let's review what we did.
So to begin with, we needed to
understand that the equation
for a plane is a test
for membership.
It's not a list of all the
points in the plane, it's a
test for membership.
The parametrization of the line,
on the other hand, is a
way of listing all of the
points on the line.
And so if our goal is to find
which particular point on the
line is contained in the
plane, then we need to
parametrize our line, and then
we need to plug in our
parametrization to our equation
for the plane, and
then solve for the value of
t which makes it true.
Finding that t then we've,
that's is equivalent to
finding a point on our line.
And I think I'll leave
it at that.