PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
Today we're going to
do another example
of a definite integral.
This time, it's going to be one
that you're going to need
to do some substitution for.
You're not going to know the
antiderivative right off the
top of your head, I think.
So, I've got it on the
board behind me.
So it's compute the integral
from minus 2 to 2 of the
function x squared cosine
of the quantity x
cubed over 8 dx.
So, this is a kind of
weird a integrand.
I roughly, you know, very, very
rough graph of kind of
what it looks like.
So this is sort of the
area of this region.
It's a positive function
over this interval.
So it's the area of this
region that I'm
asking you to compute.
So, all right, so definite
integral.
Why don't you pause the video,
take a couple minutes, work
this out yourself, come back,
we can work it out together.
All right, welcome back.
So, from looking at this
integrand here, it seems to me
that I don't know immediately
off the top of my head what
its antiderivative is.
So, I can't just sort of apply
the fundamental theorem of
calculus directly without
a little bit of work.
So there are two different
ways that I can go about
computing this then,
about computing
this definite integral.
One is, that I can forget for
the minute that it's a
definite integral and compute
the antiderivative and then
use the fundamental theorem
of calculus.
So, let's try that way first and
then we'll do it a second
way as well.
So, method one is to compute
the antiderivative.
So we compute the antiderivative
of x squared
cosine of x cubed over 8 dx.
So here, it's not a definite
integral anymore.
Now I'm just looking at
the antiderivative.
And so, OK, so either by
intelligent guessing or that--
I forget if that's what
Professor Jerison called it--
or by just a substitution
method.
So, a good thing to substitute
here, is we see inside this
function we have this x cubed
part and then outside we have
an x squared part.
So x squared dx, that's
closely related to the
differential of x cubed.
So we might try the
substitution.
We might try the substitution
u equals--
well we can maybe get rid of all
of that at once-- so make
u equals x cubed over 8.
So in that case, du is equal
to 3/8 x squared dx.
And so this integral is equal
to the integral of--
well so, x squared
dx, we have that.
So we need to multiply
and divide by 3/8.
So this is, 8/3 cosine
of u du.
All right, and so now,
OK, so the 8/3,
that's just a constant.
That pulls out in front.
That's not hard.
So then the antiderivative
of cosine u du, that's
something we know.
So this is 8/3 of minus sine--
sorry not minus; I was doing the
derivative instead of the
antiderivative.
Just 8/3 sine u.
OK.
And good.
So that's the anti plus the
constant, which we don't need
because we're going to plug
this in the fundamental
theorem of calculus
in a minute.
So it's 8/3 sine u.
And, OK, so, but that's
not good.
I need it back in
terms of my x's.
And so I have to back
substitute.
So this is 8/3 sine
of x cubed over 8.
All right, now I've got an
antiderivative of this
expression.
So now I can take this
antiderivative and apply
fundamental theorem of
calculus, Right?
So, the integral from minus 2 to
2 of x squared cosine of x
cubed over 8 dx is equal to--
well it's equal to this
antiderivative--
8/3 sine x cubed over 8 taken
between x equals minus 2
and x equals 2.
So this is equal to 8/3 times
sine of 1 minus 8/3 times sine
of minus 1.
OK, and sine of minus x is
equal to minus sine x.
So we could rewrite this as
16/3 times sine of 1.
So that's the answer.
That's the value of
this integral.
And we did this first method
by first computing the
antiderivative and then using
it with the fundamental
theorem of calculus.
The second way we can do it is
the one that we just learned
more recently in lecture.
Which is to use substitution
directly in
the definite integral.
So let me come over
here and do that.
So, method two.
So now, when we do it
this way, mostly
this looks the same.
So we start off, we don't go
back to antiderivative.
We start off with the
definite integral.
So that's one difference.
We can use the exact
same substitution.
So we can use exactly the
substitution that we used
before, which was u equals
x cubed over 8.
That doesn't change.
And we still have the same du is
equal to 3x squared over 8,
but what does change--
sorry, dx.
Good.
You need a differential always
to be equal to a differential.
So what does change
is that this--
I need to change the bounds.
Right?
If I'm keeping it as definite
integrals all the time, so I'm
changing here from an integral
with respect to x to an
integral with respect to u.
And so that means that when I
write down the second integral
with respect to u, the bounds
that I write down have to be
the bounds for u.
Not for x.
So when x is equal to minus
2, I need to know what the
corresponding value of u is.
So in this case, when x is equal
to minus 2, we see that
the lower bound here--
when x is equal to minus 2--
the lower bound on u becomes
u equals, well, minus
2 cubed over 8.
That's minus 1.
And when x is equal to 2, the
upper bound, u becomes
2 cubed over 8.
So u becomes 1.
So we have this extra step when
we do it this way, of
changing the bounds.
OK, so I do that.
So now I get the integral.
So I'm going to write u equals
minus 1 here just to remind
myself that I made
this change to 1.
OK, and now the inside
transforms exactly the same.
So it's 8/3 times cosine u du.
OK, and now again, this is
something for which I already
know the antiderivative.
So I apply the fundamental
theorem of calculus here.
So I get the integral is equal
to 8/3 sine of u, where u goes
between minus 1 and 1.
So the other thing that's
changed here is that now I
don't have to change this
back in terms of x's.
I have the values that I'm going
to plug in here already
in terms of u.
So I don't have to switch
back in terms of x's.
And so I just plug these
values in and take the
difference.
So this is equal to 8/3 sine of
1 minus 8/3 sine of minus
1, which as we said before
is 16/3 times sine of 1.
OK, so we have these two
different methods.
They're very, very, very,
similar in how you apply them.
The key differences are, that
when you do it, the
substitution in terms of
definite integrals, you have
to change your bounds
of integration.
And what you get for changing
your bounds of integration is
at the end you don't have to
switch back from u's into x's.
Whereas, if you do it by first
computing the antiderivative,
well, you don't have any bounds
of integration when you
compute the antiderivative so
you don't have to change them.
But once you computed the
antiderivative, then you have
to go and make your
back substitution.
Put everything back in terms
of x's before going on to
compute the definite integral
that you started with.
So the those are the two
different ways you can do
substitution in definite
integrals and
I'll end with that.