Welcome back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to
find an antiderivative of the
function 1 over x squared
minus 8x plus 1.
So I'll give you a while to work
on it, and then I'll come
back, and I'll show
you how I started.
So welcome back.
Well, what we'd like to do is,
find an antiderivative to 1
over x squared minus
8x plus 1.
And how we're going to do that,
is we're going to use
the technique, completing
the square.
And I'm going to set up the
problem, I'm going to get it
to a certain place, and
then I'm going to
let you finish it.
And how do you know if you
got the right answer?
Well, you actually take a
derivative of your answer, and
see if it gives you back
1 over x squared
minus 8x plus 1.
That's how you can check.
So let's start off.
If I want to complete the
square, let's just remind
ourselves how to complete the
square on this quadratic.
So I'd like something right
here that makes
this a perfect square.
Right?
Well, the 8 here in the middle,
if I want a perfect
square, if you think about
this, I'm going
to have an x minus--
I need a number here that when
I multiply it by 2, that's
where this 8 comes from,
it gives me 8.
So obviously I need this
number to be a 4.
Right?
Which puts what here?
Puts a 16 here, right?
So just to double check,
what I'm looking
for is a number here--
I need a number right here that
when I multiply by 2,
gives me negative 8, and then
I need it to figure out what
it squares to.
So that number is negative
4, and it squares to 16.
But obviously this isn't
what I have, right?
I have plus 1.
So what have I had to do to
get from here to here?
Well, I had plus 1 and now I
have plus 16, so obviously
I've added 15.
So I have to subtract 15 to keep
this, to keep these three
lines all equal to each other.
So to understand where that
comes from, let me just remind
you, my denominator was
looking like this.
I'd like it to have a perfect
square, and then subtract a
constant, or add a constant.
Right now I have something
that--
I don't have a perfect
square in here.
I can't make this into a perfect
square unless I add a
certain amount to the
constant right here.
So I had to add a 15 to
the constant here.
Notice 16 minus 15 is 1.
That's my check, also, that
the lines are equal.
And so what I've done, is I've
added 15 and subtracted 15,
and then I put this plus 16 into
here. x minus 4 quantity
squared is exactly these first
three terms. And then I keep
the minus 15.
Now, you might say, why
did you do this?
So let's make sure we
understand why we're
completing the square on this.
If we come back, I'm going to
put this line in place of
what's in the denominator there,
because these three
things are all equal.
So this is actually the integral
of dx over x minus 4
quantity squared minus 15.
Now you might say, Christine,
this looks no easier.
I don't know why you did this.
But it actually is one of our
favorite, or least favorite,
depending on how you feel about
it, types of, types of
tricks we use now, which is
the trig substitution.
So some people love this because
they just have to
memorize a little formula, and
some people love it because
they can draw a triangle and
understand what they choose.
I'm going to show you, remind
you what the formula was you
saw in class.
I believe Professor Jerison
said something like this.
If the denominator is in the
form u squared minus a
squared, this implies
that you make u
equal to a secant theta.
Now, he probably wrote it as x,
but I wrote it as u for a
very specific reason.
Because here I have x minus 4.
I have x minus 4 quantity
squared.
Now, this is where it gets
a little rough, right?
This is not a perfect square,
but it is the perfect square,
it is the square of the
square root of 15.
So I can write the denominator
in the form, something squared
minus something else squared.
And again, you might say,
why is this good?
Well, what we're going to be
able to do, is we're going to
be able to rewrite this in
terms of trigonometric
functions, which will make
it much simpler to solve.
So let's use what Professor
Jerison gave us.
And so what we see, is that
this is u and this is a.
Right?
So I get x minus 4 is
equal to square root
of 15 secant theta.
Now, you might not like this
square root of 15, but it's
just hanging out.
It's not causing any problems.
It's just a number there, so
we'll keep it a square
root of 15.
So you don't have to
worry about it.
Now what's the point again?
Let me just remind you, the
object is to get this in terms
of the trig functions.
So we should anticipate they
probably we'll have some
tangent functions
to go with this.
And there are two reasons
to think that.
The first reason to think
that is at some point, I
have to find dx.
Well, the derivative of
secant involves secant
and tangent, right?
So that's going to pull in a
tangent function somewhere.
I'm also going to have a tangent
function show up
somewhere else.
And where that's going to
be, is coming from this
denominator, this expression
in the denominator.
Because there's a certain trig
identity that we should have
memorized, but I'll
just remind you.
I'll write it here and put
a star next to it.
It's 1 plus tangent squared
theta is equal to secant
squared theta.
So this is a--
I'll even put a star
on the other side.
So we should really
remember this.
Now, where does it come from?
It comes from the cosine
squared theta plus sine
squared theta equals
1 identity.
You can divide everything
by cosine squared theta
and get this one.
So we have this identity, and so
if you notice, we're going
to be able to manipulate the
expression right here, and get
the denominator to look like
tangent squared theta.
So let's do some of that work
off to the right here.
So what did I say we needed?
We have this expression.
We need dx, so let's find--
actually, no.
Let's find the denominator
first, because I was just
talking about it.
So if I look at what x minus
4 squared is, I'm going to
substitute in this expression.
So x minus 4 squared minus 15 is
the same as, based on this
substitution, square root 15
secant theta squared minus 15,
which is 15 secant squared theta
minus 15, which, just to
hammer home the point, is 15
times the quantity secant
squared theta minus 1.
OK?
Everybody follows, hopefully.
All I've done is the
substitution I made, and then
I started expanding, or I
squared this term, and I
factored out the 15.
And now let's go back to
my start expression.
What is secant squared
theta minus 1?
It's tangent squared theta.
So we get 15 tangent
squared theta.
So that is actually what the
denominator of our integral is
going to be over there.
So I'm going to come in
and put that part--
actually, let me even
put this here, too.
So right now, our denominator
is tangent 15
tangent squared theta.
So far, so good.
But of course, if I put a dx
up here, I'm in trouble.
Because I have, it's a function
of theta now.
So I need to write this--
I shouldn't write
in terms of x.
I need to figure out what
it is in terms of theta.
And to do that, we again use the
substitution that we made.
Which is just above the
starred expression.
It was that x minus 4 equals
square root 15 secant theta.
This is going to allow us
to find what d theta
is in terms of dx.
OK?
So let's do that.
So I'm not done, by the way,
over here, I'm not done.
I've got a little gap I've got
to fill in the numerator.
So let's come back over here.
So now we have x minus
4-- let me just write
that one more time.
So we get dx is equal to
the square root of 15.
Well, what's the derivative
of secant theta?
It's secant theta tangent
theta d theta.
So now I have all the
pieces I need.
And I'm actually going to
rewrite the whole thing over
here underneath, so that
I can work with it
a little bit more.
So the dx is in the numerator.
Square root 15 secant theta tan
theta d theta, all over 15
tan squared theta.
Now, this might still look a
little messy, but we can
simplify it some more.
We divide out by 1 tangent,
we'll pull this out in front.
And notice, what's secant?
Secant theta is 1 over cosine
theta, and tangent theta is
sine theta over cosine theta.
So let's write that down.
So this becomes square
root 15 over 15.
We'll just leave it out there.
It's not hurting anyone.
So we get a 1 over cosine
theta times--
well, tangent theta, 1 over
tangent theta is cotangent
theta also.
There's another way
to think about it.
So it's cosine theta over
sine theta d theta.
So these divide out.
And I'm left with, I'm taking
now an antiderivative of 1
over sine theta, which
is cosecant theta.
So I have to find an
antiderivative of cosecant theta.
Well, you can find that with
the exact same strategy you
found, or I should say,
that Professor
Jerison used in class--
or maybe it was actually
Professor
Miller in that lecture--
to find an antiderivative
of secant theta.
So you can do the same kind of
thing with cosecant theta,
because they have the same
kind of derivatives.
Cosecant and cotangent have
very similar-looking
derivatives to tangent
and secant.
Same kinds of relationships.
So you can actually find
that antiderivative.
So this is some constant
we don't care about.
And once you find that, this
will be in terms of theta.
Your final answer needs to be in
terms of x, but you saw how
to do that, actually.
You just need to make a triangle
that represents the
relationship between
x and theta.
So I'll draw a picture of that
triangle, then I'll give a
little summary of what we did,
and then we'll stop.
So let me draw a picture
of that triangle.
So from here, all you would
do is actually find this
antiderivative, and then you
would have to make the right
kind of substitution
in terms of theta.
We want to know, how do
we find that, do that
substitution.
So the triangle is going to come
from the following thing.
We know x minus 4, again,
is square root
of 15 secant theta.
So I'm going to make
this theta.
Secant theta, well, it's 1 over
cosine theta, cosine is
adjacent over hypotenuse,
so secant is
hypotenuse over adjacent.
Right?
That's the relationship.
So x minus 4 over 15
is equal to the
hypotenuse over the adjacent.
Did I square root?
Sorry.
Square root.
So the hypotenuse is x minus 4,
the adjacent is square root
of 15, and then now I can
fill in the opposite
by Pythagorean theorem.
Right?
I just take this squared, and
I subtract this squared, and
then I take the square root.
So I get the square root of x
minus 4 squared minus 15.
So whatever I have in terms
of theta, I just
look at this triangle.
If I had in my answer, sine
theta, I would replace sine
theta by this square root
divided by x minus 4.
Because that's what
sine theta is.
And so from, that's
how I finish this
type of problem, always.
I want to have a picture of this
triangle, label a theta,
use my substitution to give me
what two of the sides are, use
the Pythagorean theorem
to get the third side.
So that's the strategy.
So let's go back and just
remind ourselves
where we came from.
We're going to go all the
way to the other side.
This was a long, long problem.
So what did we do
in this problem?
I wanted us to find an
antiderivative of something.
And right away, we can't use
partial fractions, because we
can't factor out an x here.
So I'm forced to use completing
the square.
So I completed the square first.
That was the little
algebra that I had to do first.
Then once I have that
little bit of algebra, I get
into a situation where I'm set
up for a trig substitution.
So then I had to start off and
do some trig substituting.
And the things you have to do
to make a trig substitution
work are, pick the right
substitution that makes sense,
which you were given
that in class.
You can also figure it out from
a triangle picture, if
you wanted to.
And then you have to make sure
you substitute not just for
the expression, the function
of x, but also the dx.
So we did all that, and then
we came over, further,
further, further, further,
further, here.
And we had everything
in terms of theta.
So then we had to look at--
we had all these trigonometric
functions of theta.
We simplified that as
far as we could.
We got one we could find.
Then we finally, we take the
antiderivative there, and then
in the very end, we're going
to substitute in for theta,
using the triangle we've
drawn up here.
So!
I think that's where I'm
going to stop this one.
Also, I ran out of board space,
so I have to stop.