PROFESSOR: Welcome back.
So in this session, we're going
to use the matrix method
to solve this linear system
of differential equations.
These are x dot equals
6x plus 5y, and y dot
equals x plus 2y.
So why don't you take a few
minutes to write down the
system in matrix form and
go through the matrix
method to solve it.
And I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So let's write down this
system in matrix form.
You would have a vector with
entries x and y prime equals a
matrix with entries 6, 5,
1, 2 multiplying the
column vector xy.
So now, we did big
part of the work.
The matrix method tells us
that we need to find the
eigenvalues of this matrix
to be able to basically
diagonalize it and seek
eigenvectors so that then we
can just read off the solutions
and write the
solution of the system as a
linear combination of the
eigenvectors that we found.
So let's look for the
eigenvalues first.
The eigenvalues would be
computed by seeking the
determinant of this matrix in
this form, 6 minus lambda, 5,
1, 2 minus lambda.
We're going to have an equation
on lambda, solve for
lambda, and the solutions
will be our eigenvalues.
So the determinant would be 6
minus lambda multiplying 2
minus lambda minus 5, 1
dot 5, equals to 0.
So here, the lambda that
lambda gives us
a lambda dot squared.
We have minus 6 lambda
minus 2 lambda, which
would be minus 8 lambda.
And then, we would have 2 dot 6,
which is 12, minus 5, which
gives us 7.
So quadratic equation in lambda,
and you can factorize
it and find the solutions, which
is lambda 1 equals to 1,
lambda 2 equals to 7.
So we're done with
the first part.
These are our eigenvalues.
They're not repeated.
They're just completely
different and real valued.
So now, we're going to look at
the eigenvectors associated to
each eigenvalue.
So first eigenvector would be
associated with lambda 1
equals to 1.
So we would be solving
this system.
We would be solving this
system with a new
matrix, 6 minus 1.
I'm going to spell out this
one so that 2 minus 1.
So this is just our lambda,
multiplying an unknown vector
with components a1 and a2
equals to zero vector.
And basically here, the unknowns
are a1 and a2.
So this is simply 5, 5, 1, and
1, a1, a2 equals to 0, 0.
So as you saw before, here,
basically, we can read off the
equation as being 5a1 plus 5a2
equals to 0 and another one
which is a1 plus
a2 equals to 0.
They're the same equations.
So really, we just have a1
plus a2 equals to 0.
And so our vector V1 could be
picked to just have component
1, for example, a1
equals to 1.
And its second component
would just be minus 1.
That would be one
pick for our V1.
We could normalize this vector
if you wanted to.
I'm just going to keep
it like this for now.
So if we look now for the
second negative vector
corresponding to the second
eigenvalue of 7, I would be
looking for the components of
these vectors by doing a
similar solving for
the same thing.
And I'm going to spell it out
again so that you see where
the terms are coming from.
It's just 6 minus the value
of my lambda, 0, 0.
So here, we have 6 minus
7, which is 1, 5.
And then, we have 1 and 2 minus
7, which is minus 5.
So really, what do you have is
an equation minus 1 plus 5a2
in both cases.
So we can pick a value for
a1 or a2 and write
down a vector V2.
And for example, the form of
a1 equals to, let's pick a2
equals to 1.
And we would have a1 equals
to 5, for example.
Again, if you wanted an
orthonormal basis formed by
your V1, V2, you would just
normalize these two vectors.
So here, basically, we can then
rewrite the solution to
the original system as being
linear combinations of--
so I'm just going to write
it in vector form.
The first vector 1, I
keep it in V1, V2,
that way you see it.
And then, I'll go into
the component.
We'd have V1 exponential of the
value of lambda we found
that corresponds to V1.
So it would be 1 dot t.
And then, V2 exponential of
the lambda value that
corresponds to V2.
And then, basically, we
just have constants
of integration here.
And so the solution to this
problem would be linear
combination of the vectors by
the basis of our eigenvectors
and multiplied by the
exponentials assigned a value
of the eigenvalues that we found
when we looked for the
eigenvalues of the matrix
of the system.
So here, just know that like for
the 1D problem that we saw
before, we're building a
solution based on linear
combination of lucky guesses
that we used.
And in the one equation case, we
used a guess of e to lambda
dot t in 1D.
Here, in this case, we had a
guess of a vector in the form
of lambda dot t that we use.
And then, basically, we just
solved for the lambdas, and
solved for the V's,
and did a linear
combination of all the solutions.
Like we did before in the 1D
case, we solved the lambda.
We had different values
of lambda.
We did a linear combinations
of the exponentials.
So that ends this problem.
And here, the key is just to
go through the method of
diagonalizing your matrix.
Basically, it's finding the
eigenvalues, and then
computing the eigenvectors
associated with that, and
writing your solutions in terms
of a linear combination
of the solution that you found.