PROFESSOR: Welcome to
this recitation.
In this recitation, we're
going to look at linear
systems with complex roots.
So the system we're examining
is the one giving us x dot
equals minus 3x minus 2, and
y dot equals 5x minus y.
And you're asked to use
the matrix methods
to solve this system.
So why don't you take
a pause here and try
to solve this problem?
And I'll be right back.
Welcome back.
So the first step is to write
this system in matrix form.
So we introduced a vector xy,
the matrix multiplying column
vector xy again.
The coefficients are going
to be minus 3,
minus 2, 5, minus 1.
So the first step in solving
this system is to find the
eigenvalues of the matrix A.
So the eigenvalues of matrix A
are basically the solutions to
this following determinant
equal to 0, minus 3 minus
lambda minus 2, 5, minus 1
minus lambda, determinant
equals to 0.
Here, the lambda are the
unknown eigenvalues.
And to get this determinant,
we're basically multiplying
these two terms, minus
minus 2 dot 5, which
gives us a plus sign.
So here, we're going to
have lambda squared.
3 lambda plus 1 lambda
gives us 4 lambda.
And 3 plus 10 gives us 13.
So this second order polynomial
in lambda will give
us the two eigenvalues
for this matrix.
So let's examine the
discriminant.
So we have v squared
minus 4ab.
And this gives us minus 36.
So the discriminant
is negative.
And that tells us that we are
going to have two complex
roots, which is the title
of the recitation.
And these two complex roots
are going to be complex
conjugate of each other.
So formula gives us plus or
minus i of 6 for the root of
the discriminant.
Here, we have minus 4 over 2.
So the two roots are basically
minus 2 plus
or minus i3 or 3i.
So these are our two roots.
So now, let's focus on one
of the roots to get the
eigenvector associated
with the eigenvalue.
So let's focus on the positive
one, for example.
And we could do all the
following again--
AUDIENCE: Minus 2.
PROFESSOR: Minus 2.
Thank you.
We can do all the following
calculation that I'm going to
go do now for the complex
conjugate, and I will explain
at the end how that basically
not change the result.
So for this eigenvalue, we
need to compute now the
eigenvector.
So to do that, we basically have
to use minus 3 minus--
I'm just going to write the
system here, let you
see what I'm doing.
And we are solving
this system.
So where does this
system come from?
It comes from the fact that
we're looking for an
eigenvector, v plus, that is
defined as av plus equals
lambda plus v plus.
And you can then bring
everything on the left-hand
side, a minus lambda i
applied to v plus,
gives us the zero vector.
So that's what we have here.
The unknowns on a1, a2,
and we're going to try
to solve for this.
So if we plug in now for the
value of lambda plus that we
have, we have minus 3 plus 2,
which gives us minus 1.
And then, we have a minus
3i and minus 2.
And for the second line, second
entry of this matrix
you have 5 minus 1
minus minus 2.
So we have 2 minus
1, which is 1.
And then, we have minus 3i.
A1, a2 equals to 0, 0.
So here, you can check for
yourself that these two
equations given by the first
line and the second line are
actually the same.
And so basically, to get a1 and
a2, it is sufficient to
just solve, for example, the
first one, where here, I just
wrote minus 1 minus 3i
multiplied by a1.
Minus 2 a2 equals to 0.
And I just brought the
minus 2 on this side.
So here, you can see that if we
take a1 equals to 0 equals
to plus 2, which would be our
first entry, we can then
cancel out these two and
just have a2 equals to
minus 1 minus 3i.
So this would be one eigenvector
associated with
this eigenvalue.
We could have picked
other ones.
They're basically a parallel
to this one.
So now what?
So what we need to remember is
the meaning of all of this.
Seeking the eigenvalues and the
eigenvectors is basically
equivalent to seeking a solution
in the form lambda t
exponential lambda t with the
direction of the eigenvector
associated with this
eigenvalue.
So now that we actually have
this eigenvector and this
eigenvalue, we can write
down the solution.
And I'm just going to write the
solution in x, which has
entries basically x and y.
And one way of writing it would
be just to basically
first start by writing
what we have there.
I'm just going to
spell it out.
So we have this multiplied
by 2 minus 3i.
So what do we do with this?
Well, we remember our
earlier formula.
So this is exponential minus
2t plus exponential 3it.
So we can split the exponential
3it into a cosine
and a sine.
And this, we're going to also
be able to split it into the
complex part and
the real part.
And then, we're going to combine
the real part and the
complex part.
So let's do that.
Exponential minus 2t
multiplying, basically, cosine
3t plus i sine 3t for the entry
2 minus 1 minus 3i.
So we have an i here
and an i here.
So things can be combined
into a real part.
So in the first entry here,
what are we going to have?
We're going to have cos
3t multiplying 2.
That's going to be
in the real part.
And I'm going to keep
some space.
And another entry here at the
second entry of this vector is
going to give us cosine 3t
multiplied by minus 1.
Oops, here, it should be a 3t.
Sorry.
So minus cosine 3t.
Now, where are we going to have
another real part here?
It's going to come from
a multiplication of
i sine 3t by 3i.
So the two i's together
gives a minus 1.
And we end up with
a plus 3 sine 3t.
So we're done for
the real part.
Now let's focus on the
imaginary part.
What do we have?
We have an i sine 3t
multiplying a 2.
And we have a minus 3i here
multiplying cosine 3t.
So we want to have a minus 3
cosine 3t, and finally, this
minus 1 multiplying
this sine 3t.
So now, we did--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Oh yeah.
Thank you.
2, from this operation.
So now, we did split our
solution into a real part and
an imaginary part.
So how can we write the general
solution of the system?
Well, we knew that for this
linear system of equations.
If we have a complex number
that is a solution to be a
linear equation, then its real
part and its imaginary part
are also two independent
solutions.
So we can write the general
solution of the system as a
linear combination of the real
part and the imaginary part.
And I can just label
this u1 of t and u2
of t here and vector.
And we can then write the
general solution terms of any
constant that would be
determined by the initial
condition if we had one.
Exponential minus 2t along u1
plus c2 exponential minus 2t
along vector u2, which are also
functions of t, just the
difference from what
we had before.
So here, basically we seek
for the eigenvalues
values of the matrix.
We looked for the eigenvector
associated with the complex
eigenvalue.
We were able to write
the full solution.
And then, because of the
linearity property, we were
able to just then extract
two linearly independent
solutions, the real part of the
solution we had and the
imaginary part of the
solution we had.
So what I mentioned earlier
was that we could do this
whole calculation for the other
eigenvalue with a minus.
If you try to do it and trickle
down your minus, you
would see that basically you
would just end up with minus
signs here for basically
in front of the sines.
And what you could do then is
just simply absorb that minus
sign for the general solution
in c1 and c2.
And basically, it gives you
exactly the same form for the
general solution.
So you don't need to redo
it for the second one.
You would still end up with only
two linearly independent
solutions, not four.
OK, so that ends this
recitation.