And so now we come
to problem number
two, which is a classic.
I want you to really pay
attention to it, and in any
case, you should be able
to do this problem
cold at the next exam.
Problem number two.
23, 28.
We have a conducting shell.
It's a metal.
This is the metal.
The inner core vacuum, radius
a, and the outer
shell has radius b.
And there is, right here at the
center, a point charge +
q, and here, at the outer
surface, is a
total charge of - 3q.
That total charge, undoubtedly,
is uniformly
distributed.
Whether you like it or not,
that happens automatically
when this is a metal.
All right now.
Now, you're being asked to
calculate what the electric
field is everywhere
here in space.
Here, here, and there.
Now, there's no charge inside
the conductor, because any
charge inside the conductor
would make me the electrons
experience a force.
The electrons would to start to
flow, and they would kill
the electric field.
So already for r less than b,
and larger than a in the
shell, we know that the electric
field equals 0.
So that's easy.
What, now, is the situation
for our larger than b?
I take a Gaussian sphere--
you have to always work
with symmetry.
So you bring this concentric
sphere here, and this
concentric sphere
has a radius r.
Let us assume, this could be
wrong, that the electric field
is pointing outwards.
It is certainly going
to be radial.
It has to be radial for reasons
of spherical symmetry.
And of course, the surface
elements ds will all be
everywhere perpendicular to the
surface, no matter where
you are on the sphere.
So what is Gauss's law?
Telling us now that to closed
surface integral of e is the
dot product with that ds, that
is the total charge inside the
sphere divided by epsilon 0.
Well, e is everywhere
the same in terms of
magnitude on this sphere.
And so the dot products we will
take plus 1, because we
will make the assumption
that they
are in the same direction.
If the assumption is wrong,
we will quickly find out.
So I find 4 pi r squared
times e equals the
total charge inside.
This is - 3q plus q is
- 2q divided by 4
pi epsilon 0 r squared--
no, 2q, I'm getting
ahead of myself.
Epsilon 0.
Total charge inside divided
by epsilon 0.
And so what do I find for
the electric field?
The electric field then becomes
- 2q divided by 4 pi
epsilon 0 r squared.
And if you really want to get
the direction right, this
minus sign means that my
assumption was wrong, so it's
pointing inwards.
So you can put an R roof here.
It means, you know, this minus
is winning over the plus, so
the electric field is
pointing inwards.
If now you want to know what the
electric field is inside
the inner cavity, then
again, you apply--
here is that radius a.
You again apply a spherical
surface, with radius little r,
and you yourself can very easily
convince yourself that
inside this cavity, the electric
field will now be + q
divided by 4 pi r squared
epsilon 0 R roof.
Or the e field is now not
pointing inwards, but the e
field is here in this cavity,
pointing outwards.
And notice that when r equals
0, right here, you get and
infinite value, which of course
physically has no meaning.
I would like to make a drawing,
which is very useful,
I think, of the electric
field.
I don't think you're being asked
to do this, but it's
always very useful.
The electric field as a function
of distance r from
the center.
Here is location b, and
here is location a.
So we know that right here, we
have a magnetic field which is
- 2 q divided by
4 pi epsilon 0.
r squared becomes now b squared,
because I'm at the
location b, and then it falls
off to 0 proportional to 1
over r squared.
Then inside the shell, inside
the metal, there cannot be any
e field, so it drops to 0.
There's a discontinuity here.
And then inside the cavity, it
increases as 1 over r squared,
and it goes here too.
Infinity for r equals 0.
Now we are being asked about
the induction charges.
If I have here the inner cavity,
radius a and charge +
q here, then I know that the
electric field anywhere here
in the metal is 0.
So if I take some Gaussian
surface r prime, which is
slightly larger than a, and I
apply Gauss's law, then I find
that 4 pi r prime squared
times e must be 0.
Because e is 0, and therefore
it follows that q
inside must be 0.
But how can q inside be 0,
because there is a + q here?
Well, the only way that nature
can do it, that nature
enduces, now, on of the inside
of the inner sphere a total
charge of - q, so that
the net charge inside
this sphere is 0.
And similarly, you can calculate
the induced charge
on the outer shell.
I'd like you to do that, to be
consistent with the electric
field that we just calculated.
It's a very important problem.
You have to fully
understand this.
And as I said, make sure for
next exam that you can do this
blindfolded at 3 AM in
the morning if I
were to wake you up.
Very well.
Now we want to know the electric
potential everywhere.
How is electric potential
defined?
Va potential at a minus the
potential at b is the integral
going from a to b of the
electric field's vector dot dl
over some pass length l So
here is point a, and
here is point b.
Here is some crazy routing.
Here is a little factor dl.
And at that particular location,
the e vector is like
so, and everywhere along the
path do I have to calculate
that dot product, e dot el, and
I have to integrate that
over the whole path.
That is the definition.
Very often do you see in books
that it is minus the integral
in going from b to a of e dot
dl, and that, of course, is
exactly the same thing.
We often, when we can, define
the electric potential at
infinity 0.
It's not always possible, as
you will see in the future,
but whenever we can,
we do that.
It's just convenient.
With gravity, we have a similar
situation, that
gravitational potential, it
didn't matter what you call 0.
Whether you call the ground
floor 0, or the surface of the
table 0, it doesn't matter.
And the reason is that it is
the difference in potential
that determines what the actual
physics will be doing,
and not the absolute value.
So if I go from point a in some
crazy way to point b, and
if the integral of e dot dl
along this path is independent
of how I'm going, then the
potential difference VA minus
VB, is uniquely determined.
And we call the electric
field, then, a
conservative field.
If, however, the potential
difference or I should really
say, if the integral e dot dl
depends on the routing , then
the electric field is
non-conservative.
And it's very hard to imagine
what that can be.
But you're going to see
this in the future,
with Faraday's law.
And almost no one has any
intuition for that.
And the whole concept of
potential difference is then
not even defined, because the
integral e dot dl from one
point to another depends
on the routing.
Gravitational fields are
conservative, because again
there, it doesn't matter how you
move from one point on the
table to a higher point.
But friction is
non-conservative, because if I
have here point a, and I have
here point b, and I move my
finger this way, I experience
a frictional force.
Well, if I go along a straight
line, the work that I have to
do to overcome that friction is
less than if I made these
enormous sidetrack.
So friction is a
non-conservative force.
If you multiply delta v,
electric potential, with a
charge q, then you get energy.
In a similar way, if you
multiply the gravitational
potential, which I will define
now as gh, if you multiply
that with a mass, then
you also get energy.
So you see, the electric charge
q in electricity plays
the same role as the
mass in gravity.
And one could call, then, this
the difference in electric
potential, and this,
the difference in
gravitational potential.
h is the vertical distance
between the two points that
you are considering.
Let's now go back
to our problem.
And we want to know what
va minus the vr.
We have the--
let me make sure that I have
the geometry right.
Yeah.
We have here the radius a, and
we have here + q, and we want
to know what va minus vr is,
and we want to know that
everywhere in space.
va minus vr, let's
call this r.
So what is the potential
difference between-- oh no,
this is not what I meant.
I meant this point to be a.
My shorthand notation is this
point a, potential difference
with this point r.
Well, this is a metal, so
there's no electric field.
So the potential difference
between the surface of the
inner cavity and any point
in the metal equals 0.
What, now, is the situation
when I am anywhere
between a and b?
Well, again, then e, then must
be 0, because it's 0
everywhere in the metal.
The metal is an equipotential
.
What now is the potential
difference between a point b,
say here, I call this point a,
at the surface b, and some
point p, which is at a distance
r from the center?
What now?
If va minus vp.
Well, the electric field
is pointing inwards.
We just calculated that.
It's a function of all r.
For what was 1 over r squared.
And so it should be immediately
obvious that va
must be less than vp.
If I take a plus charge and I
release the plus charge, the
plus charge will move
in this direction.
And the plus charge always moves
from a higher potential
to a lower potential.
That's something that you
really should remember.
When you're in doubt, you take a
plus charge, you release it,
it will move in a certain
direction, of
the electric force.
It always goes from higher
potential to a lower potential.
Whereas a negative charge, so
to speak, flows upstream.
It goes from a lower potential
to a higher potential.
So you already see that va
must be lower than vp.
What is the difference between
here and here?
Well, there is a neat way to do
it, and there is some kind
of a dirty way to do it.
The dirty way would be to say
OK, I take the integral from a
to p of e dot dl.
I will call the l in this case
dr. And I don't worry about
minus signs.
I don't even worry about
this dot product.
Because the dot product
either produces a plus
one or a minus one.
I just do a very dirty
integration job without
worrying about signs.
And even that turns out that
va is not smaller than vp.
I just cheat and put a minus
sign in front of it, and I
think no one can blame
me for that.
Because I know in advance that
va must be smaller than vp.
Now, if you want to do it the
elegant way, the neat way,
which of course is
a little longer,
then it goes as follows.
So now we are larger than b.
The electric field, I go now to
a complete vector notation,
equals minus 2q divided by 4 pi
epsilon 0 r squared R roof.
Would you agree?
It's pointing inwards,.
And of course I will write down,
for dl, I will write
down dr.
So the integral from point a to
point p of the e vector dot
dr can now be written as - 2q
divided by 4 pi epsilon 0
times the integral in going from
location r equals b, that
was that that point a, 2r equals
r, that was that point
p, and now notice carefully.
r roof dot, I shouldn't forget
the dot, dr, which is also a
vector, divided by r squared.
This is nothing but dr. It is
plus dr. I hope you can
convince yourself of that,
because r roof and dr are in
the same direction.
In other words, I will have to
only evaluate this integral dr
over r squared.
And that equals minus 1 over r
between b and r, and so that
equals 1 over b minus
1 over r.
And this value is positive.
Because b is smaller than r.
r was outside b.
And so this is the neat
way to do it.
The elegant way.
And so you'll find now that va
minus vp equals minus 2q
divided by 4 pi epsilon 0 times
1 over b minus 1 over r.
Potential has no direction.
It's a scalar.
We express it in terms of
volts in MKS units.
And when you go to infinity,
then r goes to infinity.
In this case, v goes to 0.
And so, if you want to know what
exactly the potential is
at that location a, which was at
that radius b, then you'll
find minus 2q divided by 4 pi
epsilon 0 times 1 over b.
This now is the potential
at the outer surface.
I would also like to make a
drawing of the potential as a
function of r.
It always helps, it gives
you some insight.
So here is the potential v,
and here is the radius r.
I have here the outer shell b,
and here the inner shell a.
Well, the electric potential
here we know equals minus 2q
divided by 4 pi epsilon 0b.
We just calculated that.
And then it falls
off as 1 over r,
proportional to 1 over 4.
In the shell, there's
no electric field.
If there's no electric field, it
must be equal in potential.
So the potential is everywhere
the same, so it
remains this value.
And now you go inside the
sphere, and that's the part
where I think I want
you to show that.
Now the potential will
increase again.
And I'll bet you anything that
it will also increase as 1
over r, and it'll go to infinity
at r equals 0.
So I want you with a Gaussian
surface, to calculate what the
potential is for r.
It's less than a, and
r is larger than 0.
What you see here is something
interesting.
That there is one spot inside
the inner cavity where the
potential is 0.
And I would like you
to calculate
at what r that occurs.
I did it.
I may have made a mistake.
And I found when r equals ab
divided by 2a plus b that
right there, the potential
is again 0.
So if this is that inner cavity
which has radius a,
then there is here somewhere a
radius where the potential
everywhere is 0.
All right.
Potential difference is
connected with work.
When I put a 1 coulomb charge in
my pocket, and I move from
one potential to another, then
if I go from a lower potential
to a higher potential, with the
1 coulomb in my pocket, I
walk uphill, I have to
do positive work.
If I go with the 1 coulomb in
my pocket from a higher
potential to a lower
potential, I
have to do no work.
I have to do negative work.
The charge moves all by itself
under influence of the
electric field.