The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit
MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
Some content in this audio is
not covered under a Creative
Commons license.
For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT
OpenCourseWare website.
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
and we will spend the next
couple of weeks grading them.
But that was pretty fun on
Friday so [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
We've been talking these
past couple of weeks--
we've been talking the past
couple of weeks about serious
games, games for education,
games as an art form, as a
means of expression.
And we're going to be continuing
some of those
discussions later on.
But the whole idea is to sort
of give you, to sort of prep
you, for a situation where
you're going to make a game
for a client.
And for this last assignment,
you're actually going to be
making a game based on a problem
that Lisa is going to
be talking about.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: My name is
Jim [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I'm a clinical psychologist.
I work at--
I was at Beth Israel, I'm just
starting at Brigham and
Women's Hospital, one of the
Harvard mafia hospitals.
And my area is using interactive
media for clinical
training but especially for
treatment of clinical problems.
So we make computer programs
to help treat clinical
disorders in psychology.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: It's
my turn to stand up.
I'm [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I'm a psychiatrist at UMass.
I trained in the same
place like Jim used
to work, Beth Israel.
And my focus is primarily
clinical.
I'm an attending psychiatrist
in a variety of settings,
inpatient, outpatient.
And what I brought up to Jim
and then Phillip was a
practical question that I will
try to present, which is
helping psychiatry residents
deal with angry, agitated, and
potentially [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
patients.
Later this is a significant
and largely unknown issue.
Certainly the research is
picking up, and we don't quite
understand the extent
of the problem.
And but I'll say more.
I'll save it for our
presentation.
Thank you for coming here.
PROFESSOR: So when they
contacted me, there was the
usual interest in trying to
make some sort of digital
piece of software to help the
training residents in learning
how to deal with violence
in mental institutions.
And immediately the first thing
that I thought, well
before we jump right into
digital, let's try doing
something in analog first.
Let's try prototyping
something first.
But it also occurred to me that,
in the real world of
game design, there's actually a
lot more jobs in game design
outside of the game industry
than inside the game industry.
There are a lot of companies out
there that are basically
looking for solutions.
Some of which may be games.
And you might end up working in
some of those capacities.
A lot of folks in advertising
for instance
are involved in games.
A lot of folks who are
interested in improving
teaching methods, or improving
simulations, working on--
trying to think of
an example--
public awareness.
And people who are also now
working in website design and
in various online services, who
are trying to think about
how to make their experiences
a little bit more game like.
There are really really good
ways of doing that, and there
are really really bad
ways of doing that.
And for the most part what we're
hoping is that, if you
end up getting one of those
jobs, you're going to be able
to bring some of your personal
insight as having actually
done game design, as opposed
to just copying what games
have done, and just assuming,
well, it kind of looks like a
game, therefore it is a game.
You guys know that now.
So this is kind of get your
feet wet, in terms of
designing something, designing
for somebody else's needs.
The important thing to keep in
mind is, who is going to be
playing your game, or who's
this game intended for.
And in what context are they
going to be playing your game.
One of the particular problems
that you're trying to address,
what's the part of
the system that
you're trying to simulate.
And what kinds of insights do
you hope people are going to
get out of that.
The problem they're going
to talk about it huge.
If you noticed I uploaded
actually four readings to the
class website.
Only one of them is required,
but all of them are useful.
I will be uploading more.
These are all reference material
for the team to use
however you wish.
Because the problem is so huge
and vast, you don't have to
solve the whole problem.
You pick one thing that you're
excited about, that you're
interested about, and that you
think that you might have a
good strategy.
Do the usual brainstorm.
We're going to be going through
brainstorming and team
selection pretty much
just this week.
And try to identify some small
part that might be addressable
with a card game or a board
game, or I'll talk a little
bit about role-playing games
in a couple of weeks.
So with that being said
I'm going to turn
it over to you guys.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: OK so we'll
try to take turns to talk
about violence in psychiatry,
in particular.
So as Jim has pointed out,
violence is a large issue.
What I'm going to try to focus
on, as I mentioned earlier,
rather than engaging with
psychiatric patients,
especially psychiatric patients
on an inpatient
program, which is where the
question for me came from.
And obviously violence
can be looked at in
a variety of ways.
And I think in one of the
handouts that I sent to
Philip, Violence in Mental
Illness, they talk about the
biological, psychological
theories that the social
dimension of violence and how
it can be understood.
If you look at the human
development, and no matter
what theory you consider,
either a traditional
drive-based theory like Freud
or Erikson's stages, each
seems to define a certain
developmental goal, and often,
achieving or achieving in a
faulty way that goal can
create potential for aggression
and sometimes violence.
A little child or an adult who's
dependent or needs are
frustrated may try to takeover
and get those met, in one way
or another.
So what I use as a
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] metaphor for
the origins of violence is a
communication breakdown.
At some level, something doesn't
happen right between
the person who gets angry and
those around him or her.
So in a most generic way,
basically communication is
less about who says what to
whom, than in what channel,
and with what affect.
The breakdown can occur
at many levels.
Again, this is the
generic form.
I hope I'll [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
what I mean.
And especially what can be done
at a practical level,
let's say when you are the
resident on call at night.
And the staff calls you up and
says so and so is getting out
of control.
She's raising her voice,
threatening, pounding walls,
wanting to get out, refusing
medications.
How do you approach
such a person?
And again, the intervention
can happen
at different levels.
And actually one goal of the
training, or potentially the
game that you might consider,
is what to do.
How do you establish when do you
engage fully, by yourself,
with outside help, when
intervention is minimal and
you just bring pens with you,
restrain the patient, use
pharmacology.
So it's a continuum
of interventions.
I'm going to just focus on
what to do when you can
actually engage the patient.
Again, continuing the metaphor
is what Walter Fisher has
described as this type of
narrative, rationality, as
opposed to the traditional
rational paradigm that defines
people as thinking beings that
actually do make decisions and
base their actions on evidential
reasoning.
Or rational people.
We analyze the situation.
We come up with the best
possible outcome.
Walter Fisher talks about that
fact that we are all
storytellers, that we try to
interact and understand others
based on the narrative
that we have about
ourselves and about others.
My assumption, and again, this
is just the introductory
metaphor if you want, that at
some point violence can be
caused by a disruption
in this narrative.
Things don't make
sense anymore.
We feel misunderstood.
We feel the victim
of an injustice.
And that those principles
apply to somebody who is
struggling with a
mental illness.
Where things have a much
narrower window of opportunity
than for people who are able
to flexibly adapt to the
demands of reality.
So we all know who this is, and
the reason I put it up--
and I have to admit I haven't
looked into the copyright, I
know there are longer and longer
copyright rules for
using cartoons, so you'll
have to forgive me.
My point is that this
is an angry person.
And as someone who
is communicating.
I think we get quickly and
clearly the fact that his
emotional range may be intense,
but it's fairly narrow.
It doesn't cover like
a spectrum.
And the communication
is fairly simple.
He's in distress.
He is imposing his point
of view, his space.
He could become very aggressive
and assaultive.
I think that the language
is very simplistic.
How would we approach the Hulk
in trying to calm him down and
change his color?
That's the end of my
introductory metaphor.
And please, feel free to
interrupt, jump in, and make
this presentation as long or
as short as you want me to.
There are many slides, but I'm
not going to go through every
single line.
I'm just using this as a
stimulus for the conversation
especially from your
perspective
and from your needs.
As I said, I'm a clinical
provider, I'm a psychiatrist.
I deal with patients all the
time, many of whom are angry
or potentially angry or
potentially assaultive.
And I may do things after so
many years instinctively.
But sometimes I have to think
through, OK, this is the
situation, how do I do to
maximize the benefit for the
patient I'm treating and
to keep myself safe.
I've been assaulted just
once, in 15 years.
It was like in the movies.
A VA patient, former Green
Beret, who got upset with the
system, and picked up a very
heavy armchair and lifted it
above his head.
And we established
eye contact then.
I think he wondered, what should
I do with this puny
little doctor?
Should I squash him or not?
And at the end, I guess it was a
last, you know, split second
moment, he decided to
throw it to my side.
A large section of the wall came
down, so I was looking at
it wondering, well
I could have been
that wall coming down.
He ran out.
It took him a while--
for people to catch
up with him.
And two cruisers full of police
officers to subdue him.
So I guess, no communication
there.
He was just subdued.
What's the magnitude
of the problem?
I think it's substantial.
And actually more than 10 years
ago, there were some
isolated reports of how
significant the problem was in
terms of the trainees, and
especially psychiatry
trainees, being the target of
verbal and physical violence.
On this first page I
talk about medical
students in one study.
Numbers are relatively small.
But again, the study
is 14 years old.
A survey of psychiatry residents
showed that assaults
or threats of violence are
clearly one of the most
difficult events in
their training.
And some were wondering
introspectively if this is the
right field for them.
Actually some students may
wonder reading this literature
whether psychiatry is
the right field
for them to go into.
And as you see in the fourth
article, almost two-thirds of
psychiatry residents were
assaulted at least once during
their training.
And obviously like with any
dangerous situation, the risk
of post-traumatic symptoms
can be substantial.
Either acute stress response
or longer lasting issues.
The idea of improving their
training and their ability to
deal with the situation
has multiple benefits.
Those who know what
to do are never or
almost never assaulted.
Not only that, if they happened
to be exposed, the
likelihood of developing
post-traumatic goes down
significantly.
So I don't think I need
to demonstrate
that point any further.
The assault rate in a more
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] relatively
recent study, 10 years old,
pretty old, you see that
overall the number of assault
rate was 30% to 40%.
Men tended to be slightly
more physically
assaulted than women.
AUDIENCE: Can you define what
assault means, exactly?
What qualifies as assault?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Assault
basically means kind of laying
hands on the person.
And the assault resulting in
an injury, of any kind.
Skin being kind of broken
through or--
AUDIENCE: Just holding
the clinician
wouldn't be an assault?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Well it would
be an assault because that
kind of grabbing action could
actually result in injury.
And I think it would be probably
very limiting to talk
only about physical injuries,
especially since the
psychological consequences are
often the longer lasting and
much more significant.
I think what the surveys have
shown also is that how
unprepared trainees in the
mental health and outside the
mental health field
are actually.
Often this is reduced to a few
lectures, especially during
orientation.
And then they are thrown into
the lion cage and they learn
on the job.
And many of these findings
are introspective.
Many trainees felt that well, I
didn't say anything, because
I thought I was supposed to
toughen up and bite the bullet
and move on.
Or this is part of the job, I
chose this, it's my fault.
Or maybe I did something
wrong.
Maybe I was the one who made
it so the assault happened.
So a lot of reasons that were
just, again, not looked into.
Fear of being scrutinized.
How come that I'm
the one that was
assaulted, and not 10 trainees.
How I'm going to explain this.
I was so frightened that I
cannot even remember clearly
what happened to me.
So there are a variety
of reasons why
people who are in training--
and again, I'm focusing on a
again a very small segment, a
specific group of trainees
in medical
and psychiatric training.
But I could easily think of
other situations of people who
are exposed to the potential
for violence and where such
training would be helpful.
Up until now, and for the most
part the data that I was able
to collect, and most people in
looking at this have been able
to collect is fairly limited.
There are certain limited
number of programs.
Methodologically the research
is quite faulty.
You can just talk about how
limited the generalizability
of the findings are.
And often people have
talked about what
happened in the past.
So clearly the recall bias is
a major limiting factor in
understanding what happened.
Also, as Jim asked me, so how
do you define assault.
One of the biggest problems
with most research in this
field is that defining assault,
aggression, is done
in very idiosyncratic ways.
It's hard to compare
different studies.
So this is a compilation of what
people in different areas
have thought about in
terms of improving
the psychiatric training.
And as you see most often, in
the last few years, the idea
of using simulation to expose
the trainees to a protected
environment that has clearly
defined boundaries and
consequences, and basically that
can be repeated almost in
identical fashion in order to
gain proficiency, this coming
up more and more.
What many training programs
are doing is to use
standardized patients
that use actors.
And that of course
would behave in
a programmed fashion.
They make get up to you and
make fists, but hopefully
they'll not get so much into
the role and then they're
punching you.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: I think this is
the real challenge, is that
there's different levels
of learning.
You can learn kind of a list of
facts, things to do if your
patient starts to get agitated
and threatening.
And you can learn how to take a
test on it and forget it the
next day, especially if
it doesn't come up
for you right away.
And then there's the question
of internalizing it so you
actually have not just kind of a
working knowledge but really
understand what you should
do in different kinds of
circumstances.
And that's where the idea of
role playing with live role
plays for the trainees--
it could be residents, and
mental health providers--
can really be helpful so they
have some sense, some
semblance of this kind
of training.
But the tricky things with these
role plays is it's not
easy to ensure that everybody
receives high quality access
to well trained actors.
Here at Harvard Medical School,
they probably do.
At UMass, they probably do.
But there's a lot of places.
And if you expand beyond
psychiatry to every mental
health center in the country,
every caseworker who is going
out to visit a patient at their
home, or social worker,
they're definitely not getting
this kind of training.
And so the ones who really I
think you said before are
really well trained are
the nurses, actually.
Because they get a different
kind of training that's really
pretty effective,
it sounds like.
But the mental health
care providers
often have no training.
And then they're the ones who
are kind of in a closed room
with the person who can
become really violent.
Especially if it's at their
home, or an inpatient unit.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Jim was making
reference to that
psychiatrist at MGH who last
year was stabbed by a patient
in the outpatient clinic.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: You all hear
about this last year?
Can you just describe
the situation?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Well, it was
late in the evening, when most
things like this have the
potential of happening.
This was a neuro evaluation
or [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
in the Bipolar Clinic at MGH.
Basically he was angry from the
beginning and was able to
stab repeatedly.
An off guard person who just
happened to walk by.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: It was a
police officer, right?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Yeah.
He was one of the security
people for
that particular clinic.
He came and he had a gun.
I don't know how often off-duty
security people carry
their guns.
But he opened and killed
the patient.
So he was charged.
Eventually was cleared.
For using excessive force.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: What happened
to the psychiatrist?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Well, the
psychiatrist was admitted into
the hospital and required
extensive surgeries.
She was stabbed in the chest
and in the neck.
It was a fairly gruesome-- she
survived and I think she's
back at work.
But this is an extreme case.
And I'm afraid that many of the
things that we talk about,
the principles that we may
come up with, may not
necessarily be so helpful, other
than thinking back at a
level of intervention.
It is quite conceivable that
for somebody who charges at
you, you won't be able to talk
him down, you won't be able to
use any of the nice
de-escalation principles that
I'm going to talk about
in a few minutes.
But, figuring out what
do, I think it means
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
AUDIENCE: You mentioned that
nurses have a different
training system for this, and
it seems to be effective.
What is that training, like what
is different about what
nurses get taught?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Well, there
are some, in most states,
there are some regulations that
try to implement some
level of training or are
designed specifically for
patients who get
out of control.
And that's not only
psychiatry.
Emergency room teams have
probably the most highest rate
of assaultive patients, across
diagnostic departments.
Often psychiatric patients,
especially patients using
substance abuse, will
get out of control.
So if you want to become an
emergency physician, or if you
work in the field as an EMT or
another capacity, you'll have
to deal with these situations.
What makes the nurses somewhat
better trained is that they
often are the frontline
staff dealing with
out of control patients.
And I think that's probably
pretty sad, because physicians
should be equally, and trainees,
physicians and
trainees should be equally
well trained.
But on the nursing front, there
has been some progress.
In Massachusetts, the Department
of Mental Health
has some mandatory training.
But there's a lot of red tape
there, but there a lot of
helpful aspects, including
aspects
related to stop attacks.
And I wish I could have
presented a recording of a
training session for staff.
When I went to it, I thought it
would be something like a
very spectacular kind of
kung-fu, how you do it.
When in fact, the emphasis is
how to keep yourself safe, and
believe it or not how to keep
the person safe, the person
that you're blocking the
punches, the person that may
be trying to strangle you, or
keep you in a stronghold, or
scratch you, or rip your hair.
Again, even when you're trying
to be intervene or you're
trying to protect yourself,
and keep the
other person safe.
No punching, kicking, no kind
of spectacular steps.
But again, that's also I feel
could be an interesting topic
for a simulation.
How do you interact with--
especially since again
I'm a totally kind of
outsider in the field.
Having kids, they were asking
me the other day about
Microsoft's Kinect.
And I thought that was really
interesting because the level
of interaction with computer
generated interfaces is very
interesting, and certainly
would be a safe bet to be
attacked by somebody
from the TV.
AUDIENCE: It sounds like the
nurses get better training
because the states require them
to have better training.
GUEST SPEAKER 2:
That's correct.
That's a part of it.
I've been trying at UMass to
suggest that not only the
staff physicians get exposed to
the training but even the
psychiatry trainees and other
trainees, especially in
emergency medicine.
They should all really
know about it.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: I suspect some
of this have to do with
the benefits of being
in a union.
So a union can demand that
nurses receive this better
training, where the physicians
don't have a union.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: It's
also about numbers.
On any unit, you
have six, seven
nurses for one physician.
And the nurses are there in
shifts around the clock.
So their likelihood of being
exposed to an out-of-control
patient are much higher.
Usually on these units people
intervene as a team.
And as a team leader that tries
to apply so many of the
principles I'm going
to talk about.
And then if there is need for
seclusion or restraints, then
that has to be done in a
coordinated fashion.
And things are much clearer,
as I said,
on the nursing front.
Maybe because they are doing
it all the time and because
there are some tight
regulations,
because they're unionized.
And at least half of the
literature really comes from
the nursing direction.
So that's a tangent.
PROFESSOR: Just want to ride
off the Kinect comment that
you were making.
We will be talking about a
little bit more about live
action games so that's kind of
how you prototype something
that's going to be a motion
gesture computer game.
You don't obfuscate.
Actually having to write code to
do that, that sort of body
recognition, is kind of annoying
and expensive.
But you can test off a lot of
ideas just by having two
people play with coding.
Safety becomes the biggest
concern for
the players as well.
It's kind of interesting in this
particular case that you
are trying to teach someone
how to prevent
damage to both parties.
That actually kind of
helps you with the
design a lot actually.
That's only one problem.
You'll go into more details
about the kinds of things to
prevent it escalating into
actual conflict.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: And the idea
is basically to do your best
to not end up at that particular
extreme of direct
combat, which is not--
So ideally you don't
have to go there.
And as I said in 15 years I've
been assaulted once.
I'm sure I was lucky.
People think that my eyebrows
are intimidating.
So don't tend to get very
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Again I'm going to tell a few,
you know, tell you about a few
pearls and a few tricks
that I personally use.
It may not be helpful
for everybody.
Over time, you develop
you own style.
The idea is to be able to make
an assessment and try to take
preventative steps.
And I think that's the secret.
And this is what I hope better
training may be the user
simulation and gaming
would be helpful.
Now I'm going to just, I'm going
to jump into talking
about prevention and
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
but identifying how you assess
and how you think about the
potential for violence.
And these are some known risk
factors for aggression.
Obviously the history of
violence is the top.
How recent, how frequently,
those people become
assaultive.
What's the pattern
of escalation.
What are the associated
symptoms.
What happens before somebody
becomes assaultive.
Why is this important?
Because you can do, and probably
should do before, you
engage with the patient an
assessment at that level.
And it will help you figure out
how deep to get involved,
how likely you are to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] the patient.
Versus saying, oh, I don't need
this, I need help, let's
go in as a team.
So that-- that makes
it important.
People often talk about
violence and a rise in
tendencies.
Young people tend to
be more assaultive,
and there's no surprise.
Also older people who have
dementia and get more
disinhibited and more likely
to become reactive.
I always like to tell
the story about a
patient with dementia.
I was moonlighting, and he swung
at me as I was passing.
And then I went to
talk to him.
Well, I don't know, you just
passed by, and I was upset,
and you were the closest.
So I thought I would try to--
So there was no way for
me to predict that.
It wasn't a serious thing, it
wasn't a predatory type of
assaultiveness where
somebody plans.
Doesn't like you,
goes after you.
A colleague of mine was
attacked by a patient.
The patient watched when people
were not around, went
into the doctors room,
locked the
door, and started punching.
So that's a totally
different animal.
So the distinction between
impulsive, affective if you
want or the type of aggression
and the predatory is essential
to keep in mind.
In some subcultures, violence is
not allowed certainly much
more frequent.
People of a lower socioeconomic
status may be
more likely to become
assaultive.
Patients of a limited cognitive
ability, especially
when institutionalized, are
way more likely to become
assaultive.
And then it's many, many
diagnoses increase the
likelihood of assaultiveness.
The top are psychotic disorders,
like schizophrenia.
Mood disorders like bipolar.
I told you about what we call
cognitive disorders,
especially dementia and
confusional states.
Patients that have had traumatic
brain injuries or
that have had epilepsy.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: There's a
real problem with Iraq or
Afghanistan veterans, when they
have had an IE explode
under their vehicle.
And they had a brain injury.
Now they have a lot of
disinhibition about violence.
And they can just go off
sometimes very unexpectedly.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: The frontal
lobe exerts a sort of
inhibitory influence on our
ability to function.
And that allows us
to plan, to think
ahead, to sequence events.
This is the executive function
of our frontal lobe.
When it's impaired either in a
trauma, or after surgery, or
being in an accident, or
becoming demented, that
ability to operate in that
fashion may be impaired.
Violence is a possible
side effect.
Substance abuse are at the top
of the list, because of the
disinhibition, both during the
intoxication phase and during
the withdrawal people tend to
become very agitated and
assaultive.
There are certain personality
disorders.
So when we think about the
percentage order, we have this
enduring maladaptive patterns
of relating to you and to
others and to the world.
The obsessive compulsive
personality disorder likes to
have things organized,
planned.
Nothing-- even going
on vacation is
an exhausting task.
Nothing has to happen
randomly.
The grandiose personalities
really need this kind of
feeling coming from
all directions.
They need to be in
the limelight.
They use people, not as real
people but as people that
provide sustenance to their
own self esteem.
Two type of personality
disorders are particularly
likely to promote violence.
The antisocial and you may have
heard the term borderline
personality disorder, which
is basically at core has
significant instability and
emotions and interpersonal
relationships and identity
and basically
their lives are a mess.
Often they feel abandoned,
they feel put down.
They may get briefly paranoid
and often they become
assaultive.
So again, I'm throwing
a lot of terms and
definitions at you.
I don't want to make this a
lecture about psychiatry.
But these are conditions
that I think are
helpful to think about.
AUDIENCE: When people with
delusional disorders like
schizophrenia get violent, is
it usually because they are
frustrated about something or
is it because they suddenly
have some sort of delusion about
their clinician that
involves requiring them to take
some sort of action that
is violent?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: I think both.
I think even people that have a
psychotic disorder have the
right to feel the victim
of an injustice or
feel frustrated or--
many of the reasons that I
talked about could happen.
But in particular,
I think the other
point is equally important.
That they may act on a
delusional conviction.
Or their psychosis may also
have hallucinations.
And command auditory
hallucinations are known to
often be the forerunners
of a violent attack.
You talk about me
and say things.
Or the voice tells me, I'm
going to go after you.
And the person feels hopeless
to resist that.
I discharged a patient,
was doing great.
Next day he comes back.
Went home, the voice told him
that he needs to hurt his
mother, otherwise he'll
get disemboweled.
So he started punching her and
then chased her with a knife.
She had to hide in a neighbor's
house until the
police arrived.
There is an interesting threat
control override here that
people who have looked at
violence have prescribed as
being sometimes the proximal
cause for violence.
People feel directly
threatened.
And they also have this
overpowering urge that they
need to act on that they
cannot resist.
It's a controversial concept.
I'm not so sure why we should
give this particular
association a higher status
than other delusional
convictions about the neighbors
watching me or
planning to kill me, or putting
together a variety of
clues that my friends are really
trying to get rid of me
and then I need to
protect myself.
But you are absolutely right.
What's interesting even though
patients with 20 psychiatric
disorders may have their reasons
to become assaultive,
in the overall bigger scheme
of things, when you look at
actual violent assaults
committed in society, they're
responsible for a tiny one.
So it's an interesting way
of looking at numbers.
Yes they could become violent,
but the reality is that their
numbers, the actual violent
acts, are very small.
But anyway this may just be a
kind of statistical trick.
AUDIENCE: You're talking about
the number of cases of violent
episodes compared to the
general population.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Exactly.
That's exactly the problem
right there.
And then there are various
acute findings when you
examine the patient.
On what we call the mental
status examination.
Obviously, hostilities,
suspiciousness, agitation are
all associated with violence.
I want us to focus one minute
on the so-called aggressive
attributional style, how do we
respond to stress when we have
a perception of threat.
This is the threat override
delusion that I mentioned.
I think that's quite relevant.
What happens in conditions of
uncertainty, and many of these
patients may have to think
in a distorted fashion.
I was talking at the
beginning about the
communication breakdown.
You have the layer of the mental
illness that shrinks
your options.
You have a particular situation
to deal with that
makes you even more likely
to become assaulted.
And this constellation of
cognitive distortions may make
it more likely for you
to become assaulted.
Neglecting the base information,
which assigns a
high weight to certain events
that otherwise are low
frequency, attending only to
facts that would confirm your
assumptions, I think--
AUDIENCE: So if the
psychiatrist's office calls to
reschedule an appointment, the
person assumes that this is
because the psychiatrist
doesn't like him.
This person doesn't want to
treat me, they don't like me,
they don't want me to be their
patient because they
rescheduled me.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Ignoring facts
that could disconfirm
your hypothesis.
I just talked to the
psychiatrist who was nice to
me, but still the fact that he
called and canceled is the
overriding explanation that
he doesn't like me.
Or focusing on common events
just because you remember
them, which is an interesting
way of explaining.
The fact that you remember
them and it brings
them up in the rack.
And other disconfirming
evidence is
totally kind of ignored.
AUDIENCE: In spite the
assumption that the train on
the other platform always
seems to arrive first.
Because those are the
ones you remember.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Or the
garden variety, the
grass is always greener.
And I talked about medications
and street drugs.
Some are more likely
to be associated.
Alcohol just by the
sheer volume.
And especially because
withdrawal is so violent.
It's a significant issue.
The intoxication phase, your
level of coordination, your
perception of facts, it's just
they're so off that you are
more likely to lose control.
Antidepressants have an
interesting impact, because in
people that have an underlying
tendency to swing in their
moods may actually all
[? blend those ?] things.
You may have heard of the news
of antidepressants promoting
violence and suicide
in adolescents.
And while statisticians are
still scratching their heads
to figure out the exact numbers,
the truth is that
mood is very unstable
in adolescents.
And often initial depression
may turn out to
be something else.
You give somebody an
antidepressant, call him or
her for followup in six
or eight months.
In the meanwhile, lots of
things could happen.
And I think in those cases,
when actually those young
adolescents committed suicide,
it was not so much about
antidepressants causing it.
Probably the antidepressants
made the symptoms worse.
It was very poor followup
and poor diagnostic.
But anyway, this is getting
too technical.
I included this last minute.
This is an interesting summary
of a nationwide study focusing
on violence risk assessment.
Let me just take two minutes
about useful measures in
assessing dynamic
to the violence.
People have looked at violence
in two ways.
They have put together
all those factors
that I presented initially.
And they have looked at the
perspective of those who have
become violent.
And they compiled the
history, clinical
risk assessment scale.
The problem is that when you're
dealing with somebody,
those scales, even though they
may give you a good image of
what happens in the long run,
they may not help you deal
with the immediate situation.
So clinical scales have been
used in [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
One developed in Norway, the
other one, the dynamic
appraisal, developed
in Australia.
These are the items
for the HCR-20.
And it's almost like a
repetition of what I said
earlier in terms of
risk factors.
This is the historical
And these are validated, because
they have been used
for more than 15 years.
The clinical scale is the
dynamic part of the HCR.
And then the risk management
scale is trying to project in
the future what you have to do
in order to ensure safety,
what could go wrong.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: So the value
of these scales is kind of
sizing up the likelihood of this
person coming violent, in
the absence of other
information.
The best predictor is probably
what they're actually doing
behaviorally in front of you.
They're reaching for something
heavy, I take that in and
weigh that heavily.
But in the absence of anything
else, you know that the people
who meet a certain profile are
more likely to be violent as a
psychiatric patient
than others.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: This is a
dynamic scale that looks at
what happens in front of you,
as you pointed out.
You're considering confusion
or debility, how boisterous
and how verbally threatening
the person is.
The most recent one is the
dynamic appraisal of the
situation aggression that has
seven factors that seems to be
the best one [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
assessment or prediction
of violence
over the next 24 hours.
And this is an interesting
psychopathy and an index.
Psychopathy has an interesting
history.
I think the current version
that we all talk about is
antisocial personality.
But basically refers to people
with minimal capacity for
empathy, whose moral dimensions
is fairly
primitive, who engage in
stealing, cheating, violence,
and don't have a lot of moral
drawbacks to do it.
It seems to be associated with
violence, not surprisingly.
And this is actually a factor
analysis that identifies those
two dimensions.
Now just at the end I want to
talk about the de-escalation
principles that I am actually
now trying to incorporate in
the standardized patients,
because these should be fairly
easy to at least present, and
then maybe hopefully to teach
the residents how to use
in terms of dealing
with agitated patients.
So actually many of them
are used by staff.
How to start interaction
with a violent patient.
How to position yourself.
Within arm's length.
Probably at 45 degrees.
For two reasons.
One, in case you're attacked,
to offer a much smaller
surface of the impact and also
to allow you a way to escape,
you have to.
Not obviously to block
the exit door.
Stand over if the person is
leaning down or in the bed.
Never turn your back.
What to do with you
your hands.
Never make fists, or kind of
keep your arms crossed, or
behind you, or in your pockets,
to kind of appear as
nonthreatening as possible.
How to regulate the
eye contact.
If it's too intense, it
can become bothersome.
If it lacks completely, then
people could conclude that you
are not really interested
or involved.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: The thing
that's important to keep in
mind with a psychiatric
patient is,
well, a couple things.
One is that mental health
patients are much more likely
to be the victims
of violence than
actually to commit violence.
And this is really the outlier,
the unusual case
where the psychiatric patient
becomes violent.
But obviously it's an
important situation.
It does happen frequently enough
to be a real concern
for the providers, for
their well being.
Basically there's different
levels of what you have to
understand how to do.
One, how to protect yourself,
and then two, how to protect
the patient.
It's almost like if your child
who's 11 years old comes at
you swinging, it's really
different than if you're
getting bumped on the subway
in terms of what
you're going to do.
Now the person who's sitting in
your office might be a lot
bigger than your 11 year old.
But you kind of get the idea.
You're not trying to punish
them, you're not trying to
inflict any more harm on them
than is absolutely needed in
order to stop the situation
and for you to get
out, or let them out.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Yes.
And that's important,
and that's somewhat
counter-intuitive.
I'm just thinking, I'm trying to
think in terms of potential
simulation, and targets for
our training paradigm.
I think an important aspect is
for the person who is going to
the training to understand
himself or herself.
How what's the reaction when
you are threatened.
And how to continue to
think on your feet.
And take decisions that are not
based on a flight or fight
or tend and befriend attitude.
This is not about dealing
with a common situation.
This is when you have to
maintain your ability to
remain therapeutic and helpful
and to minimize harm to
yourself and certainly harm
to the other person.
And the truth of the matter is
that many people in these
situations react the way that
they've always done.
I gave Jim the example of a
social worker I work with, who
every time when she is
confronted by a patient, she
gets angry and she gets
defensive and tells things to
her that I find are hurtful.
And they are just adding
gas to the fire.
I need to intervene because
you feel that it's almost
like, you know, I'm
there to umpire.
OK, time out.
Stop.
We need to do something else.
And I try to explain to her.
She just doesn't get it.
Or can theoretically figure
it out but doesn't do a
very good job at it.
When we are angry or frightened,
our behavior, the
way we talk, the way
we track, changes.
And those things can be major
triggers for the other person.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: If you're
staying really calm, and the
other person's escalating,
that's a real dampening force
on that other person from
escalating even more.
And it's really, really hard to
do, to stay professional.
And recognizing that
this aggression is
really a medical symptom.
It's like if they are bleeding
on the floor.
The difference obviously is that
it could actually hurt
you, the provider.
But you need to recognize it
as a medical symptom that
needs to be dealt with as
opposed to taking it really
personally, or you being
violent back.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: How
do you appear.
How do you--
obviously, being calm, centered,
self assured is
always helpful.
It's the message that
you're conveying.
Often if you respond to anger
by being fearful or angry
yourself, obviously these
will just escalate.
Or if you're fidgety and
pacing, and gesturing
yourself, and wondering, so what
do I do now, I think the
other person would clearly
pick up that feeling.
Touching most often than
not is not a good idea.
Even though instinctively we
would like to calm the other
person down or wonder
what it is.
This is how we learn to show
empathy and that we care, we
want to help.
Well, it may not
be a good idea.
And then this could be
a topic in itself.
Active listening would
be the most--
if you want the buzzword,
in terms of the verbal
de-escalation principle.
Often when I'm called, and
many of my colleagues are
called in such situations.
I introduce myself.
I'm telling the person no
matter how agitated
he is why I'm here.
And I'm trying to understand.
I may not respond or react
to the person's curses or
threatening behavior.
Of course I try to maintain
a safe distance.
And I continue my assessment.
Can I deal with this, or I need
help, or I need to stop
and find another way.
And I give that person feedback
about what I see, how
he or she makes me feel.
I feel you are threatening, I
feel uncomfortable, I think we
need to stop.
Do you want to talk?
What are the issues that
you're dealing with?
And I also explain and set
limits on what is acceptable
and what is not acceptable.
Often, that combination works.
I listed pharmacotherapy and
seclusion restraint because
they are part of the process,
and I think I would like
people who are trained for this
to understand that those
things are available.
Any questions so far?
AUDIENCE: I've just got a
couple of comments on
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
We can do that.
And also I wanted to suggest and
see what you think about
this, if someone would like to
play the role of a patient, I
can meet with you briefly and
just kind of prepare you to do
that if anybody is interested
in taking the role of the
aggressive patient.
You'd like to do that?
Why don't you and I step out for
just a couple of minutes.
And then [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So there's a couple
of things that have been
brought up already, immediately
seem to be
possible places where you guys
can think of what you're doing
to do your project on.
There's identifying factors.
There's a whole bunch of
different schemes and
different metrics that people
have been using.
All the way from known
personality types to
socioeconomic factors and
personal history.
You could make some kind
of [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I can imagine, some sort of like
can you figure out enough
information before
it's too late.
The dynamic assessment of
violence seems to be more of a
time pressure kind of thing.
Because you almost have to
figure out on the spot.
But factors are very
different.
But similarly I can find
de-escalation.
It seems kind of interesting,
because it almost seems like
you could make a word game.
Or a face to face kind
of thing out of that.
Can you remember what you're
supposed to do in conversation
with each other without
missing any of the
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
And that might be something.
That would be like a live
action game but not
necessarily a physical game.
It would be more like
a party game.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: One way--
this is, by the way, I didn't
want to go there to
make this too long.
But these are some parts of a
standardized patient that I'm
putting together, then I'm going
to try actually to talk
to the simulation department
at UMass, to be
played by an actor.
And this would be the
training goals.
And I'm really particularly
interested in how people
respond when they are exposed to
an angry situation or even
to an angry face.
What do you have to
do in order to
de-escalate the patient.
And what I think I'm going to
suggest to the actor is that,
you are in the room and you're
pacing up and down.
And appearing angry.
And you're allowed to use some
generic swear words.
And to have a number
of complaints.
Could be a number of them.
Nurse was too late to give
me the medications.
The girlfriend didn't
come in time.
You owe money.
You just had a job interview
today and you missed it
because you're in
the hospital.
Could be a number of things.
And then the person
approaches you.
The trainee should follow some
rules in terms of the verbal
and nonverbal de-escalation.
If that person is able to engage
you, you can become
less angry, less agitated,
more interested.
Pacing less, lower your voice.
If the trainee is just doing the
right or wrong things, you
either stay at the same level
or get more and more angry.
Of course, it's fairly demanding
for a standardized
for an actor, because the
nonverbal elements are easy.
How you regulate the distance.
How you look, how
you approach.
You inhibit your natural
tendencies to pat the person
on the shoulder, whatever.
But the verbal aspects
are more difficult.
AUDIENCE: Improvising dialog
on the spot is hard.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Exactly.
But at the same time, the goals
of the dialog are not.
Because you should probably find
out what's going on, even
though, let's say, the actor
will try to tell you about his
life, and how miserable
things are.
You know, I lost my job,
and I was kicked out.
But you need to try to
bring the person
to what really happened.
I think that's very, very
helpful because you're pinning
down a particular conflict
that triggered it.
And if you are able to
do that, then you
can take some steps.
OK.
I have a patient right
now who has
difficulty expressing herself.
And systematically there's one
particular shift where the
staff is not patient, doesn't
wait for her.
You just need to give her
a little bit more time.
And she gets upset and angry
and starts pacing.
And I have to every time say,
please, listen to her.
Or she comes up to me, she tells
me the story and then I
have to go back to the staff.
People just don't have the
patience or don't care.
So that's just a simple
intervention.
This is why you need to find
out what's going on.
And then, if you can get more
information about what brought
the person to this place.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: OK.
I think we're prepared.
She did role play before
I showed this, because
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Do
you want to do it?
You've been trained.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: No.
You're the expert actually.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: OK.
Alright.
Let's see what happens to me.
[AUDIENCE LAUGHTER]
So, I'm Dr. [? See. ?]
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
Where's John?
I want to speak to John.
I respond to him
and I want him.
Why isn't he here?
Why?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Who's
this person?
I don't know.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
Where's John?
I only want to speak to him.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Well, Nurse
John is not available.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
[BANGING NOISE]
Why isn't he available?
Why?
Only [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
I don't want to talk
to you right now.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: How
can I help you?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
Get Johnny.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: OK.
I can try to see
if he's around.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
[BANGING NOISE]
You could [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
now.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: OK.
But what else can I do?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: Um.
An education.
Stop it.
Not good.
Try to poison me.
You all want me dead.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: What am
I trying to do to you?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: Doesn't
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER 2: OK.
I can talk about that.
So tell me what kind of problems
do you have with the
medication?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
Trying to poison.
You all want me dead.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: So you
don't think the
medication is helpful?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
Course not.
Trying to kill me.
[TEARING NOISE]
[LAUGHTER]
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
They're watching me.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: What else
can I do to help?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
[INAUDIBLE]
family.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: You want me
to contact your family?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: No.
I hate them all.
They're all against me.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: It must be very
hard, to not have anyone
to talk to or feel
comfortable with.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: That's
why I want to talk
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] with John.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Well,
I'm sorry you're
struggling so much.
And I know we haven't
met before.
But I'm here and trying
to be helpful to you.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: You want
to kill me, don't you?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: No, I don't
think I want to.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
[GRUNTING]
GUEST SPEAKER 2: So we have
a number of options.
And I think you look angry.
And you're scaring people
and you're scaring me.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: Fine.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: You're
scaring me.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
[UNINTELLIGIBLE]
You're just laughing
behind me.
You're not scared.
You're just laughing.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: No, I think
you're a big, strong guy.
And when you get angry and
upset, you get to be
intimidating.
And there are other--
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: Is that
why you're going to poison me?
Scared of me?
GUEST SPEAKER 2: No.
Well, I'm not trying
to hurt you.
But we need to come up
with a solution.
Because you could get hurt and
other people could get hurt.
So we need to do something
about that.
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: I would
be better off dead.
Everyone wants me dead.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Well.
I understand you're quite
distraught today.
And I want to help you.
I may not be able
to, right away.
I'm going to try to get the
nurse that you want.
But what if I do not get him?
What's the next best thing?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
[INAUDIBLE]
I don't know.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Would it help
to contact your family?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT:
Maybe mom.
I want my mom.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: OK.
I can try to reach out to her.
And do you think that if you
change the medications maybe
you can try a combination
that could help?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: As long
as it's not poison.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: OK.
I hear you.
You don't like the medication.
You think that it's
hurting you.
But it's helped in the past.
And maybe a different
combination would be better.
Hmm?
ROLE PLAYING PATIENT: Maybe.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Maybe?
Well, thank you.
We can go on like this.
[LAUGHTER, APPLAUSE]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I have a question
concerning about the
disruption of narrative model
of why violence occurs.
Is that pretty much accepted
as the way--
GUEST SPEAKER 2: I just
made it up for this.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: I was just wondering
if there were competing,
different theories, it might
be useful for people to
understand more than one model,
or is that [INAUDIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER 2: The narrative
perspective is, if you want, a
cry from the past.
I think the last 20 years,
in science and certainly
medicine, have been dominated
by hard evidence.
Actually, the evidence-based
medicine has been taking over
the entire world, as the
ultimate standard.
So there are lists of the
strength of the evidence, and
randomized controlled designs
are the best, and clinical
impression anecdotes
are the worst.
So on this map, the narrative
or a person-like story about
the patient may not be if you
want the accepted model today.
But I think in dealing with
individual cases, I feel that
makes a lot of sense.
When you have to deal with
somebody who is very
distraught, if I tell him that
the best available evidence
was published two years ago and
showed that, you know, 20
milligrams of Abilify would work
best for psychosis, I'm
not so sure that you
would fuel the
warmth and the empathy.
But the reality, it
could be that that
evidence is is right.
He's psychotic.
And he tried to a variety
of medications.
Some of them made him fat and
pushed his triglycerides up
and raised his blood pressure.
If I switch him to Abilify in
two months, he'll get better.
But dealing with the immediate
issue, I think it's just, it's
something else.
And that knowledge about
medication, while helpful in
the long run, will not
make it very good.
So this is why I came up with
if you want, for the purpose
of this meeting, with a way of
creating a metaphor that could
sustain my verbal and nonverbal
de-escalation.
I'm trying to create some sense,
some coherence, some
meaning, some meaning
to that interaction.
And in doing that, I'm empathic
and I'm trying to
channel the energies
in a way that it's
almost like a beginning.
He's distraught.
He's ready to give up.
He's ready to shut himself
away from the world.
I'm trying to reach out to
him, without becoming his
friend, without becoming
his brother or father.
And I think in a sense
I'm restoring the
meaning of his narrative.
Somebody cares, somebody
reaches out.
PROFESSOR: Because it seems like
a very interesting system
for people, for designers
to play with.
The idea of trying, even though
there is this historic
narrative, and you may not
know enough about the
narrative to be able
to act on it.
But you'd find out things
about it by
talking to the patient.
And what you're really trying
to do is make things fit
within that person's
narrative.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: You're filling
the blanks that were
kind of somewhat destroyed
by events.
And it could be a variety
of events.
And at times you have to
use your imagination.
It's almost like intuition.
I mean, I know the principles
from every case, but how I'm
going to do it, it's
not pre-programmed.
PROFESSOR: Seems like that's
also something that you could
then play with from a design
point of view.
This idea of disruptive
narrative, and then how do you
put it back.
Just like putting the pieces
back together [INAUDIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER 2: That may be
the reason-- and that's
another speculation, I'm
just making this up--
why adventure games
are so powerful.
Because, in a sense, you're
finding a substitute narrative
that is much more controllable
than your own.
And for the time of the
game you're there.
It's almost like you're buying
a few minutes, 10 minutes, 20
minutes of a different
story line.
PROFESSOR: Actually, one of
our researchers here looks
specifically at adventure
games.
And her point of view is that
playing adventure games is
like being a performer who
hasn't been given the script.
You're still an actor in the
story, and you have to figure
out what that story is in
order to move it along.
There's one other thing that
I do want to bring up.
Obviously, I don't want any of
these games that you guys are
working on to be quizzes, to be
really fun quizzes, even.
[INAUDIBLE]
all this stuff is about.
I do want you guys to
be learning games.
And not just Trivial Pursuit,
Psychiatric Version.
That's kind of pointless.
We have had games in the past
in this class where people
basically pulled questions out
of a hat and had to answer
them, with various penalties.
Kind of fun, but that's
not what I've been
teaching you guys.
So try to think about systems.
Try to think about all these
things that they want their
trainees to learn.
Think about how they can engage
with the system, in
some small way, for
your project.
AUDIENCE: Can I ask
a question?
What are your thoughts, or what
are the field's thoughts
on lying to people, so
mitigate a situation.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Well, I would
call lying a distortion, in a
very general way.
And when people lie, they
have to make a decision.
Often, people lie for a
variety of reasons.
What I always am surprised by is
the reason to make friends,
to get friendly, to resolve
a situation.
And I don't believe in lying
as a communication tool.
Given, it may make things
easier in the short run.
Certainly clinically
it's not helpful.
I was telling you about patients
with borderline
pathology that has this
affective and relational
instability that is basically
taking over their lives.
They are some of the most
accurate lie detectors that
you can imagine.
You cannot design something
more perfect than that.
Especially having been in the
system for a long time.
They can feel the lie even
before it comes up.
And if you're going that
path with them.
AUDIENCE: So this role play,
for example, if you told
Bobby, well, let
me go get John.
You wait here for a minute.
And then you know that John
is not working right now.
He's nowhere in the hospital.
But you just told him that to
safely get out, then you get
security to come back in
with you, and you can
subdue him or something.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: That's
a great example.
And that happens all the time.
Because often when you're in
this place, many of your
requests are unreasonable.
So you need to set
some limits.
And eventually you'll end
up setting some limits.
He could have continued to
escalate until attacking me,
breaking everything
in the room.
I usually tell them about how
they make others feel.
How unacceptable some of their
behaviors are, and what are
the consequences.
So I'm going to probably tell
you if this continues, I don't
have any other choice but to
call security and you may end
up in restraints.
And with a chemical medication,
it could be
injectable, you can
take it by mouth.
So I'm coming up front with how
the next few minutes, the
proximal future, looks like.
As opposed to kind of fudge it
and get on his friendly side,
and, oh I don't mean anything,
but the security will put you
in restraints.
So I don't want to buy him out
by just becoming his friend.
If that involves lying--
that's-- some people do it.
When you're in the
corner, you're--
OK, so what do I do now.
A little lie won't hurt.
And you do it.
Maybe it's just my--
GUEST SPEAKER 1: What you just
mentioned too, that sort of
like good cop, bad cop.
Well, I wish we could have more
of a conversation here,
but security needs to put
you in restraints.
Security's the bad guy.
When that's exactly
where you want the
patient to be anyways.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: I'm OK,
but you know Jim.
He doesn't tolerate it.
He's the director and
he's going to--
[LAUGHTER]
GUEST SPEAKER 2: Does that
answer your question?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Would you--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: I guess my followup is
would you ever sneakily put
medicine in someone's food or do
something [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
GUEST SPEAKER 2: It's not only
a lawsuit waiting to happen,
of a major magnitude, but I
don't think it's right.
Even though probably reality
is that family members and
sometimes even providers in
nursing homes may do that.
But I think it's--
GUEST SPEAKER 1: You may need
to treat the person against
their will, which is often
meaning putting them into
physical restraints, which is
usually like leather kind of
things, kind of a straitjacket
thing, or maybe to a bed.
And maybe physically inject them
with something to really
sedate them.
But you should always be telling
them what you're going
to do, right.
And the reason why
you're doing it.
Even if they don't have any
choice in the matter.
GUEST SPEAKER 2: And if you feel
that the person is unable
to comprehend, then you may
need to work towards
appointing a guardian
who will take
decisions for that person.
And it's not necessarily that
the legal field has pushed
itself very hard in field.
But I think it's fair.
You meet the person where
that person is at,
and try to be helpful.
And I think, in my view, there
is no substitute for being
upfront and saying this is
what's going to happen.
He may not be my best friend,
but he knows exactly.
I'm telling the patients often
ahead what's going to happen.
In that sense, I'm giving
them choices.
So if I end up taking
them to court for
commitment, they know that.
And you would be surprised
how angry they are at the
beginning and how OK
they are later.
And how often they come up to
me and say, thank you, I was
in a very bad space and I didn't
want to, and I fought
you all the way but I think that
was the best solution.
I don't necessarily do that
to get that thanks.
I just do it as a principle.
Often it doesn't come.
It's not like people
are grateful.
Often they leave the hospital.
GUEST SPEAKER 1: Let me show a
little of this training, just
a few minutes.
This is a project I've been
working on a lot for NASA,
which is basically to develop a
mental health support system
for the long duration
space cruise.
And this is kind of a
whole other topic.
But just one piece of this was
teaching the astronauts how to
manage conflict, interpersonal
conflict more
effectively or safely.
Astronauts being a very
different population from what
we were talking about.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
--Welcome to the virtual space
station, where you can access
training and resources to help
deal with the stresses of long
duration space flights.
In the training simulator,
you'll interact with virtual
crew members to learn and
practice managing some of the
problems that might come up
on long duration missions.
The resources modules has more
advanced training that you can
do to learn about adapting to
the stresses of living in
isolation, plus interviews with
long duration flyers.
It also has a number of ebooks
and audio books on dealing
with stress.
Plus survival stories about
polar missions and other
adventures.
In the self-assessment module,
you'll find questionnaires--
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
GUEST SPEAKER 1: This is
basically the whole interface.
What I'll show you here
is our simulator.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
--This is the training
simulator.
Click on the topic you would
like to learn about.
Then the coach or mentor for
that topic will takeover and
guide you through.
--
This is the conflict
management part of the simulator.
We recommend that you do the
10 minute briefing first.
After you complete
each simulation--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Here's how these simulations
work.
You're flight engineer
one, or FE1.
Your crew mate, Chuck, is
flight engineer two.
We'll be giving you three
choices of what to say or do.
You can roll your mouse over
them to hear how they're said.
Even though some options are
more likely than others to
reduce the conflict, I recommend
that you try out
options you might not
choose in real life.
That's because all paths in
these simulations lead to
teaching points.
You can click the backup button
anytime if you want to
change your choice and go
down another pathway.
You can click on the fair
fighting manual at any time to
read some tips.
You'll also find this
manual in the
resource module's library.
Now as you go through the
simulation, I'll be right here
coaching you along the way.
OK.
Back to the simulation.
It's four months into your
mission, with five and a half
left to go.
So far, the mission's been
going pretty well.
But you're both tired, having
had to sleep shift last night.
--
Is your display getting
squirrelly?
Shoot, mine too.
Damn, I think the whole
system's down.
It was the wrong cable.
When I was installing
the recorder I
disconnected the A10 cable.
I fixed it right away but
I think it screwed
up the whole system.
Look, if ground calls, don't
tell them about the cable.
--
Ah, this is a tricky
situation.
You believe it's important to
tell the ground what happened.
At the same time, you don't want
Chuck to get in trouble.
What's your response?
--
They'll spend hours trying
to figure this out.
We got to tell them.
What's wrong with telling
the ground.
--
You're saying make a choice.
OK, but you're putting
me in a bad position.
--
I know.
But thanks you're
a real friend.
I owe you big time.
--
Houston, this is FE2.
Go ahead.
No.
Negative.
I have no idea.
Yeah I know.
I already got the
reboot started.
No, I guess it's too early to
say what the impact is.
Roger that.
I'll let you know if
it happens again.
FE2 out.
--
You're feeling very anxious
having just heard Chuck lie to
the ground.
You're worried that this might
backfire on you, if the ground
finds out that you knew
what happened.
This makes you very
angry at Chuck.
How would you like to respond?
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
GUEST SPEAKER 1: The reason I'm
showing you this is that
this is one approach that I've
taken to teaching how to
handle an interaction with
somebody through sort of a
simulation.
Now this is obviously
not a game.
There's no score.
There's no time limit.
It's more of an interactive
movie.
But with the teaching points
here, just like what Cesar's
given you is, we can give this
to an astronaut and they'll
read it in 5-10 minutes and say,
yup, got it, what's the
next thing.
That doesn't mean they actually
can use it, remember
it, absorbed it.
and I'm not saying that
this is the way they
should do your games.
But that this is one approach
that we've taken to try to get
them more involved with the
material in more of a
simulated way.
We can just do maybe one
or two more of this.
What would you like
to do here?
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
--
Chuck, we need to
talk about this.
--
What is there to talk about?
Ground doesn't need to
know every single
little detail, alright?
Plus if we do tell them, next
thing you know we're going to
be all over the news.
--
This was a good choice.
Even though Chuck seems
exasperated, you know what's
going on in his mind.
Understanding what each other is
thinking goes a long way to
solving conflict.
Chuck is concerned about the
ruckus this might cause about
negative media attention.
But now you have something
to work with.
What's your next move?
--
I know you--
you've been doing excellent
work so far.
I can see you're really
scared of them.
I know you don't want to draw
a lot of attention.
What'll you think will happen
if they figure it out?
--
OK.
You got a point.
I'll get fried.
Especially if it looked like I
was trying to cover it up.
You know, this really
is a team issue.
--
On one hand, you seemed to get
Chuck to come around to your
perspective.
But the ground really needs
to know what happened.
On the other hand, he's asking
you to share the
responsibility, even though it
really wasn't your fault.
You have mixed feelings.
You don't want to be blamed for
a mistake you didn't make.
But you're concerned about
keeping a good relationship
with Chuck.
How are you going to respond?
--
I'm sorry, Chuck.
But this was your mistake.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[LAUGHTER]
--
Houston, this is FE2.
Go ahead, FE2.
--
Houston, I think we
found the problem.
The instructions you sent up
for the recorder had some
serious problems.
When you follow the recorder
connect procedure, you can end
up disconnecting A10.
It may need to be validated.
--
Copy that, FE2.
The procedures team ran through
this in the mock-up,
but they can give
it another look.
--
In any organization [LAUGHTER]
Sometimes this can help to
create a bond within the
workgroup, because everybody
has a common enemy.
But, even though scapegoating
the ground may keep the crew
unified for a while,
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
GUEST SPEAKER 1: OK.
You kind of get the idea.
We'd like to be available by
email, in case you guys have
any questions.
PROFESSOR: I'll sent out some
tech information to the class
list and we're probably going to
spend the rest of this week
being around all of you so
we're not quite sure yet
exactly what we're
going to do yet.
Hopefully
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE].
I just have a couple more
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] things to do.
I wanted to thank you
guys first of all.
[APPLAUSE]
So let's see.
On next Wednesday, which is
the Wednesday right before
Thanksgiving, I think a couple
of folks are probably going to
be getting out--
because I've been hearing some
daffy stuff about what the TSA
might be doing, and what people
have been doing in
response to TSA [LAUGHTER].
Getting to the airport early,
if you are flying out, might
be a good idea.
Because if everybody decides
to refuse the bag scanner
scans and the body searches,
then we're talking about some
real delays.
Anyway.
So I think what I'm going to
do is [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
this class.
If there are teams who are
really wanting to do a live
action game, and they want to
get a head start on that, talk
to me directly.
And maybe what we can do is,
meet up with you as a team.
And try to get some
of ideas across.
Do a brainstorming with me.
I will also get into talking
about live action games the
following week.
I'll schedule one of the
classes for that.
So we're not going to
miss that topic.
I just worried that if we get
to it too late, and you are
making live action games, then
you don't have enough material
to work with.
Finally, about this assignment,
if the subject
matter is at all uncomfortable
for you to work with, and you
can't really find something in
this fairly large topic that
you will be comfortable working
with and you can't
find a team, talk
to me directly.
And we can work out some
other assignment.
I can't say that I have an
assignment in my back pocket
all ready to go, and more
likely than not, I'm
half-assing it too.
I would much prefer folks to
work on this problem that I
think is fascinating.
And a pretty big problem that
you can find some small
project that you're
comfortable with.
But if you are, I don't want to
make anyone uncomfortable
due to [INAUDIBLE].
So just talk to me.