PROFESSOR: Hi.
Welcome back to recitation.
In lecture you've been learning
about applications of
integration.
And one of them is
how to compute
average values of a function.
So I have a nice average value
problem for you here.
So Christine was out jogging
one day and she saw a bear,
and so she broke
into a sprint.
She starts speeding up, and her
velocity t seconds after
she started sprinting is given
by v of t equals 1500 divided
by the quantity 100 plus t minus
5 squared, the whole
thing minus 7.
And it's in meters per second.
So OK, so she starts at t equals
0, she's going 1500
divided by 125, so that's
12 minus 7, so
5 meters per second.
And she starts to speed up and
after 5 seconds she's going
1500 divided--
well this is 0--
so she's going 8 meters per
second at 5 seconds.
And then she looks over her
shoulder and she sees, oh no,
it wasn't up a bear, it was just
an unkempt math graduate
student, so then she starts
to slow down again.
She slows back down and 10
seconds later she's back to
her original velocity.
So the question is, over the 10
seconds of this sprint, she
sped up, she'd slowed down, from
5 meters per second to 8
meters per second and
then back to 5.
What was her average velocity
over this time?
So why don't you pause the
video, take some time to work
that out, come back and we
can work on it together.
So hopefully you had some luck
working on this problem.
I have over on my left here a
little picture of the graph of
this function v of t.
I described it to you earlier,
but just you see, OK, so it
starts at 5, after 5 seconds
it's at 8, and then it goes
back down to 5 at 10 seconds.
So this is roughly the picture,
so we have a feel for
what we're working with.
Now what we want to compute
is the average
velocity over this time.
So anytime you have to compute
an average value of any
function what you want to do,
you always do the same thing.
So you want to compute the total
contribution of that
function over the interval
in question.
So you want to add it up, you
want to integrate it over the
interval in question.
But then you want to divide by
the length of the integral.
So in particular, when you have
a velocity function what
that means is, you integrate
the velocity.
So that gives you the total
distance traveled, and then
you divide by the
time interval.
S you're just taking
total distance
divided by total time.
So in this case we can write
down this average value.
So I'm going to use just
a made up notation.
I'm going to write avg
of v, so what is it?
Well the first thing I have to
do is I want to not forget to
divide by the length of
the interval here.
So in this case, the interval
is from 0 to 10, so it has
length 10 minus 0,
which is 10.
So I want 1/10 in front and what
I want to multiply this
by, is I want to multiply by the
integral over this entire
interval of my function v.
Sp I just take the formula that
I had over there for v
and I plop it down
into my integral.
So it's the integral from 0 to
10 of 1500 divided by 100 plus
t minus 5 quantity squared
minus 7 dt.
So this integral is the average
value that we're
looking for.
OK.
So now we have to go about
evaluating it.
Now, this looks kind of
ugly, but actually
it's not that bad.
I mean, one thing you can
notice, so the minus 7 part,
that's going to be easy
to take care of.
And then in this more
complicated part, well there's
a kind of obvious substitution
here.
You can set u equal
t minus 5, that'll
simplify it a little bit.
and then what you'll see is that
you have an integrand of
the form something divided
by 100 plus u squared.
And so that's 10 squared
plus u squared.
So that should keep-- and the
something as a constant.
So that should put you in the
mind of a tangent substitute,
or just even not by
substitution, you can just
remember that that's an arc
tangent type of thing that
you're going to get out.
so I'm not going to go through
all the steps of doing that,
but we should get at the end--
well OK, so I've got this 1/10
out in front, so I have to
not forget about that.
I get 1/10 times, I've gone
ahead and I've computed the
anti-derivative and it's 150
times arctan of the quantity t
minus 5 over 10.
So here's that t minus 5, that's
the same t minus 5 over
there that's coming out.
Minus 7t.
And you want to take that
between t equals 0
and t equals 10.
So this is, I've just, I've gone
ahead, I've computed the
anti-derivative for us.
There's my 1/10 because I'm
doing an average value and
then I'm, it's a definite
integral and so I'm using
fundamental theorem of calculus
there on my balance.
OK, so now we just have to
plug in and evaluate.
So this is equal to,
so let's see.
So we've got when we put in t
equals 10, well the 1/10 and
the 150 gives me a 15 arctan of
1/2 minus, well it's 1/10
of 7 times 10, it's just 7.
That's from the first one.
And from the second one
I guess minus--
so it's going to be 15
arctan of minus 1/2.
When I put in t equals 0, and
when I put in t equals 0, the
7t is just 0.
OK.
This is a little messy.
We can simplify it a little
bit, because, remember
arctangent is an odd function.
So arctan of minus x is
minus arctangent of x.
So minus 15 arctan minus
1/2 is the same as
just 15 arctan 1/2.
And so we can combine those.
So we can rewrite that.
Let's go all the
way over here.
We can rewrite this as 30
arctan 1/2 minus 7.
So that's about it as
nice a form as you
can make this take.
If you wanted to plug it into
a calculator, I think you'd
see that this is approximately
equal to 6.9 and I guess the
units there are going to
be meters per second.
So her average velocity over
this time is about 6.9 meters
per second.
Let's just quickly recap
what we did.
So we started all the way back
here with this velocity
function v, and we wanted to
compute it's average value
over the intervals 0 less than
or equal to t, less than or
equal to 10.
So we did what we always do
in problems of that sort.
So we came over here, and
whenever you want to compute
an average value, you take 1
divided by the length of the
interval in question, times--
then just you integrate the
function who's average value
you want over the interval.
OK?
And so then we computed, well
we didn't show any of the
steps, but we computed the
definite integral by taking
the anti-derivative and plugging
in and it happened
that the answer worked
out to be about 6.9.
So there you go.
I'll stop there.