Welcome back to recitation.
In this video, I'd like us to do
some basic manipulation of
some power series that you
saw in the lecture.
So I have four problems here,
and what I'd like us to do, is
figure out what function each
of these series represents.
Now, you can assume that the
x-values that we are going to
insert into this function are
only x-values that let the
sums converge.
So you don't have to worry
about anything to do with
convergence of these sums. Just
assume the sums converge,
that we've picked
good x-values.
OK?
And what I'd like you to have
in the end, for A, B, C, and
D, is something like,
this sum is equal
to a specific function.
It should not include
a sum anymore.
So why don't you work on those
for a bit, pause the video,
and when you're done, restart
the video, and I'll come back,
and show you how I
work with them.
All right.
Welcome back.
Well, hopefully these were
a little bit fun for you.
I always liked them, the first
time I saw them, to see how
one could manipulate
these series.
So again, what we're trying to
do is figure out what function
these series represent.
We're assuming convergence.
And we're going to try and
manipulate them to look like
things we already know.
So I'm going to start.
I'm just going to go straight
through, a, b, c, and d.
And I'm going to rewrite the
problem each time, because I
don't want to keep
coming back.
So A, we had the sum n equals 0
to infinity, x to the n plus
2 over n factorial.
Well, this looks very close
to something we know.
It looks a lot like the one,
the function e to the x.
The difference is that
e to the x just has a
power x to the n.
But the good news is that I
am really close to that.
What I really have in the
numerator is x to
the n times x squared.
Because this x to the n plus 2,
I can write as x to the n
times x squared.
So every term has
an x squared.
So as was mentioned in the
lecture, you can treat this
really like polynomials.
In some way, you can
factor this out.
So I can rewrite this as--
well, I'll rewrite
it in two steps.
0 to infinity of x squared, x
to the n over n factorial.
So x squared times x to the n
gives me x to the n plus 2.
Right?
But I can actually now, because
this belongs to every
sum, I can pull that all
the way out in front.
Right?
And if I pull that all the way
out in front, if I move this
out to the front, I have an
x squared times this sum.
Well, what is the sum?
The sum is e to the x.
It's n equals 0 to infinity of
x to the n over n factorial.
That's just e to the x.
So this function is x
squared e to the x.
That's what a is.
If you were worried about it,
you could write e to the x as
a series, and then you could
multiply through by x squared,
and see if that's
what you get.
But you'll see, that is indeed
how this problem works.
OK.
Let's look at B. OK, B
is equal to the sum--
that's a weird summation sign,
sorry about that--
b is equal to the sum n equals
2 to infinity of x to the n.
That's what we wanted
to look at.
Well, this looks very close to
the geometric series, but it's
missing some terms. Right?
The geometric series starts
at n equals 0 to infinity.
But the point I want to make
here is that I can rewrite
this as the geometric series,
and then I can take away what
I've added in.
OK?
So these do not agree
right now.
This equals sign is
not true yet.
But what do I notice?
I notice that this one has two
more terms at the beginning
than this one has.
What are those terms?
Those are when n equals
0 and when n equals 1.
Right?
There's no n equals 0
or n equals 1 here.
The formulas are exactly
the same.
Right?
x to the n, x to the n.
They both go to infinity, but
one is starting at n equals 2,
and one's starting
at n equals 0.
Again, I want to remind you.
Why did I bother to write
this thing at all?
Because this is a function
we know.
But this equals sign is
not true right now.
Right?
I have to get rid of the
extra stuff I added.
What did I add?
I added--
let me get this as a sum.
What did I add on?
I added on x to the zero and x
to the first. So now I guess I
should have written subtract
here, right?
I should subtract x to the 0,
and I should subtract x to the
first.
I've already said it once, but
I'm going to, just to make
sure everybody follows,
say it one more time.
I now, I've taken the summation
I started with,
which went from n equals
2 to infinity.
I added two more terms
to the sum.
I made it go from
0 to infinity.
So to keep equality, I
subtracted off the two things
I added in.
I subtracted off x to the
0 and x to the first.
So now, what was the point of
this part of the exercise?
Well, the point is that I
know what this sum is.
That's the geometric series.
That's 1 over 1 minus x.
And this x to the 0 minus 1
x to the first minus x.
So this I broke up into
something I knew as a power
series, and then other pieces
that I had added in to make it
look like something I knew.
I had to subtract those off.
So that's the idea.
That one, if you wanted to go
on and simplify further, you
could do that.
But I'm willing to leave
it just as is.
'Cause the idea was really this
part up here, and then
translating it down to this.
All right.
Let me write C again.
The sum n equals 0 to infinity,
x to the n over n
factorial plus x to the n.
OK.
So the sum n equals 0 to
infinity, x to the n over n
factorial plus x to the n.
And the point to recognize here
is, again, as Professor
Jerison mentioned, you're really
treating these almost
like polynomials.
So you're taking a series, and
you're adding these terms up.
But really, what you can think
about this, is the two
separate series added up.
And so this is the sum from n
equals 0 to infinity of x to
the n over n factorial, which
we know, plus the sum from n
equals 0 to infinity of x
to the n, which we know.
The first one is just e to the
x, and the second one, we've
been dealing a lot with these
already today, is just 1
over 1 minus x.
So the point I want to make, is
if you have this convergent
series, you can split it up
into pieces over the sum.
And these two are both
convergent, we know,
separately, and so we can
write what they are.
x to the n over n factorial from
0 to infinity is e to the
x , x to the n from n equals
0 to infinity is 1
over 1 minus x.
So now we just have one more.
Let me write that one.
D was summation n equals
minus 1 to infinity x
to the n plus 1.
All right.
This was not meant to scare you,
but it was meant to test
your understanding of
sigma notation.
So the problem is, we're
starting at n equals minus 1,
but x is starting, the exponent
on x is at n plus 1.
So I want to write it in
some form that I know.
Well, let's try and get
the subscript to be 0.
so what I'm going to do, is I'm
going to change the name
of the subscript.
I'm going to let it be m
equals 0 to infinity.
OK?
And I want m to count up by 1
just the way n counts up.
So notice what I did.
When m equals 0, n equals
negative 1.
That's what we've set up
as the first term.
That means n plus 1 is equal
to 0 when m equals 0.
And since I'm going up by one
every time in my summation, my
iteration, here that that means
that for every m I have,
I just have to take n plus 1
to figure out what m is.
So I should have said
it the other way.
For every n I have, I just
have to add 1 to get m.
OK?
So here, if I start at negative
1, I start here at 0.
The next term here is 0, n
equals 0, but the next term
here is m equals 1.
The next term here would be n
equals 1, and the next term
here would be m equals 2.
So they're just off by
1, but they're still
catching every index.
Now, I don't have to change
what's up here.
Because infinity--
if I add 1 to it, I'm still
going off to infinity.
So I don't have to change
what's up here.
But I do want to write the
formula, or the formula I have
inside the sum in terms of m.
But I've already got it.
Because I know m is always equal
to n plus 1, so I can
replace this n plus 1 by an m.
And now we know that one is.
Right?
m equals 0 to infinity
of x to the m.
That's our geometric series.
So it actually, even though I
wrote it in kind of a funny
way, it was actually just still
the geometric series.
I just moved the indices a
little bit to make sure we
could play with those.
So the idea here, the whole
point of this exercise, just
to recognize how you can
manipulate these series a
little bit, so that if they're
in a form that looks kind of
like one of the functions you
know, you can see if it
actually is, you know, a product
of something with the
function you know, or the sum of
two functions you know, or
maybe one of the functions you
know is a power series, and
then you have to drop off a
couple of terms. So they each
sort of demonstrate a different
idea of how you can
manipulate these convergent
power series, based on
functions you already know.
So I'll stop there.