PROFESSOR LEWIN: First, let's
review R L C circuits.
R L C circuits in series.
I have here, a resistor.
I have here, a capacitor.
And here, a self inductor, L.
And here, I have some kinds of
a voltage source.
I call it E. And it could have
various different natures, as
we will see very shortly.
That's call this points
b, a, c, d, back to a.
The way I start these problems
always, there's nothing wrong
with that, I assume at one
moment in time that this is
positive and this is negative.
I assume that there's no charge
anywhere on the system,
on the capacitor.
And so a current will start to
flow after a while, I. That
current will charge this side of
the capacitor positive and
this one negative.
And it will return.
If we look at the
electric fields.
There must be an electric
field, E,
here in this direction.
There must be electric fields
here in the capacitor, also in
this direction, going
from plus to minus.
There's no electric field in the
self inductor because the
self inductor is made of
super conducting wire.
Just as all these wires
have no resistance.
And inside the battery, the
E field is opposing.
It goes from plus to minus.
I now apply Faraday's
law, and I go around
this closed loop circuit.
And I attached to the close
loop an open surface.
Closed loop integral.
I attach to that,
an open surface.
And the open surface is
easy to see here.
It's flat.
It's not too easy to see here.
We discussed that earlier.
It is some staircase
kind of surface.
I don't want to go into
that anymore.
But what is important is that
the magnetic flux inside the
solenoid penetrates this
open surface n
times if you n windings.
We hit that very
hard last time.
So here comes Faraday's law.
The closed loop integral of
E.dl, I split that up in an
integral and going
from a to b.
Plus the integral in
going from b to
c through the resistor.
Plus the integral in
going from c to
d through the capacitor.
Plus the integral in going from
d back to a through the
self conductor.
And this now, according to
Faraday's law, equals minus
d/dt of the magnetic flux
through that open
surface B.dA .
And it also equals
minus dI/dt .
We discussed that last time
so I won't go into it.
Now, what is the integral in
going through the battery,
that is minus E. Notice, I go
against the electric field if
I go around like this.
Here I go with the
electric field.
So it's plus IR.
Here I plus the electric field,
so it is plus Q divided
by C. And remember that
Q is always the
charge on the capacitor.
Nothing else make sense.
Whenever I use Q it is always
the of the capacitor.
And of course, there is equal
amount of positive charge here
as there is negative
charge here.
What is the integral of, from
b to a through the self
inductance?
Well that's zero because there's
no electric fields in
the self inductance.
Kirchhoff's law does not hold.
The closed loop integral
E.dl is not zero.
It's minus L dI/dt.
The relation by the way, between
this Q c and the
current is I equals dQ
on the capacitor dt.
That relates the current with
the charge on the capacitor.
Now, I'm going to reorganize
this a little bit.
I may have to save this one
because I may need it later.
So using I equals plus dQ / dt,
I find now that Q doubled
dot plus R over L times
Q dot plus Q over l
c equals that emf.
That is the emf, which
is the driver.
The one that could have
various natures.
It could be zero.
It's not necessary that
there is an emf.
It could very well be that this
has short circuited and
that we start at some initial
condition when the capacitor
is charged, we throw a switch
and some currents
will begin to flow.
So E would be zero.
There's also a possibility
that E is constant.
We would call that a battery.
And then there is the
possibility, when we deal with
alternating currents that E
equals E zero times the
cosine omega t.
But of course, any other
function is possible.
E could have this function.
This profile as a function
of time.
Or this one.
We will only in 802, deal
with these two.
And I will first consider
the first two.
You can also write this one
using I equals dQ/dt.
That I double dot plus R divided
by L times I dot plus
I over LC equals dE/dt.
The derivative of this driving
voltage so to speak.
Now if we first take the case
that the emf is zero.
There is no emf.
Or that it is constant.
Then what you are going to see
is, you're going to get into
the circuit, under certain
conditions, and I will specify
those conditions, an alternating
current, which
will ultimately die out.
If you think about it a little
bit, it's immediately obvious
why it has to die out.
We call this regime, the regime
of the light damping.
And I will only discuss this
regime of light damping and I
will specify what exactly
I mean by that.
I choose arbitrarily
that I equals zero
when t equals zero.
And when I do that, I find for a
solution for a constant emf,
emf could also be zero, equals
I zero times E to the minus t
over 2L divided by R times
the sine of omega t.
And the value 2L over R
could be called tau.
That is the decay constant.
And you will see shortly what I
mean by that decay constant.
Omega is now entirely dictated
by the various components L
and C and R. We call this one,
and you will see shortly why,
we call this one, omega
zero squared.
Now omega has to be real,
otherwise this would not have
a solution.
And that immediately tells you
then, what the conditions are
for light damping.
If 1 over LC is larger than
R squared divided by 4 L
squared, which is a condition
for a real value for omega, it
is required that R by smaller
that 2 times the L over C.
That would then be the case of
what I am discussing today of
light damping.
If this is not the case, you get
a different behavior which
I will not discuss.
What now, will the current
look like as
a function of time?
Well, here is I. We started at
I equals zero, that was the
initial condition.
And this exponential decay is
like an envelope that pinches
the current off.
It will make the current
die down.
Zero crossings are
equally spaced.
With a period t, which is
2 pi divided by omega.
And this then, is very closely
the period t that I have here.
And these periods, t,
remain constant.
And this curve here, is
this E to the minus.
And this is then
this exponent.
This is the envelope, which
squeezes down the current.
There is a mechanical energy
which is easy to see and that
may help you a little bit.
If I have here a spring, and I
have an object hanging on the
spring with mass m.
And then it oscillates about
this equilibrium position.
Then what you're going to see,
if you damp the mass in a way
that the fictional force opposes
the velocity, and is
linearly proportional of
velocity then you get exactly
the similar kind of differential
equation that we
had before.
Except you don't see L,
you don't see R's, you
don't see C's .
You see other symbols like
M's and V's, whatever.
I think you've seen them 801.
This kind of behavior
is exactly the same.
It is an oscillating bob,
exponential decay.
And when n goes through
equilibrium, you have here,
all the energy in the bob, in
terms of kinetic energy, which
is one half m v max squared.
But when the bob comes here to a
halt, so v is zero, then you
have all the energy
in potential
energy of the spring.
Which is one half
k x max squared.
And of course this x max, in
this case you will have x
here, this x max, slowly
decays in time.
So what you see here, is
interesting, you see a
sloshing back and forth between
on the one hand all
the energy in terms
of kinetic energy.
And then later everything
in potential energy.
And when you are anywhere
in between, you have a
combination of these two.
Now, in a similar way, with
the R M C circuits, as the
currents oscillate back and
forth, there's a time that the
capacitor has all the
energy in the
form of electric energy.
That is the situation
when I equals zero.
And the energy in
the capacitor is
then one half Q zero.
It is the maximum
value possible,
which decays with time.
Everything is an electric
energy.
And the energy in L, magnetic
energy, equals zero.
Then there comes a time, that
I reaches a maximum, which
again dies out.
The maximum decays.
And then Q on the capacitor is
zero, and then all the energy
is in terms of magnetic
energy.
There's no electric energy.
And that equals one half
LI which is the
maximum value squared.
So also here, you see this
sloshing back and forth
between two different
kinds of energy.
Magnetic energy, which at one
moment in time is all in the
inductor, a little later, a
quarter of an oscillation
later, everything is in terms
of electric energy in the
capacitor and it keeps sloshing
back and forth,
similar to the oscillating
spring.