31-29.
We have an L, we have
a C. R is zero.
Epsilon zero is zero.
So there is no driving
voltage.
And t equals zero.
I equals zero.
And Q of the capacitor is either
plus or minus Q zero.
One plate of course has a
positive charge and the other
plate has a negative charge.
Positive, negative.
I have some kind of
a switch here.
I have a self inductance here.
This is C and this
is L. I close the
switch at time t zero.
The current must be zero because
the self inductance
opposes any sudden increase.
And so we want to evaluate now
how the current is sloshing
back and forth.
This value, as you can
calculate, is 0.0144 Coulombs,
as the whole process starts.
Well, in order to meet the
initial condition, I equals I
zero times the sine of omega t,
the phi is zero here, omega
squared equals one over LC,
which is omega zero squared.
Because notice, there
is no resistance.
Or this is the frequency at
which the system wants to
drive itself, but
there is no R.
So when you go back to the
beginning of my session, you
will see when you make R equal
zero that you get the natural
frequency of the system, omega
zero, is the one at which the
current will start to slosh.
The charge on the capacitor
will be some maximum value
times the cosine of omega t,
because remember I is dQ dt.
I equals dQ/dt.
I take absolute values
because I'm only
interested in the magnitude.
And that will be Q zero
times omega times the
sine of omega t.
Notice I left the minus sign
out, because I'm only
interested in absolute values.
Now when I equals I zero, all
energy is in the L. In
magnetic energy.
Once half L I zero squared.
Now when I is zero, all energy
is in the capacitor in the
form of one half Q zero squared
divided by C and
there's no magnetic energy.
Again, the voltages, as you
would see them if you attached
both meters, over the C and
over the L would be 180
degrees out of face.
I want to remind you of that.
So you've got a sloshing
current back and forth.
And you got a conversion from
all magnetic energy to all
electric energy.
There's no R, so there's
no heat loss.
So the whole thing keeps
flushing back and forth and
there's never any end to it.
Because it's only the R that
will ultimately take out all
the energy.
But there wasn't any.